<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ethics on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/ethics/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (ethics)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 14:40:35 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/ethics/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Feeling like an English teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 14:40:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So I&amp;#39;m teaching my Ethics and CS class for the first time. I
originally designed the course but didn&amp;#39;t teach it the first time
around. That honor went to my friend, Master Teacher Topher
Mykolyk. He of course did an amazing job - impossible to
follow. Fortunately, this is a different cohort so they don&amp;#39;t know how
great Topher was for the course :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though I have the syllabus and Topher&amp;#39;s notes from last time
around, first time through is very week to week but I think I&amp;#39;m
starting to get my legs under me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This course is very different from what I&amp;#39;ve taught in the past. It&amp;#39;s
also  different from the ethics courses I&amp;#39;ve seen currently out
there. Specifically, I wanted a programming component in the
course. Still, there&amp;#39;s a lot more open ended discussion and opinion
based stuff going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mean, when you do a class on an algorithm like mergesort or a
construct like a loop, it is what it is. You can motivate it in
different ways and engage the class but there&amp;#39;s only one punch line
and it&amp;#39;s set in advance. Here things are a lot looser. Most issues
have two sides and even when most of the class is on one like when we
talked about predictive policing, we can still
effectively play devil&amp;#39;s advocate for the other side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It can also lead to the class going sideways. Yesterday we were
talking about basic web privacy. Tracking, cookies and the like. In my
mind I had the lesson mapped out. First, our &amp;#34;weekly ethicacy&amp;#34; student
presentation and then a short breakout, discussion on the info we
share, and then curated questions and resources  that we&amp;#39;d use in a
sequence of breakout room and whole class discussions. The trouble is,
after the first short breakout, the student conversation went directly
to what I had intended for our async work over the course of the
week. Oh well, time to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/&#34;&gt;call an audible&lt;/a&gt;. It wasn&amp;#39;t really a big deal,
the conversation moved in a different direction but it was still very
much in the wheelhouse of the day&amp;#39;s topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Must be what an English class can be like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the course is doing well but I won&amp;#39;t know for sure
until afterwards when I can debrief with the students. After all,
they&amp;#39;re the ones that ultimately determine if the class is successful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the next few weeks I&amp;#39;ll share some specifics about the class. The
programming stuff in particular. Can&amp;#39;t do that now because we&amp;#39;re in
the middle and I don&amp;#39;t want any members of the class who might be
reading this to see the reveal before it&amp;#39;s time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>