<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Policy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/policy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Policy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 06:53:49 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/policy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest Post - Missing out on a great opportunity in education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 06:53:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</guid>
      <description>Preamble I&#39;ve never accepted a guest post before but when my friend and long time colleague JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver said he had something to say I was all for it.
JonAlf&#39;s one of the best teachers I know - he started at Brandeis HS and has been at Stuy forever. Really sharp guy, great teacher, and really perceptive. When he has something to say it&#39;s 100% worth listening to.
To JonAlf - since I know this is one of my blog posts you&#39;ll actually read - you should set up a blog of your own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Thomas Friedman&#39;s editorial on the College Board&#39;s Two Codes left me concerned</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 10:20:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</guid>
      <description>There was some buzz over this editorial about the College Board last week. The two codes every child needs - Coding and the US Constitution? Who could argue with that.
I&#39;m not going to disagree. Civics and CS are important and can&#39;t wait until college. The thing that left me chilled though was that nobody&#39;s paying attention to the fact that the College Board - a private entity with its own interests has so much influence over American education.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>