<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 12:04:45 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ebooks, Nypl and Process Starvation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 12:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m a big fan of E Ink e-readers. I had one a number of years ago. An Aztak EZ Reader. It was great. Small, cheap, and independent - that is, not tied in to Amazon or Barnes and Nobles and I found myself doing a lot more recreational reading with it. I still preferred paper for technical books but for easy reading there was nothing like having tons of reading options always available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busy Week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 07:32:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m glad it&#39;s Saturday morning. It&#39;s been a busy week. It looks like there&#39;s a couple more to plough through but hopefully then I can catch my breath over spring break.
Why so busy? It&#39;s the same old story - you&#39;ve got all those projects that you&#39;re waiting on and everything comes in at the same time.
To start off, it&#39;s college decision season. The high school seniors all know their options and are deciding where to go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 17:38:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</guid>
      <description>Got a new monitor today and wanted to share.
My old one was a 27&#34; Hanns G. Actually, the old ones - my old set up was 2 of them side by side. When I started at Hunter, I was given a piddly small monitor so I tried to buy my own 27&#34; Hanns G to bring in but they were no longer available. The 27&#34; jobs available then were much more expensive so my work monitor situation has been sadly lacking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catskills Conf -  Knitting for Good 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 17:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</guid>
      <description>Two weekends ago I took a group of my first year students up to Catskills Conf, an annual event that I describe as &#34;light tech conference with a focus on diversity and inclusion meets summer camp.&#34; I&#39;ve written about the event before if anyone&#39;s interested in more details. As in past years, Devorah ran her knitting for good project. In each of the first two years of the project, attendees of Catskills Conf learned how to know and collectively knit, crocheted and assembled a blanket for Project Linux which provides hand made blankets to children in crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>