<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misc on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in misc on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 12:22:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting Our Students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/supporting-our-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 12:22:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/supporting-our-students/</guid>
      <description>Austin Cory Bart put together a great post about supporting Black students in CS1. Cory asked about this on the SIGCSE mailing list and in his post he both breaks things down and shares all the resources that he compiled from the ensuing discussion.  There&amp;#39;s a lot of good stuff both in the post and in the links but there&amp;#39;s a lot to get lost in. As teachers we can sometimes affect change at a department or school level but we can always make a difference in our classes and with our students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers and Police</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 10:56:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police/</guid>
      <description>Teachers and Police   It&amp;#39;s been an ugly few days but perhaps in some ways a hopeful few as people have been making their voices heard like never before in my lifetime. We&amp;#39;ve seen and endless stream of videos of peaceful protest and far too many instances of police officers overstepping their bounds. I keep hearing about violent protesters but those videos seem to be avoiding my feeds as are the videos of law enforcement going after the looters who are a separate group from the protestors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Before condemning try walking in their shoes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/privilege/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 19:20:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/privilege/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve got some CS Ed stuff I want to write but can&amp;#39;t bring myself to writing about it today. I rarely post outside of my wheelhouse - CS, Education and the intersection of the two.  I don&amp;#39;t really think I&amp;#39;m qualified to say much about the current crisis. The out of control police, racism, class warfare, a failed government not only at the federal level but also in New York city and state but maybe I can share something worthwhile from my narrow experiences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Covid-19 Journey (so far)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 07:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/covid/</guid>
      <description>I haven&amp;#39;t been posting much over the past couple of weeks and that&amp;#39;s partly because we&amp;#39;ve been under the weather.  Yep - Covid-19.  First things first - we&amp;#39;re all either recovered or well on the way.  I thought I&amp;#39;d write up our experience as it might be useful for others who are going through similar. This disease is weird and seems to affect people differently but three of us followed a similar path.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email or USPS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-or-usps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 14:00:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-or-usps/</guid>
      <description>USPS is in financial trouble. That&amp;#39;s been pretty well documented recently. Most reasonable people will recognize that the USPS is both an important service and while it receives no taxpayer support would be profitable were it not for the GOP imposing unfair and unrealistic pension funding requirements in 2006.  Although I&amp;#39;m an ardent supporter of the post office and feel that privatization of such an important intuition would be criminal today I want to talk about some small repercussions of so many things going to email rather than snail mail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passover 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/passover-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:59:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/passover-2020/</guid>
      <description> Yesterday was the start of Passover and like many others we weren&amp;#39;t able to physically gather with friends and family to celebrate. Since the Talmud, unlike the NYC Dept of Education, doesn&amp;#39;t seem to ban Zoom, like many others, we used Zoom to connect with family.  Tonight we&amp;#39;ll do it again.  In the meantime, I thought I&amp;#39;d share this small bit of research Natan did a couple of years ago on a traditional part of the seder: A Historically Informed Echad Mi Yodea  Enjoy </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brazilian Carrot Cake</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/carrot-cake/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 15:55:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/carrot-cake/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/carrot-cake.jpg&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;  Not my normal post but these are not normal times. Besides, this isn&amp;#39;t the first recipe I&amp;#39;ve posted.  I&amp;#39;m one of those that will, as long as supplies allow, bake and cook my way through our shelter in. Today I made Brazilian carrot cake. It&amp;#39;s not quite the same as an American carrot cake as you&amp;#39;ll see from the recipe below.  First, carrot cake rules:  Obviously since it contains carrot which is a vegetable, it&amp;#39;s healthy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Career Directions - how a sad day changed mine</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/career-directions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 14:39:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/career-directions/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend yesterday who had just started doing grad work in school leadership. It got me thinking about my original career plans and how you never know where you&amp;#39;re going to end up.  Well, not my original original career plans. When I started on Wall Street I had no idea what the future would bring. For all I knew, I could have been a career professional programmer or even gone over to the business side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;m looking forward to in 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/looking-forward-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 12:45:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/looking-forward-2020/</guid>
      <description>Happy new year to everyone.  I&amp;#39;ve been reading some prediction posts this morning on blogs and social media. Big national and world level stuff. I&amp;#39;ve never been much for predictions so I thought I&amp;#39;d share some more local and personal things I&amp;#39;m looking forward to in the coming year.  First a couple of big ones.  I&amp;#39;m just about to complete my fourth year at Hunter. Time really does fly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Can&#39;t Win If You Don&#39;t Enter</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/you-cant-win-if-you-dont-enter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 17:19:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/you-cant-win-if-you-dont-enter/</guid>
      <description>Or, as Wayne Gretzky said &amp;#34;You miss 100% of the shots you don&amp;#39;t take.&amp;#34;  Why do I mention this?  Because I&amp;#39;ve been hearing way too often from young people who are too quick to deny themselves opportunities and too often these are from students who have come from less advantaged backgrounds.  It&amp;#39;s Fall and I&amp;#39;ve been making my rounds visiting local schools to talk to seniors about colleges in general and Hunter CS in particular.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waterfalls - a trip report</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/waterfalls/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 19:18:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/waterfalls/</guid>
      <description>No, this post is not about the Waterfall development model. Devorah and I had a chance to take a little vacation up north.  First stop, Niagara Falls.      &amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;  We did the Canada side 9 years ago when we did our Erie Canal bike trip (you can read about that by checking out some of my early blog posts). This time, the American side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni Anniversaries</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alumni-anniversaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 07:32:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alumni-anniversaries/</guid>
      <description>Two days ago, a teacher&amp;#39;s comment on a frustrating situation made me mad.  Yesterday, I got to be part of something that made me very happy.  Last night, Devorah and I ventured out to Coney Island to celebrate the twentieth wedding anniversary of two former students. It&amp;#39;s such a joy and an honor to be included in these types of life events and even more so to count the couple and so many other former students and friends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Codeland 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 19:46:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</guid>
      <description>I spent today at Codeland, a one day conference in NYC designed for developers in the early stages of their careers. Just as at CSTA, I was there with the GitHub contingent.  Codeland had talks and a keynote in a common auditorium, smaller breakout workshops and a couple of small vendor areas.  I spent most of the morning upstairs in the GitHub lounge so I onl caught part of one morning talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A 10X Student Story</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ten-x-student-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 15:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ten-x-student-story/</guid>
      <description>There were a bunch of threads on the 10X Developer recently. You know - that mythical beast that&amp;#39;s 10 times more productive than the regular software engineer. I didn&amp;#39;t see any of the original threads but I&amp;#39;m guessing they started with &amp;#34;your startup needs them&amp;#34; and then moved to the &amp;#34;they can&amp;#39;t work with anyone&amp;#34; along with tons of fun tongue and cheek 1X engineer tweets.  It got me thinking about 10X students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New(ish) Blog - cscheerleader.com</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 09:05:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-blog/</guid>
      <description>Many of us know Ria Galanos. Ria - a longtime friend and longtime CS teacher who has been very active in the APCS community has started a new chapter as a software engineer at Yext. Ria&amp;#39;s also started blogging about it.  I don&amp;#39;t know the direction the blog will take but I&amp;#39;m sure it will be influenced by Ria&amp;#39;s years as an educator. I&amp;#39;m also sure it will be worth reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ebooks, Nypl and Process Starvation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 12:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m a big fan of E Ink e-readers. I had one a number of years ago. An Aztak EZ Reader. It was great. Small, cheap, and independent - that is, not tied in to Amazon or Barnes and Nobles and I found myself doing a lot more recreational reading with it. I still preferred paper for technical books but for easy reading there was nothing like having tons of reading options always available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busy Week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 07:32:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m glad it&amp;#39;s Saturday morning. It&amp;#39;s been a busy week. It looks like there&amp;#39;s a couple more to plough through but hopefully then I can catch my breath over spring break.  Why so busy? It&amp;#39;s the same old story - you&amp;#39;ve got all those projects that you&amp;#39;re waiting on and everything comes in at the same time.  To start off, it&amp;#39;s college decision season. The high school seniors all know their options and are deciding where to go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 17:38:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_right&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/monitors.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;  Got a new monitor today and wanted to share.  My old one was a 27&amp;#34; Hanns G. Actually, the old ones - my old set up was 2 of them side by side. When I started at Hunter, I was given a piddly small monitor so I tried to buy my own 27&amp;#34; Hanns G to bring in but they were no longer available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catskills Conf -  Knitting for Good 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 17:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</guid>
      <description>Two weekends ago I took a group of my first year students up to Catskills Conf, an annual event that I describe as &amp;#34;light tech conference with a focus on diversity and inclusion meets summer camp.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ve written about the event before if anyone&amp;#39;s interested in more details. As in past years, Devorah ran her knitting for good project. In each of the first two years of the project, attendees of Catskills Conf learned how to know and collectively knit, crocheted and assembled a blanket for Project Linux which provides hand made blankets to children in crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>