<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ct on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ct/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ct on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 17:48:27 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ct/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts On Code And Beyond - Computational Thinking</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/thoughts-on-code-and-beyond-ct/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 17:48:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/thoughts-on-code-and-beyond-ct/</guid>
      <description>The theme of this year&#39;s To Code and Beyond was Computational Thinking. Mark Guzdial gave the keynote. While the talk isn&#39;t currently online, check out this talk that Mark gave last March. It&#39;s not the same but the second halves are and well worth a look.
In the first half, Mark talked about other types of &#34;thinking.&#34; Scientific thinking, engineering thinking and even historical thinking. All had a good amount of overlap with both each other and with computational thinking even as we haven&#39;t yet settled on what computational thinking actually is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is There a First Grade Machine Learning Achievement Gap?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-there-a-first-grade-ml-achievement-gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 15:24:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-there-a-first-grade-ml-achievement-gap/</guid>
      <description>Today was the fifth &#34;To Code and Beyond&#34; - a one day conference hosted at Cornell Technion and once again Diane Levitt put together a great show. The theme was Computational Thinking and the day consisted of a variety of talks, panels, and activities. I plan on writing about one panel in particular but for today I wanted to address something that came up as a question. One attendee asked a panel about the achievement gap - the fact that when the CS movement got started in NY some of the more innovative and interesting work was being done with some of our most vulnerable students.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>