<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Algorithms on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/algorithms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Algorithms on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 13:51:52 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/algorithms/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Seam Carving and Dynamic Programming</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/seam-carving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 13:51:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/seam-carving/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s spring break and for me that&#39;s always been a good time to explore some new ideas.
Here&#39;s one that some of you might like, particularly if you&#39;re teaching APCS-A or something similar.
Many APCS-A teachers do a unit on image processing using the picture lab (alternate resource). Image processing is a nice platform to explore two dimensional arrays. You basically use a 2D array of pixels (points) to represent an image.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Sorting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 20:04:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I saw a facebook post asking for thoughts on teaching sorting. The question was specifically not about motivations like having the class act out sorts or sort cards but rather about the coding.
I&#39;ve been meaning to write about this since last summer when I attended Owen Astrachan&#39;s talk on the same subject.
Early in my career when teaching sorting I developed the n^2 sorts as standalone routines just as they&#39;re presented in most books but as I gained more experience as a teacher, I changed it up to build the sorts (at least some of them) from existing concepts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A* is born</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/a-star-is-born/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/a-star-is-born/</guid>
      <description>Over on the CS Educator StachExchange, which is in private beta for a few more days, I saw a post asking about how to introduce the A* search algorithm.
I taught A* as part of the APCS class at Stuy so I thought I&#39;d talk about what I did here.
Some time around mid year, we get to intermediate recursion. This is about the time, give or take, when we talk about the nlogn sorts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting - Subtle Errors</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-17-subtle-errors-sorting.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-17-subtle-errors-sorting.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 Time to wrap up sorting for a while. We just finished quicksort having gone through a series of lessons We started with Quickselect.  Then we did a quicksort, copying to new arrays during the partition  Then finally to an in place quicksort.  
 For the final quicksort we used a partition algorithm pretty much the same as the one described here.  We started testing using by building a randomly filled array like this: Random rnd = new Random(); int a[] = new int[n]; for (int i0;i&amp;amp;lt;&amp;lt;span style=&amp;quot;color: #7CB8BB;&amp;quot;&amp;gt;n&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;;i++) { a[i]  rnd.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From selection to sorting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-12-select-to-sort.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-12-select-to-sort.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 When I first saw the quicksort it was in an algorithms class back in the day. We first learned the quicksort, then choosing a good pivot element and then as an afterthought we did quickselect.  Fast forward to teaching. I was never really happy teaching quicksort. Mergesort is easy to motivate and it&#39;s pretty easy to write. Quicksort always felt a little forced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I guess I&#39;m a dumbass</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-27-dumbass/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-27-dumbass/</guid>
      <description>I like a fairly informal atmosphere in my classes. Students have to know that there&amp;rsquo;s a line between teacher and student but I also want them to feel like we&amp;rsquo;re all part of the Stuy CS family.
Whenever we start a new term, it takes a while to break down the walls. The students don&amp;rsquo;t know what to expect of me, can they trust me? Am I a bozo? Who knows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fibonacci by the tail</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-13-fibonacci/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-13-fibonacci/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re ramping up for recursion in my junior classes - state space search, nlg(n) sorts, etc. As a refresher, we took a quick look at the Fibonacci numbers.
Now, some people seem to think that it&amp;rsquo;s a tired problem. It&amp;rsquo;s mathy, it&amp;rsquo;s played out, it&amp;rsquo;s boring etc.. They just might be missing the point.
The beauty isn&amp;rsquo;t in the problem itself, but rather, that it&amp;rsquo;s a platform on which you can look at many problem solving techniques.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting from the top and from the bottom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-03-14-sorting-from-top-and-from-bottom.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-03-14-sorting-from-top-and-from-bottom.html/</guid>
      <description>Sorting from the top and from the bottom I&#39;ve been meaning to write this post for a couple of weeks, but some times life just gets in the way. I&#39;ve always thought it important to arm students with as many different tools with which to attack problems as possible. As such, the courses I teach use a number of different languages, each highlighting a different paradigm and thought process. The hope is that by the end of the sequence, they can look at problems from many different angles.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>