<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 08:53:28 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How Will Online Influence Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/how-will-online-influence-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 08:53:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/how-will-online-influence-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I always enjoy Fred Wilson&amp;#39;s predictions for the new year over on his
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2022/01/what-is-going-to-happen-in-2022&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;  was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was inspired to think a bit on his education prediction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K12 systems around the US (and around the world) faced with teacher
shortages and desperate to erase several years of learning shortfalls,
will increasingly adopt online learning services in the school
building in lieu of and in addition to in-class learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fred&amp;#39;s a VERY sharp and perceptive guy and a friend and I think
he&amp;#39;s correct on the adoption of online learning but I thought a couple
of points merited a deeper dive from a guy who&amp;#39;s spent a lifetime in
the trenches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The fist thing I think worth talking about, and this isn&amp;#39;t really
about the adoption of online learning are learning shortfalls They
don&amp;#39;t exist. Learning shortfalls due to Covid, also described as
learning loss is a made up concept. Usually pushed by politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The claim is that due to COVID students learned less than what they
were supposed to and we have to make that up. Less than what? Less
than who? Everyone in the world was hit with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This comes back to our countries love affair with high stakes
testing - every student MUST finish Algebra by 8th grade, or MUST have
a certain reading proficiency by 5th grade (whatever that means).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, we&amp;#39;re told that students work at their own
pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Which is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that a large amount of specific topics we cover in K12
could be eliminated and we&amp;#39;d be none the worse for wear. In Algebra 2
/ Trig there&amp;#39;s around a month of Circle Geometry. It seems randomly
placed and really doesn&amp;#39;t introduce any new meaningful concepts. I
suspect that it originally was placed in the course when Alg2/Trig was
the terminal HS math course and people through &amp;#34;well, kids should see
this sometime&amp;#34; but now this is no longer the case. We could easily
knock it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Likewise, look at how Geometry evolved. Even though it&amp;#39;s supposed to
be a course about proof many schools only pay lip service to teaching
it. This is a result of high stakes testing. Teachers know that
teaching proof is HARD and learning it likewise. They also know that
the students need to pass the regents to graduate and that both
student and teacher will be judged on passing the exam. Further, they
know that the best route to get the student passing is to barely deal
with proof and focus on the rest of the class which is easier to teach
and learn and is worth the lions share of the points on the regents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In English we can read one less Shakespeare and I&amp;#39;m sure we can go
down the list we&amp;#39;ll find that a lot of these things that kids didn&amp;#39;t
learn are really just arbitrary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other truth is that indeed people learn at different rates and
if we really cared about education we&amp;#39;d admit and deal with this
rather than keeping our lock step testing based system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, learning shortfalls are manufactured and could easily be
dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With that aside, we can look at online learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just to get started - I think that online learning has a place. It can
be at times a great supplement to in person learning and at times it
can be the superior option. I&amp;#39;ll write more about that soon. Probably
not for another week or so since Devorah and I are hoping to get away
to San Diego for a little vacation later this week. My concern comes
from me being much more the pessimist than Fred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, I used to be more of an optimist but working in the system for
30 years has a way of beating you down. Now I&amp;#39;m much more of a &amp;#34;hope
for the best, expect the worst&amp;#34; kind of guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My first fear is that online learning will be used just as Fred
mentioned, due to teacher shortages. I think this is likely to happen
and it&amp;#39;s not going to be pretty. Better to actually address teacher
shortages by, I don&amp;#39;t know, paying teachers fairly and having them
work in safe environments with reasonable work loads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Instead, I see a new wave of technology based solutions like online
charters which have proven to be ripe for scandal or programs like the
technology based &amp;#34;credit recovery&amp;#34; courses that came online under
Bloomberg. These were self paced online courses where students clicked
through repeatedly. Great for graduation rates. Horrible for actual
learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re also going to see technology being used not to make teachers
more effective but either to add to their workload and/or class sizes.
A small and maybe frivolous example is when politicians were talking
about eliminating snow days - they&amp;#39;ll just teach online. Now, since
you don&amp;#39;t know a snow day is coming this leaves a teacher to scramble
at the last minute to come up with something and given how much time
can go into prep, this is a BIG add to the teachers week. As a
teacher, I loved snow days not so much as a &amp;#34;party day&amp;#34; but rather as
a day where I got the gift of a day back to catch up on planning,
grading, and paperwork. Besides, I think that rare surprise day off is
actually healthy for kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A bigger example is that I&amp;#39;m thinking that we&amp;#39;ll see schools expecting
teachers be available to students and parents 24x7. We already see
this starting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A third would be instead of a small class where teachers and students
interact using technology to balloon up the class size. So much of
teaching, particularly in K12 is about relationships and interactions
and you just don&amp;#39;t get that when you decide to do a class on computers
and drive up the enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You&amp;#39;ll also see technology that seem to help teachers but even those
have a downside. Prime example - autograders. They&amp;#39;re grate for
providing students with instant feedback and for grading &amp;#34;short
answer&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;right or wrong&amp;#34; questions but when a teacher grades a
teacher sees a students work and gains insights into the student. If
I&amp;#39;m not grading projects, I&amp;#39;m losing that insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Actually, a great example is looking at student projects in the old
world and in the new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the old world, a project is assigned in class. Maybe we have a lab
day or two, then some work on their own time. More lab days, then
finally the project is due and the teacher grades. With all that in
class time, the teacher is observing and interacting and getting to
know the students and their work. To be honest, by the time I grade a
project, I already know most of the story but reading over the code
and running the program on my own is the final piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The new way? The project is assigned. Work is done outside of hte
teacher&amp;#39;s view. The teacher only sees the students work if they ask
for help outside of class hours (since you can&amp;#39;t use that important
synchronous class time for that with 100+ students) and then it&amp;#39;s
autograded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The old way takes more time and more work but that&amp;#39;s teaching and
learning. The new way will work great for the autodidacts and a number
of kids will flow through the machine but here technology which would
seem like a win, really isn&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a lot of &amp;#34;expect the worst&amp;#34; and I do want to be clear - I love
tech and think that tech can be a great boon to education if done
right. I&amp;#39;m just really wary of past experience being a predictor of
how things will go in the future. I think Smart, well meaning people
are going to continue to come up with wonderful tools that could do
worlds of good for students and teachers but I have little confidence
in the decision makers deploying them in ways that will truly benefit
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I hope I&amp;#39;m wrong and none of this pessimism will stop me from working
with technologists, ed tech people, and playing with the new toys as
they become available. I just also want to be prepared for the worst
while I&amp;#39;m hoping for  the best.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exit 2021</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/exit-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:04:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/exit-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, 2021&amp;#39;s gone and 2022 just starting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a lot of ways, I don&amp;#39;t really see this as a new year. Maybe after I
retire but for me and I&amp;#39;m guessing other working teachers the year
really starts in early September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, the calendar changed over so even if it feels like midyear to
me, it&amp;#39;s still worth a quick look back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Obviously, a trying year for all of us so I won&amp;#39;t dwell to much on
that. Professionally, I think the highlight came in early June when
our first set of Advanced Certificate students filed and received
their state certifications as CS teachers. That was big. I had the
undergraduate CS Daedalus program running long enough to have grads
and a bit of a history but taking working teachers through my program
and to state certification let me check off another mission completed
box. It felt good, particularly to be able to do it with long time
friends and collaborators like JonAlf and Topher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The lowlight professionally was probably my in person teaching. Don&amp;#39;t
get me wrong, teaching is still the highlight of what I do but I don&amp;#39;t
think I was up to par this past semester. Truth be told, I think I did
a better job fully remote in the prior year. There&amp;#39;s more to say about
that but I think it&amp;#39;s worth its own post in a few days. TL;DR -
teaching in masks and with fixed seating turned good lessons into bad
lectures. It also sucks when you overall don&amp;#39;t feel super comfortable
in the environment so it basically becomes, you go to class, you
teach, you leave. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was a teaching highlight, however which was teaching my Ethics
course. That was fun and since it was remote and with the teachers I
worked with over the summer, I think it went pretty well overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the personal front, I read more, programmed less, and continued to
try to learn to paint. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall, I can&amp;#39;t say much good about last year and I think a lot of
people feel that way so I won&amp;#39;t dwell on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to this coming year and the rest of this school year? I think I&amp;#39;m
looking forward to the fact that in late May we&amp;#39;ll be graduating our
first couple of CS Education Masters students. That&amp;#39;s the last box I
feel I have to check to be able to say mission accomplished on what I
set out to do at Hunter and then some. Other than that it should
(hopefully) be business as usual and that&amp;#39;s not a horrible thing. I&amp;#39;m
unsure if things will be better in class before the Fall given omicron
but we&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Devorah and I are planning on going away late next week so that should
recharge the batteries to get ready for the Spring semester. Heading
off to San Diego - never been so if you&amp;#39;ve got some pointers on what
to do that might be off the beaten path, drop me a line.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transparent Origami - Advent 2021 Day 13</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 13:28:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
No post so far on &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/12&#34;&gt;day 12&lt;/a&gt;. I finished part 1 but my code was pretty
messy which turned part 2 into a mess. I still have to go back to get
that second star so just like day 10, my day 12 write up is on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, I really enjoyed [[&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/13&#34;&gt;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/13&lt;/a&gt;
][today&amp;#39;s]] challenge. Paper foldind. You&amp;#39;re given transparent paper with
a bunch of marks on it. You have to fold the paper over horizontal or
vertical lines and examine the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Input was in the form of lines x,y pairs followed by lines specifying
the folds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First decision - data representation. Since we&amp;#39;ve got a grid,
temptation would be to use a 2D structure like a 2D array but there
are two problems. One is that each fold will make the paper smaller
and smaller which makes a 2D array wasteful if not clumsy. The other
issue is that we don&amp;#39;t know the ranges for our coordiates. We know
that all the values will be positive but we have no idea where they
start and end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just like with the cellular automaton, I decided to use a dictionary
where the key was  the x,y pair and the entry was the mark. I could
have used a plain list for the points but the dictionary gave me quick
lookup. Also, if part 2 had us change the marks based on if they
overlap after a fold, I&amp;#39;d be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For convenience (and as I learned later, part 2) I also wanted a
routine that could print the board. Here&amp;#39;s that routine in case you
want to see some clojure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;
  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;board-&amp;gt;string [board]
    (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[maxx (apply max (map first (keys board))) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; find the largest x&lt;/span&gt;
          maxy (apply max (map second (keys board))) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; find the largest y&lt;/span&gt;
          k (keys board)

          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; The next line makes a vector of maxy vectors&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; each of which has maxx spaces&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; basically a vector of vectors or 2D matrix if you would&lt;/span&gt;
          grid (into [] (repeat (inc maxy) (into [] (repeat (inc maxx) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;\ &lt;/span&gt;))))

          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; go through the keys to our board (which is a hash table&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; and mark those squares with a #&lt;/span&gt;
          filled-grid (reduce (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;fn &lt;/span&gt;[b [y x]] (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;assoc-in&lt;/span&gt; b [x y] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;\#&lt;/span&gt;)) grid k)

          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; change each line from a vector to a string&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; but leave the overall thing a vector since&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; it looks fine when I print it.&lt;/span&gt;
          string-grid (map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(apply str %) filled-grid)
          ]
      string-grid
      ))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we have our &amp;#34;board&amp;#34; we can then deal with folding. Folds had to
be over a horizontal (ex: y=7) or vertical (ex: x=5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was important to note that since we&amp;#39;re folding we only want to take
the points with coordinates greater than the folding line and
transform those and not just transform all the points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The actual transformation is pretty straightforward. Given the line&amp;#39;s
coordinate L the new point value can be calculated using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
newcoord = oldcoord - 2 * abs(oldcoord-L)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We just go through the points and if they have to be transformed,
update them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 1 solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 turned out to be far easier than I expected. Part 1 had us just
do the first fold. Part 2 had us do all of them at which point, if we
printed our board it would show us the 8 secret letters that formed
our anwer. Since the example on the problem page was a y fold and the
first fold of my data was an x fold I knew both my folds worked. I
just ran through all the folds and voila.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m not complaining about an easy problem. If it were harder I
might not finish and then no write up but I was expecting something
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were ways to make part two a bit more complex. I could see maybe
placing the data so far off the end so that you had to translate them
down closer to the origin so that your result would print or maybe do
something with overlapping marks when you fold as I mentioned up top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, nothing wrong with an easy day mixed in and I still think it&amp;#39;s
a great problem. This could be done by a CS0 or CS1 class. What I
particularly love about problems like this is that when you
ultimately solve it you &amp;#34;decode&amp;#34; a secret message. Much cooler than
just getting some number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, over half way done. I still have that part 2 of day 12 to finish
but still captured half the total stars for the event. That&amp;#39;s my
starting goal each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want to see my full solution, you can check it out &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day13.clj&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dumbo Octopus and the Game of Life - AOC 2011 Day 11</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 11:31:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t particularly motivated to start &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/11 &#34;&gt;day 11&lt;/a&gt; but took a look over
coffee. A grid of points where on each turn or step the points are
modified by some rule. Hey, this sounds familiar - cellular automata
like Conway&amp;#39;s Game of Life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You set up your grid and then on each turn just follow the rules. In a
traditional Cellular Automaton like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life&#34;&gt;Conway&amp;#39;s Game of Life&lt;/a&gt;, on each
turn each cell looks at its six neighbors and makes a decision as to
its next state based on the neighbors and a rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life&#34;&gt;Conway&amp;#39;s Game of Life&lt;/a&gt;, a cell is either alive or dead. On each
turn, it counts all it&amp;#39;s neighbors and then decides if it will be
alive or dead next turn based on its current state and how many
neithbors are currently alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I love talking about Cellular Automata in class although I haven&amp;#39;t
done it since my Stuy days. One of my favorite topics is using CS to
solve a maze in NetLogo. I wrote about that &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-17-maze-ca/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Cellular Automata is also not a stranger to Advent of Code with three
problems being CS problems in 2020 and I think there were more in
earlier years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This year the twist was that the rule for each step had two stages and
the second stage could repeat over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first stage was just to increment the value of each cell. The
second involved &amp;#34;flashing.&amp;#34; This would happen if a cell&amp;#39;s value
exceeded nine. If a cell flashed, it would increment the value of each
of its neighbors. This could cause a cascade by having a neighbor&amp;#39;s
value exceed nine. This kept going until the board stabalized. You
also had to account for the fact that a cell should only flip at most
once per step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part one had you calculate the number of flashes over the course of
100 steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I do CA in a class like APCS-A we usually use a 2D array to
represent our world. In NetLogo, the world is already a grid. Since
I&amp;#39;m using Clojure, I though a hash table would be easier. The keys are
x,y coordinates and the values are the state of the cell (the integer
value). To set things up I stole the code from my code from last year,
also coincidentally &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2020/blob/main/src/day11.clj&#34;&gt;day 11&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2020-day11/&#34;&gt;write up&lt;/a&gt; also talke about using a hash
table or dictionary instead of a 2D array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first stage of each step was easy. Just map the increment function
across the entire board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second step took more thought. First, I went through the board and
for any cell that was greater than 9 I incremented all its
neighbors. Then to make sure I don&amp;#39;t flash a cell more than once a
turn, I marked the current cell as being flashed. I did this by making
it a large negative number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I repeated that second step over and over until it stabilized. That
is, you went through an iteration where the board didn&amp;#39;t change - no
new flashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I set all the negative cells, which indicated they flashed to
zero in preparation for the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the loop I counted and added up how many flashes we had and that
was part 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 2 you were looking for a step where every cell flashed at the
same time. This was pretty easy because we were able to essentially
use the same engine. The only difference was that instead of doing 100
steps, you kept going until every cell flashed in one turn. That
turned out to be easy to check. You know that happened when all of the
cells at the start of a turn are 0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, the full solution can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day11.clj&#34;&gt;GitHub.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wasn&amp;#39;t motivated to start today but it turned out to be a fun little
challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bracket Bonanza (AOC 2021 day 10)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 12:15:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I know, where&amp;#39;s day 9? Thursdays (and Mondays) are already tight for
me - I teach all morning and it&amp;#39;s been a rough week. I just had very
little energy and focus all day yesterday. I snuck some time in to
finish part 1 but couldn&amp;#39;t focus on part 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today, however, my body gave me an extra half hour of sleep (til
4:30am) so I had extra time and energy. I was fortunate in that
today&amp;#39;s problem was essentially one that I&amp;#39;ve assigned time and time
again so I was able to wrap it up quickly and then go back to finish
day 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s pretty likely that there&amp;#39;ll be a day I can&amp;#39;t solve in the near
future so maybe I&amp;#39;ll write up day 9 then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But for now, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/10&#34;&gt;day 10 - Syntax Scoring&lt;/a&gt; or as I like to say a bracket
bonanza. Inputs were lines of brackets like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
[({(&amp;lt;(())[]&amp;gt;[[{[]{&amp;lt;()&amp;lt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both parts of the problem involve figuring out if the line is valid,
that is, if each open bracket has a matching close bracket without
overlap. For example (([])) is valid but (([)]) is not becaue the
inner () and the [] overlap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could be like a kid doing a technical interview and pretend I hadn&amp;#39;t
solved the problem before the interview but the truth is, I&amp;#39;ve
done problems very similar to this most times I teach data structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As you process through the input, whenever you see a closing bracket,
it &lt;strong&gt;has&lt;/strong&gt; to match up with the last seen open bracket otherwise the
expression is invalid. This means you have to maintain a data
structure in such a way that the last open bracket you see is the
first one you check whenever you see a closing brace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is, by definition, a stack. A stack is a data structure where the
last item you put in is the first item you take out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, the algorithm is pretty simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-text&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;make an empty stack
For each character in the input:
  1. If it&amp;#39;s an open bracket put it on the stack
  2. If it&amp;#39;s a close bracket, check the top of the stack.
     1. If the stack is empty you&amp;#39;ve got an invalid expression - exit
     2. If top of the stack doesn&amp;#39;t match your bracket - invalid -exit
     3. If top of the stack does match your braket, pop it off the stack and keep going&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s basically it. The only remaining task is to figure out the
specifics to answer the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1 you had to run the above algorithm on each line of input
and for each invalid expression look up the invalid character&amp;#39;s value
(provide in the problem text) and add them all up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part two you had to take the remaining characters in the lines
once you hit an invalid brace and figure out a slightly more complex
score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, given that I had basically done this problem it wasn&amp;#39;t hard but it
was fun. This could be directly assigned to any data structures class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, my code can be found here:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day10.clj&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day10.clj&#34;&gt;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day10.clj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven Segment Silliness - Advent 2021 Day08</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day08/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 13:20:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Day 8 took a lot longer than the other days. Not all that much code
and not too complex, at least after getting through a scary sounding
lead up but going from problem statement to solution took both time
and thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I started to read the problem, I wasn&amp;#39;t sure I&amp;#39;d finish it let
alone have time to write it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take a minute to read over the problem. You can find it [[&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/8&#34;&gt;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/8&lt;/a&gt;
][here.]]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A pretty intimidating wall of text. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You&amp;#39;ve got a bunch of lines, each looking like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
be cfbegad cbdgef fgaecd cgeb fdcge agebfd fecdb fabcd edb | fdgacbe cefdb cefbgd gcbe
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Each &amp;#34;word&amp;#34; represents a seven segment display. The side to the left
of the | is the input for that line and the stuff on the right, the
output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem is that each line has the inputs scrambled. We jave to
figure out which letter maps to the top segment, which the bottom,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Oh boy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that part one really wasn&amp;#39;t hard at all. In fact, it
could make a nice early CS assignment. If you look at the display for
a &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;, it has two segment on the right hand side. It&amp;#39;s the only number
that uses 2 and only 2 of the seven segments. Likewise a &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; is the
only four segment letter, &lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt; is the only one that uses 3 segments,
and &lt;strong&gt;8&lt;/strong&gt; is the only one that uses all seven segments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1 you just had to look at all the outputs  - that is, the
stuff on each line after the | and add up the number of items that
are either a 1, 4, 7, or 8. That&amp;#39;s easily accomplished by going over
each of those items and checking if they have the correct number of
characters and then figuring out the total number of these items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had already parsed my data into the a two item list where the left
item is a list of inputs and the right a list of outputs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;[ [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;cg&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;cdbga&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;bcg&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; ...] [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;geac&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ceag&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;faedcb&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;cg&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So all I had to do go through all the output sides, count the characters in
each item and then add up the number of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;myfilter [x]
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;takes a list of numbers and returns only those that are 2,4,3, or 7&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
    (filter &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(contains? &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;{&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;} %) x))


  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;part1 [  data]
    (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[results (map second data) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; pull out all the outputs&lt;/span&gt;
          counted (map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(map count %) results) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; turn the &amp;#34;words&amp;#34; into counts of their lengths&lt;/span&gt;
          f (map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;myfilter&lt;/span&gt; %) counted) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; only keep the ones that are the right lengths&lt;/span&gt;
          total (map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(count %) f) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; count how many are in each line&lt;/span&gt;
          ]
      (apply +  total))) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; add them all up &lt;/span&gt;

  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;part1&lt;/span&gt; data)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 2 we had to decode all the output lines and then turn them
into numbers and add them up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sounded really daunting. It required some thought but it wasn&amp;#39;t that
bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to build a dictionary where the keys were the digits and the
values would be the segments for that particular input line that
represent  that digit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a given line, we can do it pretty easily for the unique numbers 2,
4,3, and 7 so we just loop through all the items in a line  and when
we see an item with the appropriate length, we store the number in our
dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We might have something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;b e&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;b c e g&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;b d e&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a b c d e f g&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These were the values from the first line of the example data. Also, I
used a Clojure set  to store the values since that makes the rest of
the solution easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then took this dictionary and tried to add to it by figuring out the
5 segment numbers - specifically, 2, 3 and 5. It turns out that of the
5 segment numbers, the &lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt; is the only one that ovelaps with the two
segments from the &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; so we can find that one pretty easily. If the
five segment number wasn&amp;#39;t a 3, I looked to see if it was a 5. For
this, I looked to see if it had the left and middle segments that the
4 had. Finally, if it wasn&amp;#39;t a &lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt; or a &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt; then it had to be a &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, I did the same for the remaining segments which were all 6
segments. You can look at my full code (linked below) for specifics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we had the complet dictionary I flipped it - keys became values
and values became keys so we could look up the output numbers. From
there, it was easy to convert them to numbers and find the final
answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The part of this problem that was both fun and challenging was trying
to figure out how to decode a given letter given what you already
figured out. That took some time but getting the final answers for
problems like this are somehow more satisfying than just a straight up
&amp;#34;code it&amp;#34; problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can find my full solution &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day08.clj&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was worried I wasn&amp;#39;t going to finished this one when I first read it
but I think it&amp;#39;s my favorite of the year so far.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How you look at a problem can make it easier - AOC 2021 Day 7</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day07/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 09:04:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/7&#34;&gt;Today&amp;#39;s problem&lt;/a&gt; was similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day06/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt; in that it&amp;#39;s ease or
difficulty really depended on how you looked at the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For yesterday, the problem was hard if you approached it by modeling
each and every lanternfish but it was much easier if you modeled the 8
days of the reproduction cycle. Sure, there was still work to be done
but looking at the problem the right way made things much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same thing for today, at least for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We were given a list of crabs and their locations and the challenge
was getting them all to the same spot. Fortunately, crabs in their
submarines can only move in one dimension - they can only move
horizontally. This gives us an input that&amp;#39;s just a list of integers,
each representing a crab location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We want to move all the crabs to the same location and we want to do
it as efficiently as possible. The crab submarines use one unit of
fuel for each step taken so we want to minimize the overall amount of
fuel used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we look at this from the crab point of view this could seem
daunting - do we move the crabs one at a time? Do we have them
converge? Will we have to do some crazy recursive movement thing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out, none of the above. As soon as we realize that we don&amp;#39;t
have to figure out actual moves or actually move the crabs the problem
becomes much easier. It isn&amp;#39;t about the crabs but rather about the
locations. We want to figure out the minimal cost of moving all the
crabs to each location and then we can pick the lowest overall cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This turns out to be rather simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For each possible location (looping from smallest crab location to
larges):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;calculate the distance from each crab to this location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add up all those distances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then just need to take the smallest distance and we&amp;#39;re done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On to part two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part two, there was a change to the fuel cost. Instead of just
being the distance between the two locations, the cost of the fuel
increased by one for each step. So, for moving 1 step the cost would
be one. Two steps, 1+2, three 1+2+3 etc..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was easy enough to model. I just changed the function that
calculated the old cost with one that calculated the new cost. To do
that, I took the difference between the two endpoints and calculated
the sum from 1 up to and including that number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This added an additional loop but I figured might as well try it. It
was noticeably slower than part 1 - about 11 seconds as opposed to
around 90 msec but fast enough to get an answer and finish the problem
for the day. That said, it was easy enough to improve the solution if
you know that you can calculate the sum from 1 to n using the formula
(n*(n+1))/2. This got the speed back to just over 100 msec.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking over the adventofcode subreddit people were talking about
using the median to more quickly solve the problem but what I did was
good enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As always, the clojure code can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day07.clj&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lanternfish and lots of data (AOC 2021 Day 6)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 16:25:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today we had to model the growth of the lanternfish population
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/6&#34;&gt;problem here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lanternfish spawn new lanternfish every seven days. The trick is that
the original starting population consists of fish at different points
in the cycle. For instance, if your input data was 3,2,4 then each fish
would spawn a new fish in three, two, and four days respectively. The
new fish would set their timers to 8 and start counting down to their
spawn date on the next day and the original fish would reset it&amp;#39;s
timer to 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, lanternfish never die so the population is going to get
quite large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first glance this seems to be an easy problem to model. Read the
fish into a list or array and start processing them a day at a
time. Add fish to the end as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m guessing this would work for part 1 but doubt it would work for
part 2. Even before I started solving this just seemed like a problem
where part 2 would blow away our data set getting much to large much
too fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what to do? It turns out the problem is cyclical. Instead of
looking at fish, we can look at days. We have an 8 day cycle. Instead
of storing the fish, store the number of fish that will spawn on any
given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started by playing around with mod and trying to figure out how to
walk around the list while summing up fish but after a while my brain
started to hurt. Instead, I just did things in the most
straightforward way I could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fist, I made a list with my initial state. The example problem had a
data set of &lt;code&gt;&amp;#34;3,4,3,1 2&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt; which led to this list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Notice that I have 9  not 8 slots (indexed 0 - 8). That extra one at
the end is where I move the fish that are spawning today (day 0) so
they can start the cycle again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there, it&amp;#39;s just following the rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grab the number of fish to spawn today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Move all the fish down a day - that is, the fish in day 1 go to day
0, day 2 to day 1 etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the new fish to slot 6 (as per the specification).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the number that spawned today to the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Repeat this for the requisite number of days and then add them all up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Clojure code for the complete solution is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;      (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;solve [data days]
        (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[start-state (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;reduce&lt;/span&gt;
                           (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;fn &lt;/span&gt;[sofar next]
                             (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;update&lt;/span&gt; sofar next inc))
                           [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; ] data )]
          (apply + (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;loop &lt;/span&gt;[i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
                          gens start-state]
                     (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(&amp;lt; i days)
                       (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[last (first gens)
                             gens  (into []  ( drop &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; gens))
                             gens  (assoc gens &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; (+ (nth gens &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;) last))
                             gens  (conj gens last)
                             ]
                         (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;recur&lt;/span&gt; (inc i) gens)
                         )
                       gens)))))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For those of you not familiar with Clojure, that &lt;code&gt;reduce&lt;/code&gt; in the let on the second line is how we take the data
and build our starting state. For those of you who DO know clojure, I
could probably have made it cleaner with a threading macro instead of
the three step assignment to gens in the bottom let.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, we walk away with a memory efficient time efficient
solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s probably some recurrence that could be set up and solved to do
this all with math but since the mod stuff made my head hurt working
on a recurrence equation would probably make it explode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s usually at least one problem like this in advent of code each
year. Something where it looks like you&amp;#39;ll have to calculate forever
but it turns out you can set up a short repeating cycle to get the job
done. Unfortunately, they&amp;#39;re all too advanced for my average intro CS
students. Sure, I could go over the problem and they&amp;#39;d kindof get it
but I don&amp;#39;t think the majority would really grok it. Alternatively
they could just follow the rules given and led in class to setting up
the cycle but I&amp;#39;d love to come up with one where they can really
discover the magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I should spend some time thinking about this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One man&#39;s complex is another man&#39;s simple (AOC 2021 Day 5)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day05/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 10:40:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I wrote about the virtues of a simple straightforward
solution as opposed to a super &amp;#34;clever&amp;#34; one. Today reminded me that
what seems simple to one person might be clever to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having successfully survived bingo with a giant squid, Today&amp;#39;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/5&#34;&gt;challenge&lt;/a&gt; had us navigating our sub so as to avoid dangerous parts of
the ocean. We were given a bunch of lines represented by endpoints as
input. If we graphed all the lines, some of them would overlap. The
more the overlap, the more dangerous. Given all the points on the
graph that are covered by a line, we had to determine how many points
were covered by two or more lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if we have the following 10x10 grid with 1,1 being the
upper left adn 10,10 the lower right and the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
1,2 --&amp;gt; 8,2
3,1 --&amp;gt; 3,7
2,4 --&amp;gt; 7,4
6,1 --&amp;gt; 6,8
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
we&amp;#39;d have the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
..X..X....
XXXXXXXX..
..X..X....
.XXXXXX...
..X..X....
..X..X....
.....X....
.....X....
..........
..........
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If instead of X we marked each square with the number of times it was
drawn on we&amp;#39;d have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
..1..1....
11211211..
..1..1....
.121121...
..1..1....
..1..1....
.....1....
.....1....
..........
..........
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the above example, the answer to part 1 would be 4 since 4 squares
have more than one line on them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here our lines are all vertical and horizontal. For part 1 we only had
ton consider horizontal and vertical even though the input might
specify diagonals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 required we also deal with diagonals but only the ones with a
45 degree angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a relatively new programmer the obvious solution would be to
create a 2D array. Then you just have to scan through the data and
fill the array. Finally, go over the array and count the cells that
were hit more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This approach presents three problems. The first, which is minor is
that you&amp;#39;d first have to scan the input to determine the required
array size. The second problem is that you could have negative values
in your input so you&amp;#39;d have to somehow compensate for that
possibility. Finally, you could have spares input. What if there were
only two lines but one was from -1000000,-1000000 &amp;gt; -999999,999999
and the other from 1000000,1000000 &amp;gt; 1000001,1000001. You have two
tiny lines but you&amp;#39;d need a HUGE array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, an easier, simpler solution was to use a dictionary (also
called hash table, or map depending on language). My grid would start
as an empty map and then I&amp;#39;d add points by walking the line segments. For
example if I had a line from 0,0 &amp;gt; 2,0, I&amp;#39;d add three entries to the
map. The keys would be (0,0), (1,0), and (2,0), and the values would
be all 1 since each location was hit once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I then added the line (1,0) &amp;gt; (1,2), I&amp;#39;d end up with this final
map:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  {(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;) : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,
   (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;) : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,
   (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;) : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,
   (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;) : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,
   (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;) : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that the (1,0) entry now has a two since it was hit twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we added all the lines, pull out the values and count how many
are greater or equal to two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once armed with this approach it was easy enough to solve the
problem. You can check out the code &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day05.clj&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll maintain that I used a simple, clear, and maintainable approach
but it&amp;#39;s also worth noting that if I presented this problem to
relative beginners, depending on what tools they&amp;#39;ve used, they might
very well lean heavily on an array representation. This would
certainly be true when I was a beginner - we never saw maps or
dictionaries until we built them in our data structures courses. Now,
with students cutting their teeth in languages like Python where
dictionaries come up much earlier, perhaps today&amp;#39;s beginners would
also opt for the map / dictionary solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, I always like problems like this where there are
multiple ways of representing the data in the solution which leads to
some nice food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working code is better than clever code (AOC 2021 day 4)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day04/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 12:17:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I always tell my students that the cleverest program is
worthless if it doesn&amp;#39;t actually work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are always some kids in class that all too often try to write
the fanciest solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They&amp;#39;re the ones that write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;s){&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!*&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;(l(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;s)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;);}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
instead of something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;string_length&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;s){
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; (s[i] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;){
    i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;;
    }
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; i;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
to calculate the length of a string.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They try to code in a way they envision a master programmer coding
which invariably leads them to hours of heartache and misery as they
try to fix a poorly and complexly designed system. When I was a kid I
did this as well but learned better early on. One thing I was pretty
proud of as a young professional programmer were the number of
comments I&amp;#39;d get from peers and superiors on the readability of my
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, my view isn&amp;#39;t unique. Much more famously, Donald Knuth said
the same when he quipped that &amp;#34;premature optimization is the root of
all evil.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So while today&amp;#39;s advent of code problem presented a number of design
choices, I decided to go lazy and simple. Sure, my solution&amp;#39;s probably
slower than others but it&amp;#39;s easy and understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today&amp;#39;s problem had you playing bingo against a giant squid (full
problem &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/4&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The core was that after a number of numbers were drawn,
each time you crossing that number off your boards, you had to figure
out if a board was a winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First the input. It was easy enough to read in the file. The first
line were the bingo balls in the order they were to be drawn and then
you had a bunch of 5 line blocks, each line with 5 numbers
representing a 5x5 board. Each board was separated by a space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My strategy was to read in all the boards into a list, then as I draw
each bingo ball, replace all occurrences of the number drawn in on the
boards with an X. Then, check to see if we have 5 X&amp;#39;s in a row either
vertically or horizontally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reading was easy but there were some decisions to be made. I was going
to have a list of boards but what should a board look like? I didn&amp;#39;t
want to use a 2D array since that&amp;#39;s not Clojure&amp;#39;s strong suit but I
could easily use a list of lists (or vector of vectors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
((22 13 17 11  0)
 ( 8  2 23  4 24)
 (21  9 14 16  7)
 (6 10  3 18  5)
 (1 12 20 15 19))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I were coding in Python, I could do this as well using a list of lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This representation makes it &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; easy to check to see if we have a winner
going across but checking vertically is a little annoying and doing
the substitutions is also annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, I could represent the board as a list of 25 items
and use a mapping function to get to a specific row,col location such
as &lt;code&gt;index = board[row*5+col]&lt;/code&gt; . This representation makes checking the
board for winners a little onerous but marking squares with an X
becomes trivial - just replace all occurrences of the number in
question with an X. This can be done in Clojure using map:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;add-mark [board mark]
  (map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(= % mark) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;X&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; %) board))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thinking about it, it was really easy to switch from the list of 25
items to the list of list representations. We can do this with the
Clojure partition function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;    (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;partition&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;19&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;21&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt;))

    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; results in:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;;((0 1 2 3 4)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; (5 6 7 8 9 )&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; (10 11 12 13 14)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; (15 16 17 18 19)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; (20 21 22 23 24))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, we can use the 25 element list representation to mark the boxes
and then switch to the list of lists to check for a winner. What&amp;#39;s
better, we can transpose the list of lists, that is switch the rows
and columns so as to make the vertical check into a horizontal one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s my code to do all the checking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;has-five? [board]
  (&amp;gt;  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; board
           (map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(filter (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;fn &lt;/span&gt;[x] (= x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;X&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;))%)  ) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; keep only the Xs&lt;/span&gt;
           (map count) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; how many are there in each row&lt;/span&gt;
           (filter &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(= &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; % )) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; keep the winners (5 in a row)&lt;/span&gt;
           count) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; return true if we have any winners&lt;/span&gt;



(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;check-board [board]
  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[horiz (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;partition&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; board) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; convert 1D board to a 2D one&lt;/span&gt;
        vert  (apply mapv vector horiz)] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; transpose &lt;/span&gt;
    (or  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;has-five?&lt;/span&gt; horiz)
         (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;has-five?&lt;/span&gt; vert))))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, solving part 1 was easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;take the next ball&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mark all the locations with the ball&amp;#39;s number&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;see if there&amp;#39;s a winner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not, go back to step 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sure, we&amp;#39;re doing more transformations on the data than needed but
it&amp;#39;s clean and easy and at least from my point of view, made the whole
exercise much less error prone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On to part 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Turns out that was also pretty simple. Instead of stopping at the
first winning board we had to find the last winning board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pretty easy. We just had to modify the above procedure to the
following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;take the next ball&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mark all the locations wiht the ball&amp;#39;s number&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;remove any board that&amp;#39;s a winner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we&amp;#39;re down to one board remaining we&amp;#39;ve found the board&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not, back to step 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did this but first got a wrong answer. After looking at my results I
realized that I stopped when I got down to 1 board but it hadn&amp;#39;t
necessarily won yet. I had to then continue drawing balls and marking
squares until that final board was solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Upon later reflection, I realized my solution wasn&amp;#39;t perfect. It would
fail if there were some boards that were never solvable. This though
is an easy fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, maybe not a super clever super fast solution but a clean one that
works and is easy to understand and modify. To me that&amp;#39;s the
definition of a great solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work through the example!!!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day03/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 17:10:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2021-day03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s that time of year again. Yep, you got it. Time for &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/&#34;&gt;Advent of
Code&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m not feeling nearly as motivated as in past years but so far
so good. Finished the first three days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today I got a good reminder - work through your examples. You can find
today&amp;#39;s problem &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2021/day/3&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1 you got a list of binary numbers and had to figure out how
many ones and zeros there were in any given digit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if we had these numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
0010
0111 
1001
1010
1111
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The ones digit has 3 total ones and 2 zeros. The  2s digit has 4
ones and 1 zero. You then had to do some calculations based on if
there were more ones in a given column or more zeros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pretty straight forward. As usual, I&amp;#39;m working in Clojure so I used
map and reduce to figure out the number of ones in each column and
then did the required calculation. If you want to see the code, you
can find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021/blob/main/src/day03.clj&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Later in the day I looked at other people&amp;#39;s
solutions and it was interesting in that a lot of people approached it
differently - they basically looked at the list of numbers and rotated
it so that columns became rows and rows became columns which then make
counting ones and zeros easier,  but I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then had to rush through part 2 because I had to leave for the
ophthalmologist. I didn&amp;#39;t know if my eyes were going to be dilated and
if they were, I wasn&amp;#39;t going to be able to come back to the problem
until late in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got something done but unfortunately, didn&amp;#39;t quite
finish. Fortunately, my eyes weren&amp;#39;t dilated so after getting home I
set to finish the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 involved taking your list of numbers, calculating some values
using the part 1 code and then using those values to eliminate some of
the numbers. You then repeated this process until you were left with a
single number. See the problem statement and if you want my solution
for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got something working but my answer was incorrect. I spent, well,
frankly, too much time trying to figure out why. I was
stumped. Finally I went back to the example in the question and
actually worked through it (as opposed to glancing over it). I quickly
saw my error. I had calculated the part 1 values based on the original
data then kept applying those to the data list until it reduced to a
single number. I was supposed to recalculate the part 1 values on the
reduced data set each time instead. Once I realized this, it was a
pretty quick solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn&amp;#39;t the first time my carelessness cost me time. Back in 2016 I
spent way too long trying to fix an Advent of Code problem where the
problem was that I had the wrong parameters in a function (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this case, the moral of the story is &lt;strong&gt;work through the provided
examples!!!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s it for today. If you haven&amp;#39;t checked out Advent of Code, I
highly recommend it and if you want to see my solutions, however far I
get, you can find them &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2021&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, in the spirit of the season, Natan composed a new Chanukah
song.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re so inclined, you can check it out below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fatTWGfXO_o&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seats on a plane - addendum</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 07:15:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
While my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; was well received, I did have a few conversations
where people asked why I did this with such a seemingly minor ethical
issue. They wondered that with issues the Facebook algorithm, bail and
sentencing algorithms, gerrymandering and other issues dominating the
ethical conversation, why focus this topic around something that seems
to affect far fewer people and might not even be such a big
deal. After all, when it does come up, flight crews can probably ask a
few people to shuffle seats and voila, problem solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The thing is, this was intentional and it was intentional on two
fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, who decides if an issue is major or minor? Our perceptions
change throughout our lives and through our experiences. Something
that might appear to be minor to us or minor right now could be major
to someone else. I remember my first week teaching at Seward Park HS
right after I left industry. Such an eye opener. Even though I went to
public schools and faced my share of challenges, I had no idea how
different my students lives were from mine. Things that might have
been a minor inconvenience to me were a brick wall to them. It&amp;#39;s also
not enough to just view &amp;#34;slam dunk&amp;#34; issues through an ethical lens. We
have to indeed walk the walk. I wanted a mundane problem that may have
resulted from Innocent intent to illustrate that it&amp;#39;s not about
teaching a lesson on the topic du jour but rather it&amp;#39;s about
everything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also wanted to pick a topic that wasn&amp;#39;t right out there in the
mainstream. If I had them work on a recommendation system or some
other issue that&amp;#39;s been all over the news these days, they would have
all guessed the punchline. I thought this would be low key enough so
that they&amp;#39;d discover the ethical issue by inadvertently creating it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other reason was that I wanted to keep the issue simple and
understandable. I already suspected that the code aspect would be a
challenge for some members of the class. I didn&amp;#39;t want a super deep
ethical issue to cloud that side of the equation. A simple problem
kept everything clean. They first seated the customers, realized that
kids could be separated from parents, decided that this should be
addressed, then tried to address it. Keeping problem simple is a tried
and true teaching strategy. There&amp;#39;s so much complexity in most ethical
issues and most programming problems and students can only cope with
so much at a time. This was an attempt to keep the load to a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said in the earlier post. I think the lesson needs tweaking -
particularly in order to make the coding level appropriate but I also
think it&amp;#39;s a lesson worth keeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past week, the class has been working with regular expressions. I
get to deliver the punchline to that one tomorrow evening.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Airline Seats - An Ethics Lesson</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 14:43:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve held off on sharing any details on my Ethics in CS class because
I wanted to wait until some of it ran. I didn&amp;#39;t want to talk about a
topic and then find out that after we covered it I was all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that we&amp;#39;re well into the semester, I think it&amp;#39;s time to share a
few things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my premises when I designed the course was that most ethics
courses are taken by either people who already have religion or people
who see it as the &amp;#34;easy course&amp;#34; without programming. The few courses I
saw out there were largely based on case studies and
discussion. Nothing wrong with that - we&amp;#39;ve got that as well but I
wanted to try something a little different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to have the class play with some technical situation,
preferably with code, and then hopefully discover an ethical issue
after which we can discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here was my first attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the lesson has great potential but I also know it
needs tweaks. Most notably with teh level of comfort some of the
class had with Python. Next time around I want to address that issue
but I&amp;#39;ll talk about the specifics in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started by giving the class some code that provided a barebones
airline seating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s an empty plane. I just made windows and interior seats figuring
that windows were more desirable and didn&amp;#39;t have to differentiate them
from aisles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The code I provided also allowed for the purchase of an &amp;#34;economy plus&amp;#34;
ticket. An economy plus passenger could select their seat on
purchase. I had a function that with a 70% probability tried to select
a window seat and then it would just select a random seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You could also select a regular economy seat. For those, the airline
would assign a seat at some later point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s a plane where the economy plus seats have been sold and the
remaining seats are sold to economy but unassigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
ep-4          avail          avail          ep-2           ep-5
ep-8          avail          ep-19          avail          ep-11
ep-3          avail          avail          avail          ep-6
ep-1          avail          avail          avail          ep-9
ep-14         avail          avail          avail          ep-16
ep-15         avail          ep-20          avail          ep-18
ep-10         avail          ep-17          ep-24          ep-21
ep-13         ep-22          avail          avail          win
ep-23         avail          avail          avail          win
ep-7          avail          avail          avail          ep-12
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I asked the class to finish the routine that assigned the regular
economy seats. I also wrote a version that just assigned them
randomly. Here&amp;#39;s a sample result. Note that u-# represents a block of
purchased seats so you&amp;#39;ll notice u-1 appears multiple times
below. That passenger purchased multiple seats but they were assigned
all over the plane at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;

ep-13         u-6           u-1       ep-16      ep-24
ep-8          ep-15         u-9       u-3        ep-11
ep-22         ep-12         u-2       u-4        u-10
ep-9          ep-5          u-1       u-5        ep-25
ep-2          ep-21         ep-3      u-7        ep-17
ep-1          ep-23         u-8       u-8        ep-6
ep-14         u-12          ep-4      u-4        ep-26
ep-10         u-1           u-11      avail      ep-18
ep-20         u-6           u-11      u-9        u-2
ep-7          u-13          u-2       u-8        ep-19
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class was quick to notice that this could lead to families being
split apart and small children being seated away from parents. They
also noticed that this would affect poorer passengers more frequently
and to a greater extent than richer ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Great. Part 1 mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, the question became, should we do something about it and if so what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class noted that this was an unintended consequence of being
motivated purely by profit and airline convenience and that airlines
should do better. We also  noted that it&amp;#39;s not always so simple,
particularly if an airline is running on thin margins. Finally, we
discussed that this situation was real and in fact did result in
changes in regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following week, we discussed possible alternatives. How they might
work better and how they might affect an airlines bottom lines and if
that should really matter. We also discussed how similar ethical
scenarios might play out in other industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final piece, students had a long term assignment to code up an
updated algorithm that did better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the long and short of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d like to think that by playing with the code, discovering the
dilemma and then trying to fix it led to a deeper appreciation of the
ethical issue and to be honest, the one big thing I want my teachers
to walk away with is more awareness of potential issues and that many
of them are not as obvious or simple as &amp;#34;stop doing that&amp;#34; even though
we&amp;#39;d like them to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, I&amp;#39;ve got to work on some things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost my teachers came in with varying programming
backgrounds. They all completed a data structures in Java course over
the summer but a good number were not that comfortable with Python. I
covered Python over the first couple of weeks but I think I have to be
more structured with that in the future. More specific assignments
rather than giving them as much freedom as I did. I also think I&amp;#39;d
move this unit down in the syllabus - later after some smaller
programming assignments and then finally, I&amp;#39;d scaffold it
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even so, I think it was worthwhile and a keeper. I think it could also
be a nice ethics assignment in any programming class that covers 2D
arrays or something similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a couple of other units that follow this do it and discover
theme. Once those happen I&amp;#39;ll report back on them as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 80 Vertico, Marginalia, Consult, and Embark</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-80-vertico/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 16:38:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-80-vertico/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
In today&amp;#39;s video, we&amp;#39;ll take a look at a few new completion frameworks
for Emacs. For years I&amp;#39;ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper&#34;&gt;Ivy&lt;/a&gt; and have been very happy with
it but since I decided to rebuild my Emacs config from scratch I
thought I&amp;#39;d try the new kids on the block, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/raxod502/selectrum&#34;&gt;Selectrum&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minad/vertico&#34;&gt;Vertico&lt;/a&gt; along
with some support packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve liked Ivy from day one and still do. To be honest, from a day to day point of
view, I didn&amp;#39;t notice much difference between Ivy and the newcomers
but I do like their philosophies - they&amp;#39;re supposed to be simple and
minimalist and focus on the Emacs completion API without extending
it. You can read about their respective philosophies on their GitHub
pages. Conveniently, both have sections comparing themselves with the
other frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For configurations, I just cut and pasted the suggested configs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ultimately I settled on Vertico but both are worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The video shows off Vertico but arguably more importantly, it covers
some of the ancillary packages. First, although I don&amp;#39;t show much
about them are Prescient and Orderless - they let you control how your
selections pop up. I&amp;#39;m using Orderless which lets me search for
components by typing partial completions and using spaces to separate
but it lets you do it in any order. What I mean is that if I&amp;#39;m looking
for the command &amp;#34;vertico-mode&amp;#34; I can search by typing something like
&amp;#34;vert mode&amp;#34; which is what I&amp;#39;ve always done, but I can also do the
search for &amp;#34;mo vert&amp;#34; - typing the second part first. That&amp;#39;s pretty
slick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next is Marginalia which brings up extra context information when you
search for things. Things like command descriptions or file modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The third one we look at is Consult which is basically a collection of
useful commands using completions. Basically an answer to Ivy&amp;#39;s
Counsel commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, and this is the show stopper, the video shows Embark. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-6-swiper/&#34;&gt;My post/video on Ivy/Swiper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/raxod502/prescient.el&#34;&gt;Prescient&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oantolin/orderless&#34;&gt;Orderless&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/raxod502/selectrum&#34;&gt;Selectrum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minad/vertico&#34;&gt;Vertico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minad/marginalia/&#34;&gt;Marginalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minad/consult&#34;&gt;Consult&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oantolin/embark/&#34;&gt;Embark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and of course, the video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5ffb2at2d7w&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning 54</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 13:59:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, tomorrow, October 19, is my birthday. The big 5 4. Okay, maybe it&amp;#39;s not a
traditionally big one. It doesn&amp;#39;t end in a zero or a five but I think
it rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why? Because it&amp;#39;s one shy of 55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the magic age when I can retire collect my pension should I
choose to do so. It&amp;#39;s what you get when start young and put in over
30 years of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago I would have given an emphatic &amp;#34;no.&amp;#34; Now, I&amp;#39;m starting
to think &amp;#34;maybe.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ve written a few times here about feeling some
burnout and a lot less joy. Part of that&amp;#39;s covid and part of it&amp;#39;s doing
more than two full time jobs. Another factor is that by summer 2023,
actually, summer 2022, I&amp;#39;ll have pretty much accomplished everything
I&amp;#39;ve set out to do here. On top of this, Devorah will be able to
retire before I can so that also weighs in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. There&amp;#39;s a lot I like about Hunter and a lot I
still enjoy about my job but there&amp;#39;s stuff that&amp;#39;s just wearing me
down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of what happens, I plan to stay in the game in some
capacity. I want to figure out a situation where Devorah and I can
travel more - my one big regret, but I think I&amp;#39;ve still got something
to contribute to the CS Ed world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we can trim down my workload at Hunter and eliminate the things that
stress me out, I could be there a long time. If not, well, we&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the time being, I&amp;#39;ll enjoy tomorrow. Nothing particularly
special - normal work day followed by a family dinner. Actually,
whole family dinner is always special, just not unusual for us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feeling like an English teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 14:40:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So I&amp;#39;m teaching my Ethics and CS class for the first time. I
originally designed the course but didn&amp;#39;t teach it the first time
around. That honor went to my friend, Master Teacher Topher
Mykolyk. He of course did an amazing job - impossible to
follow. Fortunately, this is a different cohort so they don&amp;#39;t know how
great Topher was for the course :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though I have the syllabus and Topher&amp;#39;s notes from last time
around, first time through is very week to week but I think I&amp;#39;m
starting to get my legs under me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This course is very different from what I&amp;#39;ve taught in the past. It&amp;#39;s
also  different from the ethics courses I&amp;#39;ve seen currently out
there. Specifically, I wanted a programming component in the
course. Still, there&amp;#39;s a lot more open ended discussion and opinion
based stuff going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mean, when you do a class on an algorithm like mergesort or a
construct like a loop, it is what it is. You can motivate it in
different ways and engage the class but there&amp;#39;s only one punch line
and it&amp;#39;s set in advance. Here things are a lot looser. Most issues
have two sides and even when most of the class is on one like when we
talked about predictive policing, we can still
effectively play devil&amp;#39;s advocate for the other side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It can also lead to the class going sideways. Yesterday we were
talking about basic web privacy. Tracking, cookies and the like. In my
mind I had the lesson mapped out. First, our &amp;#34;weekly ethicacy&amp;#34; student
presentation and then a short breakout, discussion on the info we
share, and then curated questions and resources  that we&amp;#39;d use in a
sequence of breakout room and whole class discussions. The trouble is,
after the first short breakout, the student conversation went directly
to what I had intended for our async work over the course of the
week. Oh well, time to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/&#34;&gt;call an audible&lt;/a&gt;. It wasn&amp;#39;t really a big deal,
the conversation moved in a different direction but it was still very
much in the wheelhouse of the day&amp;#39;s topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Must be what an English class can be like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the course is doing well but I won&amp;#39;t know for sure
until afterwards when I can debrief with the students. After all,
they&amp;#39;re the ones that ultimately determine if the class is successful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the next few weeks I&amp;#39;ll share some specifics about the class. The
programming stuff in particular. Can&amp;#39;t do that now because we&amp;#39;re in
the middle and I don&amp;#39;t want any members of the class who might be
reading this to see the reveal before it&amp;#39;s time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 79 Project</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-79-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2021 11:24:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-79-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the comments on my last video talked about the new project
management support Emacs includes in it&amp;#39;s latest version -
project.el. I remembered reading about it when it rolled around but
then forgot and never checked it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Up until recently when working in projects I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bbatsov/projectile&#34;&gt;Projectile&lt;/a&gt;, a great
package by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bbatsov&#34;&gt;Bozhidar Batsov&lt;/a&gt;, also known as Bug. I only used it when
doing development work - that&amp;#39;s when I find myself jumping around
within a group of related files. At other times, I&amp;#39;m pretty much in
one file, do my thing, then move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wrote a post and did a video on Projectile a while ago - you can
check it out [[&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-33-projectile-jump/&#34;&gt;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-33-projectile-jump/&lt;/a&gt;
][here]].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned in the last video, I decided to rebuild my Emacs config
from scratch and I&amp;#39;m trying to be a bit more minimalist so with that
reminder I got, I figure it&amp;#39;s time to check out the now built in
project.el. If it&amp;#39;s as good as projectile, or even, good enough, it
could be a nice alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At it&amp;#39;s core, project.el works similarly to projectile. There&amp;#39;s a
prefix key an then an action which is restricted to your project. For
projectile, it was &lt;code&gt;C-c p&lt;/code&gt; and the default for project.el is &lt;code&gt;C-x
p&lt;/code&gt;. No big difference there. Projectile seems to have many many more
options but in general, I find that all I need is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switch to a project - &lt;code&gt;C-x p p&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find or open a file in a project - &lt;code&gt;C-x p f&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switch buffers in a project - &lt;code&gt;C-x p b&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delete all the project buffers - &lt;code&gt;C-x p k&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;List the project buffers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project.el has all except listing all the buffers. It also supports a
few other features that I think I&amp;#39;ll find useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;project dired - &lt;code&gt;C-x p d&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;project shell (or eshell) &lt;code&gt;C-x p s&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;project regex search and variants &lt;code&gt;C-x p g&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not sure if projectile has these. It probably does and I could see
them being useful. I probable won&amp;#39;t use the regex searches much
because I&amp;#39;ll likely use other tools for those like consult-ripgrep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, it certainly seems like project.el has enough coverage for my
purposes. Another difference between the two projects is that
project.el only supports a couple of project definitions - things that
are supported by Emacs&amp;#39; VC system ad things supported by Emacs EDE
thing (which I&amp;#39;ve never really played with). I seem to recall
Projectile being more flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, project.el looks like it&amp;#39;s a nice simple alternative at
least for me. Check out the video for the runthrough:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UagDCTjcifY&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My project grading workflow</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-78-grading/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 10:44:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-78-grading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Grading sucks. Even for a well crafted assignment it takes time and
rarely does it give you the same insights into your students as you
can get from just observing them and working with them, at least when
the environment supports you doing so. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This leads lots of teachers to go to auto graders. I can&amp;#39;t bring
myself going along with that. While assignments are imperfect and
tedious to grade, they do provide some insight to your students and
that&amp;#39;s an important part about being a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I always keep my eye out for ways to improve my project gradiing
workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the video below, I step through my process. It&amp;#39;s mostly Emacs but I
also use GitHub classroom and the terminal along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re here as for the Emacs, I&amp;#39;d any thoughts on alternatives or
improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re here as a teacher, I&amp;#39;d love to hear what your flow is like
and what tools you use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7HLVcQi8GGk&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching non required topics - the command line</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/non-required-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 08:56:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/non-required-topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
The other day I saw Allen Holub lamenting on how students don&amp;#39;t learn
the command line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;All my students this semester have gone through at least a year of programming classes, and some of them do not know how to do even basic stuff on the command-line. This strikes me as a huge flaw in the curriculum. Maybe the first CS class should be How Devs Use Computers 101.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Allen Holub (@allenholub) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/allenholub/status/1444393138492116992?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 2, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This reminded  me of the recent article and
discussion on how students &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pcgamer.com/students-dont-know-what-files-and-folders-are-professors-say/&#34;&gt;don&amp;#39;t know what files and folders are&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Neither of these are surprising. Back in the day, computer science
classes were populated with self selecting stereotypes and in order to
get anything done you had to be familiar with your tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wrote about this &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-15-kids-know-nuttin/&#34;&gt;years ago&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays, CS is trying to be more open and inviting and with more
modern tools you no longer need to know about files
and folders let alone a Unix command line.  Back in the day, even if
you used a program like Microsoft Word you&amp;#39;d have some idea of a file
folder structure but now with the cloud and tools like Google Docs you
just search for your documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The issue is that many CS teachers want students to know the command
line but it&amp;#39;s not part of the formal curriculum. What&amp;#39;s more, the
value of command line expertise is debatable and pretty hard to assess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I&amp;#39;m a big command line wonk. I think you gain tremendous
power and flexibility if you use it but I also recognize that there
are many career tech professionals, particularly these days that will
never use it and arguably won&amp;#39;t really benefit from it. They live in
their IDE that supports their language. It integrates with their
build, test, and debugging tools and their company&amp;#39;s commuication
platform is also right there on the side. Now, many people in tech
could still benefit from command line expertise but try convincing a
first or second year undergrad where they not only don&amp;#39;t see added
value but also see that a large chunk of the text world also doesn&amp;#39;t
see the value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you do believe that the command line is important and want
students to learn it, how do you do it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are plenty of tutorials, videos and other learning material
including clever games like &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/slackermedia/bashcrawl&#34;&gt;bashcrawl&lt;/a&gt; and I guess you could &amp;#34;force&amp;#34;
students to use the command line while in the classroom but nothing&amp;#39;s
going to stop them from using the file browser tool or an installed
IDE. Even if you severely limit the tools in lab machines, you have no
control over what they use at home and while the command line might be
more powerful, it&amp;#39;s not nearly as learner friendly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there&amp;#39;s assessment. How do you do that? You could give
memorization type questions on exams but that&amp;#39;s a really bad
idea. Since the command line is process not product, this is a tough
nut to crack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, I&amp;#39;ve struggled with this year after year and don&amp;#39;t have
a great solution. I try to encourage the command line and model how it
can be useful as much as I can but I know I&amp;#39;m only reaching a minority
of my students. In the end, I don&amp;#39;t really care if any of them
ultimately become hardcore CLI users but I really do want all of them
to gain enough exposure so that they can make an informed decision as
to its value and then make up their own minds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coding For Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/coding-for-problem-solving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 10:17:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/coding-for-problem-solving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Like most CS educators I&amp;#39;m a regular reader of Alfred Thompson&amp;#39;s
blog. Alfred&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.acthompson.net/2021/09/define-learn-to-code.html&#34;&gt;latest post&lt;/a&gt; is spot on but there was a line in it and a
particular Twitter response that reminded me that we so often forget
a big reason why people learn to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alfred mentions, as did that Tweet about coding to solve
problems. What problem are you trying to solve. This is the mainstream
push - programming helps you solve problems. I&amp;#39;ve noticed a doubling
down on this with all the efforts (including mine) to integrate CS
into other subjects. While where and how much CS should be
integrated vs standalone is a topic for another day, integrating CS
into other fields is very much a &amp;#34;help solve the problems of that
field&amp;#34; approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nothing wrong with all of this. It&amp;#39;s all good stuff but there&amp;#39;s
another side to the coin. It&amp;#39;s a side that I sometimes forget about
from in the trenches. In fact, a few years ago I was rambling on and
on about programming as problem solving and my friend and fellow CS
teacher Peter Brooks reminded me - the question doesn&amp;#39;t have to be
&amp;#34;what problem do you want to solve?&amp;#34; The question can be &amp;#34;what do you
want to create?&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes we forget that programming can be an amazingly creative
endeavor. You can use it to make something brand new and there doesn&amp;#39;t
necessarily have to be a problem to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fred Brooks puts it nicely at the start of his classic work &amp;#34;The
Mythical Man Month:&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The programmer, like the poet, works only slightly removed from pure
thought-stuff. He builds his castles in the air, from air, creating by
exertion of the imagination. Few media of creation are so flexible, so
easy to polish and rework, so readily capable of realizing grand
conceptual structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 Fred Brooks, The Mythical Man Month &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also saw elsewhere, maybe by Fred Brooks, maybe someone else talking
of a programmer being like a painter but whereas a painter has oils,
brushes, and pigments to create on a canvas, the programmer has
programming languages to create on the computer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe it&amp;#39;s the push for &amp;#34;practical&amp;#34; education, maybe the integration,
maybe the focus on testing. I have no idea but it seems that we
frequently forget about the creative side of the equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mean, yes, the APCS-P specification does mention creativity in the
interestingly enough named &amp;#34;Create Task:&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming is a collaborative and creative process that brings ideas
to life through the development of software. In the Create performance
task, you will design and implement a program that might solve a
problem, enable innovation, explore personal interests, or express
creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but it&amp;#39;s after &amp;#34;solve a problem&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;enable innovation.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That creative side though shouldn&amp;#39;t be forgotten. Some of my students
most memorable projects didn&amp;#39;t solve a problem. I remember the
&amp;#34;Cheerleader Simulator&amp;#34; in NetLogo. No problem solved there but it was
a fun project. Another was Tamika&amp;#39;s stupid mouse dexterity game. A
simple game of her own design. I say stupid not becuase it was really
stupid - it was great. Rather, I say stupid becuase that game caused
me to waste so much time that end of year when I should have been
grading!!!!!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we seek to engage a wider audience in CS we shouldn&amp;#39;t merely focus
on the problem solving nor the making money. The creative side is
really important as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning a good class into a bad lecture</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/inperson-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 08:11:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/inperson-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been teaching in person for about a month now so I thought I&amp;#39;d
give a quick update on how it&amp;#39;s going. I&amp;#39;ve written before about my
feelings on how Hunter started the semester (TL;DR - I was very
displeased) but that&amp;#39;s not the point of this post. As of today, I
believe every student has been required to be stabbed at least once
and on October 11, all students must be fully vaccinated to be on
campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, off to the report. Going in person sounds great but now that I&amp;#39;m
doing it, I&amp;#39;m having second thoughts. Let&amp;#39;s leave safety precausions
out of it, I&amp;#39;m having second thoughts just in terms of how the current
situation and related restrictions have affected my teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the low down. Students are supposed to wear masks at all
times and I wear mine as well. We&amp;#39;re supposed to socially distance but
that&amp;#39;s not possible given class and classroom sizes. Students are also
supposed to keep the same seed all the time, ostensibly for contact
tracing should anyone test positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, day one in person was important - I still haven&amp;#39;t met my
students from last year in person and I&amp;#39;d really like to. This years
students, at least I&amp;#39;ve seen all their foreheads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s actually an issue. At least for me, the masks make it MUCH
harder to know my students. Can&amp;#39;t get to know a face when you can&amp;#39;t
see two thirds of it and names are going to be even harder for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Online, at least for those who put on cameras, we could at least see
each others full faces and expressions. Zoom doesn&amp;#39;t carry the same
nuance as in person but neither does a masked face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The masks have another negative. You can&amp;#39;t hear anyone. I do my best
to actively project but students rarely do. This leads to me having
students repeat themselves multiple times and I also have to adopt a
conference speaker approach of repeating and projecting what the
student said so everyone can hear. This absolutely kills interactive
discussion and even question answer chains. It really pushes a lesson
more towards a lecture which, well, sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The social distancing and keeping seats also negatively impact the
environment. I can&amp;#39;t get in with my students like I usually do. Even
when in lecture mode, I&amp;#39;ll move to different locations of the room for
a variety of reasons - that&amp;#39;s pretty much out. I also can&amp;#39;t just get
in close to support students. Likewise, group work can&amp;#39;t happen in the
same way. They can kind of sort of work with their direct neighbor but
I can&amp;#39;t have them work with each other as I&amp;#39;d do under normal
circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. I won&amp;#39;t compromise safety for convenience but the
safety protocols do a good job in turning a good class into a bad
lecture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Online is also lousy in many ways but as long as the students are
willing you can all see each others faces and you can do all sorts of
interesting groupings and group work. I think my code review lesson
worked pretty much as well and maybe even better online last year than
it did in person the year before but I&amp;#39;m really at a loss on how to do
it as effectively in person in a few weeks with the safety
precautions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ideally, I&amp;#39;d like the freedom to mix and match. We were in person week
one, but let me decide when we&amp;#39;ll be in person and when we&amp;#39;ll be
remote. Let me use the best platform for any given lesson. This would
be a bit of a drag on the students depending on how their instructors
scheduled things but if students could use the rooms that they&amp;#39;d be in
person for as locations to work remote from it wouldn&amp;#39;t be too bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, the ideal would be to trust the teacher and let them do
what&amp;#39;s best for their students but as we all know, that&amp;#39;s never the
way. Regardless, the interesting thing to me is that while I was
clamoring for a safe in person return, the truth is, given sensible
safety precautions, in person might just not be the best way to go. At
least not all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How The Hash Is Made</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/how-the-hash-is-made/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 17:08:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/how-the-hash-is-made/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Following up on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-they-used-to-know/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Soon after I read that tweet, I read Julia&amp;#39;s post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://jvns.ca/blog/2021/09/10/hashmaps-make-things-fast/&#34;&gt;hash tables&lt;/a&gt;. This
got me thinking more about what is and isn&amp;#39;t taught in school. Hash
tables were always taught in CS programs but back in the day you might
not have used them much after your data structures or algorithms
classes. Nowadays you&amp;#39;re much more likely to use them as they&amp;#39;re built
in to so many platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hash tables and related structures are great - I use them all the time
but they can also become a go to without thinking it through. This
actually came up in conversation with the same my high level SE friend
at that big bank from the last post. He also noticed that many interviewees would always
go right to the hash table even when there were red flags in the
question to warn away fro them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a hash table to get you that nice fast expected constant time
performance, it has to be sparse - few collisions. If you implement a
closed hash table (all the data is in a single array) and there&amp;#39;s not
a lot of spare space, it will fill up and all of a sudden that O(1)
insertion and retrieval time will go linear. I can&amp;#39;t say for certain
but I&amp;#39;m guessing the vast majority of Python programmers who use hash
tables (dictionaries) all the time don&amp;#39;t really know this or if they
do never think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is this a byproduct of using the built in implementations in college
combined with self taught programmers never seeing this at all? Maybe
but this was probably a deficiency even in my day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This also came up when I accidentally interviewed for a position at
Google. There was a question about storing and accessing a bunch of
data. I don&amp;#39;t remember the question but there was a key line - &amp;#34;you
have unlimited storage&amp;#34; which is the trigger phrase for &amp;#34;use a hash
table.&amp;#34; I got a kick out of it but felt this was a you know it or you
don&amp;#39;t. I think I mentioned it to the interviewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This also brought to mind another example. Not mine - I read this in
John Bentley&amp;#39;s terrific book &lt;a href=&#34;https://tfetimes.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ProgrammingPearls2nd.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Programming Pearls.&amp;#34;&lt;/a&gt; The gist was that a
room full of very smart people were implementing a binary search. The
idea is that you have an array of data that is sorted and instead of
looking through every item one at a time, you calculate the middle of
the array, look there and then, if you haven&amp;#39;t found the item, you
throw away half the data and repeat the process with the remaining
half.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Every now and then, the implementations had a problem and nobody could
figure out why. As it turns out, in calculating the midpoint, they&amp;#39;d
add the lower value and the higher value and then divide the sum by
two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sounds reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem was that when low and high were at the upper end of the
data set the addition would go past the largest integer wrapping
around and causing wonky results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pretty subtle error but at least you&amp;#39;ve got a shot at figuring it out
if you understand integer sizes and how they work on your machine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having some solid low level knowledge won&amp;#39;t prevent this bug from
cropping up but it will give you a fighting chance at fixing it if it
does. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This particular problem probably won&amp;#39;t come up these days as integers
are MUCH larger than back in the day but I think it illustrates the
point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, just more food for thought on how CS Education has changed
over the years, what we leave in, and what we leave out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What They Used To Know</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-they-used-to-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 10:42:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-they-used-to-know/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw this tweet by Julia Evans the other day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;if you&amp;#39;ve
been working in computing for &amp;gt; 15 years -- are there fundamentals
that you learned &amp;quot;on the job&amp;quot; 15 years ago that you think
most people aren&amp;#39;t learning on the job today?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(I&amp;#39;m
thinking about how for example nobody has ever paid me to write C
code)&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Evans (@b0rk) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/b0rk/status/1435965181847343108?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September
9, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never met Julia but have been following her on Twitter and
reading her &lt;a href=&#34;https://jvns.ca/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; for some time now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The tweet got me thinking. Not so much about learning on the job but
rather on how colleges prepare their students. Recent boutique majors
and concentrations notwithstanding, a degree in CS seems to have
largely stayed the same from the early/mid 1980s when I got my BA to
today. There are variations but it was and still is largely&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;programming&amp;gt;data structures&amp;gt;algorithms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;some systems or OS stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;some theory &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;math: calc 1, calc 2, discrete, linear, maybe stats&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;another requirement or two which might differ based on institution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;electives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, programs have changed over the years. At one point, computer
graphics was hot. Now, not so much. Courses like compilers also used
to be required more frequently but overall things look much the
same. That said, there have been some major changes - at least from my
perspective and those changes really affected how students were
prepared for professional careers. Now of course this is only my
perspective so who knows how accurate it is. Regardless, it should be
good food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got my BA back in the mid 80s. That was the start of the PC
generation. Colleges were starting to get computer labs full of
IBM-PCs and then  later clones. MS-DOS ruled the day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What did that mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It meant that while a few years prior, students used a time sharing
system for their programming classes now they were using  an
IBM-PC with Turbo Pascal. I can&amp;#39;t say for sure but looking back, it
seemed that people educated in PC heavy programs had a weaker sense of
all those issues that come with multiple people and multiple processes
happening on a machine at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, having a relatively simple computer - one that you
had full control over may have led to an easier time in understanding
the low level ins and outs. You could learn about low level issues on
a PC and really understand everything. That doesn&amp;#39;t seem to happen as
much nowadays when even our personal computers and computing devices
run more like those multi user computers of old than the single
process no threads IBM-PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was an opportunity to recapture this right before the Arduino
got big. The Arduino was based on an Atmel processer with a small
instruction set - a platform where a student could understand
everything from wire to application. For all the good that the Arduion
and related projects have led to, they&amp;#39;ve abstracted that low level
away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few years later Java became a popular college CS language followed
by Python. Both of these took memory management out of the core
programming-&amp;gt;data structures-&amp;gt;algorithms sequence. Sure, you probably got to
learn a bit about memory management and related issues in your systems
classes but I have to believe you didn&amp;#39;t really own that knowledge
like you would have had you had to manage memory throughout the core
courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m not knocking the change. Moving to Java brought some
improvements and so does moving to Python. It&amp;#39;s just that as a
language or platform giveth it also taketh away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The interesting things here is that the changes I noticed were not
directly intended but rather byproducts of changes made for other
reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A final unintended consequence I noticed also seems to be a byproduct
of the Java revolution. Years ago after many programs had adopted
Java I was talking to a friend who was a high level SE at a big NY
bank. At the time finance was NY&amp;#39;s biggest tech employer. I think
Google might have recently moved to NY but wasn&amp;#39;t yet the player
they&amp;#39;d become - this was pre-IPO days and NY tech hadn&amp;#39;t yet
exploded. My friend was lamenting after a long day of interviews. None
of his interviewees - all from top rated CS colleges could handle what
he viewed as easy algorithm questions. Questions a that were
considered close to trivial by his interviewees from a few years
back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After some discussion, we developed a theory. It might not be true but
looking around the landscape in the months and years following that
discussion, it might hold some water. With the acceptance of Java
students were now, more frequently using library calls. The .sort
method, the built in List, Tree, Map, and Set classes and more. This
is not to say that the students hadn&amp;#39;t learned about, say, the
mergesort in their data structures or algorithms classes but rather
they didn&amp;#39;t live it. Maybe  they did a quick implementation but then
it was gone from their memories.  Back in the day, most people in my
peer group started in Pascal and frequently moved to C. Even though C
had it&amp;#39;s built in sort, we coded our own more frequently. We also
didn&amp;#39;t have easy access to all the data structure and algorithm
libraries that Java had so we rolled our own and continued to use
them. When kids who did that interviewed, they could more easily see
how an interview problem related to an algorithm they coded and
tweaked half a dozen times. On the other hand, those that saw it once
and moved to a library didn&amp;#39;t have that in depth understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, this is not to say that it was better in the old days. When they
removed memory management, they were able to add other
topics. Likewise when students didn&amp;#39;t need to implement their own
version of everything for their class projects, instructors could
steer students towards learning other new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not making a judgement call on better or worse but rather that
even without formal curricular changes the strengths and weaknesses of
our CS graduates have changed over the years quite possibly as a
result of unintended consequences of a variety of decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also don&amp;#39;t this only happens in CS. Take a look at math - the big
one would probably be bringing the calculator to the classroom. The in
your face change was the idea that on the one hand, students would
become weaker in arithmetic and manual calculation. On the other hand,
time could be spent on what might be considered richer topics due to
time saved. Lost in the shuffle were topics like linear
interpolation - a useful skill taught to navigate log and trig
tables. Those skills would be forever lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there&amp;#39;s my rant and ramble inspired by Julia&amp;#39;s post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A day after I saw the tweet I saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://jvns.ca/blog/2021/09/10/hashmaps-make-things-fast/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Julia. Unless some
shiny object distracts me I think I want to look at how the unintended
consequences from some of the changes I mentioned directly relates to
it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Memorable Lesson (at least for one student)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/a-memorable-lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 13:31:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/a-memorable-lesson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Back to calling an audible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Around seven years ago I was visiting with some former students at
Google in Mountain View. One of them from way back in the late 90s,
Pawel, out of the blue said there was one lesson I taught that was
particularly memorable. Not memorable in the &amp;#34;that was fun&amp;#34; way like
maybe my Halloween adventures but memorable in that he felt he got a
lot more out of it than a normal lesson. Pawel mentioned a few of the
things he still remembered about a lesson he saw over two decades
earlier. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was, in fact, one of the first big CS audibles that I can
remember calling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was second semester APCS - probably right after the AB exam. I
guess I&amp;#39;d been teaching around seven years so I&amp;#39;d classify myself as
an advanced beginner. I also hadn&amp;#39;t done any serious programming and
problem solving since I started teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Was I a fraud?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Impostor syndrome was creeping in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back then I had a bunch of students who participated in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://usaco.org/&#34;&gt;USACO&lt;/a&gt; and
would discuss the programming from their competitions. While I talked
a good game, I started to wonder if I could back it up. Should I
really be telling these kids about best practices for problem solving
ad programming if I just talked the talk and couldn&amp;#39;t walk the walk?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To test myself, I decided to work through some of the competition problems. I figured
that I didn&amp;#39;t have to be able to solve the hardest of the hard ones
since only the best of the best solved in that stratosphere but if I
should be able to solve or at least approach most of the advanced
problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After some problem solving and coding I felt much better about
myself. I wasn&amp;#39;t living a lie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I particularly liked the Digit Pals problem. Question 4 from the
1996-1997 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.angelfire.com/ca2/lorddave/usa974.html&#34;&gt;National Championship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to class a few days later. Early in the period, for some
reason, I wasn&amp;#39;t happy with where things were going so I decided to
totally change directions. I decided I&amp;#39;d do a lesson that was
basically a walkthrough of my problem solving and coding process for
Digit Pals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started by looking at the problem, working through example and then
some of the things we discussed included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;data representation (2D array)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the high level logic of removing a digit pal (recursive flood fill)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the high level logic of sliding down and over&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;how to solve the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the overall solver, I decided to go with a straightforward, blind,
recursive search. I figured it would be fast enough for two
reasons. First, I figured that since, if you remove the digit pal at
any location, it&amp;#39;s the same as removing that pal from any of it&amp;#39;s
locations so that there would likely be many many solutions and
second, there was a line in the problem statement saying that your
solution might not work on large cases. In any event, when all was
said and done and they released the test data, my solution worked
within time constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the design phase, I went to the live coding with a focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;compiling and testing every concept. That is, a single loop, a
single if, a function etc.. This may sound excessive but I&amp;#39;ve been
doing this forever and it&amp;#39;s served me well as a hobbyist and as a
professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implementing the data structure first - a 2D array and then a way
to print it so that I could always tell the state of my program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;incremental development - first remove a pal, then slide down, then
over, then the solver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it was all over the problem was solved. I&amp;#39;d like to think that
the students got something out of the audible. I learned years later
that at least one student did. As a teacher, I also got a lot out of
it. That day might not have been my first live coding lesson but it&amp;#39;s
the earliest one I remember. It was all impromptu but it got me
thinking more deeply about how I approach problem solving and
programming as well as how to teach both. Even all the little things
like my compulsive compiling and testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Funny - I have no idea what I was originally going to teach that day
but that audible turned into both a lesson I&amp;#39;ve repeated many times
as well as concrete techniques that I&amp;#39;ve used over and over through
the years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should every assignment be open ended?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/creative-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 06:43:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/creative-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.acthompson.net/2021/09/are-you-assigning-projects-or-recipes.html&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; by my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alfredtwo&#34;&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt; caught my eye yesterday. It&amp;#39;s a good
post - some good examples of inserting student creativity even into small
intro level assignments. While I like the post and agree with the
sentiment of open ended, student driven projects, I had to take issue
with the lead quote Alfred used: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you assign a project and get back 30 of the same thing, thats not
a project, that is a recipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 Chris Lehmann&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Open ended projects and student driven assignments are great and
important but so are ones with similar or identical solutions and
they&amp;#39;re also not recipes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, there&amp;#39;s a certain level of utility in a uniform assignment. If
the assignment is &amp;#34;write a program to convert Fahrenheit to Celsius&amp;#34;
you know that all the students know the conversion as you can provide
it and it also allows them to easily check their work, either through
an autograder or with each other. Yes, I know, some students students
could be tempted to cut corners and copy solutions but usually
attempts to control cheating do more to constrain students doing
things the right way than to prevent the cheaters from cheating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also, some student, particularly early on need the structure of a set
assignment and don&amp;#39;t do as well with a &amp;#34;do anything assignment.&amp;#34;
Saying &amp;#34;just make a converter&amp;#34; can be much more stressful and
difficult than convert from pounds to kilograms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to recipes? Not necessarily. Let&amp;#39;s take this small assignment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given two variables &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt;, write a code fragment that will swap
the values represented by &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt;. That is, if at the start, &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt;
represented &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt; represented &lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;, after your code, &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; would
represent &lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt; would represent &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You could even add a hint:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HINT:&lt;/strong&gt; Consider using an extra third variable in your solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn&amp;#39;t a recipe, it&amp;#39;s an assignment. Even with the hint it doesn&amp;#39;t
tell the students exactly what to do, just the desired outcome. It&amp;#39;s
not a recipe but most or all of the solutions will look remarkably
similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By contrast, a swap &amp;#34;recipe&amp;#34; might read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a new variable named &lt;strong&gt;extraBucket&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assign the value currently in &lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;extraBucket&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assign the value currently in &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assign the value currently in &lt;strong&gt;extraBucket&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a recipe. A student would literally just rewrite the steps
into the solution but even this might have it&amp;#39;s place in a class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A more advanced assignment that leads students through building and
understanding something like a merge or quicksort could be set up
similarly. Not in any way a recipe but rather a valuable exercise
where all the students end up with very similar solutions. This is not
necessarily a bad thing, in fact it was all the rage a few years ago
as it could be set up as a discovery or experiential learning
experience. I also poo pooed that as being the silver bullet but as
with most teaching techniques, it has its place. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there are opportunities to introduce student creativity even when
the assignments are, at their core, all the same. I recall a session
at either SIGCSE or CSTA by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bootstrapworld.org/&#34;&gt;Bootstrapworld&lt;/a&gt;. They were describing one
of their classes major projects. It was a game. I forget the details
but at the core, all the student projects were the same. They differed
only in the graphics they used and the story around the game. That&amp;#39;s
where Boostrapworld interjected student creativity but the core CS and
math of the student projects were all the same. Did the fact that all
the assignments were essentially the same make this bad or a recipe?
Certainly not. Students go to express themselves uniquely but at the
same time the assignment was constrained and focused on what the
Bootstrapworld designers wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there you have it. There&amp;#39;s nothing wrong with assignments where
the student results are largely the same. There&amp;#39;s also nothing wrong
with student projects that are 100% open ended. It&amp;#39;s all about the
teacher having multiple tools and using them as appropriate for their
students. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calling an audible</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 13:48:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Be ready to call an audible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was advice I got during my third year teaching. I had just
transferred from Seward Park to Stuy and was being observed for the
first time by my former teacher and now supervisor Richie
Rothenberg. I forget exactly what the lesson was on - something with
coordinate geometry I think. The lesson was okay but it wasn&amp;#39;t going
over well with the class. I was teaching at too low a level for my
audience. I could feel it as I was teaching but as I was pretty
inexperienced I wasn&amp;#39;t confident in changing things up on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, Richie and I debriefed. He said the lesson was
satisfactory - the magic word you need on any observation but that it
could have been much better. I had only been teaching at Stuy for a
few weeks and even though I was a Stuy grad I hadn&amp;#39;t had time to get
my head around where the students were at. Richie said that sometimes
you just have to call an audible. For a young teacher, easier said
than done. In addition to not having a great handle on my students yet
I also wasn&amp;#39;t confident in flying without a net. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is why it&amp;#39;s so important for teachers to really know their
stuff - both the content and how to teach it. It&amp;#39;s why I&amp;#39;m concerned
when I see so many leaders in CS education pushing scripted curricula
and PD based training to fully &amp;#34;prepare&amp;#34; CS teachers in just a few PD
sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First time through, particularly when you&amp;#39;re voluntold to teach a new
class you just want to survive. Follow that script, learn with your
kids and get through. You&amp;#39;ll grow and the kids will be richer than had
you not gone through the fire with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two or three years down the road, however, if you&amp;#39;re still just
following the script you&amp;#39;re doing your students a disservice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, having subject knowledge doesn&amp;#39;t mean you have all the
answers but it lets you call that audible when a class needs something
that is not in the lesson plan or lets you talk about multiple
positions on subjects with no single best answer like coding style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And then calling an audible isn&amp;#39;t always about making a lesson more
advanced. It can also be about sensing what a class needs at that
time. This is something I learned from Bruce Baskind at Seward
Park. I&amp;#39;ve lost touch with Bruce but he was a mentor and a friend when
I started this teaching thing and without the support I got from Bruce
and a handful of others back at Seward, I wouldn&amp;#39;t have made it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes, you&amp;#39;ve got to turn off the academics. A class might need a
team building exercise or maybe just something fun. They might just
need to turn off school for part or all of the period. Sure, you burn
a lesson but sometimes that&amp;#39;s what the kids need and at the end of the
semester, they&amp;#39;ll be further along for it. I&amp;#39;d sometimes take a block
of class time and do Story Time - literally right out of grade
school - usually something from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.personal.psu.edu/faculty/k/u/kuc14/sunny/Children%20Literature/The%20stinky%20cheese%20man/stinky%20cheese%20man.pdf&#34;&gt;The Stinky Cheese Man&lt;/a&gt; like &amp;#34;The Really
Ugly Duckling.&amp;#34; In some ways it&amp;#39;s related to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG&#34;&gt;Halloween Stuff&lt;/a&gt; I
used to do at Stuy. Those were preplanned but that was all about
relationship building with the class - the non academic stuff that
supports the academics the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As this post is beginning to wander I think I&amp;#39;ll stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up - a specific audible I called that, at least for one student,
turned into a very memorable lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Day one back in person</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/day-one-in-person/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 06:46:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/day-one-in-person/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday was my first day of in person teaching since early
March 2020. It was, interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was looking forward to actually seeing my  students in person but as
I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/32-years/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, i wasn&amp;#39;t comfortable given Hunter&amp;#39;s
current COVID policy and Delta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll be happier come mid October when 100% of students on campus will
be vaccinated but at least for now, mask compliance is high. I only
had to talk to one student in a hallway to remind him to put his mask
back on and the only other non-masked person was a staff member (too
far away for me to address) who had it under her nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In class distancing was not possible at all and I wasn&amp;#39;t happy with
that and this will certainly cause me stress for the next couple of
months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The positives? Actually meeting my students. I went through all of
last year not seeing any of them in person and in fact have only met
one face to face so far. That was just a couple of weeks ago at an
event we both attended. That was great. Even with cameras on there&amp;#39;s
no comparison with what you can pick up and communicate through body
language remote vs in person. Just not the same. A secondary positive
were the low-tech tools. I haven&amp;#39;t found a Zoom based whiteboard
solution that I like. There&amp;#39;s something to be said for a whiteboard
that&amp;#39;s up all period that can be modified not only by me but by other
members of the class along with the projected screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about the negatives? In addition to the general health questions,
both physical and mental there were a few other things I noticed. Day
one for me is always more lecture oriented. I have to give them a lot
of material - policies and procedures, syllabus information,
etc.. That&amp;#39;s not to say that the students aren&amp;#39;t involved at all but
my first day classes are usually ones where I talk more and they talk
less. When I talk, I like to roam the room. Move to different
locations - get their eyes on different parts of the room with
different students. It&amp;#39;s a small thing but something that makes a
difference. I couldn&amp;#39;t comfortably do that. Similarly, when they were
working, I wasn&amp;#39;t comfortable with my traditional circulation
routine - given that we don&amp;#39;t know students vaccine status, I didn&amp;#39;t
want to get in close with them. This also reinforces my question from
my last post about student collaboration and group work. These are
things that actually work better remotely. Breakout rooms are flawed
but they&amp;#39;re something and you can&amp;#39;t really do groups in a small
classroom while keeping distant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s next? As I said at the top, I&amp;#39;ll be more comfortable come mid
October when we&amp;#39;re all vaxxed. Until then, I&amp;#39;ll take it a day at a
time. I&amp;#39;ll probably schedule some of our classes to be remote
regardless of policy if I think that the remote tools make more sense
for a particular session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Gonna take it one class at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>\(2^5\) Years Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/32-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 13:02:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/32-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
  src=&#34;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&#34;&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was looking over my TRS statement the other day - that&amp;#39;s Teacher&amp;#39;s
Retirement System and noticed that next week I&amp;#39;ll be starting my 32nd
year teaching. That&amp;#39;s \(2^5\) or 10000 - 5 bits so I guess you can&amp;#39;t
call me a two bit teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two and a half years at Seward, over 20 at Stuy, and the rest at
Hunter College. I&amp;#39;ve had a lot of last days before school starts but
this year is different. I&amp;#39;m betting that&amp;#39;s the case for a lot of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mentioned about burnout and not feeling any joy when I wrote about the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/&#34;&gt;CSTA conference&lt;/a&gt; but we&amp;#39;re also starting a new year in a strange place
due to the pandemic. On the one hand we have vaccines but on the
other, we&amp;#39;ve got Delta. I&amp;#39;m scheduled to teach my undergraduate
classes in person and to be honest, I&amp;#39;m not 100% comfortable. Will
that affect my teaching? I guess we&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then we have practical concerns. My students should all be distancing
so how will that affect group work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I&amp;#39;m writing this I just got an email from Hunter saying that
students will have 45 days post FDA approval to get vaccinated. The
wording seems to contradict the previous policy that in order for
students to enter campus they had to be vaccinated. This is concerning
to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started teaching I was always nervous before the first day back
and then again for the first day teaching. Mid career it was more of
an excited nervousness. Ultimately the nerves went away and while I
sorely needed vacation in June by September I was looking forward to
seeing my students again. This year it&amp;#39;s mostly nervousness, discomfort and
uncertainty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t write this merely to complain but rather to share. I figure if
I&amp;#39;m feeling this way so probably are others. We&amp;#39;re not alone.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve got some CS and teaching content posts lined up and plan to start
with them next week as things get back in the swing but for now, good
luck to everyone starting back up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why it takes so long to become a better teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/feedback-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 06:54:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/feedback-loop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
  src=&#34;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&#34;&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve written about how long it takes to become a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/five-year-class/&#34;&gt;master teacher&lt;/a&gt; and
that even after 9 or 10 years most teachers are really just advanced
beginners. A big reason for that is our long feedback loop. You do
something and you can&amp;#39;t do it again for a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was listening to a podcast on my morning run by the Hudson River and
something came up about differences between quantities of items. The difference
between having n versus n+1 of something changes based on the value of n. If, for example, you have 1 versus 2 shoes - that&amp;#39;s a BIG
difference. On the other hand, if you have 100 vs 101 shoes, not so
much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about how I framed things when teaching
big-O notation. In big-O you generally just look at the dominant
term. If you have an algorithm that runs in \(O(n^2+n)\) time you
usually just say \(O(n^2)\) because \(n^2\) is the dominant term. If you n
is small, let&amp;#39;s say 2, the difference between 2 and 4 is big so the n
part of \(n^2+n\) seems important but as n gets large, say 10,000, then
the difference between 100,000,000 and 100,010,000 is negligible for
our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I try to introduce this concept when teaching big-O but listening to
the podcast and reflecting gave me some thoughts as to how I can do it
better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The trouble is, I won&amp;#39;t be able to for a while. I introduced big-O to
our teachers in our summer intensive. My next opportunity to cover the
topic will be sometime this Spring with my first year undergrads. Same
topic, but different audience so it won&amp;#39;t be quite the same. The next
time I get to do this with teachers is next summer. All this supposes
that I remember the changes I&amp;#39;m thinking about making and work them
in. I&amp;#39;m writing myself a few notes but even then, who&amp;#39;s to say if I&amp;#39;m
going to remember the nuance that I&amp;#39;m thinking now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the teaching feedback loop - get an idea, try it, and then
can&amp;#39;t iterate for a year. Get a new idea and you can&amp;#39;t try it until
the topics comes up which could be a long time from now.  True, some
things like a new pedagogical trick can be tried out more quickly but
even then you can&amp;#39;t just do it. You&amp;#39;ve got to find where it works
within your current classes and still have to account for the
countless differences that make up your classes when you&amp;#39;re ready for
the next iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
None of this is good or bad, just the nature of our profession. Just
something that I was thinking about this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College CS Teacher Certification Summer 2021</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-cohort-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 08:58:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-cohort-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last Friday concluded the summer portion of Hunter&amp;#39;s CS Teacher
Certification program. It was an intense month. All day every day from
June 28th through July 30. On the one hand between &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/&#34;&gt;burnout and covid
fatigue&lt;/a&gt; it was a tough month and I&amp;#39;m dealing with some much needed
recovery this week. On the other hand, working with JonAlf, Topher,
new team member Genady along with around 25 amazing teachers and
teacher candidates made it a highlight of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
last year, the cohort was entirely in service teachers. This year we
added three Masters students into the mix. I know we had the states
first certified CS teachers with last years cohort but I&amp;#39;m also
wondering if we&amp;#39;ll have the state&amp;#39;s first newly minted teachers with a
Masters in CS Ed when they finish come May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hopefully, this years cohort members are all getting some rest and
relaxation through August and then we&amp;#39;ll kick off again with the
school year when they&amp;#39;ll complete the program in Fall and Spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were some changes from last time around. This time, we were only
able to run 3 classes during the summer - Programming, Data
Structures, and Methods 1. Last year we ran four - these three plus
topics in CS. It was nice getting 12 credits done all at once but the
switch to 3 classes was probably a good thing. A less good thing
though was that on the state&amp;#39;s insistence we had to teach the courses
independently as opposed to in an integrated fashion. The idea was
that this way, people wouldn&amp;#39;t have to take all three but the reality
was that we had a cohort moving through the program as one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While for the most part, the programming and data structures should be
independent we lost a good deal of value not being able to integrate
methods in at the same time. Still overall, based on our perceptions
and student ratings, things worked well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the fall the cohort will continue with Ethics and Computer Science
along with Curriculum Development and then two final classes in the
Spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This will give us close to 50 certified teachers in NY state which,
while not close to enough is a good start. We&amp;#39;re hoping to more than
double that with next years cohort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest obstacle we have is that our program requires some
fundamental knowledge in a text based programming language and as it
turns out, very few teachers currently teaching CS in NYC have
that. To help address this, we&amp;#39;ll start offering free workshops in the
Fall to get current teachers up to speed so they&amp;#39;ll be more than ready
for our program come cohort three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re a CS teacher in NYC, keep an eye out for those when the
school year starts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designated Slacker</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/designated-slacker/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 12:42:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/designated-slacker/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Our teacher certification program is in full swing. All day every
day through the end of the month. We finished off the first course
about a week ago and are currently covering data structures and
methods - teaching methods that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All day every day is pretty intense and doing it on Zoom doesn&amp;#39;t
help so we try to change things up. As with many Zoom based classes,
we make use of breakout rooms for small group work. We also use Slack
for text based communication. Personally, I prefer Zulip but didn&amp;#39;t
have a chance to switch things over. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course we visit them while in breakout rooms we also use Slack
polls while they&amp;#39;re in the rooms since the visits take time and
sometimes we just want a quick temperature check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem is that we&amp;#39;re finding that often, the rooms ignore the
slack. This wasn&amp;#39;t a surprise. Whenever we visit rooms, they&amp;#39;re always
engrossed and engaged in the task. Usually one of them is screen
sharing and they&amp;#39;re all in deep discussion. More often than not they
don&amp;#39;t notice us at all until we say something - that&amp;#39;s actually kind
of cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, we decided to try to address the issue. We asked that
each breakout room have one person who&amp;#39;s job would explicitly be
mannign Slack so that when we sent something we&amp;#39;d get a response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Topher suggested that we call said person the &amp;#34;designated slacker.&amp;#34;
Who doesn&amp;#39;t want to be that????&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That is all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No CSTA conference for me this year</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 17:08:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today is the start of CSTA&amp;#39;s annual conference. Like last year, it&amp;#39;s
virtual. Unlike the past few years, this year I won&amp;#39;t be attending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a big fan of the CSTA conference. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jakebask&#34;&gt;Jake&lt;/a&gt; and team have done an
amazing job growing the conference and it&amp;#39;s been a highlight of my
year every time I&amp;#39;ve attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could say that I&amp;#39;m not attending due to my schedule - I&amp;#39;m pretty
much spending all day every day during July teaching in my CS Teacher
Certification program and at the end of the day I&amp;#39;m wiped. This is
true but it&amp;#39;s not the only reason. The truth is, I&amp;#39;m pretty burned
out. Part of it is doing too many things. At this point, the
teacher education part of my portfolio is a full time job as is my
work with the undergraduate CS students and that&amp;#39;s not counting the
extras that have worked their way onto my plate. The other part of it
I&amp;#39;m sure is Covid. I&amp;#39;m writing this because  many teachers are
overworked and add in this past year of Covid and I&amp;#39;m sure many are
feeling the same as I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I love the CSTA conference but I&amp;#39;m just not feeling it. Same with a
lot of professional stuff - just not feeling the joy these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m hoping that come August I can turn everything off for a few weeks
and recharge a bit for next year and going back in person (safely)
will provide a boost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m betting teachers around the country are feeling rather burned out
so wanted to share publicly saying you&amp;#39;re not alone, it&amp;#39;s okay and
it&amp;#39;s okay to dial it back for our own mental and physical well being. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already looking forward to a better next year and  CSTA2022, hopefully in person.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Science is not (inherently) fun</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 09:56:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-fun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw a tweet the other day by a CS teacher. They were talking about
how much easier it is to teach CS because it&amp;#39;s fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They went on about how they get to create cool problems which makes it
so much easier to teach than other subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve heard this a lot over the years particularly from teachers who
are into gaming - &amp;#34;CS is fun because you can create games.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sorry but I have to disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;300&#34; src=&#34;https://external-content.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=https%3A%2F%2Fmedia1.tenor.com%2Fimages%2F2394618fcb9a02e206f313155848d2d3%2Ftenor.gif%3Fitemid%3D5765989&amp;f=1&amp;nofb=1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. I think CS is fun (and I&amp;#39;m not a game person) but
just because I find it fun doesn&amp;#39;t mean it&amp;#39;s inherently fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I used to think like those teachers posting but one day, early in my
career I was observed by my principal. She liked the lesson but
focused in on one thing. At one point I mentioned that we could use a
specific new technique and that it was &amp;#34;cool.&amp;#34; She asked me &amp;#34;why is it
cool?&amp;#34; and more importantly &amp;#34;why should it be cool for them?&amp;#34; That got
me thinking. It was cool to me for a variety of reasons but the truth
was that in a class of 30 high school students, what&amp;#39;s cool for one
person is probably not cool for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That observation stuck with me. Something that&amp;#39;s cool for some of us
isn&amp;#39;t for others. A teacher and some students might love making games
but it does nothing for me and for many students. Same thing for the
general building stuff or solving problems. The set of things that will and won&amp;#39;t
motivate students in a CS class is a large one indeed. Now, this
doesn&amp;#39;t mean don&amp;#39;t do, for instance, games but rather understand that your students
will have a wide range of interests so if you do a unit that focuses
on games, maybe do other things in your other units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A second issue I have with the &amp;#34;CS is fun&amp;#34; thing is that it implies
that it&amp;#39;s all fun and games and not work. This is particularly a
problem transitioning from a CS0 to a CS1 class. If you don&amp;#39;t set up
the transition correctly students will find CS1 much more challenging
and harder and if it&amp;#39;s too hard or too challenging that&amp;#39;s not
fun. Besides, even if the class is fun, which should include being
challenging at the right level there will be times where things are
just not fun and that&amp;#39;s even with the best teacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The final thing that I find off putting about all the &amp;#34;computer
science is fun&amp;#34; posts. I think it&amp;#39;s unfair to other teachers and other
subjects. History can be tremendous fun - stories, adventures,
mysteries, predictions and more. It can be taught through traditional
lessons, role play, art music and the list goes on. English? That&amp;#39;s
also stories, adventures, mysteries etc.. Physics? How about show and
tell how the world works? To say we have the monopoly on fun is not
true and unfair. We currently don&amp;#39;t have the burden history which
strictly dictates what, how, and when we teach but we&amp;#39;re getting there
quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that CS will be inherently fun for some just like any
other subject and the specifics of what and how a class is taught and
to whom can greatly influence the level of fun. A strong teacher who&amp;#39;s
passionate about games teaching a game development elective will
probably be fun for most or all participants but if it were a required
course, not so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS is our field, we find it fun and interesting and we want to bring
our passion to our students. That&amp;#39;s all good but let&amp;#39;s remember that
it&amp;#39;s not special and we&amp;#39;re not special. The same can be said for other
subjects and other teachers and we have to remember that it&amp;#39;s not
about our passions but rather those of our students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>They&#39;re all good first programming languages ;-)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/first-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2021 10:06:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/first-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s been a lot of chatter recently about the first programming
language to teach. First, I read a Facebook thread focussing on Java,
C and C++ and then, presumably unrelated, Mark Guzdial posted &lt;a href=&#34;https://cacm.acm.org/blogs/blog-cacm/253393-why-did-we-ever-think-the-first-programming-language-didnt-matter/fulltext&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
which lead to another Facebook discussing and then yesterday I noticed
a Twitter thread started by someone in the Bootcamp world asking
people what their first language was which resulted in answers ranging
from JS to PHP to Perl to a bunch of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A question Mark said he was thinking about recently was &amp;#34;Why did
anyone ever think that the first programming language didnt matter?&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t think people were thinking it didn&amp;#39;t matter but it was rather
like Anton Ego&amp;#39;s commenting on Gusteu&amp;#39;s &amp;#34;Anyone can cook.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;300&#34; src=&#34;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-lS9ekZSoIxw/XRkKDhIOO5I/AAAAAAAAd9M/H-Bjekcvh4IH_86RZlFcAikZvbqBY7uuwCLcBGAs/s1600/anyone-can-cook-book.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not that anyone can cook but rather great cooking can come from
anywhere. It&amp;#39;s not that the language doesn&amp;#39;t matter but rather any
language (or maybe most any language) &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; be used as a first
language under the right set of circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All to often the argument goes like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;I start my kids with C&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;But that&amp;#39;s no good - pointers - that&amp;#39;s why I use Javascript - it&amp;#39;s practical&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;But the development tools are lousy for beginners, not to mention the tool chain&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;Yeah but it&amp;#39;s ubiquitous, anyway how about Java&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;Too much overhead. Maybe scratch&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;No way, the kids will think it&amp;#39;s inauthentic.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;I know, apl!!!!!!!!&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;DEAL!!!!&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of the discussion focuses on the language. Maybe on the related
toolset and ecosystem. A few of us though, have been pushing the fact
that there&amp;#39;s more to the equation. Teacher knowledge, comfort, and
passion is a HUGE part of the equation. So is the student level and
background. Mark raised an important factor in his post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first programming language is particularly important when we think
about programming for other-than-CS majors. Students want to learn
whats valued in their desired community of practice. If a student
wants to become a data scientist, R or Python makes a lot more sense
than learning C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is probably more relevant at the college level than K12 but still
important to consider for the earlier grades as well. I say consider
though because, as always, the real answer is &amp;#34;it depends.&amp;#34; Back when
Bioinformatics started to get hot in the &amp;#39;90s I seem to recall Perl
being the flavor of choice. Those of you who like me battled with Perl
and its &amp;#34;write once read never&amp;#34; approach to programming would agree
that even if it was the Lingua Franca of bioinformatics, I don&amp;#39;t know
if I would take beginners down a path so fraught with peril.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that the language does matter but there&amp;#39;s a lot of
latitude. Probably more for a general purpose programming intro
rather than for a specific discipline but even then. All things being
equal, I&amp;#39;d probably say that teacher comfort might be the most
important one to start with but that only holds when a teacher starts
teaching a class. I think it&amp;#39;s beholden on the teacher to then explore
alternatives and if another language makes more sense, become familiar
with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, that&amp;#39;s my two cents. This conversation comes around a
couple of times a year. A couple of rounds ago I think it revolved
around Javascript so, we&amp;#39;re talking language. Last time, I and others
brought up teachers, their backgrounds and comfort levels. Now Mark&amp;#39;s
bringing another dimension. It&amp;#39;s nice to see the dialog evolving.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>But we don&#39;t have enough teachers!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/enough-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 07:55:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/enough-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A common refrain against requiring CS in our K12 schools is that we
don&amp;#39;t have the teachers and we won&amp;#39;t any time soon. Sure, we don&amp;#39;t
right now but we won&amp;#39;t if we don&amp;#39;t do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;300&#34; src=&#34;https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/736x/16/71/5c/16715cc71bd6c28da0b32f24afec5045--simpsons-quotes-los-simpsons.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The question to ask is &amp;#34;how long will it take&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;how do we get
there?&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at New York City. We&amp;#39;ve got approximately 1,000,000
students in our public schools. Let&amp;#39;s say that&amp;#39;s grades 1
to 12. That&amp;#39;s 83333 per grade. Let&amp;#39;s take one particular grade and see
how many classes. At 34 students per class we get 2450 classes. Since
teachers typically teach five classes that means to cover 1 class for
every student in one particular grade we&amp;#39;ll need about 500 teachers to
cover a full year class. 250 if the class is only one semester. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This if, of course, just back of the envelope calculating and we&amp;#39;d
need a good deal more to really do justice to teaching CS in K12 but
500 sounds like a reasonable critical mass to say &amp;#34;we&amp;#39;re teaching CS.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How long until we can get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Hunter we started our advanced certificate program a year
ago. The cert program is specifically for teachers licensed in another
area seeking to add the New York State CS credential. Our first cohort
graduated 21 and I can proudly say they&amp;#39;re all very well prepared to
teach CS in K12. They know their content and how to teach it. We&amp;#39;re
starting another batch in two weeks and a third cohort next summer. By
June 2023 we should have between 60 and 100 teachers certified. That&amp;#39;s
not bad. We&amp;#39;ll have a core group of teacher leaders three years from
our start. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How are we doing this? What&amp;#39;s the incentive for current teachers to
get this new certification? It&amp;#39;s an opportunity to really learn some
CS and how to teach it. All the training and PD based models just
don&amp;#39;t cut it long term. On the other hand, it costs a pretty penny -
21 graduate credits. True, those credits can be applied to salary
differentials but still. Also, while the state could just flat out
require the certification but they&amp;#39;ve put in a generous ramp up -
teachers will need the credential but not for a few year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest reason we&amp;#39;ve been able to get these teachers in is the
generosity of the New York Tech community. We&amp;#39;ve been able to provide
financial support to these teachers looking to be our leaders moving
forward. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Going with that, we have 4 students currently in our Masters program
with another 6 or so slated to start in the Fall and that&amp;#39;s with zero
advertising and outreach. I expect that in a couple of years, the
demand for the certificate program will wane while it accelerates for
the masters program. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re not going to have all the teachers we need in three years or
even in five but in three we&amp;#39;ll have a solid core. As other
certification programs come online the city will increase it&amp;#39;s teacher
training capacity and as we close in on 2026 when CS4All will expect
all schools to offer CS, we&amp;#39;ll have a good number of qualified
teachers to fill the need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sure, it&amp;#39;ll take a decade or longer to finish the job but you&amp;#39;ve got
to start with a plan and a vision and lots of support. At least in NYC
we&amp;#39;ve got all three.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally got the class working - only took five years</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/five-year-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 08:36:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/five-year-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
You don&amp;#39;t become a master teacher overnight. It takes years, perhaps
decades. Year one, you&amp;#39;re just trying to survive. Year two is
frequently a small step back. Year three on is slow improvement
provide the teacher works to improve. To me and eight to ten year
teacher is usually an advanced beginner, fifteen years?
Seasoned. Master teacher? You&amp;#39;re probably pushing close to 20 years or
more. Of course, there are exceptions but this is the pattern I&amp;#39;ve
most often observed (burnout notwithstanding).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why such a long developmental timeline? Part of it is the feedback
loop. At best your cycle is one semester but more often than not it&amp;#39;s
a year. You do something once and then you don&amp;#39;t really know if it
worked until way later if ever. You also can&amp;#39;t try it again until
next year and even then, it&amp;#39;ll be with different students and possibly
with all sorts of different variables. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s why I was happy when this semester ended and I felt that I
finally got one of my classes to where I wanted it. It only took five
years. Actually five years but having taught it 8 times over those
five years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class in question is the lab/recitation for Hunter&amp;#39;s CSCI13500 -
essentially CS1. For the non-Daedalus sections, they basically do a
programming lab per week. For me, my students do those labs albeit
usually outside of class time and we do enrichment. One of the
challenges is that I have to follow the lead of the main course
instructor who designs the labs and controls the class sequence. I
have some leway but I can&amp;#39;t for instance decide to teach classes way
earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the eight iterations I&amp;#39;ve tried different different things but I
think I&amp;#39;ve finally settled on what and how things happen in the
class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I still follow the thirteen labs given by the mane instructor in
sequence, they use Gradescope and I use GitHub Classroom. I also use
unit tests to grade the labs which gives me a platform to develop the
idea of testing both in general and as an industry practice. We go
from nothing to discussing testing and me providing test cases to them
designing their tests for later labs. Since we&amp;#39;re using GitHub
Classroom that allows us to leverage that as well. We&amp;#39;ll talk about SE
practices like using version control, build tools (make), code review,
etc.. This is all part of the enrichment which also includes students
working on projects started by other students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also do some direct CS enrichment by extending some of the
labs. Two labs that have been used recently have particularly lent
themselves to extensions. One was a lab based on rotational ciphers
which I extend by covering a decoder and there&amp;#39;s a 2D image lab based
on arrays that lends itself to all sorts of extensions - I like seam
carving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is what I landed on but I also tried other things that didn&amp;#39;t
work and some of this will change in the future. The point is that it
took years. I couldn&amp;#39;t do something one week and then immediately try
something else. Sure, you can do that with specific teaching
techniques but not with a class overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the other classes I&amp;#39;m still tweaking is CSC23500 - essentially
data structures. I taught it for decades as part of APCS-AB but
Hunter&amp;#39;s a new audience - different circumstances, different
constraints, and differnet advantages. First time through I wasn&amp;#39;t
super happy with my performance. Second year I made some positive
adjustments and was happier - Covid mid semester notwithstanding. This
year, I think I got the structure down. It was remote and during Covid
so there were other challenges so I won&amp;#39;t really know until the fourth
iteration but I think I&amp;#39;m getting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, all this is to say that improvement in teaching and improvement in
classes doesn&amp;#39;t happen overnight. Education is the long game.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you build programs, teachers will come</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/people-will-teach-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 06:53:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/people-will-teach-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a month since my last post. In fact it seems that most of
the usual CS Ed bloggers are down in frequency this year. For me it&amp;#39;s
probably been Covid fatigue and the resulting funk but I&amp;#39;m going to
see if I can force myself to write more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, the other day someone was asking about CS certification in NY
state on Facebook. One comment caught my eye. It was about Michigan
dropping all requirements to teach CS because, and I&amp;#39;m paraphrasing
here, nobody who knows enough CS to go into industry will ever become
a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I both resent and resemble that remark as do a handful of my
colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve heard this argument many times. A particularly disgusting version
goes &amp;#34;if we teach CS teachers too much CS they&amp;#39;ll leave for industry.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t buy it. That&amp;#39;s just an excuse and it&amp;#39;ll keep our students from
getting the teachers they both need and deserve. Why don&amp;#39;t I buy it?
Math and Science. CS is the hot subject these days and, at least in
theory, with a strong tech background you can &amp;#34;easily&amp;#34; get a high
paying job but CS wasn&amp;#39;t always the be all and end all. There were and
are other fields that pay well and can pull from our pool of potential
teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s dig a little deeper. Nowadays you can become certified in math
or science in New York state by completing an &amp;#34;approved program,&amp;#34;
taking some state exams and jumping through a few hoops. This has led
programs in &amp;#34;math education.&amp;#34; Some of these  programs provide teachers
with a solid foundation in math but some, not so much. Back before no
child left behind, at least in New York City, you had to actually know
your math. You needed legit math credits as opposed to math-ed (which
can be legit or lame) and you had to get through the &amp;#34;board of
examiners&amp;#34; where you had to face a panel of teachers and assistant
principals who could grill you on all manner of content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Where am I going with this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, a math teacher who knows their math, at least in NY has plenty
of alternatives. Accounting has always been a mainstay but for the big
bucks we have wall street. How is it we have math teachers that know
math when wall street and those big bonuses beckon? Same thing with
some of the sciences - we&amp;#39;ve got big pharma right across the river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that some people are good in their subject area and
actually want to become teachers. This might not be the majority of CS
people, math people etc. but there are some. Math and science might be
shortage areas in schools over time but somehow schools manage to find
teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem with CS is that there was never a career path. If you knew
CS you couldn&amp;#39;t get certification so you had to go in through math or
some other subject. Then you had to find a school where you could
teach CS and of course, for seniority and job retention you were
always lumped in with another discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, a career path is developing. We&amp;#39;ve got programs like mine at
Hunter through which a prospective teacher can become certified and we
have schools starting to offer CS and they&amp;#39;ll want to hire those CS
teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;ll just take time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our first Masters cohort at Hunter has four students in it. Our
second, which will start in the Fall looks like it will have
around 6. These are small but from what I&amp;#39;m told, pretty good sizes
for a new program, particularly when there was zero advertising and
outreach. I&amp;#39;ve also started to get questions from undergraduate CS
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re not going to solve K12 CS education over night. We&amp;#39;ve got to play
the long game. Positions that need certified CS teachers are starting
to appear as are pathways to certification. There will be people who
want to teach and want to teach CS. If we give them the pathway they
will come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final thought though, knowledgeable CS teachers do have a
choice. So do knowledgable math and science teachers. If they&amp;#39;re
leaving teaching or not even entering the profession it&amp;#39;s not because
of CS, math, or science. It&amp;#39;s because we&amp;#39;ve made teaching as a
profession so undesireable and those teachers have options. That&amp;#39;s why
I found that version of the argument I mentioned up at the top so
disgusting. People who don&amp;#39;t want CS teachers to know real CS are
really saying that the only way they can get and keep teachers is to
in fact keep them uneducated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Styles</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-styles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 08:31:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-styles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
My friend Emmanuel lamented over on Facebook on &amp;#34;Learning Styles,&amp;#34; or
more specifically on how it&amp;#39;s still given credence. We all chimed in
in agreement but not an hour later I saw a Twitter thread where
education thought leaders extolled the virtues of Learning Styles all
over again. I pointed out that it&amp;#39;s a great example as to why so many
teachers scoff at &amp;#34;the research&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;research backed practices.&amp;#34;
We&amp;#39;ve seen it all before. We&amp;#39;re told we have to teach one way or we&amp;#39;re
failures only to be told a few years later that we have to do
something else. It&amp;#39;s not necessarily the research (although I question
a good deal of what I&amp;#39;ve read) but also the interpretations and
implementations. There are just too many factors that are never
considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One factor that I&amp;#39;ve rarely seen mentioned but one I think about
frequently, particularly as I work with teachers is &amp;#34;teaching styles.&amp;#34;
I&amp;#39;m not talking about any deep science here but we know that teachers
are people and people have tendencies, strengths, weaknesses, and
preferences. These are factors that are so important to teaching but
rarely considered. It&amp;#39;s always &amp;#34;teach this way&amp;#34; and never what works
for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Think about how ridiculous that is. In what other field do we ignore
the individual strengths, tendencies and even comfort level of the
professional. In sports, we know that there are &amp;#34;player&amp;#39;s coaches&amp;#34; and
&amp;#34;disciplinarians&amp;#34; and players and teams might take better to one or
the other. Likewise, a coaches act can grow stale over time as the
team evolves. Similarly a great coach works their system to the
strengths of the players and doesn&amp;#39;t rigidly try to make players
conform to a system where they just don&amp;#39;t fit. Now that doesn&amp;#39;t mean
that a coach won&amp;#39;t try to develop a players weaknesses or try to move
towards their favored system but the greats look at the skills and
personalities of all involved. It also doesn&amp;#39;t mean that you can&amp;#39;t
evolve. Former NY Giants coach Tom Coughlin was a rigid
disciplinarian and almost lost the team and his job prior to their Super Bowl run
in 2007. He evolved - became more of a players coach. He didn&amp;#39;t change
his stripes. He was still a stickler for rules and details but he
brought in a new human dimension to his coaching game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to teaching. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While you want teachers to have a large set of tools in the box they
are going to be better with some than with others. Of course you can&amp;#39;t
ignore the students and how they respond but it&amp;#39;s not a one way
street. Take my friend Jim. He&amp;#39;s one of the best two or three natural
teachers I know. I describe him as &amp;#34;the teacher I aspire to be.&amp;#34; He&amp;#39;s
amazing. Stylistically though he&amp;#39;s what I call traditional teacher
dominant. He presents, there are questions comments and answer, seat
work. Pretty old school stuff. He doesn&amp;#39;t fit the constructivist mold
nor the cooperative one but he&amp;#39;s the best. I remember talking to our
principal a number of years ago. They said &amp;#34;I can&amp;#39;t bring
superintendents and DOE officials to Jim&amp;#39;s class when they visit and
want to see what we&amp;#39;re doing. He&amp;#39;s great but they just wouldn&amp;#39;t
understand and we&amp;#39;d get a lower school rating.&amp;#34; He&amp;#39;s the best but he
doesn&amp;#39;t fit Danielson. Now before you give me the &amp;#34;but it doesn&amp;#39;t
count, he teaches at Stuy&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ll share that prior to teaching at Stuy
he taught at an overall low performing neighborhood school and
experience notwithstanding, he was the best then too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What makes Jim the best? He has his preferred style and he adjusts to
what his students need. He&amp;#39;ll take an assortment of tools out of his
belt - some discovery stuff here, some group work there but he&amp;#39;ll work
it in to augment his strengths rather than being something he&amp;#39;s not
and as a result being inauthentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For my part I too am traditional teacher dominant. I&amp;#39;m not anywhere
close to Jim&amp;#39;s level. I consider myself an above average in class
teacher who brings other things to the table and makes up for it with
honesty, sincerity, and loyalty. I&amp;#39;m 100% &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a Danielson teacher
nor am I a cooperative learning one which was all the rage when I
started my career. I&amp;#39;ll try to get new ideas and learn new techniques
and pick and choose and overall it&amp;#39;s worked pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this is to say that when teaching teachers or coaching them,
don&amp;#39;t try to turn them into you or into John Keating, Jaime Escalante,
or what have you (note to self, write up teacher movie rant some
day). Help them to look at who they are and what they bring to the
table. Mix that with the needs of their students and the cosntraints
of their teaching situation and help them to be the best they cab be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teaching styles, for lack of a better name is too frequently missing
from the education equation. It&amp;#39;s totally removed by those who want
scripted curricula and cookie cutter instruction and barely mentioned
anywhere else but teaching styles are an important component of great
teaching and I wish more people acknowledged this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York City has Certified CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/certified-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 19:35:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/certified-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m super proud to say that New York City now has state certified
Computer Science Teachers!!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/cs-cert.png&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a long road - really long if you consider I got started on
my CS Ed journey decades ago and there&amp;#39;s a long road ahead but we hit
a major milestone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started at Hunter a little over five years ago and creating teacher
certification programs was one of the goals. Back then, the state had
neither CS certification nor CS standards. The certification area was
created a year or so ago and the standards were just adopted this past
December. Hunter&amp;#39;s programs were approved December 2019 and we started
our first advanced certificate cohort last summer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Twenty one working teachers, all certified in another subject
area. They spent a big chunk of their summer with us all day every day
and continued on with classes and field work in the Fall. Many
finished last December while a few needed one more course which
they&amp;#39;re taking now. Earlier today on our Slack, teachers from that
cohort started sharing that they either received their state
certificates in the mail or that they looked themselves up on the
NYSED web site and confirmed that they were now certified to teach
computer science in the state of NY.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is big news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The entire cohort came in as strong teachers and they all grew
tremendously in terms of CS knowledge and their ability to teach
it. Now they represent the first of a growing group of certified CS
teachers - education leaders to provide a core of expertise in terms of
both CS content and how to teach it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m super proud of the cohort and super proud to be part of this. One
of the best parts for me have been meeting and working with these
great teachers and having this new learning network form - hopefully
we can keep it growing for years to come. Another is being able to get
the band back together - I was able to bring in my old partners in
crime JonAlf and Topher to teach and anyone who&amp;#39;s seen them teach know
that they&amp;#39;re the best. I couldn&amp;#39;t include our other co-conspirator,
Sam, because he was on sabbatical and couldn&amp;#39;t work but hopefully that
will change next time around. Not having a team at Hunter has been
really one of the few downsides so being able to work with my &amp;#34;go to
guys&amp;#34; again was a blast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also have our Masters program well underway so the pipeline of CS
teachers is starting to form. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is exciting news for New York City, Hunter and for me
personally. Long road ahead but as of today, a bunch of students in
NYC are being taught by state certified computer science teachers and
there will be more to come.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Sort over Zoom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/qsort-over-zoom/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 12:10:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/qsort-over-zoom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t been blogging much this year. Not sure why - probably pandemic
fatigue. It&amp;#39;s also affected my blog reading - more scanning, less deep
reading. I&amp;#39;ve also been trying to spend mode time off screen learning
how to paint (with,let&amp;#39;s say  mixed results :-) ) leaving less time
and energy to blog. Hopefully I&amp;#39;ll pick up on both ends as more people
get vaccinated and we can get to a more normal life. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, I tried a new motivation for Quicksort today so I
thought I&amp;#39;d share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve approached teaching the Quicksort in a variety of ways (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/try-something-new/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quick-sort-starting/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-03-14-sorting-from-top-and-from-bottom/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-12-select-to-sort/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) but never had a great lead in activity. Merge sort
was easy in person since you can &amp;#34;Tom Sawyer&amp;#34; &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-27-dumbass/&#34;&gt;shuffling a deck of
cards&lt;/a&gt; in class. We adapted this activity pretty well to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/merge-over-zoom/&#34;&gt;work over Zoom&lt;/a&gt;
this past summer in our teacher certification program. Quicksort
however, haven&amp;#39;t found a good one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thinking about how to leverage remote, I had an idea to try - use
polls. I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://zulip.com/&#34;&gt;Zulip&lt;/a&gt; for class discussions. It&amp;#39;s like Slack but is open
source, can be self hosted, you can post from email,  and has much
better threading. I wrote a small bot to quickly create emoji
polls. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First I asked for the students to share their birtdays - just month
and day in the form MMDD so if you were born on March 12th you would
write 0312 in the chat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, I picked one birthday at random, let&amp;#39;s say 0515. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then created a poll: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; My birthday is earlier in the year than 0515&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 My birthday is later in the year than 0515&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The bot tags the post with the emoji and the class can click on their
choice. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then talk about what we now know - &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now know the exact location of 0515 with respect to all the
dates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data set is now partially ordered (everything less than 0515 to
the left, greater to the right).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also drew out some diagrams showing what was happening &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is also one iteration of the Quicksort. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We do this again on one side and continue to discuss. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From here we finish developing the algorithm and we&amp;#39;re off to the
races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, I won&amp;#39;t know for a while how well this worked or if it did
at all but the students seemed to be engaged and so far I think it
helped get a good feel for how the algorithm worked. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Using Zulip or other chat polls in this case made the motivating
activity easy and seamless. I&amp;#39;m not sure that this particular activity
would be as easy to implement in person unless you used some
technology like clickers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We finished off the class discussing how we should test our
implementations. They&amp;#39;re going to test the sorts on a variety of data
sets including sets where all values are the same or are already
sorted. Given our naive pivot selection this should lead to some
pretty bad runtimes  fodder to motivate the next class.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>