<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Education on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Education on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 19:43:36 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/education/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PD in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 19:43:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</guid>
      <description>I spent this past Saturaday morning up at the Microsoft building in Times Square. What was I doing there? Aankit Patel invited me to check out the professional development that he and his team organized for the teachers involved in the assorted CSforAllNYC programs that his office runs.
Wow.
Lots of great things going on. I was only able to stay for a couple of hours but I spent some time in two rooms run by TEALS, a room of BJC teachers, a group working with p5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the students know more than the teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 16:07:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;ve heard it many times with computer science - &#34;the kids know more than the teacher.&#34;
On the one hand, the truth is that this isn&#39;t so much the case. Kids might use computers all the time but they don&#39;t necessarily know much about them or about computer science (link 1, link 2). Then you have students who think they know all about CS but really don&#39;t. They might have picked up a bit of coding somewhere but more often than not, the knowledge is pretty superficial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talking about CS teacher certification at CSTA 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned in my last post, this coming weekend is the Computer Science Teachers Association (CSTA) conference. I&#39;ve been a member of CSTA since the beginning but this will be only the second time I&#39;ve made it to the annual conference.
The CSTA conference might be the largest conference specifically for k12 computer science teachers and that makes it different from conferences like SIGCSE which is for CS education and education research at all levels or ISTE which seems to be more of an Ed Tech conference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving control of NYC&#39;s specialized schools to a political appointee</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I shared my thoughts on Bill de Blasio&#39;s plans to &#34;fix&#34; the selection criteria for New York City&#39;s specialized high schools. If you haven&#39;t read the post, you can find it here.
I was going to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging today but there&#39;s more to the story.
In spite of what BdB stated, it&#39;s not enough for him to switch to another measure - the middle school state exam along with some modifiers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing Admissions to the NYC Specialized High Schools</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, Bill de Blasio, the current Mayor of New York City outlined how he would &#34;fix&#34; our specialized schools. The schools he was referring to were the &#34;big three&#34; of Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, and Brooklyn Tech and then five additional schools - The High School for Math Science and Engineering at CCNY, The High School for American Studies at Lehman, Brooklyn Latin, The Queens Arts and Science High School at York College, and Staten Island Tech.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do the students finish the tests or does the test finish the students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tests-finish-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tests-finish-students/</guid>
      <description>I tweeted this the other day:
Why don&amp;#39;t so many teachers and professors understand that the test or assignment you can do in 15 minutes will take your beginning students at least an hour and probably a lot more to complete.
&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) April 18, 2018 
What led to the tweet was a discussion I was having with some students about not having enough time on tests which led to a discussion of having to drop everything to spend every waking hour on a project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools and Complexity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/</guid>
      <description>Alfred Thompson wrote about CS education tools earlier today. I&#39;ve also been meaning to write on the topic but from a different point of view.
I do my best to keep up with the latest and greatest in the CS world both on the academic side as well as the professional one. That&#39;s not really possible, but I do my best. When I have a small project to work on I&#39;ll some times use it as an excuse to play with some recent technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethics In CS Education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been meaning to write about ethics in CS education for a while. Probably since I saw this article in the NY Times but got sidetracked.
I was reminded when I saw this tweet by Hadi the other day:
This message is bigger than Facebook. Computer science faces an ethics crisis. That’s why @codeorg covers ethics and digital citizenship in our computer science courses. (And we’re thankful that most of the largest tech companies support us) https://t.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Prestigious Competitons And High Schools</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</guid>
      <description>The ACM recently announced this year&#39;s winners of the Cutler-Bell Prize in High School Computing. Over on his blog, Alfred Thompson noted that the winners were either from independent or magnet public schools. Alfred also noted that most of the winners of prestigious science competitions like the Regeneron Science Talent Search (nee Intel, nee Westinghouse) were from public magnet schools. In his post, Alfred ruminates on this and wonders &#34;how to we add the flexibility and support to more students at more schools?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sigcse2018 Making theory more acccesible</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/</guid>
      <description>Next up from SIGCSE 2018 is John MacCormick&#39;s session on Strategies for Baing the CS Theory Course on Non-decision Problems
MacCormicks&#39;s stance is that CS theory is tough the first time around and using non-decision problems is a viable approach to make theory more accessible to beginners. As MacCormick said in his paper:
  ... a decision problem may ask the yes/no question, &#34;Does this graph  have a Hamilton cycle?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How my views on education research were shaped</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/practitioners-and-researchers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/practitioners-and-researchers/</guid>
      <description>After reading a couple of comments on my last post where I talked a bit about practitioners vs researchers I thought I&#39;d expand and expound a bit.
While there are education researchers that I very much respect, overall, I&#39;m skeptical of education research. Note that I&#39;m not talking specifically about CS Ed research but rather education research in general.
Let&#39;s go back to the beginning. I entered teaching from industry. Goldman Sachs to be specific.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing the Absent Teacher Reserve (ATR) situation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</guid>
      <description>In the New York City department of education a recurring hot topic is the Absent Teacher Reserve or ATR pool.
A teacher or administrator in the ATR pool is a licensed, most likely tenured teacher not assigned permanently to a school. Each year these educators get shuttled from school to school and denied a chance to actually settle in a position.
The ATR pool was created under the Bloomberg administration. Prior to that, when there was an opening school transfers were basically seniority based and when school had too many teachers the least senior was excessed or basically out of a job until a school with an opening could be found.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</guid>
      <description>Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members of the New York State Department of Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Development beyond Scratch</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</guid>
      <description>Today was Election Day. One of the few days each year when students stay home and teachers spend all day attending what is generously known as professional development.
Years ago I was in a room with a few colleagues when my friend Dave - one of the best math teachers I know said &#34;you know, every time we have a PD day in NJ and my wife and I have to scramble to take care of the kids I get a little annoyed but then think I shouldn&#39;t get annoyed since they&#39;re spending the day doing all sorts of valuable PD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There&#39;s always something to learn (from your students)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</guid>
      <description>One thing I&#39;ve learned from teaching is that there&#39;s always something new to learn. For the kids, yes, but I&#39;m talking about for the teacher.
The other day, I taught a lesson I&#39;ve taught many times. Find the mode of a data set. That&#39;s the problem that they solve but the lesson is really about run time complexity, hidden complexity and using data structures in alternate ways.
I blogged about this before so you can get an earlier take there although the code isn&#39;t formatted correctly due to blog conversions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A test result is just a test result</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>This past weekend was Catskillsconf - my favorite event of the year. I spent the weekend up in Ulster County with a bunch of my students. some great friends old and new, and Devorah. It was a great weekend but I was mostly offline.
As a result I missed a rather heated discussion in the CS Ed Facebook groups. The debate was over whether or not Strong AP CSP exam results are indicative of a good curriculum or good professional development (PD).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Believe CS Teachers are Smart and Capable</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</guid>
      <description>People sometimes accuse me of being an elitist CS snob that I feel that CS teachers have to have advanced CS degrees.
It&#39;s not that at all. Rather, I feel that CS teachers are smart and capable. Circumstances frequently result in a teacher in front of a CS class with limited content and pedagogical content knowledge. It&#39;s not ideal but it&#39;s reality. Of course I feel that we should do everything to support and encourage these teachers but we should also insist that after a reasonable period of time, they know their stuff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the new Secret Sauce ever better?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</guid>
      <description>I read this piece earlier today on Nancy Bailey&#39;s blog.
TL;DR (although it really isn&#39;t too long so you should read it) - it&#39;s on Laurene Powell Jobs, her efforts to &#34;reform&#34; education and why she&#39;s misguided as are most of the well to do non-educators working hard to change and in many cases privatize public education.
Laura posts a nice list of simple, common sense ways to improve education. I&#39;ll repost them here:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching APCS-A for the first time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</guid>
      <description>I got an email from a friend the other day. Among other things, he mentioned that he would be teaching APCS-A for the first time this year. He&#39;s a little trepidatious. He knows his stuff but he hasn&#39;t really done much using Java.
I was going to respond in an email but thought I might share here instead.
  TL;DR - for all you APCS teachers who are new or new to Java - learn  your core CS, lean on your resources and support and it&#39;s OK to tell  your kids &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cost of AP Exams</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</guid>
      <description>Now that I&#39;m back from vacation and summer&#39;s winding down I thought I&#39;d start getting back to more classroom related posts. I still have a few summer topics I want to write about -- standards and side projects in particular but I&#39;m also looking forward to talking more about the classroom since, after all, at my core, I&#39;m a teacher. When I saw this article in my inbox this morning I thought I&#39;d talk about it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethics, Cybersecurity, ethics, curricula  and standards</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricla-standards/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricla-standards/</guid>
      <description>This morning, I read Alfred Thompson&#39;s post on teaching cybersecurity. as Alfred says, it&#39;s something of a CS Ed buzzword this summer.
Another hot topic in K12 CS Ed this summer is the inclusion of ethics in our CS courses courtesy of efforts like the #ethicalCS twitter chat every Wednesday at 8:00 Eastern time hosted by Saber Khan.
Discussions about both topics include &#34;where should we be doing this?&#34; &#34;What should we be doing?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/grit-kind-word-gun/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/grit-kind-word-gun/</guid>
      <description>Back in May, I read this post about Angela Duckworth and Grit. Grit has become an education buzzword in the past few years so I figured I should read Duckworth&#39;s book. It took this long because there was a long waiting list at the New York Public Library to get the ebook. I&#39;m still not quite finished with the book but I thought I&#39;d share some of my thoughts on the book and the buzz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on non educator  influences on CS Education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Mark Guzdial blogged about a NY Times piece discussing Silicon Valleys influence on education through Code.org.
Mark questioned the validity of the piece. If you don&#39;t read Mark&#39;s blog and you&#39;re in CS Ed you probably should.
I tried to leave a comment on Mark&#39;s blog - not about the NY Times article but rather my thoughts on why I think it&#39;s important that we remain wary and vigilant to industry and outsiders influence and impact on CS education and on education in general.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three strikes and you&#39;re out or third time&#39;s a charm</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/</guid>
      <description>Brenda Wilkerson, Director of CS and IT education for Chicago public schools was one of the keynote speakers at this year&#39;s CSTA conference. During her talk, she made a comment about it taking three times through to get it right so if you&#39;re working hard and struggling in your first year of teaching CS, it&#39;s not the time to give up. Learning to teach takes time.
She&#39;s absolutely correct. I saw this in myself and I&#39;ve seen this in many other young teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Ed advocates should pay attention to greater ed issues</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-and-all-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-and-all-ed/</guid>
      <description>For anyone involved in K12 CS education, the past few years have been a wild ride. When I first tried to make inroads in the DOE decades ago I couldn&#39;t get through the door. Now, CS Education is everyone&#39;s darling. It&#39;s really amazing. It&#39;s been a combination of grass roots efforts by teachers, non profit education efforts such as TEALS, advocacy of groups like Code.org and amazing individuals like Fred Wilson who has probably done more to move the needle of CS Ed in NY than any other 10 people combined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A friendly reminder to use the right language when describing CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/languages-or-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/languages-or-cs/</guid>
      <description>I was part of this conversation the other day:
When science teachers asked me if I taught AP Java I&amp;#39;d always respond by asking them if they taught AP Microscope.
&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) July 7, 2017 
I always use that line to emphasize that I teach CS - a way of thinking and problem solving and looking at the world. The languages we use in our classes are tools to help us communicate ideas not the ends but rather a means.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Certification - not a good idea</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/</guid>
      <description>You&#39;ve probably seen an image like this:
It&#39;s what you see when you try to access a secure web site but the web site itself certified itself as being secure.
When people see this on a professional site it sets off all manner of red flags. We feel much more comfortable when go to a site and we don&#39;t see that error. When we see the secure green lock in the url bar indicating that this site is certified through an external trusted source.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Plea to AP teachers- don&#39;t measure yourself by your scores</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/</guid>
      <description>AP scores just came out. As usual, I see the posts and take part in conversations where teachers talk about their results. Some are happy about their results, some aren&#39;t, some don&#39;t really care.
I just want to make a plea to all AP teachers out there:
Don&#39;t let your value be dictated by the college board or any other exam.
I never really cared much about my students&#39; actual AP scores.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teachers - teacher first or content first</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</guid>
      <description>Is it easier to take CS people and teach them to teach or is it easier to take teachers and teach them CS?
The question gets batted around from time to time.
This time via twitter:
Some think it&amp;#39;s easier to teach a teacher to teach CS than to teach a CS pro to teach. @alfredtwo is not one of them https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ
&amp;mdash; Diane Levitt (@diane_levitt) July 3, 2017</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Retaining Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</guid>
      <description>Back in February, I shared my thoughts on losing CS teachers to the tech industy. TL;DR - I don&#39;t think it will be a CS Ed problem.
That said, I do think that it will be hard to find good CS teachers but the reason is because it will get harder and harder to find good teachers in general.
There are plenty of reasons why it&#39;s harder to become a career teacher but I don&#39;t want to talk about those today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mayoral Control - only when your guy&#39;s the mayor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/mayoral-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/mayoral-control/</guid>
      <description>The hot debate this past week in NY Education circles is Mayoral Control. When I started teaching, New York City schools were controlled by the Board of Education. The board appointed a chancellor. The system was supposed to balance community control as well as some centralized decision making. The system was created in the late 60s and was entrenched through my schooling. By the time I was a teacher I think it was pretty much a given that the system didn&#39;t work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2017</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow morning I fly out to Seattle for SIGCSE 2017. For those of you not in the CS Education space, SIGCSE is the ACM (Association for Computing Machinery) special interest group for computer science education.
I&#39;ve wanted to go for years but have never been able. It&#39;s hard for a high school teacher to miss a week in mid March, particularly in places with a school calendar similar to New York.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will we lose CS teachers to industry?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/draft-will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/draft-will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</guid>
      <description>If we properly prepare CS teachers, won&#39;t they just jump ship and take  tech industry jobs?  I hear that a lot.
Tech pays big. Teaching? Not so much. Tech workers are respected and have flexible jobs. Teaching? Again, not so much.
Those chanting these refrains advocate the current simple teacher &#34;training&#34; - scripted lessons, minimal pedagogical content knowledge, even less real content knowledge. That will keep them in the classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quality Devs and Coding Contests</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quality-devs-and-coding-contests/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quality-devs-and-coding-contests/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been planning to put together a response to Alfred Thompson&#39;s recent post - Software Developers - Quantity vs Quality.
TL;DR, although it isn&#39;t really long and I do encourage you to read Alfred&#39;s post: a couple of articles talk about how the U.S. has the most people entering CS competitions like HackerRank but Americans are not at the top of the leaderboard. does this mean that there&#39;s less talent in America?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting with scheme</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/staring-with-scheme/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/staring-with-scheme/</guid>
      <description>Scheme is one of the languages used in Stuy&#39;s intro CS course. Like any other language, there are pros and cons of using it to introduce students to CS. Here are some of the reasons why I like Scheme as a first language and why despite that, I don&#39;t recommend it in many cases.
Scheme certainly isn&#39;t mainstream. That&#39;s not the main reason why I like it but it is a side benefit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selecting a starting language - why not Javascript</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/</guid>
      <description>I was catching up with the team at Stuy the other day and they mentioned that they were periodically getting pushback on their choice of languages, particularly in the intro class. The pushback was mostly in the form of &#34;why don&#39;t you start them with Javascript?&#34;
Back in the day, when I created our intro class where we use Scheme, NetLogo and then later Python, I&#39;d get similar pushback but then it was &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should CS Ed be in bed with the College Board</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m guessing my views on this aren&#39;t very popular -that&#39;s OK, every community needs a curmudgeon.
A few years ago, I cautioned if we weren&#39;t careful, once the big players got involved, CS Ed would go the way of other disciplines, and not in a good way. It looks like indeed we&#39;re well on our way down that road.
I&#39;ve ranted before about things like non-profits, drop in and summer programs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BS? - BA</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ba-bs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ba-bs/</guid>
      <description>I didn&#39;t know Hunter College had computer science.  I heard that refrain more than once during my fall visits to high schools. Part of the reason for this is due to Hunter CS&#39;s low profile and small size in spite of its high quality.
Part, though, was also because of some misconceptions about Computer Science programs. I&#39;d hear things like &#34;but they only offer a BA not a BS,&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selling out or getting a seat at the table</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/</guid>
      <description>The other day, a friend posited a question on Facebook (paraphrased):
  If called upon, would you take a job in an administration who&#39;s policies you strongly  disagreed with?  Would you go work for an administration that you reviled in order to get a seat at the table? To try to affect change from the inside or would you consider yourself a sellout or worse, publicly promote positions you disagree with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluate teachers like they do in the real world</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/evaluating-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/evaluating-teachers/</guid>
      <description>This old article has been reposted a few times in my circles over the past few weeks http://educationnext.org/facadeofexcellence/. It&#39;s from 2003 and complains about the lack of flexibility schools had back then with regard to hiring and salary. The article is old and out of date and the seniority system no longer holds for hiring but it does for lay offs. The salary scale from back then, though, is still in place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science Talent Search winners do not a great school make</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-focus-on-sts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-focus-on-sts/</guid>
      <description>Over on Facebook, my Alma Mater and long time employer, Stuyvesant High School seems to be making a big push to up it&#39;s Regeneron Science Talent Search game. For those of you who aren&#39;t familiar, that&#39;s the latest incarnation of the Westinghouse Science Talent Search from back in my day.
It seems that Stuyvesant hasn&#39;t had that many semi finalists, finalists, and winners over the past few years and isn&#39;t happy about it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Hunter CS is so important to NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/</guid>
      <description>If you know me you know that my morning reads include a visit over to avc.com, Today, Fred&#39;s post talked about development and progress, evolution, if you would, in the city. Although not directly related, it got me thinking about gentrification.
To me, gentrification all too often seems to result in pushing out people and business that were there during the hard times.
We don&#39;t need to force out long time residents that can no longer make rent - we need to uplift communities with pathways to towards greater economic opportunity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Thinkers in Scotland</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m way behind on my Communications of the ACM. I generally only read them when I use my trainer in the mornings and with summer running and outside riding, I&#39;m still on the December 2015 issue.
This morning, I read a viewpoint by Jeremy Scott and Alan Bundy on a program in Scotland. If you&#39;re an ACM member, and if you&#39;re a CS practitioner, student, academic, or teacher you should be, you can read the piece for details.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impostor Syndrome - I&#39;m not good enough</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been meaning to comment on these tweets for a while:
I went to high school with some scary smart people. Never made math team. Didn&amp;#39;t get into honors math. Thought I wasn&amp;#39;t good at it.
&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) June 30, 2016  @zamansky :D
that&amp;#39;s the thing though you can get such an inferiority complex by always comparing yourself to others https://t.co/LvaMjp1WVf
&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) July 1, 2016</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federal Aid for Code Schools - is this a good thing?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</guid>
      <description>I saw this headline earlier today: The U.S. Just Made a Bold Move to Improve Diversity in Tech.
The article talks about a program by which a number of code schools will be able to accept federal student aid. I don&#39;t know if we&#39;re talking student loans or grants but I&#39;m not sure it matters.
The headline sounds great. I&#39;m not so sure that this is a good thing.
My thinking&#39;s evolved over the years but right now, everything tells me that public funds and for profit education don&#39;t mix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ed Disruption - why it&#39;s different</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I read this post by Eliot Horowitz, founder and CTO of MongoDB.
Eliot titled the post &#34;Innovate vs Appropriate&#34; and talks about the importance of knowing when to come up with something new vs when to use the accepted tool, technique, or method. Eliot, of course is discussing this as it applies to MongoDB and it&#39;s well worth a read but it got me thinking about the ever popular need to &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hillary and Student Loans</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I read over Hillary&#39;s briefing on her initiative on Technology and Innovation.
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have my doubts. My feeling is that she&#39;s pretty much aligned with the current administration education wise and the current administration has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public education.
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much like some of the others, I don&#39;t want to get into that today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navajo Math Circles</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of Navajo Math Circles, a documentary on a Math Circle put in place to support and enrich the currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment programs. I&#39;m most familiar with the New York Math Circle. I&#39;m friends with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in their summer program for a couple of years.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>