<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>programming on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in programming on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 15:53:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/programming/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Back To Python</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/back-to-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 15:53:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/back-to-python/</guid>
      <description>With summer right around the corner I&amp;#39;m hoping to spend at least a little time on some personal coding projects. There are a few work related tools I&amp;#39;d love to develop and just some random areas of CS I&amp;#39;d like to explore. If I finish them, the work projects will be web based.  I was thinking about using this as an opportunity to do a deeper dive into Clojure having used it for some experiments and competitions like Advent of Code but at the end of the day I decided not to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Give me a break (and a continue)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/break-continue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 08:39:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/break-continue/</guid>
      <description>What can I do to discourage my students from using the &amp;#34;break&amp;#34; statement?   That was more or less the gist of the comment and it elicited some good responses. This time the conversation was on Facebook but I&amp;#39;ve seen this one and participated in it many times before. I never liked the question when presented as a &amp;#34;how can I stop them&amp;#34; one. I equally dislike when the offered advice is basically &amp;#34;never use break no matter what&amp;#34; or something similar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Globals Breaks And Returns, oh my</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 15:48:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</guid>
      <description>Never use global variables    Never break out of a loop    These are two &amp;#34;best practices&amp;#34; that are frequently touted in early CS classes both at the high school and college level.  They came up a couple of times yesterday. Once in the Facebook APCS-A teachers group and once on Alfred Thompson&amp;#39;s blog.  Alfred post was topically on global variables.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>