<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Advent of Code on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/advent-of-code/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Advent of Code on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 19:01:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/advent-of-code/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 3</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 19:01:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day3/</guid>
      <description>Today&#39;s problem dealt with intersecting paths. You start with two inputs, figure out the paths they represent and where they intersect and then find the intersection that correctly answers the question.
For part 1 you have to find the intersection closest to the origin. From a teacher&#39;s point of view, the interesting part here is data representation. This problem deals with a two dimensional grid on which the paths live. For most students, at least in my experience, if they&#39;re trained in a language like C++ or Java they go for the direct representation - a 2D array.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 17:11:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day2/</guid>
      <description>Day 2 of Advent of Code 2019 was also pretty straightforward and once again I wrote my solution in Clojure but in order to talk about this from a teacher&#39;s point of view, we&#39;ll look at a Python solution.
At its core, this is a simulation problem - read the data into an array or list and write a program to run through the steps. At first I was hoping that the solution would consume the data - that is, once you read past an instruction you don&#39;t go back to it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2019 Day 1</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 14:23:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day1/</guid>
      <description>Like most programming challenges, Advent of Code ramps out from easier, more accessible problems to harder, more complex ones. As such, a number of the early challenges are great problems for early CS students.
I thought that while I watched my NY Giants play valiantly in their attempt to get a high draft pick I&#39;d talk about today&#39;s challenge from a teacher&#39;s point of view.
The summary of part one is that you have a list of inputs (masses of components) and for each one you have to perform a calculation (how much fuel is needed).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>