<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Github on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/github/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Github on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 09:44:29 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/github/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Github Classroom and Travis CI</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 09:44:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been using GitHub with my classes since GitHub&#39;s early days. Over time I&#39;ve gotten my workflows down. I use a combination of shell scripts - many just written on the fly, GitHub organizations, and some naming conventions and protocols that have served me well.
A few years ago, the GitHub Education team started GitHub Classroom. I looked at it at the time. It was pretty cool but I had my workflow so I didn&#39;t adopt it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pull Requests and Other People&#39;s Code</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pull-requests/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pull-requests/</guid>
      <description>One of the things I&#39;ve heard for years from former students - both those looking for jobs and those looking to hire is that colleges don&#39;t really do a good job preparing students for careers in tech. Sure they teach the algorithms and the theory but ther are a lot of missing pieces, particularly on the practical end. I&#39;m certainly not advocating turning CS programs into coding schools but there are many low cost opportunities to bring practical real world best practices in to the CS classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Coding or Cheating</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</guid>
      <description>I haven&#39;t been teaching this past semester. That&#39;s why I haven&#39;t been writing much about lessons. I miss working with students but that will resume in the fall and this semester has allowed me to get a jump on new projects.
It&#39;s also allowed me to look at some student issues from a bit of a distance.
One issue that keeps coming up is cheating.
Some of it, classroom cheating. my friend Ria recently asked a question on Facebook about it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>