<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Github on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/github/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Github on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 12:53:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/github/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Github Org Explorer - now with oauth</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-org-explorer-oauth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 12:53:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-org-explorer-oauth/</guid>
      <description>A while ago I wrote about a small side project - GitHub Org Explorer - a small tool to make it easier to manager GitHub repositories based on organization. I&#39;m using it as a replacement for the GitHub provided Classroom Assistant. I find it more flexible in terms of exporting assignments to my own machine and it allows me to delete repos en masse which is critical after the semester is over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Org Explorer</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-org-explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2020 14:40:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-org-explorer/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m a big fan of GitHub Classroom and use it for all of my class assignments. It&#39;s great for organizing, distributing, and collecting assignments and gets the kids used to using real world tools at the same time. I&#39;ve written a bunch of posts on how I use it:
 How I use GitHub Classroom Communicating with Students - meybe GitHub to the rescue GitHub as a tool for education (part of a 4 part series)  As well as a couple of others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using GitHub issues for class communicatoin</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/git-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 16:17:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/git-issues/</guid>
      <description>Last week I talked about using GitHub issues as a mechanism for class communication. I thought it might be helpful to follow up on it and also felt that a video would be better than text.
So, here it is, 16 minutes on how you can use GitHub issues for class communication. I don&#39;t show examples of everything like @ tagging but I think it shows some of the power of using GitHub and GitHub classroom beyond just a software repo and versioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019 - Using GitHub as a CMS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 12:09:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</guid>
      <description>With ISTE ending, the next big event for CS treachers is the annual CSTA Conference. I first attended two years ago in Baltimore. Last year the conference, in Omaha was bigger and better in every way imaginable. I expect this year to be the best yet.
I don&#39;t go to a lot of conferences so I don&#39;t have much to compare CSTA with but I like the fact that it&#39;s is about half the size of SIGCSE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I use Github Classroom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 16:42:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s been an amazingly unproductive weekend. Mostly because I&#39;ve been sick with the flu. It sucks but since the rest of the family&#39;s away anway at least I&#39;m not making everyone miserable.
I did manage to stage my next couple of classes and figured that writing this post wouldn&#39;t take too much energy since it&#39;s mostly a video.
Earlier, I talked about using GitHub and TravicCI and this time around I show how I use GitHub classroom to set up, disseminate, and collect assignments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Helps Me Help Students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-helps-me-help-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 18:55:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-helps-me-help-students/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I was reminded why I love GitHub in support of my classes. One of my students posted a question about our current lab. They posted a synopsis of the problem along with the error message.
Since we&#39;re all working on GitHub the student&#39;s work was already up online Since I started using GitHub Classroom I was able to quickly navigate to the repo. This might have been enough but to really in to the students work I cloned the repo and went into Emacs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Github Classroom and Travis CI</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 09:44:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been using GitHub with my classes since GitHub&#39;s early days. Over time I&#39;ve gotten my workflows down. I use a combination of shell scripts - many just written on the fly, GitHub organizations, and some naming conventions and protocols that have served me well.
A few years ago, the GitHub Education team started GitHub Classroom. I looked at it at the time. It was pretty cool but I had my workflow so I didn&#39;t adopt it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pull Requests and Other People&#39;s Code</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pull-requests/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pull-requests/</guid>
      <description>One of the things I&#39;ve heard for years from former students - both those looking for jobs and those looking to hire is that colleges don&#39;t really do a good job preparing students for careers in tech. Sure they teach the algorithms and the theory but ther are a lot of missing pieces, particularly on the practical end. I&#39;m certainly not advocating turning CS programs into coding schools but there are many low cost opportunities to bring practical real world best practices in to the CS classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Coding or Cheating</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</guid>
      <description>I haven&#39;t been teaching this past semester. That&#39;s why I haven&#39;t been writing much about lessons. I miss working with students but that will resume in the fall and this semester has allowed me to get a jump on new projects.
It&#39;s also allowed me to look at some student issues from a bit of a distance.
One issue that keeps coming up is cheating.
Some of it, classroom cheating. my friend Ria recently asked a question on Facebook about it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>