<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Certification on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/certification/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Certification on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/certification/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/strong-teacher-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/strong-teacher-certification/</guid>
      <description>About a week ago New York State&#39;s new regulation creating a K12 CS teacher certification went live. Just the other day I was honored to be interviewed by Matt Flamm of Crain&#39;s New York in a follow up piece about it.
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs that lead to certification is HUGE. In my view, it&#39;s a game changer.
Let&#39;s Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/ny-cs-certificate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/ny-cs-certificate/</guid>
      <description>Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members of the New York State Department of Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Certification - not a good idea</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/dont-self-certify/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/dont-self-certify/</guid>
      <description>You&#39;ve probably seen an image like this:
It&#39;s what you see when you try to access a secure web site but the web site itself certified itself as being secure.
When people see this on a professional site it sets off all manner of red flags. We feel much more comfortable when go to a site and we don&#39;t see that error. When we see the secure green lock in the url bar indicating that this site is certified through an external trusted source.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>