<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Csed on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csed/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Csed on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 09:08:57 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csed/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Math isn&#39;t always fun but you can do fun things with math</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/math-not-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 09:08:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/math-not-fun/</guid>
      <description>Garth Flint recently wrote another post talking about some of the PD going on in his neck of the woods. Garth talks about the disconnect between the professors putting on the PD and what goes on in the K12 classrooms of the attending teachers. Here&#39;s the money quote:
  “Why do all college CS profs think everyone loves math? Want to turn  kids off to programming? Throw math at them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teacher PD at Grow with Google</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-at-gwg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 08:12:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-at-gwg/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday we held our third monthly Professional Development session for teachers of &#34;APCS-A, Similar, and Beyond.&#34; It&#39;s great to see that we&#39;re starting to form a core of a community of CS teachers teaching some of the more advanced classes as there is a core group that keeps coming back for more. Even better is the fact that we&#39;re gaining a couple of new teachers at each session.
Last time, we were at Digital Ocean, a cloud provide that has been very involved in education since their creation and has been a tremendous boon to my education projects over the years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing A Textbook</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/choosing-a-textbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 10:41:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/choosing-a-textbook/</guid>
      <description>Now and again there are requests on the assorted CS Education forums asking about which text book to use. These requests are usually for APCS-A. There are usually a number of &#34;I&#39;m very happy with ...&#34; replies but I thought I&#39;d take a bit of a deeper dive into what teachers might want to consider when evaluating a textbook.
It was never an issue when I started as a math teacher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adapting A Nifty Assignment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 08:20:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</guid>
      <description>The Nifty Assignments session at SGICSE is always a popular one.
Go to the site and you&#39;ll find links to all the assignments presented from 1999 to the present year.
On the one hand, it&#39;s a great resource. On the other, the assignments vary in nifty-ness depending on one&#39;s personal taste. To me, there seemed to be a run of nifty assignments that were really just &#34;take a generic assignment and fancy up the graphics&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March PD for CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 15:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</guid>
      <description>Back in December we ran our first PD session for CS teachers. This was to address the need for professional development for teachers who were more experienced in terms of computer science - we aimed this at people who were ready to teach APCS-A, similar, or beyond and also to start to build a community for these teachers.
We had trouble setting things up for February but we&#39;re good to go for March, April and May.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use A Real Language</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 15:08:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</guid>
      <description>Why can&#39;t we use a real language!  This topic has been coming up a lot recently. Now I&#39;m not talking about the Drag and drop vs textual language thing. Let me be clear. To me a Drag and Drop language can certainly be a real language and many are. I also think they&#39;re terrific when used correctly. I just think they&#39;re frequently misapplied in later grades.
No, I&#39;m talking about people asking things like &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code, Data Structures, and Hidden Complexity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 15:17:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</guid>
      <description>Since 2015, Eric Wastl has gifted us each December with Advent of Code - a 25 day programming competition that I very much enjoy. This year I haven&#39;t been able to get to too many of the problems. I only completed the first two days on the day they were released, problem three a day late and then I didn&#39;t get back to the problems until almost 12/25 - the final day of the competition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting schools and talking tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 15:49:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</guid>
      <description>Back in September I talked about embarking on my Fall 2018 HS CS Tour. Since then I&#39;ve visited about a dozen schools. I&#39;d like to thank my friends who helped connect me to schools - particularly Aankit Patel and Diane Levitt.
Even though the original motivation for the visits was to get the word out about Hunter CS and the awesome things we&#39;re doing in the Hunter CS Honors program I always tried to make my talks about something that would be relevant for the entire audience and not just the few that were great fits for my program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Development - APCS-A, similar and beyond</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 08:56:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</guid>
      <description>A while ago I wrote about our plans at Hunter to run professional development for CS teachers. Specifically, running once a month sessions for teachers who teach APCS-A, similar and beyond.
The idea started as a joke but morphed into a legit idea.
I was talking to some friends about CTLE hours and how ridiculous the system is. NY State teachers need 100 hours of CTLE credit (PD hours) every so many years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Sorting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 20:04:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I saw a facebook post asking for thoughts on teaching sorting. The question was specifically not about motivations like having the class act out sorts or sort cards but rather about the coding.
I&#39;ve been meaning to write about this since last summer when I attended Owen Astrachan&#39;s talk on the same subject.
Early in my career when teaching sorting I developed the n^2 sorts as standalone routines just as they&#39;re presented in most books but as I gained more experience as a teacher, I changed it up to build the sorts (at least some of them) from existing concepts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Globals Breaks And Returns, oh my</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 15:48:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</guid>
      <description>Never use global variables Never break out of a loop  These are two &#34;best practices&#34; that are frequently touted in early CS classes both at the high school and college level.
They came up a couple of times yesterday. Once in the Facebook APCS-A teachers group and once on Alfred Thompson&#39;s blog.
Alfred post was topically on global variables. Actually it was deeper than just global variables. It&#39;s also about how students progress - what they can figure out at various stages of progress and how what seems like a good idea early on the path to computer science doesn&#39;t seem so great later on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the students know more than the teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 16:07:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;ve heard it many times with computer science - &#34;the kids know more than the teacher.&#34;
On the one hand, the truth is that this isn&#39;t so much the case. Kids might use computers all the time but they don&#39;t necessarily know much about them or about computer science (link 1, link 2). Then you have students who think they know all about CS but really don&#39;t. They might have picked up a bit of coding somewhere but more often than not, the knowledge is pretty superficial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve written before about why Hunter College CS is so important for NYC and I&#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors CS program - a program in which students receive a scholarship along with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have made a lot of progress over the past two years and each year I roll out new special activities and events for my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS vs CT vs Coding</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 12:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s been a lot of buzz recently concernting Computational Thinking (CT) vs Computer Science (CS) vs Coding / Programming on the interwebs.
 Some of the questions and concerns that I&#39;ve seen recently include: What is CT?? Will rich schools get CS and poor only CT? Will rich schools get CS and poor on coding?  The first question is a big one and as a community we haven&#39;t answered it yet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>