<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 15:43:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/community/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Class Legends</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/class-legends/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 15:43:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/class-legends/</guid>
      <description>Let&#39;s talk about something other than distance learning and COVID-19.
You know you&#39;ve been doing something a long time when you&#39;ve got legends.
Over on my alumni mailing list JonAlf shared a web site showing off what his current students were doing in their computer graphics class. Somewhere in the thread, Con replied:
 Someone should put up a video of the fabulous and fantastically famous hand animation called FINGER.MDL. It dates from a little before my time, but stories elevated it to legendary status.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Focus To Feel Normal</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/focus-to-feel-normal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 17:46:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/focus-to-feel-normal/</guid>
      <description>Austin Cory Bart tweeted this a little while ago.
I don&amp;#39;t always consider how much power I have as a faculty. Right now, I&amp;#39;d really like to expend that power to make my students understand that I don&amp;#39;t want them focused on my course during a global pandemic. Not right now. Later, but not right now.
&amp;mdash; Austin Cory Bart (@AustinCorgiBart) March 13, 2020 
While Cory&#39;s right about this it&#39;s also good to remember that as we&#39;re all going remote, focusing on our courses can be important for our students not merely due to content but in this time of uncertainty to have something to focus on to remind us of community and remind us of normal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Remote Classes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/remote-classes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 09:34:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/remote-classes/</guid>
      <description>Over at AVC Fred Wilson just posted about Outschool&#39;s efforts to support students and teachers in the event of school closures due to the Coronavirus. All the details and relevant links are in the post.
I looked a bit into Outschool when Fred first wrote about them but never had a chance to do a deep dive.
Now, internet based teaching is not going to be as effective as in person teaching but I was thinking about how far things have come.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSEvents.nyc</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 18:52:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago, a handful of CS Ed folks got together. One issue we discussed was that of finding CS related events both for students and teachers.
One of our conveners, Dan Fenjves of UPPERLINE CODE talked about possibly hosting a central site. Today, Dan announced http://csevents.nyc/. A site where organizers can submit and students and teachers can find upcoming events. Right now it&#39;s NY centric but it does list some events beyond the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CS Education Subreddit</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 07:37:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</guid>
      <description>Amy Ko posted this yesterday:
CSEd people: many have struggled to use Twitter for discussion. How about Twitter for broadcasting, but when replies turn to discussion, we use https://t.co/2oivuriOoU? It&amp;#39;s a better (albeit imperfect) platform for civil discourse. Subreddit mods @AustinCorgiBart @zamansky?
&amp;mdash; Amy J. Ko (@amyjko) February 21, 2020 
I&#39;d love to see more traffic there. For full disclosure, I&#39;m one of the moderators but in my defense, I&#39;m not much of a moderator and as Cory said, I too am happy to either keep moderating or to step aside.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presenting At CSTA 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 13:05:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</guid>
      <description>Presenting at CSTA 2020 I noticed a few tweets and posts from people announcing that they&#39;d be presenting at CSTA2020 - the big computer science teachers conference held every July.
A common thread in a few of these were trepidation&#39;s presenters. Excited to be doing this but nervous.
It&#39;s interesting that teachers, myself included, sometimes get nervous before presentations even though we present every day as part of our jobs. I know it&#39;s different as we have the same kids every day but even day 1 jitters each semester aren&#39;t the same as the presentation anxiety that some of us face.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels in the Architecture - when they used to build schools like cathedrals.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 07:31:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</guid>
      <description>One of the side benefits of visiting high schools is that I end up going all over the city. This takes me to neighborhoods that I normally wouldn&#39;t have reason to visit. For a New York History wonk that can be pretty cool even if you just limit yourself to looking at the schools. A few of the schools I visited in the last couple of weeks before the new year were self contained whole building schools:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:59:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</guid>
      <description>Thanksgiving weekend is also reunion weekend. I&#39;ve been on and off invited to Stuy reunions over the years. Not as often it seems as some teachers but more often than others. I always do my best to attend. I have very fond memories of many students and many classes over many years and think a lot about them so feel very honored whenever I&#39;m invited to one of these.
In the past each class due a reunion did its own thing - some club or bar usually in Manhattan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a feeling of community. Students aren&#39;t on campus every day and come from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&#39;t have a CS &#34;hang out&#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&#39;re scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
I&#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>