<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Assessments on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/assessments/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Assessments on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 17:13:24 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/assessments/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My test grading policy</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/grading-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 17:13:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/grading-policy/</guid>
      <description>I was working on writing a midterm the other day so figured I&#39;d talk a bit about my test grading policy.
Before getting to the specifics, let me set the stage. I spent most of my career at Stuyvesant - a public magnet school in NYC. There are many great students who are interested in learning but there&#39;s also a focus on grades. and this leads to a non-insignificant portion of the student body that is grade obsessed and will do everything and anything for every point possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating Perfect AP Exam Scores</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/celebrating-perfect-scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 12:24:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/celebrating-perfect-scores/</guid>
      <description>So, it turns out that there were 601 perfect scores on this years APCS-A exam. Over on Facebook a great question was raised - what does this mean and should we celebrate this?
What does it mean? There&#39;s no way to know. Maybe the number of perfect scores is just scaling up linearly with test takers. Maybe More kids are being exposed to CS prior to APCS-A and that&#39;s leading to more correct answers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Grades</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/predicting-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 12:03:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/predicting-grades/</guid>
      <description>Just saw this:
Evaluation metric idea: take snapshots of students&amp;#39; grades each week (specifically, the grade they actually see in your LMS). How well do these correlate with your final assigned grade? Were students getting good estimates?
&amp;mdash; Austin Cory Bart (@AustinCorgiBart) May 18, 2019 
It made me think of a couple of conversations I had with more senior teachers early in my career.
They&#39;d tell me &#34;by and large, you know what the kids are going to get after a few week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do the students finish the tests or does the test finish the students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tests-finish-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tests-finish-students/</guid>
      <description>I tweeted this the other day:
Why don&amp;#39;t so many teachers and professors understand that the test or assignment you can do in 15 minutes will take your beginning students at least an hour and probably a lot more to complete.
&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) April 18, 2018 
What led to the tweet was a discussion I was having with some students about not having enough time on tests which led to a discussion of having to drop everything to spend every waking hour on a project.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>