<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>java on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/java/</link>
    <description>Recent content in java on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:29:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/java/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Java IDES for teaching teachers.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:29:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</guid>
      <description>Since Hunter uses C++ as it&amp;#39;s core language, I haven&amp;#39;t used Java much in the past three years. That&amp;#39;s going to change pretty soon. Once we start offering our CS teacher Certificate and Masters programs I&amp;#39;ll once again start teaching with Java as that&amp;#39;s one of the langauges that we want to prepare our teachers with.  That means deciding on a set of tools and so I&amp;#39;ve been spending time evaluating Java programming environments with an eye on the beginner since not only do the teachers I work with have to be comfortable with the tool but more importantly they will have to be able to support the tool for all of their students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 09:40:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>Two of the hardest topics to make meaningful to students in APCS-A are inheritance and interfaces. It&amp;#39;s not that they&amp;#39;re super difficult topics but rather that they&amp;#39;re not often needed, useful, or superior to not using them on beginner assignments. More often than not the motivation is a bit forced as are the assignments.  Inheritance is its own can of worms and to be honest, something I&amp;#39;ve not found to be all that useful or necessary.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>