<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CS on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (CS)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 12:10:53 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Sort over Zoom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/qsort-over-zoom/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 12:10:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/qsort-over-zoom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t been blogging much this year. Not sure why - probably pandemic
fatigue. It&amp;#39;s also affected my blog reading - more scanning, less deep
reading. I&amp;#39;ve also been trying to spend mode time off screen learning
how to paint (with,let&amp;#39;s say  mixed results :-) ) leaving less time
and energy to blog. Hopefully I&amp;#39;ll pick up on both ends as more people
get vaccinated and we can get to a more normal life. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, I tried a new motivation for Quicksort today so I
thought I&amp;#39;d share.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve approached teaching the Quicksort in a variety of ways (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/try-something-new/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quick-sort-starting/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-03-14-sorting-from-top-and-from-bottom/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-12-select-to-sort/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) but never had a great lead in activity. Merge sort
was easy in person since you can &amp;#34;Tom Sawyer&amp;#34; &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-27-dumbass/&#34;&gt;shuffling a deck of
cards&lt;/a&gt; in class. We adapted this activity pretty well to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/merge-over-zoom/&#34;&gt;work over Zoom&lt;/a&gt;
this past summer in our teacher certification program. Quicksort
however, haven&amp;#39;t found a good one. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thinking about how to leverage remote, I had an idea to try - use
polls. I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://zulip.com/&#34;&gt;Zulip&lt;/a&gt; for class discussions. It&amp;#39;s like Slack but is open
source, can be self hosted, you can post from email,  and has much
better threading. I wrote a small bot to quickly create emoji
polls. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First I asked for the students to share their birtdays - just month
and day in the form MMDD so if you were born on March 12th you would
write 0312 in the chat. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, I picked one birthday at random, let&amp;#39;s say 0515. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then created a poll: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
🐶 My birthday is earlier in the year than 0515
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
🐱 My birthday is later in the year than 0515
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The bot tags the post with the emoji and the class can click on their
choice. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then talk about what we now know - 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We now know the exact location of 0515 with respect to all the
dates
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The data set is now partially ordered (everything less than 0515 to
the left, greater to the right).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also drew out some diagrams showing what was happening 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is also one iteration of the Quicksort. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We do this again on one side and continue to discuss. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From here we finish developing the algorithm and we&amp;#39;re off to the
races.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, I won&amp;#39;t know for a while how well this worked or if it did
at all but the students seemed to be engaged and so far I think it
helped get a good feel for how the algorithm worked. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Using Zulip or other chat polls in this case made the motivating
activity easy and seamless. I&amp;#39;m not sure that this particular activity
would be as easy to implement in person unless you used some
technology like clickers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We finished off the class discussing how we should test our
implementations. They&amp;#39;re going to test the sorts on a variety of data
sets including sets where all values are the same or are already
sorted. Given our naive pivot selection this should lead to some
pretty bad runtimes – fodder to motivate the next class.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Teaching Recursion</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/recursion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 13:49:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/recursion/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I read three posts on teaching recursion. &lt;a href=&#34;https://parentheticallyspeaking.org/articles/how-not-to-teach-recursion/&#34;&gt;First&lt;/a&gt; by Shriram
Krishnamurthi discussing his thoughts on how recursion is taught
incorrectly. This prompted Adam Michlin to &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.ceos.io/2021/01/02/why-you-shouldnt-teach-recursion-yet/&#34;&gt;write about&lt;/a&gt; teaching
recursion later with some commentary on APCS and then finally, Alfred
Thompson added &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.acthompson.net/2021/01/recursionhow-and-when-to-teach.html&#34;&gt;his thoughts&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Much like everything else in education there is no single right way to
do things. To say as an absolute that you should or shouldn&amp;#39;t teach in
a certain way is wrong - too many variable.s In my experience you can
teach recursion early or late but the structure of your program and
your choice of tools can influence how successful you&amp;#39;ll be. If you&amp;#39;re
teaching a programming course in a language like Python or Java and
are teaching control structures first you&amp;#39;re going to have a hard time
doing recursion early. They&amp;#39;ll get looping structures before they know
the constructs that support recursion - either for control or for
representing data. On the other hand, if you teach objects first you
might have more success.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if you&amp;#39;re using a language like Scheme where lists
and recursion are right in the forefront you&amp;#39;ll likely have more
success with recursion early rather than late. I wrote a bit about
this &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/recursion-early/&#34;&gt;a couple of years ago&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll leave the &amp;#34;how important is recursion&amp;#34; question for annother time
but I want to address one more thing here. In yesterday&amp;#39;s posts four
traditional recursion problems received a solid bashing and I don&amp;#39;t
think it was fair. As I said up top, &lt;del&gt;only a Sith deals in absolutes&lt;/del&gt;
in teaching, there are no absolutes. Is factorial a wonderful
motivation for recursion - particularly for a student who knows loops?
Probably not but can it have some value? Let&amp;#39;s see…
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Factorial
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While this might not be a terrific motivator it does have some
niceties. Most students will know factorial but will only be able
describe it informally - &amp;#34;multiply all the numbers between 1 and n.&amp;#34;
The recursive definition is more, precise, for lack of a better word.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, there&amp;#39;s a direct translation between the recursive definition
and the code. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, it&amp;#39;s about as bare bones as you get - no data structures or
undue complexity. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is this going to motivate a student to learn recursion? No.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Can it be used to help paint a more complete picture? Probably.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Fibonacci 
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also got a bad rap in the above linked posts. It shares the benefit of
the recursive definition directly translating to a coded solution with
factorial. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fibonacci is also a problem where they originally learned it via the
recurssive rule &amp;#34;the next Fibonacci number is the sum of the two
previous fibonacci numbers.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It also seems that when students find the Fibonacci number problem
challenging to solve as beginners without recursion. The whole a
becomes b. b becomes c thing can be tricky for beginners. In  my
experience, they find the recursive solution to be more natural. This
is also interesting because they usually don&amp;#39;t find recursive
factorial more natural than a loop (assuming they learned loops
first).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, the slowness of the solution is feature, not a bug. It&amp;#39;s a
platform to talk about how recursion isn&amp;#39;t always the answer but you
can think about a problem recursively and if the solution isn&amp;#39;t right
it might lead you to a better solution. This comes up later with
dynamic programming. Just last year (he he) during Advent of Code I
ended up solving one of the problems via dynamic programming. How did
I get there? Thinking about the problem recursively. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here you get a great platform for now comparing solutions - iterative,
recursive, tail recursive, memoization - take it as far as you want.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Euclid&amp;#39;s algorithm 
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can&amp;#39;t comment on Euclid&amp;#39;s algorithm since I can&amp;#39;t recall ever
teaching it as part of recursion so I&amp;#39;ll substitute Newton&amp;#39;s method
for square root approximation. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The thing is that here, the goal isn&amp;#39;t really recursion. It&amp;#39;s just a
problem that can be tackled with either recursion or iteration. The
reason it&amp;#39;s a neat problem is because you can talk about floating
point accuracy issues along with how close of an approximation you
might want or need. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Towers of Hanoi
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally we get the Towers of Hanoi. Sure it&amp;#39;s contrived but it can
also be fun and by being a new and different problem students can try
to use any strategies that might lead to a solution, recursive or
otherwise:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
try some small examples
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
see if examples relate to each other
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
base case?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big deal though is that Towers of Hanoi isn&amp;#39;t really about Towers
of Hanoi - it&amp;#39;s really a platform to talk about all sorts of good
stuff. I wrote all about it &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-10-towers-of-hanoi/&#34;&gt;a decade ago&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Other stuff
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, of course you can introduce recursion in other ways particularly
if you use a language like Scheme. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bottom line is that without taking into considerations lots of other
factors - student backgrounds, teacher comfort. Time, experience,
facilities, goals and desired aoutcomes, and more you can&amp;#39;t really say
one way is right or one way is wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrary Trees</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/arbitrary-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 18:45:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/arbitrary-trees/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been 10 days from my last post. Not really a big break for me
historically but certainly a big one given how much I&amp;#39;ve been posting
this year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Been under the weather for the past couple of weeks dealing with
COVID-19. Haven&amp;#39;t had super bad symptoms and as symptoms have been
getting fewer and less severe I&amp;#39;m hoping I&amp;#39;m close to a full recovery.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, I&amp;#39;m feeling good enough for a quick post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my data structures class we&amp;#39;ve been working on binary trees. Most
of the unit is focused on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_search_tree&#34;&gt;Binary Search Trees&lt;/a&gt;. They used to be a big
part of the B part of the old APCS-AB and are still a mainstay of
college CS2 classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, we covered all the basics. Creation, insertion, search,
traversal, and deletion. We discovered the run times and how a tree
structure can yield lgn behavior but can also degenerate to linear. We
also give a preview of more advanced data structures like red/back and
2-3 trees that address these issues (not to mention things like BTrees
and Splay trees).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One side topic I always like talking about during this unit though are
arbitrary trees. That is, trees where each node can have an arbitrary
number of children. Students usually start by creating nodes with an
array of children and then sometimes a linked list of children but I
like discussing something simpler. A tree where in each node you hold
two pointers - a pointer to the first child and a pointer to the next
sibling. I like this because internally it&amp;#39;s the same as a binary
search tree where you also have two pointers in each node a left and a
right. Same &amp;#34;physical&amp;#34; representation but two very different
variations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/arbtree.png&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The image on the left is the actual arbitrary tree and the one on the
right shows the internal representation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of applications, the file system is a
great example of an arbitrary tree. Another one that I like even more
is the DOM representation of a web page. That&amp;#39;s nice because there are
Javascript functions to get the next sibling.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I put a short video together for my class. Here it is in case anyone
is interested. It&amp;#39;s code agnostic so would be suitable for an APCS-A
class that also covers data structures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K1lR3ssgxLc&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K1lR3ssgxLc&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Problems</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 08:12:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I organize a monthly professional development session for CS
teachers. It&amp;#39;s targeted at teachers who are beyond the beginner stage
and don&amp;#39;t want yet another hello world blinky arduino scratch
workshop. Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, given the need for CS teachers we need
plenty of beginner workshops but we also need to take teachers to the
next level. I refer to my workshops as being for teachers of APCS-A,
similar, or beyond. Participants get three hours of CTLE credit and
thanks to our gracious hosts at &lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalocean.com&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; get to use a great space
and enjoy a free meal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I particularly enjoyed last weeks workshop for two reasons. One is
that we talked about &amp;#34;interesting problems.&amp;#34; This in itself is
interesting because different teachers find different things
interesting. For me, this time around, I was thinking of problems that
could be approached by beginners but had some interesting insight that
allowed them to look at the problem differently and solve it more
efficiently. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second reason I liked this session is because I wasn&amp;#39;t the only
one presenting!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started the session talking about the Happy Ladybugs problem - a
Hackerrank problem I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then passed off to Justin who talked about finding the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull&#34;&gt;convex hull&lt;/a&gt;
bounding a set of points. Justin talked about how you can relate this
abstract geometry problem to real world problems like bounding
neighborhoods as well as how this can be graphically motivated and
then moved to discussing &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull_algorithms&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;. Students can pretty easily come
up with a in inefficient O(n^4) solution and then Justin talked about
incrementally guiding them through alternate solutions ending with
something that runs in O(nlgn). At the end of the day we had a problem
that could be done in a variety of ways with students at different
levels of experience. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then moved to Barry&amp;#39;s presentation of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baphl.org/20/&#34;&gt;puzzle hunt&lt;/a&gt; problem he
adapted. It involved decoding, translation, number bases and Barry
uses it as a platform to work with stacks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I finished the evening talking about three problems but we didn&amp;#39;t look
at solutions. These were teasers for next time when we also hope to do a
SIGCSE recap.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My code works -- and I have no idea why!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/my-code-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 16:22:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/my-code-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://encrypted-tbn0.gstatic.com/images?q=tbn%3AANd9GcT-4l2Bv_a85wYiS-5pWgYdfb6lb50CIwZ3GvjtNIwqVL1VruoL&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my pet annoyances is how code ecosystems have gotten more and
more complex. Sometimes I think tool designers put together build
systems to show how clever they are rather than to solve dependency
problems as cleanly and simply as possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the break I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-org-explorer/&#34;&gt;GitHub Org Explorer&lt;/a&gt; - a tool to help deal with
GitHub classroom repositories. It worked but was using &amp;#34;basic&amp;#34;
authentication where it sent a username and password with every
request. As GitHub was deprecating that from their API I started to
look at converting the application to use oauth. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First I threw together a little &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojurescript-electron-oauth-test&#34;&gt;proof of concept app&lt;/a&gt; that just
authenticated with GitHub and then started to move that code into my
explorer app.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First problem – the code that that worked in the proof of concept was
crashing out in my actual app. I ultimately did a line by line
analysis and couldn&amp;#39;t find a difference. Even the configuration files
appeared the same. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, in a fit of desperation, I killed all the supporting
libraries that the build system installed and downloaded them again. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It worked!!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It didn&amp;#39;t inspire much confidence though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I went on and finished converting the app to oauth. All done,
right? Wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I tried to build everything on another system and it crashed
out. Weird. It worked on one machine but not another. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Solved that problem by wiping out the entire build system - node and
npm using nvm and shadow-cljs and it worked.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But it didn&amp;#39;t. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was one final hurdle. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I used the build system to compile and run in &amp;#34;development&amp;#34; mode
everything worked. Compile for production? Not so much.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What could it be?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After about a day of fretting, I discovered  that for some reason,
when compiling for dev you get certain libraries including a string
formatting one I was using. When compiling for production you didn&amp;#39;t
get them. Why would anyone set up a build system that way???????
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Given that I&amp;#39;m using a bunch of tools that I&amp;#39;m new to - using
shadow-cljs to go from clojurescript to javascript all ending up with
a build for the electron platform - I just stopped using the library 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Problem solved. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, sort of. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can now run my app but I&amp;#39;m still not filled with confidence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;ve been at this game for a very long time. I&amp;#39;ve been
programming for around 40 years. Imagine what it&amp;#39;s like for student or
beginner.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can&amp;#39;t tell you how many times I&amp;#39;ve seen a post on the learn
programming subreddit from some beginner who learned using an online
tool or in a class that had them develop in a sandbox and they left
with no clue how to write a real program outside of the classroom
environment. If they&amp;#39;re not prepared to merely write a program outside
of some courseware system they&amp;#39;ll have little chance going up against
webpack, lienengen, cmake and the like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying that we should throw our beginners out into the wild
and start them with vi, C, and autotools but nobody&amp;#39;s paying attention
to the whole journey from Hello World to the real world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Somebody should.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI For All</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-ai-for-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 07:00:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-ai-for-all/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday we had another Professional Development Workshop for High
School CS Teachers and as usual, I wnat to express my thanks to
&lt;a href=&#34;digitalocean.com&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; for continuing to provide space, food, and great overall support.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This time though, instead of JonAlf and I having
to run the show we had a guest speaker. We were joined by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd&#34;&gt;Sarah Judd&lt;/a&gt;
of &lt;a href=&#34;http://ai-4-all.org/about/what-is-ai/&#34;&gt;AI4ALL&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sarah gave an overview of what AI4ALL was up to and why but the core
of her presentation was taking us through some of the exercises 
they have been developing at AI4All. Specifically, they&amp;#39;re developing
what they call &lt;a href=&#34;http://ai-4-all.org/open-learning/&#34;&gt;AI4All Open Learning&lt;/a&gt; which consists of curricular
materials aimed at high school students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we only had a short time, Sarah took us on a whirlwind tour of what
they&amp;#39;re building from the baseline concepts of AI that she feels (and
I agree) that every students should know up to specific AI topics like
neural nets. Obviously you can&amp;#39;t cover even a single course in one
evening professional development session but Sarah did a great job
giving both a taste and an overview.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The activities were all engaging and and covered both ethical/societal
issues as well as the technical/CS. I appreciated that the materials weren&amp;#39;t
presented as canned experiences but rather tools that a teacher would
use to deliver their own experiences. On the other hand I&amp;#39;m skeptical
of the website&amp;#39;s claims of &amp;#34;No AI or computer science experience
necessary.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m a firm believer that a CS teacher must know both CS
and how to teach it - maybe not at first due to necessity, but
ultimately. Regardless, Sarah has both real teaching experience and CS
knowledge and I put more faith in what she&amp;#39;s saying than a PR blurb on a
web site. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now you&amp;#39;ll notice I haven&amp;#39;t said anything specific about Sarah&amp;#39;s
presentation or AI4All and that&amp;#39;s because Sarah will be giving a
variation of it at SIGCSE in March. If you teach high school and are
going to be at SIGCSE, I highly recommend you check out her session.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If not, perhaps I&amp;#39;ll blog more specifics after the event.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping Current Between Semesters</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/keeping-current-between-semesters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 11:56:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/keeping-current-between-semesters/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
People say that one of the impossible problems for CS teachers is
keeping current - they say the field is constantly changing, how can a
teacher keep up with all the new things going on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, on the one hand it isn&amp;#39;t true - most of the core of CS is the
same. We still teach roughly the same programming constructs, data
structures and algorithms. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, it is true. When I was in college, OOP was just
starting to pick up steam and now an established and one might argue,
dominant paradigm. Functional programming has been around forever but
is only recently making inroads into the mainstream. Some fields have
radically changed. Just look at AI and related fields now that data is
so abundant. I remember looking over a Natural Language Processing
text in the mid 90s and it was all about programs with tons of if
statements. A later edition read more like a statistics text book.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there are the changing technologies - the web and how we program
it, new languages, embedded systems are more accesible and much more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So the field both changes and stays the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the ways I try to stay on top of things is with my own personal
projects. We encourage our students to write side projects
to scratch itches so why shouldn&amp;#39;t we do the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This might be taking a course like when I did the Stanford online AI
and ML courses or it might be writing something like when I wanted to
figure out that &lt;a href=&#34;https://reactjs.org/&#34;&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; thing that was all the rage a couple of years
ago but ended up diving more deeply into  &lt;a href=&#34;https://vuejs.org/&#34;&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; as I felt it made
more sense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that we&amp;#39;re between semesters at Hunter I thought I&amp;#39;d scratch an
itch related to &lt;a href=&#34;https://classroom.github.com/classrooms&#34;&gt;GitHub Classroom&lt;/a&gt;. I love the tool but it has two pain
points. First, you end up accumulating a HUGE number of repositories
(one per student per assignment) and deleting them is a bear of a
task. The second is that while you can download all the submissions
for a given assignment, there&amp;#39;s no easy way to download all the
assignments for a given student. There are also some issues mapping
student names to GitHub accounts but I&amp;#39;ve pretty much worked that one
out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I figured I&amp;#39;d spend some time this December and January learning
some new technologies adn writing something to make those pain points
go away.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what will I be learning about?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
The GitHub API
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve worked with APIs before and even messed around with &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt;. The
change is that their &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/v4/&#34;&gt;latest&lt;/a&gt; version uses GraphQL which brings me to my
first brand new technology:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
GraphQL
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://graphql.org/&#34;&gt;GraphQL&lt;/a&gt; is a query language developed by Facebook for APIs. In spite
of the name, it has nothing to do with databases. The idea is instead
of a bunch of random REST endpoints with every API call being
different you have one endpoint. You put together a query describing
what you want and the services responds with your content. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It looks pretty neat but we&amp;#39;ll see.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Reagent / Clojurescript
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next thing I&amp;#39;ll be playing with is &lt;a href=&#34;https://clojurescript.org/&#34;&gt;Clojurescript&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://reagent-project.github.io/&#34;&gt;Reagent&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;ve
been playing on and off with Clojure for a while ahd Clojurescript
transpiles Clojure to Javascript instead of compiling for the
JVM. I&amp;#39;ve  already made a few &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life&#34;&gt;small&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-breakout&#34;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-snake&#34;&gt;using&lt;/a&gt; it and like it much
better for the web than Javascript. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learnreagent.com/&#34;&gt;Reagent&lt;/a&gt; is essentially React for
Clojurescript.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Electron
&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought for a while about doing this as a command line tool since
that&amp;#39;s how I usually work but decided that if I do finish it something
GUI based might be useful to more people. I then considered a web
applicaiton but realized that wouldn&amp;#39;t do since there isn&amp;#39;t a way to
clone GitHub repos from a web application due to security issues. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then briefly considered doing a Clojure based GUI which would
basically be something like a Java Swing application but then decided
to explore &lt;a href=&#34;https://electronjs.org/&#34;&gt;Electron&lt;/a&gt;. An Electron appication is essentially a locally
run web application. You write it in a similar manner to a web app -
HTML/CSS/JS or in my case Clojurescript but then it&amp;#39;s run locally on a
platfomr based on the open source Chromium browser. Since it&amp;#39;s running
locally it has access to the local filesystem and resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve already started to play with things and already learned a
lot. Looking forward to coming out of this with a bunch of new
technologies and tools in the toolbelt and maybe an application that
will solve a couple of annoyances with what&amp;#39;s overall a great product.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi Stage Assignments - the good and the bad - Advent of Code</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/multi-stage-assignments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 17:19:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/multi-stage-assignments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
In the real world you&amp;#39;re usually not building your own projects from
scratch. Much more frequently you&amp;#39;re working on a team and you and
other players come and go over time. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is in stark contrast to most CS educational experiences where
students typically complete relatively small assignments from
beginning to end. One of my biggest fears way back when as I was about
to graduate college was when I woke up one night in a cold sweath &amp;#34;oh
crap - in a couple of weeks I&amp;#39;m going to have to actually produce good
code. Not just code good enough to get by the grader.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, as a general rule,  having students build a project and then later
extend it or, even better, having them extend another student&amp;#39;s project
can be a very good experience. On the other hand, it can also be a
very bad one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great feeling when you leverage a previous project to create
something new. On the other hand, there can be tremendous frustration
if the original project forms a faulty foundation and you have to go
back and rebuild and even then you&amp;#39;re never 100% sure that you&amp;#39;re
building on a solid base.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Building on a previous project has been big in this years &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of
Code&lt;/a&gt;. It started with &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/2&#34;&gt;day 2&lt;/a&gt; when we were asked to write a simple
computer that ran &amp;#34;intcode programs.&amp;#34; Not a bad little challenge. It
then returned in &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/5&#34;&gt;day 5&lt;/a&gt; where we had to add a number of features to our
intcode machines. This too was a nice assignment. It had to be built
on a correct and complete day 2 solution but as far as I could tell,
regardless of how you completed day 2 there was a straightforward way
to extend it to integrate the requirements for day 5.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Things got interesting in &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/7&#34;&gt;day 7&lt;/a&gt; and this is where a teacher, or
competition designer for that matter has to start being careful. Day 5
had us modify and build on day 2 but day 7 had us &lt;strong&gt;use&lt;/strong&gt; what we
created in days 2 and 5. From a teacher who&amp;#39;s building assignments
point of view, this changes the equation. Day 2 and 5 had you build
something that took some input and produced some output. Now, in day 7
you had to do something on top of your intcode machine, feed it into
it (or them as it turned out) and get an output. Depending on the
assumptions you made in building your intcode machine you would either
have an easy time with day 7 or you&amp;#39;d have to go back and redo day 2
and/or 5 - much less fun. As part 2 of day 7 had us running multiple
intcode machines &amp;#34;simultaneously,&amp;#34; my set up didn&amp;#39;t work. I still have
to go back and finish that problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Herein lies a big problem with multi part assignments. Unless you
really lay out the parameters of the early assignment students can,
and frequently will make assumptions you never dreamed of. Those
assumptions can make their lives easier in parts 2 and beyond but it
can also leave them with an impossible task. This on top of any
student that doesn&amp;#39;t finish the early version to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moving on, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/9&#34;&gt;day 9&lt;/a&gt; added some more features to the intcode machine and
since then, days &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt; have all used our intcode
machine. I&amp;#39;ve had issues with my machine for days 11 and 13 and have
to fix my intcode machine&amp;#39;s input/output handling to finish those
challenges but my machine worked well enough to complete days 15, 17,
and 19.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, at the end of the day building on a previous project can be very
cool and for a student very rewarding but it can also be really
challenging. On top of the issue I&amp;#39;ve already talked about this can
also leave students in a very uneasy state when extending a project by
using it rather than building on it. Did they write the early parts
fully correctly or just enough to get by the early test cases? It can
be very unsettling to work on an uncertain foundation. What&amp;#39;s more,
while a teacher can even provide base code, this might only be useful
to help check results as now having a student use provided code adds
yet another challenge (albeit one that provides many useful lesosns).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to doing this in Advent of Code? I doubt &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ericwastl&#34;&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt; and the other
organizers will read this but in case they do, this isn&amp;#39;t a complaint
about Advent of Code. I love the event and we can all quibble about
details we like or don&amp;#39;t like. Advent of Code also isn&amp;#39;t a class with
a grade and if I never finish, let&amp;#39;s say, day 11, there are no
consequences - unlike if a student doesn&amp;#39;t finish part 2 of a graded
project. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m writing this because I think there are some interesting parallels
between creating an event like Advent of Code and designing projects
and lessons for students and more interestingly , where those //s
diverge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now to get to grading. Hoping to get done to spend at least a few
minutes on &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/20&#34;&gt;day 20&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 8 - addendum - generating inputs</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 17:04:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
As I said in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/8&#34;&gt;day 8&lt;/a&gt; would be a nice project or lesson in
an APCS-A or college CS1 class. Another nice problem would be to
write a program to generate an image in the format required by the
question. Alternatively, a teacher doing day 8 with their classes
might want to generate a bunch of images for the students to test
their decoders on. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I&amp;#39;d write one to see how appropriate it would be for the
students. I tried to do it without anything fancy or advanced.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, you&amp;#39;ll need a way to generate the block text for the
images. I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.patorjk.com/software/taag/#p=display&amp;amp;f=Banner3&amp;amp;t=Hello&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; site and used the &lt;strong&gt;Banner3&lt;/strong&gt; font. I generated
some text and saved it in a file. The important thing for our purposes
is that any space will count as white and any character as black.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The encoded image is a N * Width * Height sequence of digits  where
each Width * Height sequence of digits represents one layer. See the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/8&#34;&gt;problem text&lt;/a&gt; for details.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can follow along with the code &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day08-generator.py&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, here&amp;#39;s how the program works:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The top 51 lines of the program consist of a routine which I&amp;#39;ll
describe later and code to handle command line argument (to set the
number of layers).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, on line 55 I erad  in the file with the source image (from stdin). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In line 57 through 63, I loop over the data and changed each non space
or newline to a star character. I really don&amp;#39;t have to do this but I
wanted to see what the image looked like in just &amp;#34;black and white.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Line 65 through 67 is where I split on the newlines. Now I could take
the length of any line to get the image width and the number of lines
the height.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
70 through 79 creates a long list for the image. At each location, I
generate a list of values. Each list has one entry per layer. The
actual pixel value (1 or 0) is stored at a random location. Everything
before that is a random choice between the real color and transparent
and everything after is just random. Details for that step are in the
&lt;code&gt;genpixel&lt;/code&gt; routine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, in 83 through 89 I loop over each layer and for each layer
the image and and output all the values into a single string. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is then output to stdout while the dimensions go to stderr.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I had a source image in a file named &amp;#34;hello.dat&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;d convert it to
source input for day 8 by typing &lt;code&gt;cat hello.dat | python3 day08-generator.py
-l 10 &amp;gt; day08-input.dat&lt;/code&gt;. This would create a 10 layer input.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s it. Once again, the code is all &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day08-generator.py&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It would make for another
nice student assignment or for a teacher to prepare inputs for the
class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day - 8</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 08:42:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent most of last week up in Albany working on the NY State K12 CS
Standards so fell a bit behind. I had to go back to complete &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/5&#34;&gt;day 5&lt;/a&gt; but
still haven&amp;#39;t finished &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/7&#34;&gt;day 7&lt;/a&gt; which builds on day 5 which in turn
builds on &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/2&#34;&gt;day 2&lt;/a&gt;. I might not get to finishing 7 for a while but it
looks like a good chance to play with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.braveclojure.com/core-async/&#34;&gt;core.async&lt;/a&gt; - Clojure&amp;#39;s
facilities for concurrency. I also want to write up &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/6&#34;&gt;day 6&lt;/a&gt; but today
let&amp;#39;s look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/8&#34;&gt;day 8&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Day 8 is image processing problem so it fits nicely into an APCS-A
type class. You&amp;#39;re given the height and width of the image and you&amp;#39;re
told that the image comes in layers. The input is a long string of
digits. So, if you&amp;#39;re told that the width is 5 and height is 3 you
might get this as your input representing an image with 3 layers:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;100210120100120001102020112100000121002110102&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Adding commas and spaces:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;10021,01201,00120   00110,20201,12100   00012,10021,10102&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first part of the task is to find the layer with the most 0s and
return the number of 1s multiplied with the number of 2s.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is just a nice little data parsing problem. You have to break the
input into &lt;code&gt;width*height&lt;/code&gt; chunks, see which has the most zeros, count
the ones and the twos and return the result. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 is where the image stuff comes in. We&amp;#39;re told that a color
value of 0 is black, 1 is white, and 2 is transparent. We&amp;#39;re also told
that the image&amp;#39;s actual color is the first color it sees (black or
white) when going through the layers. Depending on how you read in
your data, this could be easy or hard. You have to scan down the
layers and keep the first non-transparent color. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1, I read my data into a list of lists where each item was a
layer. I did this in Clojure, but the Python representation of the
sample image above might look something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;[ [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;],
  [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;],
  [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was no reason to subdivide each layer into rows and columns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1, I wanted to have lists where each list was all the values
of each pixel across the layers. This meant &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transpose&#34;&gt;transposing&lt;/a&gt; the matrix -
tat is, if you look at the above list of lists as a matrix, switching
the rows and columns. This was pretty easy to do in Clojure using
&lt;code&gt;(apply mapv vector matrix)&lt;/code&gt; but it shouldn&amp;#39;t be too hard in other
languages.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, we have to keep the first non-transparent color we see in each
list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The final fun part is then taking the colors and printing out the
final image.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s what I got:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;XXX  XXXX  XX   XX  X  X 
X  X X    X  X X  X X X  
X  X XXX  X    X  X XX   
XXX  X    X    XXXX X X  
X    X    X  X X  X X X  
X    X     XX  X  X X  X &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s nice about this problem from a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view? First,
it&amp;#39;s the puzzle aspect of finding the hidden text. Second, it&amp;#39;s an
image problem which in APCS-A usually means 2D arrays but you can also
solve it without any 2D matrices. My solution involved a bunch of
filtering of data and the matrix transpose. Both interesting concepts
to bring to your classes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want to see my Clojure solution, you can find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day08.clj&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 4</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 19:32:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/4&#34;&gt;Day 4&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the day was spent working on the NY State CS standards
to I didn&amp;#39;t figure to have much time to work on the
problem. Fortunately, I was able to knock out part 1 before work
started and part 2 was a quick adjustment when I got back to it at the
start of lunch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once again, it was a problem with a few interesting teacher side
aspects.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I only wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day04.clj&#34;&gt;Clojure solution&lt;/a&gt; today so that&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;ll use for my
code examples.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The gist was that you were going to use a 6 digit integer as a
password but only  subset of the numbers between a start and end
point. Only numbers in that range for which these two properties held:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were at least one repeated digit, that is 123445 is o since
we have two consecutive 4s but 124354 isn&amp;#39;t
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The digits are increasing. That is, given any digit, the digit to
its right has either the same or a greater value.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You had to find the number of &amp;#34;valid passwords.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first read this sounds like a math problem but it really
isn&amp;#39;t. Looking at the first constraint, if you convert the number to a
string, looking to see that at least two consecutive characters are
the same is pretty easy - it&amp;#39;s just a simple loop. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that it&amp;#39;s even easier using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.regular-expressions.info/&#34;&gt;Regular Expressions&lt;/a&gt;. Regular
expressions (regex) aren&amp;#39;t usually an explicit part of a CS sequence
but man are they useful. Basically they allow you to set up a pattern
that will match text. Some examples:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;pattern&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matches&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;doesn&amp;#39;t match&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aa[0-9]bb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Matches aa a digit than bb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aa3bb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ax3b, aacbb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a+bb[a-z]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;one or more of a then two b then an a-z&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aabbc&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aabcb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can use parentheses to form a &amp;#34;match group&amp;#34; and then use &amp;#34;\1&amp;#34; to
match the group, so this regular expression:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-regex&#34; data-lang=&#34;regex&#34;&gt;([0-9])\1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
will match two any substring with two of digits, adjacent. Many regex
engines allow you to use &lt;strong&gt;\d&lt;/strong&gt; instead of &lt;strong&gt;[0-9]&lt;/strong&gt; as a shorthand for
match a single digit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the line that will take a list of potential passwords in a
variable &lt;strong&gt;passwords&lt;/strong&gt; and return a list that only containsn the
passwords that meet the two consecutive of the same digit rule.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(filter &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(re-seq &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;(\d)\1&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; %) passwords)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I knew that Python has a &lt;strong&gt;partition&lt;/strong&gt; function that would take a string
with a potential password (I convert the number to a string before
doing the regex test above). It would take a string &amp;#34;1245&amp;#34; and convert
it into something like this &lt;strong&gt;(1,2), (2,3), (3,4), (4,5)&lt;/strong&gt;. Here&amp;#39;s the instruction:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;partition&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; %) passwords)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next we test each pair in the partition to see that the first value in
the pair is less than or equal to the second one:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(every? (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;fn &lt;/span&gt;[ [a b]] (&amp;lt;= (int a) (int b))) %) passwrods)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pull out the ones where the above is true and count them:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(count (filter true?))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that&amp;#39;s part one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Python equivalent would be easier to read for the non-lisper but
the idea is the same and pretty straightforward. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I like is that we just solved a number problem without math, just
text processing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 is more of the same. This time we still need a pair of adjacent
same digits but runs of 3 or more didn&amp;#39;t count. Now, 122234 wouldn&amp;#39;t
be a valid password because the run is of 3 while 1222344 would
because while the repeated 2s don&amp;#39;t count the 4s would.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, this is just more text processing:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Check to make sure the sequence is increasing (as above)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remove all the sequences of 3 or more repeats. This can also be
xdone using a regular expression search and replace. In Clojure
it&amp;#39;s:
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;     cleaned (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;string/replace&lt;/span&gt; s &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;([0-9])\1\1+&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;) 
     &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
The [0-9]\1\1+ says match any sequence of 3 or more of the same
digit and we replace it with an empty string.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the remaining string has a pair of adjacent same digits (as
above) its a valid password.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that&amp;#39;s it. Both parts solved as a text processing problem. What
I love here is that it seems to be a numeric problem but it has a text
based solution. Certainly something worth talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another thing I thought about as a teacher but didn&amp;#39;t pay attention to
in my solution was efficiency. My range consisted of about 500,000
values to check. Not huge enough to make a time difference but it&amp;#39;s
worth noting that there are only about 500 that fulfill the
&amp;#34;increasing&amp;#34; requirement but almost 200,000 that have a double digit
subsequence. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This means it could be more efficient to look for increasing first and
throw away most of the data and then do the digit test. This type of
ordering can be a big deal for other problems so could be worth
discussing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another issue is pipelining. Are you looping over the entire (or even
culled) data set over and over or can you take each number and put it
through a sequence of tests and/or transformations - the pipeline
could also lead to a more efficient solution.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of good teacher fodder.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In closing I&amp;#39;ll mention one last thought - not mine but rather a
suggestion I found while perusing the Advent of Code subreddit after I
had submitted my solutions 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Someone noted that since a valid number has increasing digits, if
digits appear more than once they &lt;strong&gt;have&lt;/strong&gt; to be adjacent to each
other. If they weren&amp;#39;t they&amp;#39;d violate the increasing restriction. This
means that you could solve this problem more numerically by:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
do the &amp;#34;increasing&amp;#34; test
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Find the sum of the counts of each digit value (0 through 9)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Test to see if at least one digit appears twice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Based on tomorrows schedule I doubt I&amp;#39;ll get to AoC day 5 but we&amp;#39;ll
see.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 3</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 19:01:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/3&#34;&gt;problem&lt;/a&gt; dealt with intersecting paths. You start with two
inputs, figure out the paths they represent and where they intersect
and then find the intersection that correctly answers the question.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1 you have to find the intersection closest to the
origin. From a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view, the interesting part here is
data representation. This problem deals with a two dimensional grid on
which the paths live. For most students, at least in my experience, if
they&amp;#39;re trained in a language like C++ or Java they go for the direct
representation - a 2D array. For many problems this makes a lot of
sense. For this one, however, it probably doesn&amp;#39;t. We start at a
specific point but can travel in any direction for any distance. This
means we might need a crazy large array and what&amp;#39;s more, it&amp;#39;s probably
going to be sparsely filled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A more practical solution involves maintaining a data structure with
just the individual points of interest - the points on the path. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I chose a dictionary (or hash-map or hash-table depending on language)
The key would be a tuple representing a point and the value would hold
whatever data was needed. For part one that would be a set of the
paths that went through the point. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if we had a path made up of 2 intersecting lines:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-ditaa&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ditaa&#34; data-lang=&#34;ditaa&#34;&gt; |
-+-----
 |&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We could use a 2D array to represent it (assume the lines have ID&amp;#39;s 1
and 2):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1 2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s already a good deal of wasted space. using a dictionarey we&amp;#39;d
have:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;key (row,col)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(0,1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,0)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1 2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,2)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,3)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,4)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,5()&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,6)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(2,1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Which becomes much more space efficient once we go beyond the smallest
test cases.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we have the representation, the problem becomes one of stepping
through the paths and adding them to the dictionary. After that we can
pull out the small number of entries in our dictionary that were
visited by both paths and then we can find the final answer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I coded this up in Clojure &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day03.clj&#34;&gt;(solution here)&lt;/a&gt; but forgot to account for the fact that
when a path repeats itself it shouldn&amp;#39;t count as an intersection for
the purpose of the problem. Oops. I fudged things to get the right
answer but then had to head off to Albany.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I arrived I fixed the code but was pretty zonked so decide to
code the second part in Python &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day03.py&#34;&gt;(solution here)&lt;/a&gt;. Both solutions are pretty similar but
as I&amp;#39;m more comfortable with Python it didn&amp;#39;t require too much focus
to get it right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Given the wording of this problem, I think that most people will steer
towards the type of dictionary representation I used rather than a 2D
array but this way of storing data is worth discussing with classes
when you might otherwise use a 2D array.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When might you ask?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about something like Conway&amp;#39;s Game of Life. When this is done in a
CS1 class the world is usually represented as a 2D array. It&amp;#39;s simple
 and direct. Another approach would be to only store the live cells in
a list. You can check out a Clojurescript implementation that does
just that &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life/tree/master/src&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another would be the N-Queens problem. Insead of a board, just store
the queens locations. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Image processing? Well, there probably not. When doing image work,
you actually use all the cells in the 2D array.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s pretty much all I have to say about today&amp;#39;s problem. It got me
thinking about alternate ways of representing our data. That&amp;#39;s
something we usually don&amp;#39;t have too much of an opportunity to discuss
with our students. That&amp;#39;s unfortunate.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 17:11:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/2&#34;&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt; of Advent of Code 2019 was also pretty straightforward and once
again I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day02.clj&#34;&gt;my solution&lt;/a&gt; in Clojure but in order to talk about this
from a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view, we&amp;#39;ll look at a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day02.py&#34;&gt;Python solution&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At its core, this is a simulation problem - read the data into an
array or list and write a program to run through the steps. At first I
was hoping that the solution would consume the data - that is, once
you read past an instruction you don&amp;#39;t go back to it. If it was, I was
going to try to write some clever reduce. It wasn&amp;#39;t. In this problem,
any instruction could affect any part of the data set. This means you
have to keep the entire data set in memory and preferably in a random
access structure like an array. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Step 1 is to read in the data and convert it into a list of integers.
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;data  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [ int(x) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day02.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;read()&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t know comprehensions you can just do something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; []
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; item &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day02.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;read()&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;):
      data&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;append(int(item))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we just have to run the simulation:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-pythonf&#34; data-lang=&#34;pythonf&#34;&gt;def run_program(program):
    ip = 0
    while True:
        op = program[ip]
        if op == 99:
            break
        a = program[ program[ip+1] ]
        b = program[ program[ip+2] ]
        dest = program[ip+3]
        if op == 1:
            program[dest] =  a + b
        else:
            program[dest] = a * b
        ip = ip + 4
    return program[0]

def part1(program):
    program[1]=12
    program[2]=2
    return run_program((program))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The most likely source of error here is forgetting to change the
values in &lt;code&gt;program[1]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[2]&lt;/code&gt; in lines 18 and 19 as
specified in the question. The other likely error is forgetting to do
the two level indirection in lines 7 and 8. That is writing
&lt;code&gt;program[ip+1]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[ip+2]&lt;/code&gt; by mistake. Truth be told, I made
both of these mistakes but I didn&amp;#39;t find them to be &amp;#34;interesting&amp;#34;
mistakes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The interesting part of this program is part 2 where instead of
setting &lt;code&gt;program[1]&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[2]&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt; you have to try
values between 0 and 99 inclusive for each entry until you find a
specific answer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a great platform to talk about memory. The problem refers to
the values you put into &lt;code&gt;program[1]&lt;/code&gt; as &lt;strong&gt;nouns&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[2]&lt;/code&gt; as
&lt;strong&gt;verbs&lt;/strong&gt;. The issue is that every time you run your program for a
specific &lt;strong&gt;noun verb&lt;/strong&gt; combination you change the array (list)
representing your program. If you don&amp;#39;t reset the array to its
original contents before the next run, the next run will be working
off of new values and therefore give you incorrect results. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a great platform for discussion. Students usually start with
&lt;strong&gt;pass by value&lt;/strong&gt; semantics so passing a list to a function and then
having the list change can seem weird even though it can still be pass
by value:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# bad example to follow&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;change_list&lt;/span&gt;(l):
      l[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;9999&lt;/span&gt;

  l&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;]
  change_list(l)
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# changes l[3] to 9999&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s a finished solution:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 1&lt;/span&gt;data  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [ int(x) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day02.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;read()&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;run_program&lt;/span&gt;(program):
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 4&lt;/span&gt;    ip &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 5&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; True:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 6&lt;/span&gt;        op &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; program[ip]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 7&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; op &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 8&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt; 9&lt;/span&gt;        a &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; program[ program[ip&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;] ]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;        b &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; program[ program[ip&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;] ]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;        dest &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; program[ip&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; op &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;            program[dest] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;  a &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; b
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;            program[dest] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; a &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; b
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;        ip &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; ip &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; program[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;part1&lt;/span&gt;(data):
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;    program &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; data[:]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;    program[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;    program[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; run_program((program))
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;26&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;part2&lt;/span&gt;(data):
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;27&lt;/span&gt;    results &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; []
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;28&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; noun &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;):
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;29&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; verb &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;):
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;            program &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; data[:]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;31&lt;/span&gt;            program[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; noun
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;32&lt;/span&gt;            program[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; verb
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;33&lt;/span&gt;            r &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; run_program(program)
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;34&lt;/span&gt;            results&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;append( (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;noun&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;verb, r))
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;35&lt;/span&gt;    ans &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [ x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; results &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; x[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;19690720&lt;/span&gt;]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;36&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; ans
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;37&lt;/span&gt;    
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;38&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(part1(data))
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;39&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(part2(data))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that in line 30 we copy over the original data for each noun,verb
combo. also note the list comprehension in line 35 to find the final
answer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One last potential error point is notice that we had to add the array
copy in line 20. Otherwise part1 will change the data and if we run it
before part2 we won&amp;#39;t get the correct result.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. Another nice problem and even though it&amp;#39;s a
straightforward problem, there&amp;#39;s still some interesting meat to
discuss with your students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow, snowstorm notwithstanding, I&amp;#39;ll be heading up to Albany for
the remainder of the week so might not be able to get to day 3 and
beyond until Friday so who knows if I&amp;#39;ll post any more of these
write ups.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2019 Day 1</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 14:23:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Like most programming challenges, &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; ramps out from
easier, more accessible problems to harder, more complex ones. As
such, a number of the early challenges are great problems for early CS
students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought that while I watched my NY Giants play valiantly in their
attempt to get a high draft pick I&amp;#39;d talk about today&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/1&#34;&gt;challenge&lt;/a&gt;
from a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The summary of part one is that you have a list of inputs (masses of
components) and for each one you have to perform a calculation (how
much fuel is needed). The answer will be the sum of the fuels.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The most challenging part of this for a beginner might be reading in
the data but that&amp;#39;s not too much of a challenge:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day01.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;readlines()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we can calculate part1:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day01.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;readlines()

  sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; mass &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; data:
      sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; int(mass)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(sum)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 adds a twist. Now, you have to also consider the fuel needed
for the fuel you&amp;#39;ve added. Basically, you have to calculate how much
fuel you&amp;#39;ll need for a given item and then how much fuel you&amp;#39;ll need
for that fuel. You repeat this until the amount of fuel you need is
either 0 or negative. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/1&#34;&gt;the challenge&lt;/a&gt; for more info on this. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is our first &amp;#34;teaching moment.&amp;#34; This is going to be messy to work
into our part1 solution but if we had factored out the original fuel
calculation we could probably reused it and maybe more of our
solution:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day01.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;readlines()

  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;calc_fuel&lt;/span&gt;(mass):
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; int(mass)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;

  sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; mass &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; data:
      sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; calc_fuel(mass)
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(sum)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we can just add an inner loop that repeatedly adds the fuel costs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day01.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;readlines()

  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;calc_fuel&lt;/span&gt;(mass):
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; int(mass)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;

  sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; mass &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; data:
      fuel &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; calc_fuel(mass)
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; fuel &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;:
          sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; sum &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; fuel
          fuel &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;  calc_fuel(fuel)
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(sum)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
More &amp;#34;teachable moments.&amp;#34; We have to change up variables in our fuel
calculations (lines 8 and 11) and for a beginner, the loop within a
loop can be somewhat muddled. It&amp;#39;s more complex but it&amp;#39;s doing
something that &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; more complex. It&amp;#39;s also good nested loop practice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For more advanced students, if they&amp;#39;re familiar with list
comprehensions you can really clean up part 1:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day01.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;readlines()
  data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [int(x) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; data] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# convert to ints before starting&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;calc_fuel&lt;/span&gt;(mass):
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; mass&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# part 1&lt;/span&gt;
  part1 &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; sum([calc_fuel(x) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; data])&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but I think part 2 either stay&amp;#39;s more or less as is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I wrote my solutions in Clojure:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;ns &lt;/span&gt;day01
  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;:require&lt;/span&gt; [clojure.string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;:as&lt;/span&gt; string]
            [utils &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;:as&lt;/span&gt; u]))


(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def &lt;/span&gt;test-masses [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1969&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100756&lt;/span&gt;])

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; load data&lt;/span&gt;
(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def &lt;/span&gt;masses (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
             (slurp &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day01.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
             string/split-lines
             (map u/parse-int)
             ))


(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;calc-mass-part1 [mass]
  (- (quot mass &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;))

(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;part1 [masses]
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;calculate fuel for each mass then sum them all&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
  (reduce + (map calc-mass-part1 masses)))



(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;calc-mass-part2
  ([mass] (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;calc-mass-part2&lt;/span&gt; mass &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;))
  ([mass cost]
   &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Same as part 1 but loop to calculate fuel for the fuel&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
   (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[fuel (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;calc-mass-part1&lt;/span&gt; mass)]
     (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(&amp;lt;= fuel &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)
       cost
       (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;recur&lt;/span&gt; fuel (+ cost fuel))))))
  
(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;part2 [masses]
  (reduce + (map calc-mass-part2 masses )))

(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;main []
(println (str &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Part1: &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;part1&lt;/span&gt; masses)))
(println (str &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Part2: &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;part2&lt;/span&gt; masses)))
)

(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So that&amp;#39;s day 1. I don&amp;#39;t know if I&amp;#39;ll write up any more or, given my
travel and work schedule for the week,if I&amp;#39;ll even be able  to work
on more problems until next weekend. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event. If you&amp;#39;re teaching CS0 or CS1 students, you should
really check out Advent of Code.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent Of Code 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-of-code-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 09:02:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-of-code-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s almost December which means it&amp;#39;s almost time for &lt;a href=&#34;http:/adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of Code
2019&lt;/a&gt;. Advent of code is an annual computer programming competition
created and ruyn by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ericwastl&#34;&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s been running since 2015. I&amp;#39;ve
written about it before, mostly from a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/solve-a-to-solve-b/&#34;&gt;Solve A to Solve B&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/&#34;&gt;Data structures and Hidden Complexity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-4-6/&#34;&gt;Tools can shape
how we think&lt;/a&gt; and a few others). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Basically, Eric releases one poblem a day at midnight from Dec 1
through Dec 25. Each problem has two parts with a correct solution to
part 1 unlocking part 2. Problems can be solved using any language as
each challenge just requires you to enter the correct result rather
than you submitting code. This allows you to use any language or even
no language at all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of difficulty, some problems are certainly doable by students
in CS1 or even CS0. In fact, Eric takes great pains to keep from using
CSSpeak so as to make the problems approachable even if you aren&amp;#39;t a
CS major or professional.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re a CS Teacher you can find some great lesson and problem
ideas here. If you&amp;#39;re a student, they&amp;#39;re great interview prep and will
stretch your problem solving capabilities. If you&amp;#39;re just a techie,
they&amp;#39;re just fun challenges. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There aren&amp;#39;t any prizes so it&amp;#39;s all just for the fun of it. You can
also get help and see great discussions on the challenges over on the
Advent of Code &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/&#34;&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;. Lots of people also put their solutions up
online. I&amp;#39;ve never finished but you can find a bunch of my old
solutions up on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky?utf8=%25E2%259C%2593&amp;amp;tab=repositories&amp;amp;q=adve&amp;amp;type=&amp;amp;language=&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, you can get to the challenges from previous years by just
adding the year to the url, that is:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode/2019&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2019&#34;&gt;http://adventofcode.com/2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2018&#34;&gt;http://adventofcode.com/2018&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2017&#34;&gt;http://adventofcode.com/2017&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2016&#34;&gt;http://adventofcode.com/2016&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2015&#34;&gt;http://adventofcode.com/2015&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, here&amp;#39;s a really interesting video by Eric on the whole AoC
thing:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bS9882S0ZHs&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bS9882S0ZHs&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 3 - word chains</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/word-chains/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 05:45:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/word-chains/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
At this point, we&amp;#39;ve done a fair amount of playing with text so it&amp;#39;s
time for a fun little project. We&amp;#39;re going to generate some text &amp;#34;in
the style&amp;#34; of a source text. The technique we&amp;#39;re going to use is
usually called a Markov Chain text generator. Basically a model where
the next state or word is based entirely on the current state. I don&amp;#39;t
dwell on the math under the hood but in case you&amp;#39;re interested, here
are a few links: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://setosa.io/ev/markov-chains/&#34;&gt;Explained Visually&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.math.ucdavis.edu/~daddel/linear_algebra_appl/Applications/MarkovChain/MarkovChain_9_18/MarkovChain_9_18.html&#34;&gt;UC Davis Math&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can motivate this lesson in a number of ways. One is to start by
showing some generated text - for this, a flowery, poetic text like
the Book of Psalms works well. You can generate text a bunch of times
until you get a good result. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the start of the Book of Psalms:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;Blessed is the man that walketh not in the counsel of the
ungodly, nor standeth in the way of sinners, nor sitteth in
the seat of the scornful.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and here&amp;#39;s some generated text:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;Blessed is the people that delight in war. Princes shall come out of
Zion,  the perfection of beauty god hath shined our god shall come and
shall declare thy mighty acts. I will speak of the glory of the lord
surely i will not lie unto David.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I added the punctuation as our generator strips it all and converts
the text to lower case.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The generated text looks reasonable in some ways but is clearly wrong
in others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This leads to the conversation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we look at the original text, it starts with &amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34; but if we
look at our bag of words we also can see that &amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34; appears 49
times. What&amp;#39;s interesting for generating text are the words the follow
&amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34; and the number of times they follow it. Here they are
(sorted for convenience):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Word&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;How many times it follows the word &amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;are&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;art&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;be&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;blessed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;depart&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;for&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;his&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;in&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;that&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;thee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;thy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;upon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wealth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So we&amp;#39;ll have a lot of things like &amp;#34;blessed be the&amp;#34; &amp;#34;blessed be he&amp;#34;
etc. but only one occurrence of &amp;#34;blessed upon….&amp;#34; To generate text, we
can build a dictionary where the keys are the words and the values are
all the words that follow the key. We can build this with a variation
on our bag of words builder:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that we need a counting loop rather than just iterating over the
list since we need both the current item and the one after it in each
iteration.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The (partial) value for the wordlists for the Book of Psalms would be:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point, generating text is easy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Start with a word
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Add the word to yoru story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Look  it up in your wordlists dictionary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
select a random word from that words dictionary entry (it&amp;#39;s list).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That becomes the word for the next iteration
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Repeat until you have enough words.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This won&amp;#39;t add any punctuation and it will crash when it gets to the
last word in the original text (as it can&amp;#39;t find any &amp;#34;next words&amp;#34; but
basically it will work. Here&amp;#39;s the code:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;code&gt;random.choice()&lt;/code&gt; randomly selects a word from a list. This is
perfect for us since words that follow our key more frequently will
have more entries in the list and thus appear more often. I decided to
build a list of words and then use the &lt;code&gt;&amp;#34; &amp;#34;.join()&lt;/code&gt; to turn it all
into a space separated string.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is pretty fun but the students will note that it really doesn&amp;#39;t
work that well. This can lead to increasing our sample. Instead of
using a single word as our key and having chain links based on two
words (key, random choice from value), we can use three word
links. Use a two word tuple for the key and the same list of words as
the value.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, a partial dictionary based on this idea from Macbeth Act
1 Scene 1 could be:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This takes a bit more work to build and also a bit more work to
generate text but it&amp;#39;s eminently doable and the result is
better. What about three word keys? Four? These aren&amp;#39;t hard to write
and ambitious students can write a generic dicitonary builder and
story generator routine so as to be able to use any key lenght.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Students will find that the longer the key, the better the resultant
story. They&amp;#39;ll also notice that at some point, all you&amp;#39;ll ever
generate is the original back again. This is a great time to talk
about over-training.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This can be a fun unit and / or assignment. I used source materials
that I like but any text will work.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lesson and project inspiration from old BSD games</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bsdgames/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 13:55:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bsdgames/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
When I was writing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-speak-jive/&#34;&gt;I Speak Jive&lt;/a&gt; post, the first thing I had to do
was find those old programs. It turned out to be harder than I
thought. I found online versions but it took a while to find &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hyperrealm/talkfilters&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
GitHub repo.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the way, I seemed to recall that these might be bundled with a
bunch of old &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vattam/BSDGames&#34;&gt;BSD games&lt;/a&gt; so I took a look at the BSD games package for
Linux. While I didn&amp;#39;t find the filters, I found a whole bunch of old
programs that I hadn&amp;#39;t played with in years along with a few that I
never knew existed. To me it felt like an interesting project and
lesson treasure trove so I wanted to share.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think this makes more sense to do as a video so I can actually show
the programs as they run so check out the video at the end of this
post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the video I talk about controlling the cursor on the screen so that
students can write programs like the ones I demo. That can be done in
a number of ways. You could use a library like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mabe02/lanterna&#34;&gt;lanterna&lt;/a&gt; for Java or
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curses_%2528programming_library%2529&#34;&gt;curses&lt;/a&gt; or ncurses for C but you can also just use Ansi Escape
codes. Basically you print out &lt;a href=&#34;http://ascii-table.com/ansi-escape-sequences-vt-100.php&#34;&gt;special escape squences&lt;/a&gt; to move the
cursor, clear the screen and even set text and background colors. For
example, to move the cursor to the middle of the screen and print
&lt;strong&gt;Hello&lt;/strong&gt; you would use this: &lt;code&gt;System.out.print(&amp;#34;^[[12;40HHello&amp;#34;);&lt;/code&gt; The
first &lt;code&gt;^[&lt;/code&gt; is actually the ascii code for the escape character. I
enter it in Emacs by typing Control-q then hitting the escape
key. Other editors will have a way of doing the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So here you go – old BSD games. I hope you get as many ideas out of
this as I did.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Uyvh1Q9SLbE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
&lt;p&gt;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 2 - bag of words</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bag-of-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 08:15:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bag-of-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Following up on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we&amp;#39;re going to continue to talk about
playing with text. This time, building and working with a bag of words
from a text. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A bag of words is a simple language processing model where you just
consider individual words in a text. What they are and how many times
they occur. This is a pretty simple model but you can still have a
good bit of fun with your students with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if you take a text like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This land is your land
this land is my land
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once you clean the a data as per the previous post you get the
following bag:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;word&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;land&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;my&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;this&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;your&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not too interesting but it gets more interesting on a larger text. We
used:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Act 1 Scene 1 from Macbeth (for testing - it&amp;#39;s only 13 lines)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Cyrano de Bergerac (because it&amp;#39;s my favorite play)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moby Dick (chapter 1)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moby Dick (full text)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Book of Psalms
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Assuming a cleaned string with all the text, building the bag is
pretty easy:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_text &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;a string with all the cleaned text&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;bag&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;{}
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; cleaned_text&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split():
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;  bag&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;setdefault(word,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;  bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;code&gt;setdefault&lt;/code&gt; in line three says that if &lt;code&gt;word&lt;/code&gt; isn&amp;#39;t a key in the
dictionary then insert it with a value of 0, otherwise, if &lt;code&gt;word&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt;
already a key in the dictionary do nothing. This saves us from
constructs like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; bag:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;      bag[word]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;      bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we have our bag we can do some explorations. Take out all the
values using &lt;code&gt;bag.values()&lt;/code&gt; and sort them. Ask &amp;#34;what words are going
to occur most frequently?&amp;#34; It&amp;#39;s easy to guess that it will be words
like &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;of&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; etc.. Words that don&amp;#39;t really tell us anything
about the text. It&amp;#39;s a fun puzzle to figure out where the
&amp;#34;interesting&amp;#34; words start and even the question of what might make a
word in a text &amp;#34;interesting.&amp;#34; Words like &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt;, *and&amp;#34;, etc. are known
as &lt;a href=&#34;http://xpo6.com/list-of-english-stop-words/&#34;&gt;stop words&lt;/a&gt;. Depending on the application, you might want ot remove
them. Then again, you might not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Usually we take a bit of time just to play with the bag, looking at
the types of words in various count ranges. Sometimes we&amp;#39;ll make bags
for different chapters of books and compare them. This is also when I
cover Python list comprehensions which make experimenting on bags of
words much cleaner. Say, for instance you want to find all the words
that occur between 50 and 100 times. Without list comprehensions you
might write:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;  result &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; []
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; bag:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;          result&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;append(word) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# or (word,count) or whatever&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While with the comprehension it&amp;#39;s:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  result &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [ word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; bag &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;]
  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides basic exploring, what else can you do? You can make word
vectors, that is a list or vector where an element is 1 if the word is
present and 0 otherwise. Then you can do simple document
comparisons. You can kick this up a notch if you calculate word
frequencies based on the bag counts and use these. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can also do basic sentiment analysis. Download a list of
&amp;#34;positive&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;negative&amp;#34; words and then check bags against them. You
can check to see how many negative or positive words are in a bag or
you can work with frequencies. You can also use other categories. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While we were discussing this at our PD, some teachers thought that
their classes might ahve a hard time doing all of this  from scratch
but thought that they could provide either the cleaning code or the
bag building code and have the students build experiments off of the
base. I thought it was a great idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of our session we all agreed to think about how we might
build a lesson or unit out of this bag of words idea. I&amp;#39;ll leave you
all with some web sites that use these ideas in what I think are
interesting ways:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://davidamackenzie.com/tmbg_lyrics/&#34;&gt;They Might Be Giants Lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.sap.com/2014/01/07/measuring-word-use-frequency-in-rap-song-lyrics/&#34;&gt;Word use in rap lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://genius.com/Sameoldshawn-rap-stats-breaking-down-the-words-in-rap-lyrics-over-time-annotated&#34;&gt;Another analysis of rap lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://towardsdatascience.com/text-analysis-of-successful-song-lyrics-e41a4ccb26f5&#34;&gt;Analysis of succesful song lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School Visit Update 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/school-visit-update-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:25:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/school-visit-update-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been spending a lot of time at area high schools this fall. Today
I was at &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franklin_Delano_Roosevelt_High_School_(New_York_City)&#34;&gt;FDR High School&lt;/a&gt; in Broooklyn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg/330px-FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg/330px-FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg/330px-FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;500px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I only learned about FDR HS a little over a year ago when I met their
CS teacher &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jhans404&#34;&gt;Josh Hans&lt;/a&gt; at a NYC PD event. I visit last fall and then
again today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Whenever I visit a school it&amp;#39;s a different experience. Sometimes I
speak to the CS classes, sometimes at an event like a CS Week
hackathon, once I even got to address an entire senior class in an
auditorium. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really loved how Josh and FDR set things up for me today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before I get to the arrangement, let&amp;#39;s talk about the talk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I meet with a room of seniors, even a room full of CS students, I
know that only a few students are going to end up with me at
Hunter. A room of 30 seniors should probably end up in something like
25 different colleges. I also know that even in a CS class many of
the students will end up pursuing other majors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s right for me to take a full class period and
talk just about Hunter and my Daedalus program so instead I start by
talking about college choices. I try to share things that I&amp;#39;ve learned
over my career as a student, teacher, parent, and now someone reading
applications with my audiuence. Things I&amp;#39;ve learned from both my
experiences and through my relationships with former students. At the
end we talk about Hunter, Hunter CS and the Daedalus program.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been told that the approach has been really valuable to the
majority of students I&amp;#39;ve delivered it to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were a few things that Josh set up today that made it a lot of
fun. First, we were in the auditorium. I had Josh&amp;#39;s APCS-A class but
he also invited a couple of others. I also had APCS-P students and
also a class of Calculus students. This was a big deal. Just like
everyone, I&amp;#39;m working hard to build a program with a diverse
population and sometimes outreach is difficult. Specifically, if a
school only allows me to speak with their APCS-A students, I
frequently end up with a pre-culled group. If a school, for example,
has a very low percentage of women in their APCS-A class and that&amp;#39;s
where I&amp;#39;m speaking, I&amp;#39;m not going to be able to convince many women to
look into what we&amp;#39;re offering. By having the calc sutdents in the
audience I had a more diverse audience and also almost certainly had
the chance to expose some students to CS in a new and different
way. Now, don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. Given the nature of my program, I really
love talking to APCS-A students and going with probability, they&amp;#39;re
the most likely the ones to want my program but I love casting the
wider net.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other think Josh did was he gave me two periods. My talk usually
takes most of a period with little time for discussion. It should take
less but I tend to go into yammer mode and start telling
stories. Sorry - it&amp;#39;s just what I do. With two periods we had plenty
of time for discussion afterwards. What&amp;#39;s more, after most of the
students left, I was left with about 6 students who wanted to continue
to talk. I really enjoyed that. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once I was done I did what I usually do - went to the local bakery to
bring home some baked goods. I stopped at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/18th+Avenue+Bakery/@40.6212881,-73.9847415,17z/data=!4m8!1m2!2m1!1sbakery!3m4!1s0x0:0xd4dca91422790dec!8m2!3d40.6217849!4d-73.9877902&#34;&gt;18th street Bakery&lt;/a&gt;. An
Italian place and got an assortment. Also had a great chat with the
lady at the counter. It reminded me of when I&amp;#39;d go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yelp.com/biz/moishes-kosher-bakery-new-york&#34;&gt;Moishes Bakery&lt;/a&gt;
before they closed albeit Italian rather than Jewish. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I pointed to a pile of cookes and asked &amp;#34;what are these?&amp;#34; and she
merely said &amp;#34;No!!!!!&amp;#34; We joked back and forth and she explained that
they were on the older side and didn&amp;#39;t feel right selling them and was
going to throw the rest of the batch out. They&amp;#39;d bake new ones for
tomorrow. I was disappointed not to try a new cookie but glad that I
wasn&amp;#39;t sold stale goods. It was like at Moishes when I once asked
about the Babka and was told &amp;#34;that was made  on Wednesday, you don&amp;#39;t
want it. This is what&amp;#39;s fresh. New Babka tomorrow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, then, on the way home, thinking about Moishes and realizing that
there were  also Jewish bakeries in the neighborhood I decided to see
if I could find &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kichel&#34;&gt;Kichel&lt;/a&gt; - one of Devorah&amp;#39;s favorite cookies. I
sometimes make them but haven&amp;#39;t in a while. I found some at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Korn&amp;#39;s+Bakery/@40.630628,-73.9799457,17z/data=!4m9!1m3!2m2!1sbakery!6e5!3m4!1s0x0:0xf6f303e4b6cd6dfe!8m2!3d40.6308331!4d-73.9764149&#34;&gt;Korn&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt;
Bakery and then it was back into Manhattan.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, overall a succesful day. I got to talk to a bunch of great High
School cookies and got tasty neighborhood baked goods. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve hit a bunch of schools already this fall as I work to spread the
gospel about CS and about Hunter&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.huntercs.org&#34;&gt;Daedalus&lt;/a&gt; program and am still
looking to get more on the schedule so if you know a school that&amp;#39;s a
good fit a visit, hit me up.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Give me a break (and a continue)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/break-continue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 08:39:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/break-continue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What can I do to discourage my students from using the &amp;#34;break&amp;#34;
statement?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was more or less the gist of the comment and it elicited some
good responses. This time the conversation was on Facebook but I&amp;#39;ve
seen this one and participated in it many times before. I never liked
the question when presented as a &amp;#34;how can I stop them&amp;#34; one.  I equally
dislike when the offered advice is basically &amp;#34;never use break no
matter what&amp;#34; or something similar. When writing code the best advice
is rarely to never or always do something. The question should really
be &amp;#34;when is it appropriate for my students to use a break statement
and how can I steer them  towards using it correctly.&amp;#34; The answer, of
course is &amp;#34;it depends.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For those unfamiliar with the statements, &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; jumps to the end and
exits the loop or switch statement that encloses it. The &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt;
statement jumps up to the next iteration of its enclosing loop. I&amp;#39;ll
show some examples below.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s true that you never &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; to use break but in my opinion, if
used correctly it can create clearer code. Let&amp;#39;s look at a related
situation. Suppose you write a function to find and return some item
from  a data set (in pseudocode):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You could tighten it up a bit but there are two things that I don&amp;#39;t
like about the above solution. First, it goes through the entire data
set even if the item you&amp;#39;re searching for is near the beginning. You
could fix that by putting in a more complex loop boolean:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;0&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; numitems &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;found &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;++)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Second. you&amp;#39;ve got the conditional after the loop. I find the
following much clearer:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me this is perfectly clear. Look for an item, if and when we find
it, we&amp;#39;re done so let&amp;#39;s get out of here. If not, the loop finishes and
we return the not found stuff at the end. It&amp;#39;s clean, easy to
understand, and potentially a little faster.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You have a similar situation with &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt;. Without it you might have
code like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And with:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not significantly different. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People who don&amp;#39;t like the break statement usually adhere to a very
strict interpretation of structured programming - one entry point, one
exit point but I&amp;#39;d argue that break (and continue) are not like
arbitrary jumps. They&amp;#39;re well defined and don&amp;#39;t introduce spaghetti
code. They either specifically exit a bounding language construct or
jump to the next iteration. Actually, now that I think about it,
&lt;code&gt;exceptions&lt;/code&gt; can be used in a way that mucks with clear code in a much
more dangerous way than break and continue can.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s an example with continue:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
as opposed to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Which is better? It&amp;#39;s purely subjective. Nothing wrong with either.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll share a final example. This one lifted from an &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/&#34;&gt;older post&lt;/a&gt; on
&amp;#34;best practices.&amp;#34; If you&amp;#39;re writing an event handler, you could put
the exit event in the loop boolean but I find including it
as a case using a &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; to be cleaner:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c++&#34; data-lang=&#34;c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt;, like most langauge
constructs can be used for either good or evil. There have been times
when they&amp;#39;ve led me to cleaner code so I&amp;#39;ve used them. At other times,
using them would have been forced.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we agree that &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt; can be appropriate, the other
question is when to introduce them. One comment from the most recent
Facebook thread on this (name withheld since that&amp;#39;s a semi-private
forum) was that it shouldn&amp;#39;t be right off the bat but rather after
they&amp;#39;re comfortable with loops, conditionals and booleans so that they
can use the new constructs when they make sense and not willy-nilly. I
tend to agree with this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I think it&amp;#39;s important to show our kids constructs like
&lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt; and it&amp;#39;s also important for us to talk about
good code and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/best-practices-cli/&#34;&gt;best practices&lt;/a&gt; but the important thing is that we don&amp;#39;t
have our kids blindly follow any practice but empower them to make good
decisions based on their situations.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Technical Interviews And Diversity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/technical-interviews-and-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2019 11:27:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/technical-interviews-and-diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I recently stumbled upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/laurieontech/with_replies&#34;&gt;Laurie Barth&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter and noticed a couple
of tweets about tech interviews and the hiring process, something I&amp;#39;ve
been thinking about recently.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Solid rant. I
think the teach to the programming test market already exists. And
it’s why interviewers who subscribe to these tactics get upset if a
candidate admits they’ve seen the problem previously. Because it ruins
the illusion that this is revealing how candidates think. &lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/DpHgQx0TST&#34;&gt;https://t.co/DpHgQx0TST&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Laurie (@laurieontech) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/laurieontech/status/1121879805862064131?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April
26, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;One of the
things I often think about is feeling like I got lucky making it
through some of my interviews...and then killed it on the job. We know
interviews don’t match the on the job skills, it’s about time we did
something about it. &lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/xmUXkGvtoA&#34;&gt;https://t.co/xmUXkGvtoA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Laurie (@laurieontech) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/laurieontech/status/1122496300912717825?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April
28, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I guess I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about it because I&amp;#39;m teaching a section of
Data Structures which, along with Algorithms, provides the base
knowledge you need to have a shot at the typical &amp;#34;Google Style&amp;#34;
technical interview.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I say &amp;#34;base knowledge&amp;#34; because just completing those two classes
doesn&amp;#39;t really prepare you. It gives you the building blocks but you
really have to prep specifically for the types of questions they might
give you. Unfortunately, for most kids it involves a whole lot of
rejection and failure before you start getting offers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You might get a problem that has a bad brute force solution and during
the relatively short interview, devoid of your typical resources and
comforts you have to turn it into a much more efficient one. The
argument is that the interviewer is really trying to see how you think
about a problem but having spoken to many, many tech employees who do these
interviews that&amp;#39;s a specious argument at best. It&amp;#39;s really a test of
&amp;#34;who has seen the problem or something similar before but can fake
that they haven&amp;#39;t the best.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While it&amp;#39;s true that you will get some candidates who can solve the
problems on the spot you&amp;#39;re going to miss out on a whole bunch of
great candidates who just don&amp;#39;t do well on that &amp;#34;Google style&amp;#34; of
interview. At the same time we keep hearing that, as Laurie tweeted,
the skills required on the job don&amp;#39;t match the ones needed to pass the
interview. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This doesn&amp;#39;t really matter to the big, hot companies. The Googles and
Facebooks of the world. So many students coming out of college want to
work for them that they can afford to miss on tons of great candidates
so long as they hit on enough good ones. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I put the word &amp;#34;diversity&amp;#34; in the title of this post and you might
wonder what I was going for there. So far, I&amp;#39;m just ranting about the
interview process. This becomes a diversity and privilige issue
because the process favors &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; CS schools with established CS
cultures. I&amp;#39;m not talking about the fact that they pre-select high
performing candidates nor the fact that all the tech companies go to
those schools, sometimes exclusively for recruiting. I&amp;#39;m talking about
how the school&amp;#39;s student tech culture helps prepare the students for
the technical interview. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From my discussions with many graduates from many of these institutions, while
classes don&amp;#39;t prep for interviews, students at these CS schools
regularly share interview questions. Friends and classmates talk about
the questions they got and help each other out with practice
sessions - formal or otherwise. I&amp;#39;m certainly not faulting students
for doing this but it&amp;#39;s another known  secret. We all know that the
more tech interview questions you see the better prepared you&amp;#39;ll be -
both because you&amp;#39;ll get better at that specific problem solving skill
and also because you&amp;#39;ll likely get interview questions that are
already in your library. It&amp;#39;s that latter part that makes the whole
process very nod, nod, wink wink. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nothing stops other students at other schools from doing similar but
it&amp;#39;s much harder at a commuter school where kids live off campus and
have to work part time jobs. It&amp;#39;s the reason I&amp;#39;m fighting so hard for
space and working on building a postitive tech culture at Hunter. Not
specifically for interviews but to help my students become a support
network for each other.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll finish by noting that while this &amp;#34;technical interview&amp;#34; process
might more or less work for the big boys - the hot company du jour, it
probably doesn&amp;#39;t for eveyrone else. A buddy of mine was talking to me
about the process he uses at his much smaller company. He noted that
he could use the &amp;#34;Google interview&amp;#34; process for his future employees
but since his company was much smaller and lesser known, people who
did well would probably also get offers from the big boys and go work
for them. His goal was to come up with a process that catches the
great candidates that &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;#39;t&lt;/strong&gt; do well on the Google interview to try
to catch the great talent that doesn&amp;#39;t do well on today&amp;#39;s technical
interviews. A number of smaller companies seem to be starting to do
this and from the few I&amp;#39;ve spoken to it seems to be going well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I get that big companies are machines and look for uniformity in all
processes including the interview process but there has to be a
better, more human way to evaluate talent than a one size fits all
process where the norm is failure - particularly when it seldom
relates to actual skills needed on the job.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seam Carving and Dynamic Programming</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/seam-carving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 13:51:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/seam-carving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s spring break and for me that&amp;#39;s always been a good time to explore
some new ideas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s one that some of you might like, particularly if you&amp;#39;re
teaching APCS-A or something similar. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many APCS-A teachers do a unit on image processing using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/viewer?url=http%253A%252F%252Fmedia.collegeboard.com%252FdigitalServices%252Fpdf%252Fap%252Fpicture-lab-studentguide.pdf%0A&#34;&gt;picture
lab&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apcs.mathorama.com/index.php?n=Main.PictureLab&#34;&gt;alternate resource&lt;/a&gt;). Image processing is a nice platform to
explore two dimensional arrays. You basically use a 2D array of pixels
(points) to represent an image. You can just use a 2D array of ints
and store 0-255 at each location for a grayscale image and three ints
per pixel for red, green, blue. For this you can just use a simple
2D array of some color class - I think there&amp;#39;s even one built into
Java that you can use.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like to use the PPM format to save and later reload the images. PPM
is a simple text format. It starts with a header, then an optional
comment (starting with #), the width and height (4x4 in the example
below), then the maximum color number. Here&amp;#39;s an example:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
P3
# feep.ppm
4 4
15
 0  0  0    0  0  0    0  0  0   15  0 15
 0  0  0    0 15  7    0  0  0    0  0  0
 0  0  0    0  0  0    0 15  7    0  0  0
15  0 15    0  0  0    0  0  0    0  0  0
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can even cut and paste the above into a file and view it with an
image viewer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can find the full format specification &lt;a href=&#34;http://netpbm.sourceforge.net/doc/ppm.html%0A&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netpbm_format&#34;&gt;alternate resource&lt;/a&gt;). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The picture lab has a bunch of interesting exercise ideas but if
you&amp;#39;re looking for something &amp;#34;next level&amp;#34; check this out:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6NcIJXTlugc&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6NcIJXTlugc&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Seam Carving is no longer a new cutting edge
technique but it still blows me away. It&amp;#39;s also a really cool project
for more advanced students for two reasons: one, it&amp;#39;s not a toy
assignment - it&amp;#39;s from real research and two, it contains a very
approachable example of dynamic programming which I&amp;#39;ll talk about in a
bit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you watch the video, there are two pieces that can sound
intimidating. One is the &amp;#34;dynamic programming algorithm.&amp;#34; The other is
when they talk about the &amp;#34;gradient magnitude.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Gradient magnitude. That sounds pretty hard. Actually, it could be
worse. When I first starting looking at the basics of image processing
it was described as &amp;#34;the derivative of the pixels.&amp;#34; &lt;strong&gt;The dirivative of
the pixels????&lt;/strong&gt; I have to know calculus for this?????? Not really. I
hate it when they use big words for simple ideas. All they&amp;#39;re really
talking about is the difference between the color of neighboring
pixels. That is, how much the color changes from one pixel to the
next. Let&amp;#39;s say you have a greyscale image (or have converted an image
to greyscale by averaging the red green and blue values), if you have
a vertical row of pixels with all the values of, let&amp;#39;s say 200 and the
row right next to it is also of values 200, then the two lines are of
the same color - there is no difference. If one pixel has a value of
200 and its neighbor has a value of 50, it changes quite a lot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The APCS-A picture lab describes a simple way to calculate this in
exercise 9 (linked above). You can also just do a search on &amp;#34;edge
detection tutorial&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;sobol edge detection tutorial&amp;#34; or something
similar.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For Seam Carving, you have to find a sequence of pixels from one side
of the image to the other where the sum off all the differences is the
lowest. This is where the dynamic programming comes in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_programming&#34;&gt;Dynamic Programming&lt;/a&gt; is a technique that, in basic terms takes a
problem that decomposes into subproblems and you store the optimal
subproblem solution rather than recalculating it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Probably the easiest example is Fibonacci numbers. You can generate
Fibonacci numbers recursively using something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;(n):
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; n&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;:
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; fib(n&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;fib(n&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s very simple but it gets very slow very fast. That&amp;#39;s because it
keeps recalculating the same subproblems over and over and over.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can &amp;#34;fix&amp;#34; this by creating a list of previously found Fibonacci 
numbers and just return them rather than recalculating:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  fibs &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# make room for 1000 fib numbers&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;(n):
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; fibs[n] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;:
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# we already have the answer, just return it&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; fibs[n]
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# otherwise, calculate it, store it, return it&lt;/span&gt;
          f &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; fib(n&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;fib(n&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;)
          fibs[n]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;f
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; f&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and that&amp;#39;s a dynamic programming solution for Fibonacci numbers,
specifically using a technique known as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memoization&#34;&gt;memoization&lt;/a&gt;.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How does this apply to finding the proper seam to remove? The one with
the lowest total change? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, go through the image array and build a second 2D array where
each element contains the pixels &amp;#34;gradient magnitude&amp;#34; or change using
either the method described in task 9 of the picture lab or
elsewhere. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the first row, the sum of each pixels path so far is just the
array element.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For each successive row, the value of any pixel is going to be it&amp;#39;s
value plus one of the values abov it, either up left, up center, or up
right. Specifically, the elements new value will be it&amp;#39;s value + the
smallest of the above three.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, given this array representing the color changes:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/seam-mat1.png&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When calculating the second item in the second row, you&amp;#39;ll consider
the three values above it:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/seam-mat2.png&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The smallest is 0 so that 2 remains a 2. If we do this for every
element in the second row we get the following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/seam-mat3.png&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The green boxes added a 0 from the line above but the yellow ones
added the smallest non zero value from the above  row. Note that the
edges just considered the two values above them and didn&amp;#39;t wrap.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Working the rest of the way through, you get this final array:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/seam-mat4.png&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can now easily identify the best seam to remove by finding the
smallest value in the bottom row and working your way up to the top.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All together this is very doable by an advanced APCS-A student and the
results are very cool, particularly if you do it in an interactive
environment like processing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, check out seam carving. I&amp;#39;ll leave you with one more link to a
longer presentation on the topic: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZBtXl3EuU14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZBtXl3EuU14&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZBtXl3EuU14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adapting A Nifty Assignment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 08:20:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/samples/animation/Animated_325.gif&#34; alt=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/samples/animation/Animated_325.gif&#34; title=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/samples/animation/Animated_325.gif&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Nifty Assignments&lt;/a&gt; session at SGICSE is always a popular one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;the site&lt;/a&gt; and you&amp;#39;ll find links to all the assignments presented
from 1999 to the present year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, it&amp;#39;s a great resource. On the other, the assignments
vary in nifty-ness depending on one&amp;#39;s personal taste. To me, there
seemed to be a run of nifty assignments that were really just &amp;#34;take a
generic assignment and fancy up the graphics&amp;#34; mixed in with one&amp;#39;s that
I found really cool. There&amp;#39;s also no way to really tell if an
assignment scratches your fancy without clicking through and reading
all of them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I&amp;#39;d talk about one of the assignments presented at this past
SIGCSE. I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;ll have an opportunity to use it directly but
I did find it pretty nifty. I also thought I&amp;#39;d share some tweaks I&amp;#39;d
consider if I were to use it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The assignment is Jeffrey L. Popyack&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/&#34;&gt;Post-It Pandemoniim&lt;/a&gt; assignment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first glance, or rather at the start of the presentation it seemed
a pretty lightweight assignment - kids make a pixelated image by
putting colored postit notes on a grid. That&amp;#39;s a simple, nice
intro to 2D arrays but not all that nifty. The nifty part came when
you drilled down into the details. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The assignment starts with a GIF image. First you process it  with a program
provided hich produces sheets describing a 3x5 section of the overall
image. These sheets are ultimately distributed to the students
perofming the activity. This still doesn&amp;#39;t sound tremendously deep but
the activity also lets you talk about file formats with color
palettes. The idea that instead of storing the rgb triple for each
pixel you store an index into a palette of 256 colors that&amp;#39;s also
embedded into the file. This is a great way to introduce indirect
lookups. Another feature Poplyack spoke about was compression. He
mentioned the project lending itself to Run Length Encoding. The idea
that if the image has a run of adjacent pixels of the same color,
let&amp;#39;s say 9 reds in a row, instead of encoding them as &amp;#34;RRRRRRRRR&amp;#34; you
would use something like &amp;#34;9R.&amp;#34; Add this all together and it&amp;#39;s pretty
nifty. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I did have a problem, though with the compression part. During the
talk, Poplyack talked about Run Length Encoding which is pretty simple
and approachable to beginners. GIF, however, as far as I know uses
Lempel-Ziv compression which is much more complex.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I were to use this assignment, I&amp;#39;d probable make a few changes. I&amp;#39;m
not sure which of the following I&amp;#39;d actually do but here&amp;#39;s what I
would think about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First I would consider using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netpbm_format&#34;&gt;NetPBM&lt;/a&gt; formats. Some of these formats
are simple ASCII. You can see some examples on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netpbm_format&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
page. This lets them go directly from the file to the poster. You also
have binary encoded versions of the format which adds a layer of
complexity if desired.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second thing I would consider is using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PCX&#34;&gt;PCX&lt;/a&gt; files instead of
GIFs. PCX is a pretty simple format. It uses a color palette and also
RLE compression so while it&amp;#39;s no longer as well known as GIF I think
it might present a more accessible way of getting to a format with Run
Length Encoding and a palette.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not sure of the exact direction I&amp;#39;d go in with this assignment but
these are the additional things I&amp;#39;d think about. It&amp;#39;s pretty nifty as
is but as with a lot of nifty assignments, part of the fun is
customizing it for your situation.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2019 - the keynotes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2019-keynotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 15:25:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2019-keynotes/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s that time of the year to write a series of blog posts about
SIGCSE. I thought I&amp;#39;d start with one on the keynotes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were four keynote speakers. Marie desJardins, Gloria Townsend,
Mark Guzdial, and Blair Taylor. I wasn&amp;#39;t at the first timer&amp;#39;s lunch
where Townsend spoke so I won&amp;#39;t talk at all about that keynote.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also not going to summarize the talks. Andy Ko wrote up a terrific
summary of his &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/bits-and-behavior/sigcse-2019-trip-report-celebrating-50-years-b3460835a09a&#34;&gt;SIGCSE experience&lt;/a&gt; and did a much better job giving
overviews to the keynotes than I ever could so I&amp;#39;ll just refer you to
Andy&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/bits-and-behavior/sigcse-2019-trip-report-celebrating-50-years-b3460835a09a&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Rather, I&amp;#39;m just going to talk a bit about what they
left me thinking about. It might be something that&amp;#39;s pretty tangential
to the actual talk but hey, it&amp;#39;s the direction that the speaker sent
my brain to follow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Marie des Jardin - the pinch hitter
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Marie desJardins wasn&amp;#39;t supposed to be the keynote. She was filling in
for a flu ridden &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freeman_A._Hrabowski_III&#34;&gt;Freeman Hrabowski&lt;/a&gt; at the last minute and she did a
more than admirable job.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big line for me was her plea for us not to create &amp;#34;weed out&amp;#34;
courses but rather to create &amp;#34;launch&amp;#34; courses. I think this resonated
with many in the audience. It got me thinking about something that&amp;#39;s
been a concern of mine for a while. We see a lot of examples of making
student&amp;#39;s first CS experience more gentle and more varied. Probably
the biggest example is APCS-P but you can also find it in many college
CS0 classes. Hunter&amp;#39;s no exception - we&amp;#39;re now in the second year of a
more varied CS0 class (although truth be told, our problem
wasn&amp;#39;t so much that our old CS0 was a gatekeeper but more that
students hardly did any programming). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started to become aware of the problem as I would hear stories of
kids who did Girls Who Code programs who then dropped out of CS
classes that were too hard and then later when my former students at
Harvard told me that many kids &amp;#34;dropped like flies&amp;#34; in the class after
CS50. I&amp;#39;ve also seen these problems at Hunter but at least here I know
we&amp;#39;re working on it. Having a more accessible entry point is terrific
but not if you just set the kids up to fail one step down the line. It
seems that not enough people are looking at the complete path: from
first course to last and the transitions in between. This is a hidden
danger. We can proudly say that diversity and enrollments are up based
on those first experiences and no one&amp;#39;s the wiser that we&amp;#39;re killing
the kids later on. We have to do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Mark Guzdial - the outstanding contributer
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mark was this year&amp;#39;s winner of SIGCSE&amp;#39;s Award for Outstanding
Contribution to CS Education. A well deserved award. Mark&amp;#39;s talk was
terrific and similar to the one he gave at the Code and Beyond
conference in NY which I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/thoughts-on-code-and-beyond-ct/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As with the previous keynote you can get a great summary if you read
Andy&amp;#39;s post linked above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One point Mark made was that he felt that all students should learn
programming but if I remember the talk correctly he didn&amp;#39;t make a
strong statement about all students learning CS. He also said that
first course our CS majors take shouldn&amp;#39;t be the same as the first
course for non majors. I see where Mark&amp;#39;s coming from I&amp;#39;m not sure I
agree. Well, I do agree given what a first CS course for a major
typically looks like versus what a never-CS major might need for life but
the few CS0 for non major courses I&amp;#39;ve seen don&amp;#39;t leave their students
with enough to continue on to the CS major or a minor (which could be
valuable to a HUGE swath of students) so they end up taking the CS0
for CS majors anyway. This means one more course and one more
semester. More cost and more time spent. I&amp;#39;ll say that I do agree with
Mark UNLESS you can design a course that can address the needs of both
parties and the truth is I think you can. We did it at Stuy. Students
come back with that having been their only course and talk of its
usefulness and utility and students come back having used it to launch
a tech career in later high school, college, and beyond. What we built
isn&amp;#39;t perfect and is for a particular population but as proof of
concept it&amp;#39;s convinced me that a single course for both can be done
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another one of Mark&amp;#39;s big points was taking CS into other subject
areas. I love this and I love when he said (apologies if the quote&amp;#39;s a
little off) &amp;#34;They need things and we can build stuff&amp;#34; as a call to
action to partner with and to develop the languages and tools needed
to support a new vision of CS embedded in other subject areas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My thoughts here are that as a community we are ignoring the realities
of K12 education. Mark mentioned Bootstrap World, a sprogram both he
and I like very much. It is embedded in Algebra classes and uses CS in
Racket (nee Scheme) to support learning said algebra. Mark noted that
Racket looks like Algebra and that&amp;#39;s one of the reasons Bootstrap
works. Another fact often left out is that algebra is frequently
taught either over two years or with a double period allocated to
it. It is given more time than most classes and that allows teachers to experiment
a bit more with instruction. Even if we develop more tools like
Bootstrap that align themselves to teaching other subjects those
subject teachers might not have the time to dedicate to the new
tool. Why not? That&amp;#39;s another thing Mark indirectly mentioned. At one
point he said that we might have to &amp;#34;take a step back&amp;#34; first in terms
of results and quite frankly, K12 teachers sometimes can&amp;#39;t take that
chance. In addition to not wanting to give their current students a
worse experience even with the promise that future classes would get a
better one they have to face the specter of high stakes testing. If
I&amp;#39;m using a new CS tool in a history class and my student&amp;#39;s test
results go down, they might have to repeat the class and the teacher
could put their license in jeopardy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the end I loved just about everything Mark had to say but it still
got me thinking about a lot and to me that&amp;#39;s one of the hallmarks of a
great talk. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Blair Taylor - the controversy
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Blair Taylor gave the final keynote and this one had some controversy
around it. Andy&amp;#39;s blog post again summarizes things well. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My only take on the content is that the talk was more about
Dr. Taylor&amp;#39;s journey and less about Cyber Security (I hate it that
it&amp;#39;s now just being called &amp;#34;cyber&amp;#34;) but that was fine. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I want to talk about here is not so much the controversy over how
some people took parts of Dr. Taylor&amp;#39;s talk and the Q&amp;amp;A at the end but
rather the fact that more and more recently I&amp;#39;ve felt that as a
community we can&amp;#39;t talk about difficult issues concerning gender,
race, and the like. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I consider myself an ally to under represented and under served groups
but have found myself in situations recently where unless I 100%
parrot one side&amp;#39;s extreme view I&amp;#39;m accused of sexism or racism at
which point ANYTHING I say is treated as such. One is not allowed to
see any nuance in what is a very complex topic. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point, the speaker made a joke. She prefaced it with something
like &amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m going to tell this offensive joke&amp;#34; and that she could,
presumably because she is a women. The joke fell flat (although I&amp;#39;ve
told the story of the keynote to a few women in tech and they chuckled
and said they actually kind of liked the joke). My take was that the
speaker was setting the stage to maybe dive into a difficult
conversation. My take was also that some members of the audience right
then and there decided that the speaker was wrong about all things. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the talk I was a bit more convinced that this was the case as I
read a tweet stream explaining what happened that included the joke
but none of the context for the reader to make an informed decision. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the end, I felt that Dr. Taylor has honestly worked for under
represented groups and while this might be unpopular, her pragmatism of
sometimes swallowing an insult and &amp;#34;having a sense of humor&amp;#34; is the
right thing to do. Unfortunately, Dr. Taylor misread the audience and that
some people decided somewhere in her talk that even though she was
working to empower women in her own way, it wasn&amp;#39;t &amp;#34;my way&amp;#34; so it was
wrong. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The situation was unfortunate and my big fear is that as a community
we still have a long way to go before we can have these conversations
and personally, as someone who considers themselves an ally of the
undeserved I&amp;#39;m becoming more gun shy of partaking in discussions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
That&amp;#39;s all for now.
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s my take on the keynotes. Much more to come on the
conference in future posts. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March PD for CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 15:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Back in December we ran our first &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/&#34;&gt;PD session for CS teachers&lt;/a&gt;. This was
to address the need for professional development for teachers who were
more experienced in terms of computer science - we aimed this at people who were ready to
teach APCS-A, similar, or beyond and also to start to build a
community for these teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had trouble setting things up for February but we&amp;#39;re good to go for
March, April and May.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just as with our first session, each session will consist of a content
piece, a pedagogy piece, and will overall be driven by the
participants.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next session is set for Thursday, March 14 from 5:00 - 8:00 and
will be hosted by Digital Ocean. The sessions will earn you 3 CTLE
hours and dinner will be provided.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you or a CS teacher you know is interested in this, they can sign
up here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/forms/DCXqPtwYS47Ooo8j1&#34;&gt;https://goo.gl/forms/DCXqPtwYS47Ooo8j1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 09:40:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Two of the hardest topics to make meaningful to students in APCS-A are
inheritance and interfaces. It&amp;#39;s not that they&amp;#39;re super difficult
topics but rather that they&amp;#39;re not often needed, useful, or superior
to not using them on beginner assignments. More often than not the
motivation is a bit forced as are the assignments. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Inheritance is its own can of worms and to be honest, something I&amp;#39;ve
not found to be all that useful or necessary. The class abstraction
made sense to me for a number of projects but deep inheritance just
hasn&amp;#39;t come up much. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, today I thought I&amp;#39;d talk about interfaces.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When Java was first built a decision was made not to allow multiple
inheritance - the idea that a class can be derived from multiple
parents. Multiple inheritance is powerful but it can also be
complicated and confusing. By not including multiple inheritance Java
ended up easier to work with than say C++ but there were times where
you needed features that multiple inheritance provide. Specifically
there are times when you need some functionality that operates across
multiple unrelated classes. Without any other features, you&amp;#39;d have to
start &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; of your classes from a single based class and include that
functionality. Clearly not a good idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first useful example is probably &lt;code&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first blush it might not seem all that useful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s suppose you are doing something like finding the first String
(alphabetically) from an array:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s easy enough but what if you had another class, &lt;code&gt;Shape&lt;/code&gt; where
you wanted to find the &amp;#34;smallest&amp;#34; based on area and a third class
&lt;code&gt;Person&lt;/code&gt; where you want to find the smallest by age? Without
interfaces you would need three independent search routines or set up
a crazy inheritance hierarchy where &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Person&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Shape&lt;/code&gt; all
come from the same parent. Instead, by having your two new classes
implement the &lt;code&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt; interface all three can use the same
search:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not entirely true. The above solution will give you compiler
warnings. You&amp;#39;ll have to decide if it makes sense to jump through the
hoops necessary to get rid of the warnings or if it&amp;#39;s sufficient to do
some vigorous had waving.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the benefit of interfaces. You can create functionality that
works across classes. In addition to writing things like our
 &lt;code&gt;findSmallest&lt;/code&gt; above, if our classes implement &lt;code&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt; we can sort
collections of our classes using the built in sort methods.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a benefit that our students can probably appreciate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anther place interfaces come up and make sense are with GUI
programming. It&amp;#39;s pretty easy to show the utility of using interfaces
with the assorted listeners. That said, Java GUI programming is
something of a bear so maybe that&amp;#39;s not the way to go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Where else can you explore interfaces in APCS-A? Any program where you
have different entities that change in different ways over time. This
might be a simulation where time passes via a control loop or maybe a
game where time passes a turn at a time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, you might have a simulation with various resources that
implement an interface with an &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; routine:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe a food resource updates by raising or lowering the amount of
food it provides or perhaps an animal resource updates its location. You could
have an array of objects that implement this interface and just call
update on each one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You could do the same with a game. Maybe the human player&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; 
prompts for keyboard input while non player characters just calculate
their next state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Interfaces are not the easiest thing to teach. The mechanics are
straightforward but the motivation is frequently forced for
beginners. I was never 100% happy with how I did it and now that I&amp;#39;m
in a C++ shop it doesn&amp;#39;t come up but I hope this is helpful to some of
you out there.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solve A To Solve B</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/solve-a-to-solve-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 19:36:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/solve-a-to-solve-b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So many programming assignments involve a direct solution. Write a
program to do this or write a problem to solve that. It&amp;#39;s pretty
typical. There&amp;#39;s nothing wrong with assignments like these. They allow
students to practice what they&amp;#39;ve been learning and it gives them the
opportunity to create some cool programs. All the same, I like it when
there&amp;#39;s an indirect problem. You&amp;#39;re faced with a problem but in order
to solve it you first have to solve some other problem
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s why I liked &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2018/day/10&#34;&gt;day 10&lt;/a&gt; from this year&amp;#39;s Advent of Code. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At it&amp;#39;s core the question presents you with a collection of points
along with velocities in this form::
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
position=&amp;lt; 9,  1&amp;gt; velocity=&amp;lt; 0,  2&amp;gt;
position=&amp;lt; 7,  0&amp;gt; velocity=&amp;lt;-1,  0&amp;gt;
position=&amp;lt; 3, -2&amp;gt; velocity=&amp;lt;-1,  1&amp;gt;
position=&amp;lt; 6, 10&amp;gt; velocity=&amp;lt;-2, -1&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Each point moves by adding the x and y components if its velocity each
second. For example, the last two points listed above - points (3,-2)
nad (6,10) would be transformed overtime as follows:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Point&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Velocity&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Second 0&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Second 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Second 2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Second 3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Second 4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3, -2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-1,1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,-2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,-1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0,1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-1,2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6,10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-2,-1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6,10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0,7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-2 6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At some point in time, if you look at the points on a grid they will
spell out a message or at least a sequence of letters. The question
asks you to figure out that message. There&amp;#39;s a complete example and a
nice story around the problem on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2018/day/10&#34;&gt;Advent of Code site&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first thought is probably to run this as a simulation. Set up a
loop, update the point locations, visualize and see if you have an
answer. This isn&amp;#39;t trivial for a beginner but it&amp;#39;s certainly
approachable. It also has a big problem. Unless you happen to have
some optical character recognition libaray handy you have to draw and
look at the output on every change. Given that it could take thousands
of iterations, this is not practical at all. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can do better by solving another problem first. The key insight is
that each point travels along a line. In fact, this problem is a great
time to talk about a parametric representation of a line like 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;script type=&amp;#34;text/javascript&amp;#34; src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.1/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&#34;&gt;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.1/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
\(L=P+tV\) 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Where \(P\)represents an \((x,y)\) point and \(V\) a direction vector
\((dx,dy)\).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of where the points start, at some point all of them will
be contained within your field of view after which they will continue
along their paths outside of that field of view. We can look at a
bounding box for all of the points and when that bounding box is
smallest we should be at or close to our message.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is readily accomplished. We can find a bounding box by finding the
smallest and largest x and y coordinates for all the current points
and using \((X_{min},Y_{min})\) and \((X_{max},Y_{max})\) as the
diagonals of a bounding rectangle and then compare areas of these
rectangles. They should decrease at first and then eventually
increase. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; time &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,some_large_value,stepsize):
      new_pts &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; transform(pts,time) 
      bbox &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bounding_box(new_pts)
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (area(bbox) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; area(previous_bbox)):
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt; we&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;re close to or at the smallest bounding box&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can start with a big &lt;code&gt;stepsize&lt;/code&gt; and then refine it down until we
hone in on the smallest bounding box.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there, we can transform all the points using the time that
resulted in the smallest bounding box and then display the points to
see our message. We might have to go through a small window of times
since the actual message might just be close to the configuration
yielded from the smallest bounding box. Of course that visualization
takes some doing - the actual viewing window might not align with your
screeen coordinates, they could all, for example, be negative so
you&amp;#39;ll probably have to do one last transformation to translate and
possibly scale the final points to make it all viewable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I first solved the problem, I just dumped the coordinates into a
2 dimentional array and printed it but afterwards I wrote a little
clojurescript html5 canvas visualization:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/advent-2018-10.gif&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34; height=&#34;20px&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. It&amp;#39;s not a trivial problem for beginners but it is doable. There&amp;#39;s a
lot to deal with:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
parse the data
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn&amp;#39;t too bad. You could cover regular expressions but even
without it isn&amp;#39;t too big of a deal. You could also just use an editor
to extract the important data or preprocess this for the kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Figure out how to transform the points.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This also isn&amp;#39;t too bad. Just loop over all the points with &lt;code&gt;newpoint
= oldpoint + t * velocity&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Figure out the bounding boxes
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also not too bad. Loop over all the points to find the smallest and
largest x and y coordinates
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Set up a loop to find the smallest bounding box and hence the time
that the message will appear.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and then finally:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
draw the points to visually inspect the answer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This might be the most persnickety part. When I first coded it my
output was upside down and backwards but good enough.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can&amp;#39;t fully put my finger on it but I really enjoyed this problem. I
hope you enjoyed my writeup. If you want to check out my solution for
this (minus the clojurescript visualization) along with the other
Advent of Code problems I finished this year you can find them &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2018&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code, Data Structures, and Hidden Complexity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 15:17:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Since 2015, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ericwastl&#34;&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt; has gifted us each December with &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of
Code&lt;/a&gt; - a 25 day programming competition that I very much enjoy. This
year I haven&amp;#39;t been able to get to too many of the problems. I only
completed the first two days on the day they were released, problem
three a day late and then I didn&amp;#39;t get back to the problems until
almost 12/25 - the final day of the competition. I&amp;#39;ve spent a bit of
time over the break working through the problems. I&amp;#39;m currently
through 9. I started working through the problems in Clojure - part of
my yearly attempt to dive into the language but then did a few in
Python just to speed up my progress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I did &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2018/day/9&#34;&gt;question 9&lt;/a&gt; which I found interesting as a teacher -
so much so that I think I&amp;#39;ll assign at some point in the future.
At the core of the problem you have to maintain a list of items
inserting and deleting items at assorted locations. I threw together
this solution:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;num_players &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;431&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# 9&lt;/span&gt;
last_score &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;70950&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# 255&lt;/span&gt;
players &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(num_players&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)]

player&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
board&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;]
next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; last_score:
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;:
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#regular insert&lt;/span&gt;
        L &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; len(board)
        index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;L
        index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;L
        board&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;insert(index,next_marble)
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
        players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; next_marble
        index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;len(board)
        players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;board[index]
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; board[index]
    player&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(player&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;num_players
    next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(max(players))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It worked and I got my first star. This unlocked part 2 which changed
the number of marbles in the game from 70950 to 70950&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;00&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. This
brings me to my first observation - hidden complexity. Seeing my input
I knew my part 2 would be crazy slow. The solution requires you insert
and delete into a list over and over again and I did it using a Python
list and a Python list is backed by an array. This means that every
insert and delete will be linear and I had a whole bunch of them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s another great simple example of hidden complexity. Students and
beginners use Python lists as if they were linked structures with
direct indexing - the best of all worlds. It&amp;#39;s great if you&amp;#39;re dealing
with small data sets but unless you&amp;#39;re careful things can get very
slow very fast. It&amp;#39;s important that students learn about this and it
appears that many don&amp;#39;t. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though I knew the program would take forever to run it was my bed
time so I started it on part two and turned in for the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I woke up I had an answer to part 2, entered it and earned my
next star. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course I knew that the solution should really be written using a
doubly linked list. The funny thing is that if you&amp;#39;re comfortable with
creating dynamic data structures like linked lists, writing a solution
using a doubly linked list and running it on part 2 actually takes a fraction of
the time of writing the original solution and running it. To make
sure, I did it. I decided to code it up in Java since I might assign
something like this to my students in C++. You can check it out &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2018/tree/master/java&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second take away was that it&amp;#39;s actually beneficial for students to
be able comfortable with pointers and dynamic memory and while
creating a linked list let alone a tree can be tricky at first, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/it-gets-easier-advent19/&#34;&gt;it
does get easier.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With all the debate going on over coding vs computational thinking vs
CS it&amp;#39;s things like this - thinking about things like this that marks
one of the ways a computer scientist is different from a programmer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Development - APCS-A, similar and beyond</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 08:56:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A while ago I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/&#34;&gt;our plans&lt;/a&gt; at Hunter to run professional
development for CS teachers. Specifically, running once a month
sessions for teachers who teach APCS-A, similar and beyond.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea started as a joke but morphed into a legit idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was talking to some friends about CTLE hours and how ridiculous the
system is. NY State teachers need 100 hours of CTLE credit (PD hours)
every so many years. It&amp;#39;s something of a scam for a few
reasons. First, two of the biggest providers are the NYC DOE and the
UFT, the teacher&amp;#39;s union. I&amp;#39;ve been told they both charge money for
many CTLE credit bearing activities. That certainly doesn&amp;#39;t seem
kosher – your boss and your union set up a system to charge you to keep your
job. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, it turns out that Hunter is certified to issue CTLE credits so
we joked that we should get dinner and hang out once a month and call
it professional development. We were only half joking - whenever you
get a bunch of teachers in a room they talk shop and that is actually
the best PD there is. Upon talking among ourselves and also to other
teachers we realized there was a legitimate need for PD for teachers
who were beyond the basics and so we turned this silly idea into the
real deal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday we had our first session. We had about 25 attendees for
a three hour session.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can&amp;#39;t tell you if it was any good - you&amp;#39;ll have to ask the
participants, I can tell you what we did and what we plan moving
forward.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We started with a content piece. I ran through &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-03-23-who_won_the_election-quadratic_to_linear_time/&#34;&gt;this lesson&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/&#34;&gt;this
one&lt;/a&gt;) where the students find the mode of a list, realize it&amp;#39;s a slow
(n^2) algorithm and then refine it to a linear solution. The key idea
is to give the students an intuitive feeling for run time issues and
also to introduce them to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-17-hidden-complexity.html/&#34;&gt;hidden complexity&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After this we had dinner, provided by our friends at Google. Over
dinner the teachers talked shop. In addition to getting to know each
other, their programs, and their classes we also asked them to
consider these three items:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What are things that cause you difficulty that you&amp;#39;d like us to
cover?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What are things you wish you knew about that you&amp;#39;d like us to
cover?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What are things you&amp;#39;re comfortable with that you&amp;#39;d be willing to
share with the group?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After dinner we circled up and JonAlf presented the way he set up
student note taking in his class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/pd-apcs-a.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, we discussed next steps - specifically what we came up with
for those three bullet points above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like the idea of having at least one short content piece, one short
pedagogy piece and a deeper dive at each meeting. For the first one,
JonAlf and I had to guess as to what might be useful and at the
appropriate level. We advertised for teachers who did APCS-A, similar,
or beyond but I&amp;#39;m sure we had teachers for whom the mode lesson was a
bit too advanced to do without scaffolding and also some for whom it
was way to simple. As we continue to meet, we&amp;#39;ll nail down the right
level and the right activities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The real hope is that many of the participants will become regulars
and together we&amp;#39;ll turn this into both an amazing once a month
activity and also a community of teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Right now, I&amp;#39;m looking for companies who want to feed us and possibly
provide space so if you know of any, hook me up. We&amp;#39;re also collecting
feedback and ideas from the attendees. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re targetting February for our next session followed by March,
April, May and possibly June.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the meantime, stay tuned.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 19:43:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent this past Saturday morning up at the Microsoft building in
Times Square. What was I doing there? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aankit?lang=en&#34;&gt;Aankit Patel&lt;/a&gt; invited me to check
out the professional development that he and his team organized for
the teachers involved in the assorted CSforAllNYC programs that his
office runs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of great things going on. I was only able to stay for a couple of
hours but I spent some time in two rooms run by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, a room of &lt;a href=&#34;https://bjc.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;BJC&lt;/a&gt;
teachers, a group working with &lt;a href=&#34;https://p5js.org&#34;&gt;p5.js&lt;/a&gt;, one doing physical computing and
a bunch more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While there was good content all around I was really impressed with
the sense of community in many of the rooms. One of the hardest parts
of being a computer science teacher in K12 is that you&amp;#39;re frequently
the only CS teacher in your school. That can be an awfully lonely
existence. It&amp;#39;s hard to be the only teacher. No one to bounce lesson
ideas off of or to debrief with and if you leave your school they&amp;#39;re
left in the lurch. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s simply amazing that all these NYC teachers have opportunities
like this past weekends PD and the communty it provides. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, teachers who are not part of city programs like
SEP or TEALS don&amp;#39;t have these opportunities and at Hunter we&amp;#39;re trying
to do our piece to help solve that problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few months ago I wrote about our plans to roll out once a month
professional development sessions for CTLE hours specifically aimed at
teachers who are ready for the next step. Those who are already
comfortable with the first courses and student experiences. I&amp;#39;m
describing the sessions as being for high school teachers teaching
APCS-A, similar or beyond.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Were hosting our first session on December 13th. There will be a
couple of presentations or activities to get us started but the bulk
of the time will be about planning the rest of the sessions which will
run until the end of the school year and the hope is that we will
cover both content beyond the basics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re a public school CS teacher in NYC (and need CTLE hours)
and you&amp;#39;re ready for something more advanced than the usual PD
opportunities, why don&amp;#39;t you join us. Just sign up &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/forms/FJDyCx7qFec1yPjr1&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Space is
limited so if we fill, we&amp;#39;ll add you to the waitlist and we&amp;#39;ll work on
trying to find a bigger space to acomodate more teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to getting this thing started!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman - part 3</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 17:25:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Parts 1 and 2
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Part 3
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the first two parts of this set of posts I wrote about the
motivation and design a question answering system that can answer
&amp;#34;who&amp;#34; queries like &amp;#34;who played Spiderman&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;who shot John Lennon?&amp;#34;
It&amp;#39;s not perfect. When doing the Spiderman query, chances are the
desired answer will be at or near the top of the list of most
frequently appearing names but so will &amp;#34;Peter Parker.&amp;#34; How do you
distinguish between a real answer and a fictional name? Likewise, if
you ask &amp;#34;Who shot John Lennon?&amp;#34; You&amp;#39;ll probably get Mark David (if you
search for two word names) or if you&amp;#39;re more inclusive, Mark David
Chapman, but you&amp;#39;ll also find John Lennon at or near the top of your
results.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This system may not be perfect but then again, it can be written by one or a
small group of students relatively new to CS in a few periods as
opposed to a team of full time Google Software Engineers. I also truly
 &lt;strong&gt;like&lt;/strong&gt; the fact that it isn&amp;#39;t perfect. Too many student experiences involve
perfect questions with predetermined perfect answers. I love the fact
that they see false positives and true negatives in this. I love that
they can get pretty good but not perfect results. This makes the
experience more interesting, more fun, and more authentic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This lesson can also easily be extended beyond &amp;#34;who&amp;#34; queries. &amp;#34;When&amp;#34;
queries are also pretty straightforward. Things like &amp;#34;When was D-Day&amp;#34;
or &amp;#34;When did Elvis die?&amp;#34; For a &amp;#34;when&amp;#34; query, you start the same way as
for a &amp;#34;who&amp;#34; query. Use the search API to get a bunch of documents that
mention the query terms. Then you look for dates. Dates can be even
easier to search for than names. Particularly if your students know
regular expressions. Dates could be things like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
two digits / two digits / two digits
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Month name number, number
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
or in regular expressions, something like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[0-9]{2}/[0-9]{2}/[0-9]{2}/
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
(Jan|Feb|Mar…)[0-9]{2}, {0-9]{4}}
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just as with &amp;#34;who&amp;#34; queries there are issues to deal with - searching
for &amp;#34;when did Elvis die&amp;#34; might give you when Elvis was born instead
but again, these are great motivators for further exploration and
discussion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there&amp;#39;s the project. What level of students can do this? It
depends. I first did this in my Software Devepment class. That class
was offered to student who had completed APCS-A. The class covered
using APIs and setting up a web application using Python and Flask so
they were able to do the entire project, soup to nuts. An APCS class
could also do the project without the web application just so long as
they have access to the search API. In fact, an intro programming
class could also have success with this project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was actually one of the lessons I&amp;#39;ve missed since I haven&amp;#39;t been
able to work it into my Hunter courses so I was really happy when the
class discussion led me to call and audible and talk about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I hope some of you out there experiment with it and if you do, I&amp;#39;d
love to hear about your tweaks, implementations and successes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Parts 1 and 2
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 16:04:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Parts 1 and 3
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Part 2
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we left off &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/&#34;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt; we used a search engine API to gather a
whole bunch of documents with the term &amp;#34;played Spiderman&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;who
played Spiderman.&amp;#34; Now we have to process these documents to answer
the question. Fortunately, the documents are basically just big
strings of text.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since we&amp;#39;re doing a &amp;#34;who&amp;#34; query  we want to find all the names in all
the documents. This leads to a class discussion on how to find names
in a large string. They&amp;#39;ll come up with rules like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
two adjacent words each with a capital first letter.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
an honorific (Mr, Ms, etc.) followed by a capitalized word
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A word that matches a name from a &amp;#34;popular name&amp;#34; list followed by a
capitalized word.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class might come up with different or additional rules. Actually
writing the code to pull out the names is an nice little assignment
that can be done with classes at many different levels. A beginning
class might just use string operations while an intermediate one could
use regular expressions. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will the students write code that always finds all the names? Probably
not. Will their code incorrectly identify some word sets as names?
Most likely. It doesn&amp;#39;t really matter. Actually, this is a good
thing. You now have a great platform to talk about false positives and
true negatives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now the moment of truth - what&amp;#39;s the most common name? To answer that
you have to decide on the meaning of &amp;#34;most common.&amp;#34; Is it the name
that appeared the most times? How about the name that appeared in the
most documents? Does it matter? Whichever way you do it, chances are
the correct answer will be near the top of your list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up in part 3 - other types of queries and why I love this sequence of
lessons so much.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Parts 1 and 3
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 1 or my Nifty Assignment (that was rejected)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 17:16:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Parts 2 and 3
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[[/post/who-played-spiderman-2/][Part 2]
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t going to teach this lesson today. I was planning on starting
a multi day project starting with an exercise in specification writing
and design.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Beforehand though, we had to talk about classes. One of my students
asked if probability and/or statistics were really important for CS. I
started to cite a few examples and then decided to segue into
this. Normally, I do this as a couple of lessons which leads to a
project, we just did the first part. I might do it as a project with
my class later on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also submitted this as a &amp;#34;Nifty Assignment&amp;#34; for SIGCSE a couple of
years ago but it wasn&amp;#39;t accepted. I was going to share the lesson at
some point so, well, here goes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It starts with a question:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Who played Spiderman?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s it. Every student writes down their answer. No talking, no
Googling or other searching, just write something down.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then go around the room an tally up the answers. I got something
like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Toby Maguire&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tom Holland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Andrew Garfield&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Peter Parker&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So as a class, we think that Toby MAguire played Spiderman with Tom
Holland also being a good choice. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After painstakingly explaining that Peter Parker couldn&amp;#39;t play
Spiderman because he &lt;strong&gt;IS&lt;/strong&gt; Spiderman I also shared some of the more
interesting answers I&amp;#39;ve gotten over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve gotten &amp;#34;the lady playing the song on the violin in the movie in
front of the subway&amp;#34; which is technically correct and I also get
Willem Dafoe because as the Green Goblin / Norman Osborn he &lt;strong&gt;PLAYED&lt;/strong&gt; Spiderman.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, it appears that if we get a lot of data on who &amp;#34;played
Spiderman&amp;#34; it&amp;#39;s likely that the most popular result is the right
answer or at least the right answer will be among the most popular
results. Of course, this is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nbc.com/saturday-night-live/video/common-knowledge/n9612&#34;&gt;not always the case&lt;/a&gt; but with reliable
data sources. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, the basic idea is that if we have a question to answer like &amp;#34;Who
played spiderman?&amp;#34; we can start by collecting a whole bunch of
documents from the web with terms like &amp;#34;played Spiderman&amp;#34; in them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I first taught this lesson, we used the Google API to search for
web pages with the search terms in them but more recently I&amp;#39;ve used
the Bing API instead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This leaves us with a large number of documents that could potentially
answer a search for &amp;#34;who played Spiderman?&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ll leave it at this for now. Next time, we&amp;#39;ll talk about how we can
go from this collection of documents to a likely answer to our query. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tune in again tomorrow, same bat Time, same bat channel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Parts 2 and 3
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[[/post/who-played-spiderman-2/][Part 2]
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compile Each Concept</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2018 14:46:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ve all been there:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Student: Teacher, I need help
Teacher (comes over)
Student (shows screen listing three bazillion errors)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The student has just written pages of code and finally decided to try
to run it only to end up with pages of errors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Error messages can at times be hard to read for beginners but to see
and truth be told, they frequently don&amp;#39;t even read them but over the
years I&amp;#39;ve developed a practice that I&amp;#39;ve found helpful as a software
developer and if students adopt the same practice it can save them a
lot of time and effort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea is very simple. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Compile and test one concept at a time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It might seem silly, but if I&amp;#39;m writing a a program, my first compile
might be code that looks like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  using std&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;cout;
  using std&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;endl;

  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;()
  {
  
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;;
  }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
or 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;HelloWorld&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;String&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; args&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
	
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This might seem silly but it really doesn&amp;#39;t take any effort. I have a
key sequence to do this under Emacs and if I&amp;#39;m using an interactive
language like Python or Clojure I just have to hit &lt;code&gt;c-c c-c&lt;/code&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This might seem silly but I do it out of muscle memory and it
immediately tells me I don&amp;#39;t have any syntax errors and my build system
works.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Going further, I compile and test every time I code up what I call a
concept. What&amp;#39;s a concept? Let&amp;#39;s look at some code. A student might
write something like this to find prime number up to n:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;prime_list&lt;/span&gt;(n):
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,n):
        i_isPrime &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; True
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;):
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; :
                i_isPrime &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; False
                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; i_isPrime:
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(i)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a lot going on there. To me, a concept is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A loop
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A complex calculation
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
a conditional
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of these can have other concepts within.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the above code, I&amp;#39;d probable write it as follows, adding in tests
and print statements throughout the process:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Step 1:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;prime_list&lt;/span&gt;(n):
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,n):
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(i)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Step 2
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;prime_list&lt;/span&gt;(n):
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,n):
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;):
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(i,j)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Step 3
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;prime_list&lt;/span&gt;(n):
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,n):
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;):
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; :
                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(i,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;is not prime&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; i_isPrime:
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(i)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Step 4 
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;prime_list&lt;/span&gt;(n):
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,n):
        i_isPrime &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; True
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;):
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; :
                i_isPrime &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; False
                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(i,i_isPrime)
  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Step 5
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;prime_list&lt;/span&gt;(n):
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,n):
        i_isPrime &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; True
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;):
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;j &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; :
                i_isPrime &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; False
                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; i_isPrime:
            &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(i)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It might not play out exactly this way but if not it would be something
similar. The idea is that if you test every time you add one concept
or construct there are fewer places where you can introduce an error.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you enter 100 lines before you test there are 100 places where
things can go wrong. If you type 10, there are only 10. On top of
that, if you&amp;#39;ve added 100 lines, conecptually you&amp;#39;ve probably added a
lot and the error can be anywhere. While it&amp;#39;s not always the case,
most of the time, if you just added an &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt;, the problem will be in the
&lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt; or as a result of the if. Same with a &lt;strong&gt;loop&lt;/strong&gt; or any other construct.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once you get in the habit, it&amp;#39;s easy and doesn&amp;#39;t really take any
time. A couple of keystrokes to compile and a couple more to run. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All too often students try to write everything at once and it&amp;#39;s so
rare that it works. If we can get them to develop incrementally
they&amp;#39;ll be able to write much more complex systems and write them with
much less frustration.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a school for CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/creating-a-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/creating-a-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/09/do-we-really-need-cs-focused-high.html&#34;&gt;Do we really need CS focused high schools?&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the question Alfred Thompson asked partly in reaction to my
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/that-time-bill-gates-visited-afse&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; talking about Bill Gates&amp;#39; visit to &lt;a href=&#34;http://afsenyc.org&#34;&gt;AFSE&lt;/a&gt;, a NYC public school
with a CS focus.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On both posts, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/reallymdp&#34;&gt;Michael Preston&lt;/a&gt; shared some important and good points about
AFSE as a starting point and gateway that helped lead to CS4All in NYC
and also specifically about AFSE.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In response to Alfred&amp;#39;s question I thought it was time I shared a bit
about what I was pushing for AFSE back when I was involved. I wasn&amp;#39;t
able to talk publicly about any of this at the time because I was
warned very sternly by one DOE person involved that I shouldn&amp;#39;t talk
to &amp;#34;outsiders&amp;#34; about my concerns or designs. In retrospect, since I
stopped getting replies to my emails and was apparently dropped from
email lists after they selected their founding principal, I probably
should have been more public about my critiques. On the other hand, I
should have been more politic internally prior to getting to that
point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reading Alfred&amp;#39;s post, what I was pushing for AFSE at the time cuts
right to Alfred&amp;#39;s question so I thought I&amp;#39;d write about it today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before starting though I want to be &lt;strong&gt;absolutely clear&lt;/strong&gt; about one
thing. This is not a critique of AFSE as it stands. There are some
great teachers and wonderful students there and I do what I can to
support both whenever I can. This is a post about my design vs the
DOE&amp;#39;s design and later implementation. Also note that the numbers,
sizes, restrictions and designs are all based on NY state and NYC
requirements along with what one can typically do in a NYC public
school.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though it&amp;#39;s the least important issue with respect to a CS school
or not, let&amp;#39;s start by getting the dirty word out of the way. Given
the stated mission of the school (at the time) I wanted a screen. Not
a &amp;#34;Stuy test&amp;#34; screen but something. Probably something more along the
lines of the screen used by the Manhattan Science Hunter High
School. We never got that far in discussing it. My contention was and
still is that if you want to produce &amp;#34;Google ready&amp;#34; software engineers
by high school graduation, particularly in a small school, you can&amp;#39;t
start with kids 2 or 3 years behind in math. Now, if your goal isn&amp;#39;t
&amp;#34;Google ready engineers&amp;#34; but rather to use CS to engage a population
that isn&amp;#39;t otherwise engaged, I can get behind that and you don&amp;#39;t need
a screen. It&amp;#39;s important however to note it&amp;#39;s a different mission.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The DOE would maintain that you don&amp;#39;t need any screen and kids can
start out years behind and by the end of their senior year they&amp;#39;d be
years ahead. It doesn&amp;#39;t work that way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They&amp;#39;d ask tech people at meetings what they looked for in employees
knowing that they&amp;#39;d get back &amp;#34;teamwork, creativity etc.&amp;#34; I would of
course follow up with &amp;#34;where do you look for these candidates&amp;#34; and
they&amp;#39;d say &amp;#34;MIT, Cal Tech, Harvard.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The DOE insisted on no screen. This is fine but it&amp;#39;s no surprise that
Google&amp;#39;s not beating down the doors for AFSE graduates right out of
high school and the math regents show that you indeed can&amp;#39;t take kids
from multiple years behind and end up with them multiple years ahead
given typical school resources. They&amp;#39;re doing really good work there
but there&amp;#39;s no such thing as a miracle school just hard work and
incremental progress. I have heard more than once that the founding
principal had lobbied for a screen so I feel my original assessment
was correct.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up, size. The DOE insisted on a small school focused on CS. They
wanted a school of around 136 kids per grade, which makes for 4
&amp;#34;homerooms,&amp;#34; and that the school would focus on CS. My proposal was
very different. I advocated for a school with about 340 kids per grade
and not specifically focused on CS but rather with a great model CS
program - a Software Engineering Institute at the blah blah school if
you would.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A small school can&amp;#39;t support a wide range of classes. With 4 classes
of kids per grade you don&amp;#39;t have a lot of schedule flexibility in
terms of class levels or electives. You also have very few teachers
per subject - for a subject taught for a full year every year for a
single period, you&amp;#39;d have one teacher per grade in that subject. If
you&amp;#39;re a school for CS you&amp;#39;re not going to be able to offer a robust
schedule of music or arts classes. Likewise an arts school is going to
be hard pressed to offer a suite of science electives. Remember,
public schools are not flush with money and can&amp;#39;t just offer loads of
courses for a handful of kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What we end up with is a school with limited offerings beyond CS and
we&amp;#39;re asking kids to decide in 8th grade if that&amp;#39;s the career path for
them. This is a hidden problem of all small schools. Kids shouldn&amp;#39;t
have to decide on their future in the 8th grade. They should all be
able to go to schools that offer a wide range of subjects to a good
degree of depth. Only large public schools can do this. I know that
public schools come with their own problems but this is one of the
trade offs. I believe that having this selection done in 8th grade
along with the tech stereotypes and preconceptions is a big part of
the schools difficulty in appealing to girls.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now even if every student who applied and is randomly accepted into
AFSE does indeed want to be a CS person then we&amp;#39;ve also lost because
we&amp;#39;ve done nothing to get more kids into the pool. It could still
potentially function as a model school in terms of courses or possibly
pedagogy but it won&amp;#39;t expose and inspire anyone new with respect to
tech.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s contrast that with what I proposed. I wanted around 340 kids per
grade or 10 &amp;#34;homerooms.&amp;#34; How did I arrive at that number? It wasn&amp;#39;t
just a guess. Schools like Stuyvesant or Brooklyn Tech are clearly too
large and impersonal but small 136 kids per grade schools are too
small. The 10 homeroom per grade school seems to be the best
compromise. There are enough teachers so that there&amp;#39;s institutional
memory when one leaves, enough of them and students for a varied set
of electives. It also means that there are enough teachers to avoid
bad fits between teacher and student. At the same time, it&amp;#39;s not so
large that kids get lost. I also spoke with some of the best
programmers I know - not computer programmers but people who schedule
students for classes in schools and this seems to be the best
compromise size range. Also, with this size you don&amp;#39;t necessarily need
a screen if you want &amp;#34;Google ready&amp;#34; software engineers. There will be
enough of a range kids that come in behind and kids that come in ahead
can get what they need.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also didn&amp;#39;t want it to be a CS school but rather a school with great
CS. That way it would appeal to a range of students. Kids who think
they want to do CS and those who don&amp;#39;t. At the end of they day some of
the kids that think they wanted CS won&amp;#39;t want it and those kids will
have other options. At the same time some of the non-tech kids will
take the required CS and find out that &amp;#34;this is neat stuff&amp;#34; and we get
to increase the number of people in the tent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I still believe my design would have worked out better but that&amp;#39;s not
to say that I don&amp;#39;t think that AFSE has been and is important. As Mike
pointed out in his comment, AFSE was the first unscreened school to
offer legit and it did (and does) offer a place for CS kids that don&amp;#39;t
get into or don&amp;#39;t want to go to a place like Stuy which is very much a
large school and an unforgiving machine. It was also a showpiece that
helped pave the way for CS in all NYC schools. All of that&amp;#39;s good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I do regret parts of what went down between me and DOE. I don&amp;#39;t regret
sticking to my beliefs in terms of school design but I would like to
have been able to handle the politics of the situation better. Had I
remained involved I think I had more to offer. I don&amp;#39;t regret it too
much – at the time it went from the DOE telling me one week to &amp;#34;you
can have any role in the school you want&amp;#34; to the next week &amp;#34;we want to
introduce you to the person who we&amp;#39;re making principal&amp;#34; and I
recognize that I&amp;#39;d have a hard time putting that aside now and the me
of a decade ago would have found it impossible. That said, I think
everyone would have been better off if both sides could have played
things better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d still love to have the chance someday to set up and run a school
of my design with my team. It&amp;#39;ll probably never happen but it would be
nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you need to know binary for CS?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/why-binary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/why-binary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, Alfred Thompson asked &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alfredtwo/status/1036982959587446784&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Why is it important for CS students
to understand binary?&amp;#34;&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter which led to a number of interesting
responses. Alfred summarized and wrote his own thoughts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/09/why-teach-binary-in-computer-science.html&#34;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to add a comment but I already wrote a post for yesterday so
put it off until today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First let me say that you can have a very successful career in tech
and not really know binary or number bases other than 10. That career
could be as as programmer, software engineer, network specialist,
devops or in many other areas that fall on the CS side of tech.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You also can&amp;#39;t really get through a CS program without learning about
binary. If you&amp;#39;re self taught or go to a code school then that&amp;#39;s
another story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The question is, is it worth the time spent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One can easily argue that systems - that is low level, close to the
metal knowledge is one of the two &amp;#34;latins&amp;#34; of CS, the other being CS
theory. You might not explicitly use either but they give you a
stronger foundation in everything. You also can&amp;#39;t study systems without a
good knowledge of binary so if you want to do anything low level, you
need it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about beyond those easy but not all to convincing to new students
answers?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s loo at a few things we can do with binary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A big part of binary notation is that you can look at data as a string
of bits. You can also manipulate that data using things like &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;xor&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At it&amp;#39;s core &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt; let&amp;#39;s you turn off bits. &lt;code&gt;And&lt;/code&gt; any bit with a 0 and
it will become a 0. &lt;code&gt;And&lt;/code&gt; it with a 1 and it stays the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
\begin{array}{ccccc}
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
and &amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\\hline
&amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
\end{array}
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Or&lt;/code&gt; is used to turn on bits. You &lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt; any bit with a 1 and it gets
turned on. &lt;code&gt;Or&lt;/code&gt; it with a 0 and it stays as it was.
$$
\begin{array}{ccccc}
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
or &amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\\hline
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\
\end{array}
$$
&lt;code&gt;Xor&lt;/code&gt; a bit with a 1 and the bit flips, with a 0 it stays the same.
$$
\begin{array}{ccccc}
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
xor &amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\\hline
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\
\end{array}
$$
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What can we do with this? For one thing, image processing. Students
frequently play with images where each pixel is represented as a 24
bit color. Three bytes, one each for red, green, and blue. Each byte
is really 8 bits. We can use bitwise operations on the binary digits
to turn on or off color.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s say we have this rgb triple: (200, 15, 80) which in hexadecimal
is C8 0F 50 or 10111000 00001111 01010000 in binary. If we want to
turn off the reddest reds we could &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt; the color with 00001111
11111111 11111111 or 0FFFFF:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
$$
\begin{array}{cccc}
&amp;amp; 10111000 &amp;amp; 00001111 &amp;amp; 01010000\\
and &amp;amp; 00001111 &amp;amp; 11111111 &amp;amp; 11111111\\\hline
&amp;amp; 00001000 &amp;amp; 00001111 &amp;amp; 01010000\\
\end{array}
$$
Yes, you could just use the base 10
values and keep on calling color setting and conversion functions but
if you understand binary it&amp;#39;s quicker and easier and what&amp;#39;s going on
will actually make sense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course you probably wouldn&amp;#39;t write out the binary but would rather
use the hex notation which once a student realizes is just 4 bit
groupings of binary becomes really easy. As a bonus, once you&amp;#39;re used
to binary and hex those hexadecimal color values will all of a sudden
make sense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is just the tip of the image processing and graphics iceberg with
respect to binary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Related although I haven&amp;#39;t played with it myself, I&amp;#39;d imagine you could use
these types of bitwise operations on images to play with
steganography.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another use of binary is in cybersecurity. Things like buffer
overflows and blowing the stack all make much more sense if you know
how memory is arranged and that&amp;#39;s easier to understand if you
understand binary, bytes, and word sizes. I do experiments with my
classes when we use C or C++ where they access arrays off the ends and
end up messing with neighboring variables. It seems like magic unless
you know about memory and to know memory you need to know binary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about image file formats? Many image file formats start with a
fixed size header. Here&amp;#39;s the header definition for the GIF file
format:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Offset&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Length&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Contents&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;#34;GIF&amp;#34;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;#34;87a&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;89a&amp;#34;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt;Logical Screen Width&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt;Logical Screen Height&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1  byte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bit0: Global Color Table Flag (GCTF)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;bit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1..3:  Color&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Resolution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;bit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4:  Sort&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Flag to Global Color Table&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;bit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5..7:  Size&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;of Global Color Table:2^(1+n)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1  byte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt;Background Color Index&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1  byte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt;Pixel Aspect Ratio&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;?  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt;Global Color Table(0..255 x 3 bytes)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bytes  &amp;lt;Blocks&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bytes  &amp;lt;Trailer&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(0x3b)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The header info is defined bit by bit so you have to know about binary
and know how to manipulate data on a bit level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those were three biggies but there are other places where knowing
binary makes tons of sense:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
flag type parameters
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
understanding floating point numbers
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
using shifts for quick doubling and halving of data
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does this mean that binary has to be or should be in a first course?
No. Should it be somewhere? Certainly and rather than doing binary
because it&amp;#39;s on the test or because &amp;#34;you should know it&amp;#34; you can pick
and choose your spots and cover it when it will be fun and interesting
for your kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
world
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rite Of Passage Projects</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rite-of-passage-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rite-of-passage-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
JCS&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://irreal.org/blog/?p=7414#comment-4045190612&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on Irreal today brought me back. It was about &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brief_(text_editor)&#34;&gt;Brief&lt;/a&gt; which
was the editing hotness back in the day. I played with it a little
really mostly used Emacs clones for real work when I was stuck on
MS-DOS systems. Usually either &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JOVE&#34;&gt;JOVE&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epsilon_(text_editor)&#34;&gt;Epsilon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the comments Jon reminded me about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MKS_Toolkit&#34;&gt;MKS Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;
which brought most everyday Unix tools to DOS along with a shell and
a version of Vi. I didn&amp;#39;t use Vi much and I only used their shell
until I wrote my own.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about &amp;#34;rite of passage&amp;#34; projects. I was in
college in the mid to late 80s. It was the heyday of the
IBM-PC. Schools still used older time sharing systems like DEC-20s and
Vaxen but the PC was all the rage. The cool thing about them was that
you had full control and access to the machine and it was simple
enough to get your head around pretty much everything about it. The
downside was that MS-DOS was very limited and of course there was
little to no networking going on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, you could dive into the low level machine language
stuff very easily. Get Norton&amp;#39;s book:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://covers.openlibrary.org/b/id/7446489-L.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://covers.openlibrary.org/b/id/7446489-L.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://covers.openlibrary.org/b/id/7446489-L.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; height=&#34;250&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and you&amp;#39;re on your way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand many student&amp;#39;s graduated with no concept of time
sharing and the ramifications of sharing a system or resources were
foreign to many kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though we always look back to the &amp;#34;good old days,&amp;#34; in many ways
things weren&amp;#39;t much different. I got a very strong background in
academic CS from NYU (Courant Institute) but just like today, there
was no real preparation for the real world.If you wanted to really develop your
coding chops you had to work on side projects.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I seem to recall, a typical &amp;#34;rite of passage&amp;#34; side project was writing
your own shell. It didn&amp;#39;t have to be anything as powerful as BASH or
ZSH but it would typically be much more powerful than DOS and much
more Unixy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I recall writing my first shell down in UC-49 of Tisch Hall when the
computer labs weren&amp;#39;t busy. I wrote it in C which was what the cool
kids used back then. Specifically I used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Williams_Company&#34;&gt;Let&amp;#39;s C&lt;/a&gt; compiler from the
Mark Williams company. This was before Turbo C 2.0 so Let&amp;#39;s C was
pretty much the only game in town for a cheap Unix style C compiler
for DOS. There was also Run/C but that was a C interpreter, not a
compiler. I also used that to learn C. Funny story - I certainly
didn&amp;#39;t know this at the time but Run/C was written by Peter
Brooks. Peter and I would later meet when he became my colleague at
Stuyvesant teaching CS and I now have the privilege of being able to
call him friend. I joke that I owe him ~ $100 for the interpreter from
back in the day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since this was on DOS, I couldn&amp;#39;t do real Unix style pipes like
&lt;code&gt;cat file | sort | uniq -c | sort -n&lt;/code&gt; but I did simulate it with redirection and temporary
files. It also supported aliases, simple scripts and I think a few
other things.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was pretty happy with it and used it for a couple of years. It was
also one of the first substantial programs I wrote. I learned a lot
from doing it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another &amp;#34;rite of passage&amp;#34; program that was common back then was a
text based window library. Somethig like ncurses that would allow you
to make text based windows and menus on the text only screen. I also
wrote one of these and actually got to use it for a project when I
started working at Goldman.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I guess the third &amp;#34;rite of passage&amp;#34; project I remember was writing a C
compiler but that was different because it was for a class. It was a
significant project but the class didn&amp;#39;t really help with writing a
large program in general - it was all about the compiler and all the
theory behind it. Great course but not one in software engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays the projects have changed. Text based windowing is long gone
and while I still think writing a shell is a useful and rewarding
exercise it&amp;#39;s not scratching an itch the way it did back when we were
stuck on DOS. I guess writing a full stack web app is probably a
pretty typical one for students these days.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Any others?
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter CS - a lot of progress in a short time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I was back on campus for an early orientation session for
Hunter&amp;#39;s incoming Daedalus CS honors students. It was the first time
all of us got to meet face to face. The students I met with will be
my third cohort. I got to thinking how far we&amp;#39;ve come in under three
years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter&amp;#39;s had a strong but little known undergraduate
CS program for as long as I&amp;#39;ve known. Much like any program, we&amp;#39;ve got
our strengths and weaknesses but you go through our program and
academically you&amp;#39;ll be as well prepared as from anywhere else. We have some
challenges being a commuter school, a liberal arts school and a school
not commonly thought of for CS but the core has always been there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter has been making a concerted effort to up its computer science
game and my joining the team has been part of that. The Daedalus
program is an honors scholarship program. It&amp;#39;s similar to the well
known CUNY Macaulay program but it&amp;#39;s specific to Hunter and specific to
CS. Our kids get scholarships, laptops, special classes (with me),
activities and events and more. Our first cohort had 12. This past
year we had 23 but a funny thing happened right after we started. Hunter&amp;#39;s
Macaulay CS students heard about what was going on and wanted in. The
end result was that last years cohort had a total of 27 students
as we invited the incoming Hunter Macaulay CS students into the
fold. This year, we&amp;#39;re up to about 50 total and it looks to be a very
strong group. To be honest I&amp;#39;m a little
scared of growing this quickly. The kids will be great but it will be
a challenge building the community across multiple classes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m really pleased with the first two cohorts performance both in
class and out. They&amp;#39;re progressing well through the academic program
and are ahead of schedule in terms of internships and outside
activities but I&amp;#39;m even happier that they&amp;#39;ve been working to level up
Hunter CS as a whole. They started a once a week Dojo last year where
all Hunter CS students could hang out and work on tech projects and
have a speaker series on tap for this coming year. For my part, I&amp;#39;ve
got a couple of new ideas up my sleeve but I&amp;#39;m going to keep them
under wraps for now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Three years ago Hunter wasn&amp;#39;t so much on the map for CS inclined high
school students and while there&amp;#39;s much work to be done, many of our
incoming cohort members chose us over other programs that have
traditionally been considered CS strongholds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, our efforts to connect Hunter CS to the NY Tech community have begun to
raise our profile on the other end of the pipeline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s still a long rode ahead but I thought I&amp;#39;d give myself a day to
look back on how far we&amp;#39;ve come in a short time. Having a great public college option for CS
education is critical for NYC. This was one of the things I left Stuy to
accomplish and we&amp;#39;re well on our way.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching recursion early? Make sure to use a good tool.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/recursion-early/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/recursion-early/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I replied this tweet yesterday and thought I&amp;#39;d expound a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;We started kids using scheme on 10th grade at stuy so did recursion early. Not everyone got all of it but it think it made things much easier for those that you more CS later.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/1001508028439519233?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We introduced recursion very early in our intro course at Stuy and I
think it worked well. In that course we started by using Racket (nee
Scheme) as the first programming unit. Originally we
started the kids out first using NetLogo or StarLogo and followed with
Scheme but after a few years we switched the order.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wouldn&amp;#39;t always recommend Scheme for a first course and in fact
frequently don&amp;#39;t but given how the Stuy course was introduced and
developed it made sense and worked.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Was it worth doing things this way? I think so. Prior to that intro
course becoming a requirement I got to see students coming in from
different pathways to APCS. Some came in raw with zero formal
experience, some self taught, some through that intro course and some
having taken another more traditional intro programming course or
experience. The kids who started on Scheme had no more difficulty
mastering loops and iteration but had an easier time getting to the
more advanced recursive techniques. This wasn&amp;#39;t a surprise - it wasn&amp;#39;t
their first rodeo. This also jived with reports I read at the time
that felt that when students did recursion first, iteration was just
as easy but when they did iteration first, recursion was harder.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can of course make a strong case that recursion isn&amp;#39;t necessary
for a kid that isn&amp;#39;t going to study more CS. I&amp;#39;ll merely argue that
what we did at Stuy worked with that population and I wouldn&amp;#39;t change
it. At the same time, I&amp;#39;ve helped a number of teachers design classes and programs
where we agreed that recursion first was not the way to go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, it wasn&amp;#39;t that I specifically wanted to do recursion
early but rather, there were a number of things I wanted to do with
the class for which Scheme made sense and recursion was just one of
them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some reasons to like (or for some, to dislike) Scheme early:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s functional – everything is a function. While this is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
technically not true, we can fudge it a bit at this level. You put
things in parens so instead of add(a,b) you write (add a b) or
really (+ a b). You can also do (+ a b c). Things that would be
statements are also functions: (if Booelean TruePart FalsePart) is the &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt;
statement. For example &lt;code&gt;(if (&amp;gt;= a b) a b)&lt;/code&gt; returns the larger of a
and b.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Because it&amp;#39;s functional it avoids the issue kids have with &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; being
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
for assignment rather than comparison.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It has great support for list processing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Recursion is much more natural.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a super simple language with simple rules and a simple, small  syntax
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, Scheme isn&amp;#39;t perfect and some people dislike the above
reasons. It&amp;#39;s also easy to come up with a number of other good reasons
not to use a language like Scheme.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the recursion front, it makes things much easier. There are no
loops so recursion develops as a natural form for repetition:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-scheme&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;f (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;)
(* x  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; (- x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)))))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This defines a function that takes one parameter and returns
&lt;code&gt;x*(x-1)*(x-2)...&lt;/code&gt;. It repeats, but never ends. This leads to adding
a base case:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-scheme&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;f (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;)
(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(&amp;lt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
(* x (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; (- x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;))))))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Which is your basic factorial function.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since this use of recursion for repetition  develops naturally as we
introduce language concepts it&amp;#39;s easier for kids to get their heads
around it as opposed to when they&amp;#39;ve seen loops already and have an
&amp;#34;easier&amp;#34; alternative. You can make the case that you could introduce
recursion this way in a language with loops like Python but once loops
are available and particularly when loops are idiomatic, students will
find them and getting them to think recursively will be more
difficult.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Scheme and most other functional programming languages also have
strong support for lists and list recursion. This means you don&amp;#39;t have
to limit yourself to mathy problems. Think about a todo list:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go to the market
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Buy a gallon of milk
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If they have eggs, get a dozen (heh heh)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go home
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Processing a todo list is really a recursive problem:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the list is empty you&amp;#39;re done
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take the first item off  the list
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do it
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Recurse
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once you start working with lists, you can play with all sorts of
recursive examples.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the Scheme unit the big project is creating a sentence
generator. The kids don&amp;#39;t know it but they&amp;#39;re learning about grammars
and in fact are writing a recursive descent parser - they just think
they&amp;#39;re writing a program that creates silly sentences. It&amp;#39;s a really
nice project that uses recursion in a way that&amp;#39;s different and I&amp;#39;d
argue more fun and interesting than the usual approaches.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I chose Scheme for a variety of reasons. I also chose NetLogo for
specific reasons. Unlike Scheme (or most other popular learning
languages), NetLogo is really all about agent based parallel
processing. There are concepts that we can explore easily and in depth
with NetLogo that would be tremendously difficult in any other
language and at the same time, there are things that are easy to
explore in other languages that Netlogo doesn&amp;#39;t lend itself to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, in the end, this post really isn&amp;#39;t about when to teach
recursion. It&amp;#39;s more about how languages lend themselves to solving
different problems and teaching different concepts in different
ways. If all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a
nail. Fortunately, we can do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
About a week ago New York State&amp;#39;s new regulation creating a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180327/NEWS/180329893/new-york-will-finally-have-certified-computer-science-teachers&#34;&gt;K12 CS
teacher certification&lt;/a&gt; went live. Just the other day I was honored to be
interviewed by  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mflamm_reporter&#34;&gt;Matt Flamm&lt;/a&gt; of Crain&amp;#39;s New York in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180410/TECHNOLOGY/180419999/asked-answered-teacher-changed-jobs-to-push-for-new-york-states-new&#34;&gt;follow up piece&lt;/a&gt;
about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs
that lead to certification is &lt;strong&gt;HUGE&lt;/strong&gt;. In my view, it&amp;#39;s a game changer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From a course offerings point of view it&amp;#39;s the wild west. I don&amp;#39;t mean
this as a bad thing, it&amp;#39;s just that there&amp;#39;s a huge range of offerings
from AP to home brew, physical computing, game based, cyber security,
you name it, there&amp;#39;s a curriculum. The long and short of this is that
schools need teachers to teach all of these experiences. Without a
strong certification pathway we&amp;#39;re going to be stuck with the current
training based model where teachers are trained to deliver canned
curricula rather than truly teach. With strong teacher preparation
programs teachers will be prepared not only to deliver all the
existing curricula but, arguable more importantly design their own
learning experiences appropriate for the populations they work with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is important and alone would make having CS certification
worthwhile but to me the BIG win is that it creates a viable career
path.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People say we&amp;#39;ll never find enough CS teachers because the tech
industry pays so well. I&amp;#39;ve never believed that. We find math teachers
even though many could flee to finance and chem teachers in spite of
big pharma&amp;#39;s call so why can&amp;#39;t we find CS teachers? Because we&amp;#39;ve
never provided a path into the profession and a viable career track.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Certification means that over time schools will be able to build CS
teachers and the discipline will be treated as the other
subjects. Prior to certification, a CS teacher might be cut if a
school&amp;#39;s math department downsized. With certification, the career
track for a CS teacher is the same as the track for any other teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It also means that young people starting out who are interested in
both teaching and computer science will have a way of getting into the
profession - something that has never before existed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having CS certification alone won&amp;#39;t woo a
plethora of current tech professionals into teaching but over time,
we&amp;#39;ll start to have CS Ed majors or CS majors pursuing CS ED Masters
degrees and entering the profession. This won&amp;#39;t happen in a press or
election cycle but it will happen.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This all hinges on quality prep programs. I think I&amp;#39;ve hit the sweet
spot with what I&amp;#39;ve designed at Hunter. The critical components are of
course content and pedagogy. Teacher candidates must have both
sufficient depth and breadth in the subject and all the pedagogical
content knowledge that comes along with it. I don&amp;#39;t agree with the
common approach of taking a course to teach a course - that is, having
courses like &amp;#34;APCS - Principles for teachers&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;APCS - A for
teachers.&amp;#34;  I want my teachers to be able to teach any reasonable
curriculum or design their own so we&amp;#39;ll be rolling out courses that
examine the commonly offerd curricula but prepare teachers for a whole
lot more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been an exciting week in NY CS Ed and there&amp;#39;s a lot more to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>