<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cs Education on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs-education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cs Education on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 07:48:14 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs-education/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I Speak Jive</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-speak-jive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 07:48:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-speak-jive/</guid>
      <description>When I wrote about the HighWebEd I mentioned John William&#39;&#39;s talk on Agile. He spoke about how the movie Airplane! was filmed in an Agile manner and gave as an example the development of the &#34;jive&#34; scenes.

Apparently the creative team had a script but it wasn&#39;t working. The first pair that read for the role, Norman Gibbs and Al White had their owned take. Not only dir the team cast them on the spot and follow their creative lead (hence Agile) but they also apparently apologized to the two actors as the original attempt was so bad compared t what Gibbs and White brought to the table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classes Or After school programs - which is more important for female retention in CS?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/classes-or-afterschool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 21:47:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/classes-or-afterschool/</guid>
      <description>This morning Mark Guzdial tweeted on his latest post:
Results from Longitudinal Study of Female Persistence in CS: AP CS matters, After-school programs and Internships do not https://t.co/GOzp3045Hp
&amp;mdash; Mark Guzdial (@guzdial) October 14, 2019 
I&#39;m glad Mark wrote about this as it&#39;s something that&#39;s important to both research and publicize but it&#39;s really not a surprise.
I&#39;m going to start by dismissing the statement that &#34;... participation in the Aspirations awards program were teh best predictors of persistence three years after the high school survey in both CS and other technology-related majors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheating on CS projects</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cheating-on-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 17:33:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cheating-on-projects/</guid>
      <description>Alfred Thompson posted today about cheating on CS class projects. It was in response to Garth Flint&#39;s post on finding interesting projects which in turn referenced earlier posts by Alfred and me.
Garth laments that it&#39;s hard to find projects that are both interesting and meaty but where solutions can&#39;t easily be searched for online. Alfred notes that cheating will happen and that it&#39;s an ethics issue. This is why I try to create a culture of sharing and acknowledging credit (that is, citing sources) but I&#39;m not naive enough to believe there isn&#39;t any cheating in my classes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching techniques - industry to classroom and classroom to industry</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/industry-techniques-in-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 12:34:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/industry-techniques-in-class/</guid>
      <description>There are things we do in school and there are things we do in industry and they&#39;re not always the same. In school we might use a learning language or an IDE which gives additional support and at times even take away language features while at work you might you might make heavy use of continuous integration tools.
On the other hand, sometimes we use the same things. Java is used in schools and in industry, StackOverflow consulted in both and many schools use professional IDEs like Eclipse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pig Latin - a beginner lesson with some depth</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/piglatin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 17:11:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/piglatin/</guid>
      <description>I recently did a unit where I had my students convert words into Pig Latin. I like the problem because to start it only requires strings, functions and if statements but there is some depth to the unit.
We start with simplified rules:
 If the word starts with a vowel, add &#34;ay&#34; to the end of the word If it starts with a consonant move the first latter to the end and add &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced CS Early - Are they learning it or just using it?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/are-they-learning-or-jus-using/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 17:41:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/are-they-learning-or-jus-using/</guid>
      <description>I recently took a look at the Cryptopals Crypto Challenges. It&#39;s a series of challenges through which you can learn all about crypto and crypto attacks. They say they&#39;ll eventually have solutions but since the site appears to be at least a few years old, who knows it they&#39;ll ever publish them.
One interesting thing about the site is that it really doesn&#39;t have a lot of content to teach you the concepts around the challenges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outside Evaluators</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/outside-evaluators/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 19:23:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/outside-evaluators/</guid>
      <description>I was planning on writing up all the exciting CS Education work I got to be involved in these past two days but I saw a post on one of the CS discussion forums that got me riled.
There&#39;s a teacher (name withheld to protect the innocent) who wants to create an advanced course for his students but his administration is requesting an outside measure of accountability. This sounds reasonable on the surface but I found it really insulting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Code And Case Studies</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/big-code-and-case-studies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 11:22:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/big-code-and-case-studies/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m enjoying reading about Ria Galanos&#39; new chapter on her blog. In her most recent post Ria briefly talks about the fact that very few professional developers start from scratch and most work in existing large code bases. She wonders why the College Board got rid of the APCS-A case study and talked about how it gave students an opportunity to work on a multi-file complex system. Over the past few years others have wondered if the College Board should bring it back.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 11:23:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019/</guid>
      <description>So, I got back from CSTA2019 and promptly got a summer cold which laid me up for the past couple of days.
Phoenix was beautiful even with it being unbearably hot at times and it&#39;s a place I think I&#39;d like to visit again when it&#39;s a bit cooler.
I said in an earlier post that for me, CSTA is typically more of a person conference and less of a session conference and that held true again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planning For CSTA 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 17:26:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</guid>
      <description>Looking forward to flying out to Phoenix for CSTA-2019 Saturday morning. The conference doesn&#39;t officially start until Sunday, Monday for me since I&#39;m not doing any of the pre-conference workshops. We&#39;ll have most of Saturday as long as we&#39;re up to it, Sunday, and Monday morning. Actually, there is the GitHub reception on Sunday evening so that&#39;s kind of official conference stuff.
As to the conference, I&#39;m super looking forward to it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proof By Authority</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/proof-by-authority/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 07:00:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/proof-by-authority/</guid>
      <description>No,I&#39;m not talking aboutArgument from Authority - something that very much plagues CS Education and education in general where an annointed few who may, or may not really know what they&#39;re talking about are given creedence because they&#39;ve been there the longest, work for the companies with the biggest names, have the economic backing or otherwise have been given the stage.
I&#39;m talking about Proof by Authority which I fondly remember from those silly Proof techniques lists that went around in the day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Year in Review - the classes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/semester-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 09:02:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/semester-review/</guid>
      <description>Now that the semester&#39;s over I&#39;ve had a chance to reflect a bit on my teaching over the past year.
This year I taught two classes each semester so the load was a little higher. First semester was one class of our CS0 and one of the lab/enrichment component that goes with CS1. Nothing big to report there as I&#39;ve done them both before.
The biggest difference was that I had to deal with two separate classes even though they&#39;re one cohort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grokking Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/grokking-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 07:29:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/grokking-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>Someone mentioned Grokking Algorithms by Aditya Y. Bhargava in one of the CS educator Facbeook groups. It looked interesting so I thought I&#39;d give it a once over.
It&#39;s certainly an accessible book. Text mixed with cute line drawings, &#34;hand written&#34; text, diagrams and picture.s It reminded me of one of my favorite, most accessible Calculus books Who Was Fourier.
Overall I enjoyed the book but I&#39;m not sure what its best audience is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do It First</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/do-it-first/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 08:00:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/do-it-first/</guid>
      <description>Reading Garth Flint&#39;s end of year post and Alfred Thompson&#39;s follow up had me thinking about a couple of things.
One was spurred when Garth wrote &#34;They also have to figure out the math before they code.&#34; This made me think about all the details we sometimes take for for granted. Things that are hard for our students that we just know. It&#39;s frequently math that we might find trivial but it could also be much simpler things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AP Classes, Placing Students, and First Topic Exposures</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/placing-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 13:27:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/placing-students/</guid>
      <description>Just like last year, I&#39;m taking in two classes worth of students in to my honors program. The challenge is that I can only teach two classes and I&#39;ve got to figure out what to teach and then which students belong in which class.
It basically comes down to one of two courses, our CS0 (CSCI127) and our CS1 (CSCI135).
CSCI127 is a first programming experience. The normal class is taught as a large lecture with small recitation/labs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog For Self Professional Devleopment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/blog-for-pd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 07:12:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/blog-for-pd/</guid>
      <description>Lat day of the 2019 NCWIT Summmit. Got up crazy early, got back from my run and saw this when I checked Twitter:
A1: CSTA, Twitter chats like this one, @guzdial and @alfredtwo&amp;#39;s blogs among others. In all cases because those places start from assuming I&amp;#39;m a CS teacher, rather than starting from assuming I&amp;#39;m a teacher who is better at teaching something else. #csk8 https://t.co/6DO77fzq0j
&amp;mdash; Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) May 16, 2019</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hunter Daedalus Fall 2019 recruiting class</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 08:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</guid>
      <description>Now that high school seniors have all committed to their respective colleges I though I&#39;d share some information on Hunter&#39;s incoming Daedalus (honors CS) cohort.
I joke about the first cohort saying that nobody applied to the program. That&#39;s kind of true. I jointed Hunter a little over three years ago in late January. That was after high school seniors had already applied to college and at that time the program didn&#39;t exist.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Community Curated List of CS Education Resources</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs/</guid>
      <description>One of the things I mentioned in my post on the CS Educators StackExchange was the fragmentation of resources for CS Educators. My friend and fellow CS teacher Ben pointed out that this is appropriate as we&#39;re so young as a community. He&#39;s absolutely right but until we mature, discover-ability can be a problem. We all have our resources and I for one am frequently surprised when talking to a friend and discovering that they don&#39;t know about a site or a mailing list that I&#39;ve known about for years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Educators StackExchange</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/</guid>
      <description>The CS Educators StackExchange is now in public beta. For those of you who are not in tech, StackExchange is a network of question answering sites. StackOverflow is probably the most famous - many peoples go to site for computer science and programming questions and answers.
During this period of public beta the site will be working on defining itself and also on developing a critical mass of users. I hope the site succeeds and I encourage everyone to check it out, ask questions, answer some and let&#39;s all see where this goes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>