<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ethics on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ethics/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (ethics)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 07:15:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ethics/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Seats on a plane - addendum</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 07:15:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
While my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; was well received, I did have a few conversations
where people asked why I did this with such a seemingly minor ethical
issue. They wondered that with issues the Facebook algorithm, bail and
sentencing algorithms, gerrymandering and other issues dominating the
ethical conversation, why focus this topic around something that seems
to affect far fewer people and might not even be such a big
deal. After all, when it does come up, flight crews can probably ask a
few people to shuffle seats and voila, problem solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The thing is, this was intentional and it was intentional on two
fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, who decides if an issue is major or minor? Our perceptions
change throughout our lives and through our experiences. Something
that might appear to be minor to us or minor right now could be major
to someone else. I remember my first week teaching at Seward Park HS
right after I left industry. Such an eye opener. Even though I went to
public schools and faced my share of challenges, I had no idea how
different my students lives were from mine. Things that might have
been a minor inconvenience to me were a brick wall to them. It&amp;#39;s also
not enough to just view &amp;#34;slam dunk&amp;#34; issues through an ethical lens. We
have to indeed walk the walk. I wanted a mundane problem that may have
resulted from Innocent intent to illustrate that it&amp;#39;s not about
teaching a lesson on the topic du jour but rather it&amp;#39;s about
everything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also wanted to pick a topic that wasn&amp;#39;t right out there in the
mainstream. If I had them work on a recommendation system or some
other issue that&amp;#39;s been all over the news these days, they would have
all guessed the punchline. I thought this would be low key enough so
that they&amp;#39;d discover the ethical issue by inadvertently creating it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other reason was that I wanted to keep the issue simple and
understandable. I already suspected that the code aspect would be a
challenge for some members of the class. I didn&amp;#39;t want a super deep
ethical issue to cloud that side of the equation. A simple problem
kept everything clean. They first seated the customers, realized that
kids could be separated from parents, decided that this should be
addressed, then tried to address it. Keeping problem simple is a tried
and true teaching strategy. There&amp;#39;s so much complexity in most ethical
issues and most programming problems and students can only cope with
so much at a time. This was an attempt to keep the load to a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said in the earlier post. I think the lesson needs tweaking -
particularly in order to make the coding level appropriate but I also
think it&amp;#39;s a lesson worth keeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past week, the class has been working with regular expressions. I
get to deliver the punchline to that one tomorrow evening.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Airline Seats - An Ethics Lesson</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 14:43:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/airline-seats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve held off on sharing any details on my Ethics in CS class because
I wanted to wait until some of it ran. I didn&amp;#39;t want to talk about a
topic and then find out that after we covered it I was all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that we&amp;#39;re well into the semester, I think it&amp;#39;s time to share a
few things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my premises when I designed the course was that most ethics
courses are taken by either people who already have religion or people
who see it as the &amp;#34;easy course&amp;#34; without programming. The few courses I
saw out there were largely based on case studies and
discussion. Nothing wrong with that - we&amp;#39;ve got that as well but I
wanted to try something a little different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to have the class play with some technical situation,
preferably with code, and then hopefully discover an ethical issue
after which we can discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here was my first attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the lesson has great potential but I also know it
needs tweaks. Most notably with teh level of comfort some of the
class had with Python. Next time around I want to address that issue
but I&amp;#39;ll talk about the specifics in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started by giving the class some code that provided a barebones
airline seating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s an empty plane. I just made windows and interior seats figuring
that windows were more desirable and didn&amp;#39;t have to differentiate them
from aisles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
  win          avail          avail          avail            win
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The code I provided also allowed for the purchase of an &amp;#34;economy plus&amp;#34;
ticket. An economy plus passenger could select their seat on
purchase. I had a function that with a 70% probability tried to select
a window seat and then it would just select a random seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You could also select a regular economy seat. For those, the airline
would assign a seat at some later point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s a plane where the economy plus seats have been sold and the
remaining seats are sold to economy but unassigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
ep-4          avail          avail          ep-2           ep-5
ep-8          avail          ep-19          avail          ep-11
ep-3          avail          avail          avail          ep-6
ep-1          avail          avail          avail          ep-9
ep-14         avail          avail          avail          ep-16
ep-15         avail          ep-20          avail          ep-18
ep-10         avail          ep-17          ep-24          ep-21
ep-13         ep-22          avail          avail          win
ep-23         avail          avail          avail          win
ep-7          avail          avail          avail          ep-12
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I asked the class to finish the routine that assigned the regular
economy seats. I also wrote a version that just assigned them
randomly. Here&amp;#39;s a sample result. Note that u-# represents a block of
purchased seats so you&amp;#39;ll notice u-1 appears multiple times
below. That passenger purchased multiple seats but they were assigned
all over the plane at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;

ep-13         u-6           u-1       ep-16      ep-24
ep-8          ep-15         u-9       u-3        ep-11
ep-22         ep-12         u-2       u-4        u-10
ep-9          ep-5          u-1       u-5        ep-25
ep-2          ep-21         ep-3      u-7        ep-17
ep-1          ep-23         u-8       u-8        ep-6
ep-14         u-12          ep-4      u-4        ep-26
ep-10         u-1           u-11      avail      ep-18
ep-20         u-6           u-11      u-9        u-2
ep-7          u-13          u-2       u-8        ep-19
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class was quick to notice that this could lead to families being
split apart and small children being seated away from parents. They
also noticed that this would affect poorer passengers more frequently
and to a greater extent than richer ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Great. Part 1 mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, the question became, should we do something about it and if so what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class noted that this was an unintended consequence of being
motivated purely by profit and airline convenience and that airlines
should do better. We also  noted that it&amp;#39;s not always so simple,
particularly if an airline is running on thin margins. Finally, we
discussed that this situation was real and in fact did result in
changes in regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following week, we discussed possible alternatives. How they might
work better and how they might affect an airlines bottom lines and if
that should really matter. We also discussed how similar ethical
scenarios might play out in other industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final piece, students had a long term assignment to code up an
updated algorithm that did better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the long and short of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d like to think that by playing with the code, discovering the
dilemma and then trying to fix it led to a deeper appreciation of the
ethical issue and to be honest, the one big thing I want my teachers
to walk away with is more awareness of potential issues and that many
of them are not as obvious or simple as &amp;#34;stop doing that&amp;#34; even though
we&amp;#39;d like them to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, I&amp;#39;ve got to work on some things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost my teachers came in with varying programming
backgrounds. They all completed a data structures in Java course over
the summer but a good number were not that comfortable with Python. I
covered Python over the first couple of weeks but I think I have to be
more structured with that in the future. More specific assignments
rather than giving them as much freedom as I did. I also think I&amp;#39;d
move this unit down in the syllabus - later after some smaller
programming assignments and then finally, I&amp;#39;d scaffold it
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even so, I think it was worthwhile and a keeper. I think it could also
be a nice ethics assignment in any programming class that covers 2D
arrays or something similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a couple of other units that follow this do it and discover
theme. Once those happen I&amp;#39;ll report back on them as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feeling like an English teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 14:40:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So I&amp;#39;m teaching my Ethics and CS class for the first time. I
originally designed the course but didn&amp;#39;t teach it the first time
around. That honor went to my friend, Master Teacher Topher
Mykolyk. He of course did an amazing job - impossible to
follow. Fortunately, this is a different cohort so they don&amp;#39;t know how
great Topher was for the course :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though I have the syllabus and Topher&amp;#39;s notes from last time
around, first time through is very week to week but I think I&amp;#39;m
starting to get my legs under me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This course is very different from what I&amp;#39;ve taught in the past. It&amp;#39;s
also  different from the ethics courses I&amp;#39;ve seen currently out
there. Specifically, I wanted a programming component in the
course. Still, there&amp;#39;s a lot more open ended discussion and opinion
based stuff going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mean, when you do a class on an algorithm like mergesort or a
construct like a loop, it is what it is. You can motivate it in
different ways and engage the class but there&amp;#39;s only one punch line
and it&amp;#39;s set in advance. Here things are a lot looser. Most issues
have two sides and even when most of the class is on one like when we
talked about predictive policing, we can still
effectively play devil&amp;#39;s advocate for the other side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It can also lead to the class going sideways. Yesterday we were
talking about basic web privacy. Tracking, cookies and the like. In my
mind I had the lesson mapped out. First, our &amp;#34;weekly ethicacy&amp;#34; student
presentation and then a short breakout, discussion on the info we
share, and then curated questions and resources  that we&amp;#39;d use in a
sequence of breakout room and whole class discussions. The trouble is,
after the first short breakout, the student conversation went directly
to what I had intended for our async work over the course of the
week. Oh well, time to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/&#34;&gt;call an audible&lt;/a&gt;. It wasn&amp;#39;t really a big deal,
the conversation moved in a different direction but it was still very
much in the wheelhouse of the day&amp;#39;s topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Must be what an English class can be like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the course is doing well but I won&amp;#39;t know for sure
until afterwards when I can debrief with the students. After all,
they&amp;#39;re the ones that ultimately determine if the class is successful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the next few weeks I&amp;#39;ll share some specifics about the class. The
programming stuff in particular. Can&amp;#39;t do that now because we&amp;#39;re in
the middle and I don&amp;#39;t want any members of the class who might be
reading this to see the reveal before it&amp;#39;s time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time To Create An Ethics Course</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/time-to-create-an-ethics-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/time-to-create-an-ethics-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I think it&amp;#39;s time for me to start developing a CS Ethics class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An ethics course isn&amp;#39;t a replacement for having teachers that live and
model good behavior and weave ethical issues throughout the curriculum
but still, adding a separate course on top of that has its merits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not in a rush to create this course. I might be done in a month or
it might take a couple of years. When I&amp;#39;m done, I&amp;#39;ll add it as an
option in my CS Teacher education programs but hopefully it will be an
attractive course for undergrad CS majors as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While it&amp;#39;s easy enough to come up with possible topics - privacy,
moral responsibilities, biased algorithms, net neutrality and on and
on I&amp;#39;m looking for this course to have a serious coding component. I
want the students to build things to really understand the
implications of what they&amp;#39;re studying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One topic I definitely want to cover is &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2011/10/youre-not-so-anonymous/&#34;&gt;anonimity&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;d love to find
the right combination of data sets and have the class discover that
some hidden information in the sets isn&amp;#39;t nearly as hidden as it seems
to be. When I was at Stuy, I was thinking about
having the kids give me permission to use their class schedules since
even with names removed we could probably identify many kids by
electives and overlapping classes. I have no idea what I&amp;#39;ll be able to
do at Hunter. If I can come up with something good I think this will
form the basis of a pretty amazing part of the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another project I&amp;#39;d love to put together is something dealing with a
biased algorithm. Again, I don&amp;#39;t know where this will go, maybe
something where I can seed the class so that different groups
implement some project differently and we can then analyze each groups
biases, hidden or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Beyond these two, I&amp;#39;m not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about you? Anyone out there have any good ideas for programming
projects for an ethical CS course? If so, please share. It might be a
while but when I do finish putting this together I&amp;#39;ll be sure to
publish whatever the end result is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>