<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ethics on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ethics/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (ethics)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 14:40:35 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ethics/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Feeling like an English teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 14:40:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/english-teacher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So I&amp;#39;m teaching my Ethics and CS class for the first time. I
originally designed the course but didn&amp;#39;t teach it the first time
around. That honor went to my friend, Master Teacher Topher
Mykolyk. He of course did an amazing job - impossible to
follow. Fortunately, this is a different cohort so they don&amp;#39;t know how
great Topher was for the course :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though I have the syllabus and Topher&amp;#39;s notes from last time
around, first time through is very week to week but I think I&amp;#39;m
starting to get my legs under me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This course is very different from what I&amp;#39;ve taught in the past. It&amp;#39;s
also  different from the ethics courses I&amp;#39;ve seen currently out
there. Specifically, I wanted a programming component in the
course. Still, there&amp;#39;s a lot more open ended discussion and opinion
based stuff going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mean, when you do a class on an algorithm like mergesort or a
construct like a loop, it is what it is. You can motivate it in
different ways and engage the class but there&amp;#39;s only one punch line
and it&amp;#39;s set in advance. Here things are a lot looser. Most issues
have two sides and even when most of the class is on one like when we
talked about predictive policing, we can still
effectively play devil&amp;#39;s advocate for the other side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It can also lead to the class going sideways. Yesterday we were
talking about basic web privacy. Tracking, cookies and the like. In my
mind I had the lesson mapped out. First, our &amp;#34;weekly ethicacy&amp;#34; student
presentation and then a short breakout, discussion on the info we
share, and then curated questions and resources  that we&amp;#39;d use in a
sequence of breakout room and whole class discussions. The trouble is,
after the first short breakout, the student conversation went directly
to what I had intended for our async work over the course of the
week. Oh well, time to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/&#34;&gt;call an audible&lt;/a&gt;. It wasn&amp;#39;t really a big deal,
the conversation moved in a different direction but it was still very
much in the wheelhouse of the day&amp;#39;s topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Must be what an English class can be like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the course is doing well but I won&amp;#39;t know for sure
until afterwards when I can debrief with the students. After all,
they&amp;#39;re the ones that ultimately determine if the class is successful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the next few weeks I&amp;#39;ll share some specifics about the class. The
programming stuff in particular. Can&amp;#39;t do that now because we&amp;#39;re in
the middle and I don&amp;#39;t want any members of the class who might be
reading this to see the reveal before it&amp;#39;s time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time To Create An Ethics Course</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/time-to-create-an-ethics-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/time-to-create-an-ethics-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I think it&amp;#39;s time for me to start developing a CS Ethics class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An ethics course isn&amp;#39;t a replacement for having teachers that live and
model good behavior and weave ethical issues throughout the curriculum
but still, adding a separate course on top of that has its merits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not in a rush to create this course. I might be done in a month or
it might take a couple of years. When I&amp;#39;m done, I&amp;#39;ll add it as an
option in my CS Teacher education programs but hopefully it will be an
attractive course for undergrad CS majors as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While it&amp;#39;s easy enough to come up with possible topics - privacy,
moral responsibilities, biased algorithms, net neutrality and on and
on I&amp;#39;m looking for this course to have a serious coding component. I
want the students to build things to really understand the
implications of what they&amp;#39;re studying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One topic I definitely want to cover is &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2011/10/youre-not-so-anonymous/&#34;&gt;anonimity&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;d love to find
the right combination of data sets and have the class discover that
some hidden information in the sets isn&amp;#39;t nearly as hidden as it seems
to be. When I was at Stuy, I was thinking about
having the kids give me permission to use their class schedules since
even with names removed we could probably identify many kids by
electives and overlapping classes. I have no idea what I&amp;#39;ll be able to
do at Hunter. If I can come up with something good I think this will
form the basis of a pretty amazing part of the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another project I&amp;#39;d love to put together is something dealing with a
biased algorithm. Again, I don&amp;#39;t know where this will go, maybe
something where I can seed the class so that different groups
implement some project differently and we can then analyze each groups
biases, hidden or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Beyond these two, I&amp;#39;m not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about you? Anyone out there have any good ideas for programming
projects for an ethical CS course? If so, please share. It might be a
while but when I do finish putting this together I&amp;#39;ll be sure to
publish whatever the end result is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>