<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>csta on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in csta on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 11:46:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csta/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA Awards 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-awards-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 11:46:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-awards-2020/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m guessing that pretty much everyone who stops by this blog knows about the CSTA (Computer Science Teacher&amp;#39;s Association) and most of you probably know about some awards they, well, award. Just in case, I thought I&amp;#39;d share.  Here are three awards, two of which are open for nominations / applications now. If you know someone deserving, nominate them. I&amp;#39;m guessing students don&amp;#39;t really know about the Cutler-Bell award so if you have any deserving students, please share the info with them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 11:23:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019/</guid>
      <description>So, I got back from CSTA2019 and promptly got a summer cold which laid me up for the past couple of days.  Phoenix was beautiful even with it being unbearably hot at times and it&amp;#39;s a place I think I&amp;#39;d like to visit again when it&amp;#39;s a bit cooler.  I said in an earlier post that for me, CSTA is typically more of a person conference and less of a session conference and that held true again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019 Preconference</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-preconference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2019 10:41:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-preconference/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s Monday morning, 7:45AM local time. Being on East Coast time, Devorah and I have already been up for about 3 hours, hit the gym and our first cups of our chosen caffeinated beverages.  Since it&amp;#39;s not unbearably hot outside - a cool and dry 80 in the shade - we&amp;#39;re sitting outside. Devorah&amp;#39;s knitting another square for Blanket Statement so I figured I&amp;#39;d write a few words about what we&amp;#39;ve been doing here in Phoenix leading up to our starting with our conference later today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planning For CSTA 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 17:26:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</guid>
      <description>Looking forward to flying out to Phoenix for CSTA-2019 Saturday morning. The conference doesn&amp;#39;t officially start until Sunday, Monday for me since I&amp;#39;m not doing any of the pre-conference workshops. We&amp;#39;ll have most of Saturday as long as we&amp;#39;re up to it, Sunday, and Monday morning. Actually, there is the GitHub reception on Sunday evening so that&amp;#39;s kind of official conference stuff.  As to the conference, I&amp;#39;m super looking forward to it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crochet at CSTA</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/crochet-at-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 05:03:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/crochet-at-csta/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;  Ok, probably more knitting but Crochet at CSTA was the line used in the newsletter and it sounds better.  As some of you know, my wife Devorah is all about the fiber arts. Knitting, spinning, dying, weaving, the works. We&amp;#39;ve got a loom, two spinning wheels, two bobbin lace pillows, and bins and bins of deconstructed sheep, llamas, alpacas, and angora bunnies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019 - Using GitHub as a CMS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 12:09:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</guid>
      <description>With ISTE ending, the next big event for CS treachers is the annual CSTA Conference. I first attended two years ago in Baltimore. Last year the conference, in Omaha was bigger and better in every way imaginable. I expect this year to be the best yet.  I don&amp;#39;t go to a lot of conferences so I don&amp;#39;t have much to compare CSTA with but I like the fact that it&amp;#39;s is about half the size of SIGCSE.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>