<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pedagogy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/pedagogy/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (pedagogy)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/pedagogy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Faces of Project Based Learning</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/two-faces-of-pbl/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/two-faces-of-pbl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
If one looks at my twitter feed they&amp;#39;ll notice that in addition to CS
Ed, another issue I&amp;#39;m passionate about is school reform or rather
resistance to what is popularly known as and mislabeled as school reform. I&amp;#39;m anti
vouchers, charter schools, high stakes testing and more. One of the
heroes of this resistance is education historian Diane Ravitch. I&amp;#39;m a
big fan of Diane&amp;#39;s and she&amp;#39;s one of the true great champions of public
schools, kids, and teachers. She blogged today about how a superintendent on Long Island &lt;a href=&#34;https://dianeravitch.net/2018/07/27/new-york-district-on-long-island-shows-that-problem-based-curriculum-produces-better-results-than-test-prep/&#34;&gt;replaced test
prep with project based learning&lt;/a&gt;. The post which talks about how this
superintendent improved test results  is worth a read. My only
quibble was that we shouldn&amp;#39;t read anything into the results for a
variety of reasons including the fact that the group of students who
did the project based learning (PBL) units instead of test prep were
self selecting volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the comments caught my eye:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PBL is just another “student-centered” fad…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
PBL operates on the myth of “transference” perpetuated by non-educators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The comment continues on with a number of good points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I writing about it here? Because PBL is a big CS Ed buzzword
and like most buzzwords there&amp;#39;s both truth at the root of the hype and
hype that distorts the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When done right with the right group of kids, project based learning
can be wonderful but it takes a lot of time and effort. You can&amp;#39;t just
set the kids loose to learn. You&amp;#39;ve got to train them to work
together, set up the project, as the teacher, you&amp;#39;ve got to know the
subject so as to know when to guide, when to tell, when to prod, and when to leave
them alone. Doing it right, at least for most students, is certainly
not giving them the instruction sheet and going off the check your
email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, it&amp;#39;s easy to do it wrong. If you&amp;#39;ve got high
performing kids, they&amp;#39;ll figure things out. If you&amp;#39;ve got a few high
performing kids, they can mask the fact that the majority of a group
isn&amp;#39;t getting things. You might have an assignment where a kid figures
out a formula from discovered data and might be able to then use it to
make predictions but there&amp;#39;s a good chance they won&amp;#39;t understand why
it works or it&amp;#39;s root derivation. That&amp;#39;s where we need the teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the dangers of bad PBL is that it&amp;#39;s sexy. Kids are engaged and
it appears to work - particularly when the teacher doesn&amp;#39;t know the
subject area. This is my great fear whenever I hear things about
teachers being &amp;#34;Lead Learners.&amp;#34; Sure, when you&amp;#39;re a converted
something else teacher moving into CS you won&amp;#39;t know the subject
matter but that has to change over time. I&amp;#39;ve seen enough instances of
cases where teachers never develop their chops and just throw projects
at the kids augmented by scripted curricula or computer driver
content. The kids get through the class or program but are not
prepared for the next class or next level. I&amp;#39;ve seen this with the old
Cisco curriculum, any number of after school and summer programs -
some VERY highly regarded ones and I think we&amp;#39;ll see more and more of
this in states that are pushing CSforAll without developing the
necessary pre and in service programs for their teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t let my last two paragraphs leave you feeling that I&amp;#39;m anti
PBL. I&amp;#39;m not. It&amp;#39;s great when done right and if you have thee time and
resources in your school and classes you should be using it when
appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want some pointers on how to get going in the right direction with PBL in CS  check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Computer-Science-K-12-Imagining-possibilities-ebook/dp/B07DYDXBSH/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1532808363&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=doug+bergman&#34;&gt;this
book&lt;/a&gt; by my buddy Doug Bergman. It&amp;#39;s a great getting started guide by a
great teacher. He&amp;#39;s basically Mr. PBL and he does it right.  If you&amp;#39;re new to CS you&amp;#39;ll still need to learn content
and if you&amp;#39;re new to teaching, you&amp;#39;ll be developing your chops for
your entire career but it&amp;#39;s a great resource to get you and then your
kids started on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD for people who know CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw a couple of tweets from Sarah Judd this morning:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-conversation=&#34;none&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;A lot of CS Ed PD assumes you are new to CS. I really want CS Ed PD for people like us that came from a CS background and want to understand the pedagogy for CS in particular better. Do you know of some?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd/status/1011785286693552139?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-conversation=&#34;none&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Yes! I love SIGCSE and CSTA. I just feel like... Math teachers don&amp;#39;t get PD that starts with &amp;quot;and this is how you add and subtract!&amp;quot; and I&amp;#39;d love more CS PD that assumes the content is there, and can focus on the pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd/status/1011966102795059200?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It wasn&amp;#39;t the first time I&amp;#39;ve heard this refrain. Last year I attended
my first CSTA conference. I had numerous conversations with CS
teachers on the fact that everything was on an intro level in terms of
both content and teaching. Further conversations with local teachers
with stronger CS backgrounds led me to run a professional development
session at Hunter this past election day for more experienced CS
teachers at schools that offered more than the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While it&amp;#39;s not surprising that most of the PD opportunities for CS teachers are
rather rudimentary given that nationally most programs are new and
most teachers are new to the subject but there are a few deeper
reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, there are big players in the CS Ed movement that are pushing
curricula and specific programs and that leads to scripted PD for
their products and not depth of knowledge nor deep pedagogical content
knowledge let alone basic pedagogy. Add to this the fact that many of
the &amp;#34;thought leaders&amp;#34; in the space don&amp;#39;t have experience teaching CS
at the K12 level and in many cases don&amp;#39;t have a background either in
teaching nor tech and you can see where the problem comes from. On top
of this we have the erosion of respect for teaching as a profession
where reformers are trying to take the teacher out of teaching and are
trying to reduce pedagogy to following scripts. This problem goes well
beyond CS Ed but as the new kid on the block it probably hits us
hardest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any case, preparing beginners is both necessary and appropriate for
the time being but we can and must do a better job than what&amp;#39;s
currently &amp;#34;state of the art.&amp;#34; At the same time we have to do something
with the CS teachers who indeed do have strong content knowledge but
don&amp;#39;t feel comfortable with imparting that knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what should we do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For new teachers the solution will ultimately have to come
from pre-service programs but what we end up getting is going to
largely be dictated on what&amp;#39;s required by individual states. If states
merely require passing an exam like the Praxis CS exam which, from
what I can gather isn&amp;#39;t a horrible content exam then we&amp;#39;re going to
see CS teachers bumble through their early to mid careers while trying
to figure out how to teach CS much like I did way back when. If they
end up endorsing pre-service programs that are focused on specific
curricula - APCS-A for teachers, APCS-P for teachers, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/math-for-math-teachers/&#34;&gt;Math for Math
teachers&lt;/a&gt; if you will but for CS, we&amp;#39;re also not going to get strong
well prepared pedagogues. On the other hand if you can design a
program that has a strong pedagogical component to go along with the
content, you have a chance. Even with a well designed program
implementation will still be a challenge. Who will teach it? Education
professors who don&amp;#39;t have CS backgrounds? CS professors with little
pedagogical training? Neither of those groups necessarily have any
real experience as actual K12 teachers. If you can find honest to
goodness experienced, strong K12 CS teachers to teach your pedagogy
courses that&amp;#39;s a big win but that&amp;#39;s going to be hard in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think we designed a great program at Hunter and have a practical and
strong implementation plan. If you&amp;#39;re going to be
at CSTA2018 you can hear all about it and why we designed it as we did
in the talk I&amp;#39;m giving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the more experienced I don&amp;#39;t have a universal answer but I can say
what I&amp;#39;m planning. Teachers in NY have to complete 100 CTLE hours
every five years. For beginners, there are plenty of options, at least
content wise. For teachers who know CS, not so much. I was at a meetup
talking to a few friends a couple of weeks ago and one mentioned that
they get most of their hours in Math for America CS
workshops. Unfortunately more than a few of my CS teacher friends who
are in MFA tell me that the CS content in these workshops, while they
do satisfy the hours, are somewhat lacking on the CS / CS pedagogy
side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;m planning - we (Hunter) will host a once a month
dinner/session for CS teachers who are a little farther along CS
wise. I haven&amp;#39;t worked out all the details yet but I&amp;#39;ve got a few tech
companies that are already interested in sponsoring and helping out
should we need anything and we&amp;#39;ll probably set most of our agenda for
the year at the first session where I&amp;#39;ll make my best guess at a
useful agenda. This is something I&amp;#39;m pretty excited about. It should
help create a network of more experienced CS teachers which will both
help bolster that segment of the community and provide a long term
resource to newcomers and it should be a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In some ways, this is why I ended up joining Hunter. Regardless of
what the city and state do, we&amp;#39;re going to prepare the teachers and if
you have a well prepared teacher, you&amp;#39;ve got a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching recursion early? Make sure to use a good tool.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/recursion-early/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/recursion-early/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I replied this tweet yesterday and thought I&amp;#39;d expound a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;We started kids using scheme on 10th grade at stuy so did recursion early. Not everyone got all of it but it think it made things much easier for those that you more CS later.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/1001508028439519233?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We introduced recursion very early in our intro course at Stuy and I
think it worked well. In that course we started by using Racket (nee
Scheme) as the first programming unit. Originally we
started the kids out first using NetLogo or StarLogo and followed with
Scheme but after a few years we switched the order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wouldn&amp;#39;t always recommend Scheme for a first course and in fact
frequently don&amp;#39;t but given how the Stuy course was introduced and
developed it made sense and worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Was it worth doing things this way? I think so. Prior to that intro
course becoming a requirement I got to see students coming in from
different pathways to APCS. Some came in raw with zero formal
experience, some self taught, some through that intro course and some
having taken another more traditional intro programming course or
experience. The kids who started on Scheme had no more difficulty
mastering loops and iteration but had an easier time getting to the
more advanced recursive techniques. This wasn&amp;#39;t a surprise - it wasn&amp;#39;t
their first rodeo. This also jived with reports I read at the time
that felt that when students did recursion first, iteration was just
as easy but when they did iteration first, recursion was harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can of course make a strong case that recursion isn&amp;#39;t necessary
for a kid that isn&amp;#39;t going to study more CS. I&amp;#39;ll merely argue that
what we did at Stuy worked with that population and I wouldn&amp;#39;t change
it. At the same time, I&amp;#39;ve helped a number of teachers design classes and programs
where we agreed that recursion first was not the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, it wasn&amp;#39;t that I specifically wanted to do recursion
early but rather, there were a number of things I wanted to do with
the class for which Scheme made sense and recursion was just one of
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some reasons to like (or for some, to dislike) Scheme early:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s functional – everything is a function. While this is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;technically not true, we can fudge it a bit at this level. You put
things in parens so instead of add(a,b) you write (add a b) or
really (+ a b). You can also do (+ a b c). Things that would be
statements are also functions: (if Booelean TruePart FalsePart) is the &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt;
statement. For example &lt;code&gt;(if (&amp;gt;= a b) a b)&lt;/code&gt; returns the larger of a
and b.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because it&amp;#39;s functional it avoids the issue kids have with &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; being&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for assignment rather than comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has great support for list processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recursion is much more natural.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s a super simple language with simple rules and a simple, small  syntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Scheme isn&amp;#39;t perfect and some people dislike the above
reasons. It&amp;#39;s also easy to come up with a number of other good reasons
not to use a language like Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the recursion front, it makes things much easier. There are no
loops so recursion develops as a natural form for repetition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-scheme&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;f (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(* x  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; (- x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This defines a function that takes one parameter and returns
&lt;code&gt;x*(x-1)*(x-2)...&lt;/code&gt;. It repeats, but never ends. This leads to adding
a base case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-scheme&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;f (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(&amp;lt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(* x (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; (- x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;))))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Which is your basic factorial function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since this use of recursion for repetition  develops naturally as we
introduce language concepts it&amp;#39;s easier for kids to get their heads
around it as opposed to when they&amp;#39;ve seen loops already and have an
&amp;#34;easier&amp;#34; alternative. You can make the case that you could introduce
recursion this way in a language with loops like Python but once loops
are available and particularly when loops are idiomatic, students will
find them and getting them to think recursively will be more
difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Scheme and most other functional programming languages also have
strong support for lists and list recursion. This means you don&amp;#39;t have
to limit yourself to mathy problems. Think about a todo list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy a gallon of milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they have eggs, get a dozen (heh heh)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Processing a todo list is really a recursive problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the list is empty you&amp;#39;re done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the first item off  the list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recurse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you start working with lists, you can play with all sorts of
recursive examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the Scheme unit the big project is creating a sentence
generator. The kids don&amp;#39;t know it but they&amp;#39;re learning about grammars
and in fact are writing a recursive descent parser - they just think
they&amp;#39;re writing a program that creates silly sentences. It&amp;#39;s a really
nice project that uses recursion in a way that&amp;#39;s different and I&amp;#39;d
argue more fun and interesting than the usual approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I chose Scheme for a variety of reasons. I also chose NetLogo for
specific reasons. Unlike Scheme (or most other popular learning
languages), NetLogo is really all about agent based parallel
processing. There are concepts that we can explore easily and in depth
with NetLogo that would be tremendously difficult in any other
language and at the same time, there are things that are easy to
explore in other languages that Netlogo doesn&amp;#39;t lend itself to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, in the end, this post really isn&amp;#39;t about when to teach
recursion. It&amp;#39;s more about how languages lend themselves to solving
different problems and teaching different concepts in different
ways. If all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a
nail. Fortunately, we can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do It The Dumb Way</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/do-it-the-dumb-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/do-it-the-dumb-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s so much to like in the shape drawing lessons I talked about
in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/&#34;&gt;refactoring&lt;/a&gt; post that I thought I&amp;#39;d share a little more here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It can be argued that the most important things for a program to do is work. The
most clever, elegant, creative program is worthless if it doesn&amp;#39;t
produce the desired result. All too often, beginners and hot shot beginners in particular try to
be too clever too early and get themselves into trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When doing the shape drawing lessons the first couple of shape are
pretty easy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;

| ****            |    | *               |
| ****            |    | **              |
| ****            |    | ***             |
| ****            |    | ****            |
| ****            |    |                 |
|                 |    |                 |
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but things get more interesting with the right justified triangle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
----*       *
---**      **
--***     ***
-****    ****
*****   *****
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For this triangle, students want to come up with the formula for the
number of spaces. They usually figure out something like this with
&lt;code&gt;h-i-1&lt;/code&gt; spaces and &lt;code&gt;i+1&lt;/code&gt; stars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c++&#34; data-lang=&#34;c++&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The formulas become harder to figure out as the shapes become more
complex and sometimes students get stymied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that while they&amp;#39;re struggling to find the perfect
solution, it&amp;#39;s sometimes better to do it the dumb way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Consider drawing a trapezoid like this example of height 5 and
starting width 12:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
************
**********
********
******
****
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A student could come up with the &amp;#34;formulas&amp;#34; for spaces and stars but
sometimes there&amp;#39;s a more straightforward way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Consider the number of spaces on each line on the left hand side of
the shape. First line is 0 then 1, 2 etc. Why not start a variable
&lt;code&gt;spaces&lt;/code&gt; at 0 and increment it on each loop iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the number of stars, it&amp;#39;s starting at the width and being reduced
by 2 each time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This leads to a solution similar to this (using the line routine from
the earlier refactoring post):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c++&#34; data-lang=&#34;c++&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This solution is simple to construct, simple to understand, and quite
frankly, hard to get wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It can also lead a student to discovering a pattern or &amp;#34;formula&amp;#34; such
as what was used to solve the earlier problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This might seem to some as a cheap way out, the dumb approach -
creating extra variables and have them count along the way but I
don&amp;#39;t. There&amp;#39;s nothing wrong with simple and straightforward. Yes, you
could come up with an elegant formula but the bottom line is you need
something to count 0,1,2,3… so create a variable to do it. You need
something to count 12,10,8,… create one for that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m not advocating writing 100 if statements rather than a loop
but I think you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The best solution is one that works and Sometimes the &amp;#34;dumb&amp;#34; approach is the best approach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refactoring</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of my laments on teaching computer science is that students are
rarely taught and given the chance to develop  good programming
practices. There&amp;#39;s usually not enough time. Beginners work on small
&amp;#34;toys&amp;#34; which don&amp;#39;t lend themselves to good software development
practices and later on, there&amp;#39;s so much other material like
algorithms, data structures etc. to teach and
learn that programming practices usually amount to lines like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#34;Make sure to comment your code..&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;Indent properly…&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;Use functions…&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;It&amp;#39;s important to test your code…&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
so when I see an opportunity to use a simple example to drive home a
good practice,  I try to jump on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Drawing shapes with text is a typical early project. I&amp;#39;ve seen it in
text books and online and have been doing it for years. I recall doing
it back in the 80s in Fortran IV when the programs we wrote were on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punched_card&#34;&gt;punch cards&lt;/a&gt;, run
overnight on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_1130&#34;&gt;IBM 1130&lt;/a&gt;, and printouts picked up the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a nice use of nested loops. The students will write functions to
create assorted shapes out of asterisks  like rectangles and
triangles. Typical solutions look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c++&#34; data-lang=&#34;c++&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Which results in shapes like these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;

| ****            |    | *               |
| ****            |    | **              |
| ****            |    | ***             |
| ****            |    | ****            |
| ****            |    |                 |
|                 |    |                 |
|                 |    |                 |
| *************** |    | *               |
| *************** |    | **              |
| *************** |    | ***             |
| *************** |    | ****            |
| *************** |    | *****           |
| *************** |    | ******          |
| *************** |    | *******         |
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there will be more interesting shapes including things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;

*       *            *****
**      ***           *   *            and more
***     *****          *   *
****      ***           *****
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a great time to talk about refactoring.  All of the shape
drawing functions follow the same pattern - there&amp;#39;s an outer loop for
the height and then one or more inner loops to draw each line. We can
factor out the inner loops in to a separate &lt;code&gt;line()&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c++&#34; data-lang=&#34;c++&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s just like factoring in algebra:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;latex-block&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
(RectangleOuterLoop × Line) + (TriangleOuterLoop × Line) ⇒ Line  (Rectangleouterloop × TriangleOuterloop)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We end up with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c++&#34; data-lang=&#34;c++&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s simpler, cleaner, and also can lead us to thinking about the
&amp;#34;harder&amp;#34; shapes in an interesting way. Instead of looking at the right
justified triangle as a triangle, we can think of each level as two
lines - one of spaces (shown here as dashes) followed by a line of
stars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
----*       *
---**      **
--***     ***
-****    ****
*****   *****
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Noticing that  for a height of 5, the dashed lines count down in
length 4,3,2,1,0 and the star lines count up 1,2,3,4,5, we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-c++&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c++&#34; data-lang=&#34;c++&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here we have typical early CS assignment that really lends itself to
talking about structuring programs and refactoring. Where else can we
inject good programming practices in ways that make sense early on?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sigcse2018 Bootstrapworld on Creativity in CS classes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-bootstrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-bootstrap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I really didn&amp;#39;t know what to expect at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3159471&#34;&gt;Creativity, Customization,
and Ownership: Game Design in Bootstrap: Algebra&lt;/a&gt; session. I&amp;#39;ve been a
big fan of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bootstrapworld.org/&#34;&gt;Bootstrep&lt;/a&gt; for years and looking at the authors, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/10/cs-teacher-interview-emmanuel.html&#34;&gt;Emmanuel
Schanzer&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s been a freind forever. I&amp;#39;ve never met &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ShriramKMurthi&#34;&gt;Shriram Krishnamurthi&lt;/a&gt;
in person but am looking forward to it. We&amp;#39;ve traded emails and blog
comments. I&amp;#39;d like to consider him a friend and I certainly respect
him and his work even though we frequently disagree around the
edges. The third author and presenter, Kathi Fisler was new to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Bootstrap program is embedded in algebra classes. In it, students
use Racket (nee scheme) to reinforce math skills while building
computer science skills. The big student project is a graphical game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When designing the project, students are asked to decide on and find
four resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The background image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The player image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The target image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The enemy image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students are given a short amount of time to decide on and find these
four images. I think it was about ten minutes and that&amp;#39;s it. That&amp;#39;s
all the &amp;#34;creativity&amp;#34; in the assignment. After that, all the students
are essentially creating the same game with different skins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This design makes sense. You can&amp;#39;t have students going all over the
place. Constraining the assignment in this way allows teachers who
might now be strong in computer science to guide the kids through the
program to completion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the time I was thinking: I really like all of this but is it really
open ended creativity and discovery with respect to math or computer
science? As it turned out, Fisler addressed this point at the end of
the talk in a way that made me vary happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fisler went on to describe the rest of the student experience and then
went on to talk about the statistics they gathered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One big takeaway was that while all the students were essentially
writing the same game varying only the graphical elements, this
encouraged students to create very different themes. They also created
rich stories around their games. The project might not have been
&amp;#34;creative&amp;#34; with respect to the CS or Math directions but it was certainly
creative in other important areas. The other takeaway was that
survey&amp;#39;s indicated all sorts of positives from the program as a whole
so the project didn&amp;#39;t seem to have suffered by having the students
essentially write the same program. Participants were proud of their
work, they felt their games were different from their peers and in
general the experience was good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During questions, someone asked about adding a fifth element - a
projectile or missile. It turns out that at one point the program had a
projectile component but that led to the vast majority of projects to
be themed in very similar ways. Even though not the same, it reminded me to something Randy
Pausch said in his &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo&#34;&gt;Last Lecture&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You make whatever you want. Two rules: no shooting violence and no
pornography. Not because I’m opposed to those in particular, but you know, that’s been done with
VR, right? [laughter] And you’d be amazed how many 19-year-old boys are completely out of ideas
when you take those off the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the very end, Fisler addressed my questions about creativity and
discovery. She posed these questions of her own: &amp;#34;Do we overstate the
case for creativity?&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;Is pure constructivism a win?&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve ranted on contructivism before. It can be great but a
constructivist lesson takes a knowledgeable educator and a lot of time,
preparation, and effort. It&amp;#39;s a big ask for, say, a high school
teacher who&amp;#39;s already taking home hours of work every evening. Too
often I&amp;#39;ve seen the following &amp;#34;contructivist&amp;#34; model instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take an isntructor that doesn&amp;#39;t know their craft, the content, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;niether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the kids play with stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show off the couple of autodidacts that figure it out as success&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll rant more about this &amp;#34;model&amp;#34; with respect to the new buzz word
&amp;#34;lead learner&amp;#34; at some point in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the creativity side, it&amp;#39;s important but there are also times for
the instructor to lead and for guidelines to be followed.
We want to foster creativity but that doesn&amp;#39;t mean that it&amp;#39;s 100%
creativity 100% of the time. Education is like life, a balance. The
Bootstrap program had to constrain the CS and math learning but
allowed for creativity in other areas. It&amp;#39;s smart and it&amp;#39;s a win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I still want to meet Shriram in person one day and now also Kathi
Fisler. I didn&amp;#39;t know what to expect walking in but I left the talk
reminded of why I&amp;#39;m such a fan of Emmanuel, his team, and their work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sigcse2018 - Malloc Lab</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-malloc-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-malloc-lab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t going to go to this session. I started out in a panel on
integrating social good into CS Ed. With the panel not meeting my
expectations I moved over to my second choice - the system programming
sessions where I saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3159597&#34;&gt;Implementing Malloc: Students and Systems
Programming&lt;/a&gt;, a paper presented by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~bpr/&#34;&gt;Brian Railing&lt;/a&gt; of CMU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really liked both the paper and the talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CMU computer science students all take a systems course that uses
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Computer-Systems-Programmers-Perspective-3/dp/9332573905/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_14_t_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=Y5ZKG2V8ZYZZPZHQP8SQ&#34;&gt;Computer Systems: A Programmer&amp;#39;s Perspective&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s a great book. I
read through the first edition years ago and felt it was great
resource not only in a systems course but also for self study. One of
the labs has the students implement their own memory allocation calls,
or &lt;strong&gt;malloc&lt;/strong&gt; for us old time C wonks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were a number of self perceived  deficiencies with the
assignment such as encouraging bad programming style by modeling
less than ideal practices but the biggest deficiency as that students
could game the assignment. Students could do very well on the
assignment by exploiting knowledge of the assignment rather than by
writing a full and correct malloc implementation. One example is that
students were able to figure out that no allocation would be more than
100MB so they really didn&amp;#39;t have to deal with 64 bit pointers. They
could use smaller offsets thus simplifying the assignment. The
assignment became more about figuring out how to get it through the
grader and less about learning memory management. I&amp;#39;m sure I&amp;#39;m
overstating it but that&amp;#39;s the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Railing explained all of the deficiencies and then how they changed
the assignment to address them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the assignment had fewer loopholes to game so
students had to really write the malloc library and presumably learn
about memory management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also added an intermediate deliverable so students couldn&amp;#39;t leave
everything for the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Near the end of the talk, Railing discussed results where he pointed
out that students final exam scores didn&amp;#39;t change but they did better
on the malloc questions. It wasn&amp;#39;t clear if the overall scores didn&amp;#39;t
change, meaning that the students did better on the malloc questions
but worse somewhere else or if they did similarly to past students on
the other sections and in addition they scored better on the malloc
questions. I&amp;#39;m not sold on the final exam questions being the best way
to evaluate learning but it is an easy data point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I loved the presentation and paper and I love what Railing is doing
but my big takeaway was…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, Duh…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;students aren&amp;#39;t doing as they should&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teacher realizes students are gaming assignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teacher reworks assignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;students do better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teachers do this all the time. Of course when we do it, it&amp;#39;s not
&amp;#34;research.&amp;#34; This was a recurring theme for me at SIGCSE2018 and I
tweeted it. While it&amp;#39;s true that K12 teachers can learn a lot about CS
content from higher ed, people in higher ed can learn a lot about
teaching from teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What Railing presented was terrific and important as changing
assignments like this will now be considered by people who haven&amp;#39;t
thought about this before but this is second nature to a teacher. Of
course I&amp;#39;m talking about a good teacher, not one who blindly follows
scripted lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t mean this as a slight to professors. They&amp;#39;re hired and
promoted based on research so much of their job involves another skill
set. I know many professors who care very much about teaching but they
might only teach one or two classes a semester that meets once or
twice a week while a typical high school teacher meets 150 students a
day five days a week over five different classes a day.  Much more of
an opportunity for deliberate practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This presents a huge challenge. How can professors who are hired and
promoted as researchers be given the time and ability to develop as
teachers? What about adjuncts or Teaching Assistants? I&amp;#39;d imagine it&amp;#39;s
even harder for them. I know that colleges have lines for teaching
faculty but from what I can see, those instructors are usually super
overloaded with classes and students so that doesn&amp;#39;t solve the
problem. Even if you do have teaching faculty that have the time to
develop their craft, how do you get those teaching chops over to the
research faculty?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the session, I was talking about this with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~mjs/&#34;&gt;Mark Stehlik&lt;/a&gt;,
Assistant Dean at CMU&amp;#39;s School of Computer Science. Mark was telling
me about CMU&amp;#39;s efforts to develop teaching faculty across the
disciplines. I was happy to hear about the efforts CMU was taking but
it sounds like they have the same challenges with respect to pedagogy
as everyone else. If it&amp;#39;s a challenge for CMU with all their
resources, what does that mean for the rest of us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, it was encouraging to go to a number of sessions where it was
clear that professors - both teaching and research faculty are serious
about the craft of teaching and conferences like SIGCSE can bring them
together with those of us who don&amp;#39;t have the chops as researchers but
do so as teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools can shape how we think</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-4-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-4-6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been having fun with this years &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; competition. So
far, I&amp;#39;ve been able to keep up but with I expect that to change in
another couple of days since I&amp;#39;ll be traveling for the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After solving a problem, I like looking over some of the other
solutions on the Advent of Code &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/&#34;&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;. Even with similar
agorithmic solutions there&amp;#39;s a decent amount of variation in the
actual code and solutions in different languages can look radically
different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That got me thinking about how the tools we know and use both shape the ways we
approach solving problems and creating things and either limit or
empower us to go from a mental model of a solution or creation to an
actual artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Relating to this are the common themes that come up in the CS
Education world. The idea that it&amp;#39;s computer science not programming
and certainly not merely coding. That&amp;#39;s true but the tools and
languages we use shape the whole thinking part and can also give the
students a valuable practical tool that they can leverage to great
advantage in both future classes and work and life endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I decided to do this rant as a video. I hope you enjoy it:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x8cZgEogWNw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; gesture=&#34;media&#34; allow=&#34;encrypted-media&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new first language? What&#39;s the follow up plan?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-language-changing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-language-changing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
This morning, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/guzdial&#34;&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about Stanford possibly &lt;a href=&#34;https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/04/21/cs-department-updates-introductory-courses-java-is-gone/&#34;&gt;moving away
from Java&lt;/a&gt; as their intro language. This comes on the heels of a
semi-regular thread on one of the lists I&amp;#39;m on asking about what
languages are used at assorted colleges around the country. Invariably
the Pascal -&amp;gt; C++ -&amp;gt; Java progression of APCS turns up in these
threads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are plenty of arguments to be made both for and against pretty
much any language or platform. There&amp;#39;s no single best universal
answer. Each choice giveth and each choice taketh away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I&amp;#39;m really curious about is who&amp;#39;s looking at intro languages in
the context of complete programs or even complete educations that
could span multiple institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Early language choices can make a big difference in engaging and
exciting newcomers but there are ramifications later on that few seem
to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take the APCS change from C++ to Java. It removed memory management
from the first year course. It also simplified issues relating to
pass by value vs pass by reference (or, rather, passing address by
value), bought much more strongly into OOP and moved more towards
using built in implementations of data structures like Lists rather
than rolling your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Removing memory management from the first year course in and of itself
isn&amp;#39;t a problem as long as it&amp;#39;s taught and taught effectively
somewhere later on. It could be argued that &amp;#34;memory is already covered
in our required systems course.&amp;#34; That could be the case, but there are
many concepts that kids don&amp;#39;t get the first time around. Is an
institution that covered memory management in CS1/2 and then came back
to it in a later Systems course giving their students the same
understanding now that they&amp;#39;ve eliminated the CS1/2 experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about OOP buy in. Personally, I&amp;#39;ve never been a big OOP fan but
that&amp;#39;s neither here nor there. What I have found is that depending on
how a student is exposed to programming in CS1/CS2 can have a big
influence on how they approach problems later. Did the move to Java
cause more of our students to try to use shoehorn OOP into a problem
that really shouldn&amp;#39;t be approached in an OOP manner?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I suspect that the use of built in data structures has had a
negative impact. A few years after the switch to Java, I was talking
to a senior tech worker. He was having a bad day - interviewing
potential internees and full time engineers. My friend was complaining
that the kids couldn&amp;#39;t come up with solutions to what he thought were
pretty straightforward questions. He felt that had the kids actually
implemented algorithms like the nlogn sorts rather than just learning
java .sort method and just talking about the algorithm they&amp;#39;d be
better prepared. I&amp;#39;ve heard this sentiment repeated over and over
throughout the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that Java is a horrible language or horrible for
teaching - that&amp;#39;s another debate. The point is that you can&amp;#39;t just
look at the intro class and who it draws in. You have to consider how
it will prepare students for the next level and you have to look at
the big picture – will our students get everything they need by the
time they leave us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many schools have moved to Python. Will that effect students take on
type systems later on? Will the flexibility and constructs like list
comprehensions make it harder to teach recursion since there are
&amp;#34;easier&amp;#34; ways to do it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
None of these are really problems so long as the CS1/2 (or even CS0)
isn&amp;#39;t taught in a vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I fear, however that too often we&amp;#39;re paying attention to the intake of
the pipe and not so much the output.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub as a tool for education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
When I started using git and GitHub with my students it was a natural
progression having started with started with CVS and then, as
technology changed moving through Subversion and then Mercurial. It
was all about using sensible professional software development
techniques while making it easier for students to submit work and for
me to evaluate their submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over time, I found that git and GitHub in fact provided some extra
support for educators right out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3&#34;&gt;last github post&lt;/a&gt; I talked about using the results of &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;
and looking at diffs. Both provide ways of seeing what a student did
and when. The commit log and history make it easier to hold students accountable to working
through a project and not leavings for the last minute. The diffs make
it easier to see what&amp;#39;s changed both to see progress and also to help
support students as they develop their projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you use Emacs, as I do, you can use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pidu/git-timemachine&#34;&gt;git timemachine&lt;/a&gt; package
which does a great job visualizing changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/timemachine.gif&#34; alt=&#34;/img/sigcse-github/timemachine.gif&#34; title=&#34;/img/sigcse-github/timemachine.gif&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other editors might have a similar feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The contribution graphs also provide a quick snapshot which shows what
team members are contributing and when:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph.png&#34; alt=&#34;/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph.png&#34; title=&#34;/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph.png&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The punchcard graph is also useful to see when students actually do
their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph2.png&#34; alt=&#34;/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph2.png&#34; title=&#34;/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph2.png&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
GitHub also make it easy to set up starter code or to have students
&amp;#34;take over&amp;#34; each others projects by forking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m very happy using git and GitHub as is but if you want more
support, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://classroom.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub Classroom&lt;/a&gt;. Had it existed when I started,
I&amp;#39;d probably have used it but since I had already gotten used to my
work flows I&amp;#39;ve stuck with raw git and github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In case you missed the earlier posts describing the process I use to
introduce github to my classes here they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-1&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-2&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m hoping some of you have found this set of four posts useful or at
least interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A free multi-state clicker with built in redundency</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last Friday, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/guzdial&#34;&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about the woes of &lt;a href=&#34;https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/03/31/the-need-for-better-software-and-systems-to-support-active-cs-learning/%0A&#34;&gt;using clickers&lt;/a&gt; in a
class. The amount of effort required to use his school&amp;#39;s approved
clicker technology sounds ridiculous so while we need tools to better
engage students in large class settings we need better tools that can
be integrated into our classes more easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never used clickers. On top of stories like Mark&amp;#39;s, there are  a
number of problems with using clickers in a public school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can&amp;#39;t force students to buy them and in NYC, until recently,
students couldn&amp;#39;t use their phones (which they also might not have).
Forgetting the expense, if the school provides them, is it one per
student? If so, who&amp;#39;s going to administer the clicker to student
mapping and how will that be communicated to the teachers. If college
tech infrastructures are sometimes lacking, high schools are orders of
magnitudes worse. The resources just aren&amp;#39;t there. Then we have to
deal with loss and breakage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher somehow gets a class set of clickers, they have to deal
with mapping clickers to students for all of their classes and make
sure the right student has the right clicker. Again, loss  and
breakage is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then you have to create the question content and hope that everything
works in class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The value added given the overhead just doesn&amp;#39;t seem worth it
particularly since high school classes, while large, are not in the
hundreds and there are other methods of student engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s what I use instead. It&amp;#39;s not perfect but it&amp;#39;s low cost and low
effort with a pretty high return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The basic configuration, is a simple three state broadcast device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not without its problems and I don&amp;#39;t think it would work as well
in a large lecture but given the cost, it&amp;#39;s well worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonzup.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/thumbs/fonzup.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/thumbs/fonzup.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thumbs.
Periodically, I&amp;#39;ll poll my class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img width=&amp;#34;30%&amp;#34;src=&amp;#34;file:/img/thumbs/sidethumb.png&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img width=&amp;#34;30%&amp;#34; src=&amp;#34;file:/img/thumbs/upthumb.jpg&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;img width=&amp;#34;30%&amp;#34; src=&amp;#34;file:/img/thumbs/downthumb.jpg&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/spam&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thumb to the side? Everything&amp;#39;s OK. Keep going as you&amp;#39;re going. I get
it. Basically, things are good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thumb up? Speed up, you&amp;#39;re going too slow, I got it five minutes ago or
some similar big positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thumb down? I have no idea what you&amp;#39;re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s cheap, easy, quick, and once you can get your class to buy in,
you can get a quick sense of the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The downsides?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The class has to have a level of comfort so that students vote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;honestly and don&amp;#39;t just give you positive feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No data collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The upsides?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cheap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;works on any topic on the fly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even if the votes are artificially skewed towards positive, it does&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;forces the class to be at least a little attentive and to engage in
some physical response&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can get analog responses by allowing students to adjust wrist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rotation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to the redundancy? I&amp;#39;ve never had a kid leave their thumb at home
or lose it and even if they did, they&amp;#39;ve got a second hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonztwo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/thumbs/fonztwo.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/thumbs/fonztwo.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This also works in extreme environments. Try using a clicker or mobile
app with gloves or mittens on or underwater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t teach large lectures so I don&amp;#39;t know how this would work in a
huge class. I&amp;#39;d imagine it&amp;#39;s still worth it given that it&amp;#39;s so low
friction and low cost of entry even if it&amp;#39;s not perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher looks at Advent of Code 2016 #2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today we&amp;#39;re looking at &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; 2016 &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/2&#34;&gt;number 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To change things up, I thought I&amp;#39;d do a video where I live code a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The solution I present is pretty straightforward - use a 2D array (or
technically, an array of strings) to represent the keypad, parse the
input, and follow the input instructions to build the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I really like about Advent of Code is that every
problem has two parts and depending on how you solved part 1, you may
or may not have extra work to do for part 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, I wrote about one of the coding techniques I
try to convey to my students. The idea of &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-26-change-the-data.md&#34;&gt;changing the data&lt;/a&gt; to take
away edge and special cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part two of this problem is a perfect time to use that technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the video, I hope you enjoy it:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EC8gSrYQ11g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher looks at Advent of Code 2016 #1</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I recently &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/&#34;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; - a series of programming
problems relseased one a day. While they vary in terms of level of
difficulty, a number of them make nice problems for introductory to
mid level programming classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I&amp;#39;d share some of my thoughts on a few of them starting with
the first problem from this years competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/1&#34;&gt;Take a minute to read it over.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first glance, it might seem to a young programmer that this problem
requires a two dimensional array - all about (x,y) coordinates but
then there&amp;#39;s a problem - there are no limits on coordinates and we
can&amp;#39;t make an unlimited size array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After thinking a bit, hopefully the programmer realizes that all they
need to do is keep track of the how the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(x,y)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; location changes over
time. In the solution below, we start at &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(0,0)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and count the steps as
we update two variables &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;x&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we finish processing the moves, we have our current location in
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(x,y)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and we have the number of steps taken to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The solution below hsa a couple of niceties that a beginning
programmer might not know or use (and I&amp;#39;m not arguing that what&amp;#39;s written is
superior in any way, it&amp;#39;s just what I ended up writing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I make use of tuple destructuring:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;x,y &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
which assigns &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;x&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to the first item in the tuple and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; the
second. I used that a number of times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also use a list  I call &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dirs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to hold dx and dy values for the
four direcitons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;dirs&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;),(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;),(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;),(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This made it easier to to update the location based on the 4
directions. I could also have just used if statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s all the code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;x,y &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# assume our starting location is 0,0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# we start with d=0 -&amp;gt; facing north&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# as we turn left or right, we can just increment or decrement d&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# and dirs[d] will give us the appropriate dx and dy to update&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# our locatoin for the next step&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;dirs&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;),(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;),(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;),(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;d&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# This is only needed for part 2  - We track visited locations&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# by adding them to the dictionary. If we try to add a location&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# that&amp;#39;s already been visited we know that we&amp;#39;ve found our final&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# location&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# locs={}  # uncomment this line for part 2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;totalsteps&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; l:
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# the first char in i is the direction to turn in (L or R)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# the rest represents the number of steps.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;dir&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;i[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;steps&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;int(i[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;:])
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; dir&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;L&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;d &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (d&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;d &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (d&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(dx,dy) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; dirs[d]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(steps):
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(x,y) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; dx, y &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; dy)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;totalsteps&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;totalsteps&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Uncomment this block for part 2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# each time we have a new location, see if it&amp;#39;s already in&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# locs, if it isn&amp;#39;t, add it.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# if it is, we&amp;#39;re visiting somewhere twice so we&amp;#39;re done.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#if ((x,y) not in locs):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#    locs[(x,y)]=1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#else:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#    print((x,y))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#    print(abs(x)+abs(y)) # the answer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#    sys.exit(0)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#    break&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;print(x,y)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;print(abs(x)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;abs(y)) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# the answer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall, a nice little problem for beginning and intermediate
students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Term, New Tool - repl.it</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-term-new-tool-repl.it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-term-new-tool-repl.it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re now a week in to my first class at Hunter. It&amp;#39;s a little early
for me to really compare and contrast the high school to college
experience but I thought I&amp;#39;d share some thoughts on a tool that I&amp;#39;ve
recently started to play with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My students were all supposed to be issued laptops at the beginning of
the semester. The plan was to have them learn Linux, the command line,
and a little DevOps along the way. I guess I shouldn&amp;#39;t have been too
surprised to learn that the laptops weren&amp;#39;t going to come in until
late September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Scratch all that advance lesson planning. A brief scramble and I was
able to relocate the class into a computer lab but now we can&amp;#39;t
customize the kids environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Time to look for an online solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re starting the kids off in Python, a choice that I&amp;#39;ll talk about
in some future post and normally my online go to for Python is
&lt;a href=&#34;http://codesters.com&#34;&gt;codesters.com&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m a big fan of the codesters team and product. This
time, though, I decided to try something else. Specifically &lt;a href=&#34;http://repl.it&#34;&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt;. Partly because, as with
codesters, I like the people behind it. It&amp;#39;s also pretty simple and it
supports a lot of different languages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APL, ES2015 ,Bloop, BrainF, C, CoffeeScript, C++, C++11, C#, Emoticon,
Forth, F#, Go, Java, JavaScript, LOLCODE, Lua, Nodejs, PHP, Python,
Python3, QBasic, Roy, Ruby, Rust, Scheme, Swift, Unlambda, and HTML, CSS, JS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s still a pretty new product so there are occasional hiccups but
I&amp;#39;m really liking things so far. Some of the things I like include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a simple clean interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sharing and embedding code:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;script src=&amp;#34;//repl.it/embed/DF3m/19.js&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;project mode which allows multi file projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;examples to get you started&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the thing I&amp;#39;m really liking are the teacher features they&amp;#39;re
working on. The teacher interface isn&amp;#39;t fancy. I like that. Things are
simple and clean and they let me get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had two extra minutes in class yesterday and in that time, I was
able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a classroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invite all my students by email&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create 2 quick assignments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assignment page lets you give starter code as well as instructions
and it also lets you put in tests that are run when a student submits
their work for instant feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really like the tests feature on projects. So far, I&amp;#39;ve only played
with Python unit tests. Repl.it uses a really easy to follow
interface and has a sample test to guide you. There&amp;#39;s also an option
for input/output matching which includes flexible matching and regular
expressions but I haven&amp;#39;t played with it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall, I&amp;#39;m liking this tool. When the kids get their laptops we&amp;#39;ll
probably use it somewhat less as they start to learn to use their own
systems but I&amp;#39;m glad to have repl.it in my teaching arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lesson plans - scripts to springboards</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent last Saturday up at the Microsoft offices in Times Square
observing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; training session. My fried &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nathanielgranor&#34;&gt;Nathaniel Granor&lt;/a&gt;, Teals
Regional Manager in the east has invited me a number of times and this
time I was able to make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t know, TEALS is a program that takes volunteers in the
tech industry and places them in classrooms. Unlike other programs,
the TEALS volunteers work with the teachers while the kids learn some
CS. The idea is that the teacher will learn about CS from the
volunteer and the volunteer will learn something about teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not the same as having a strong, knowledgeable CS teacher in the
classroom but until we get there, TEALS is doing great work giving
kids something that they need and otherwise wouldn&amp;#39;t get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point, Nathaniel started to talk to the volunteers about lesson
plans emphasizing the fact that TEALS would provide all the lesson materials and
the plans so these new to teaching tech volunteers wouldn&amp;#39;t have to
make curricular decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The lesson plan form was pretty traditional and pretty formulaic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;warm up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instruction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very similar to what I was shown back in the day during my two day
&amp;#34;teaching boot camp&amp;#34; that kicked off my career [fn:: full disclosure: I
came in to teaching with zero education credentials and took the
minimum number of ed classes for my license after I started.] and very
appropriate as an effective and efficient way to prepare these
volunteers for their first days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about my lesson planning over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started, I was teaching math but I wasn&amp;#39;t really a math
guy - I was CS all the way. I had to remember the math from high
school, learn the new topics, and figure out how to teach it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had a very supportive department but they were busy with their own
classes and this was pre internet. Fortunately, the NYC DOE published
lesson plan books. They were basically bound volumes of xerox copies
of hand written and typed lesson plans provided by experienced
teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent many hours copying them, studying  them, and then later
tweaking them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They were a life saver back then. How was the teaching? OK. Not
great. I got the material to the kids but I was nothing special. This
is where I started to form my bias against the scripted teaching
that&amp;#39;s being pushed down today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I developed my chops, I started to design my own experiences for my
classes and things improved. By the time I was done teaching math -
maybe 4 years in, I was just scratching the surface of being a math
teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One year in, I started teaching CS along with math at Seward
Park. When I was bumped to Stuy, I went back to math for  a year and a
half and then it was all CS all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For CS, we didn&amp;#39;t have lesson plan books so I had to craft everything
from scratch. It was a lot of work but the results were much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first, I would actually write out lesson plans a la math lesson
plans. A &amp;#34;do now,&amp;#34; &amp;#34;instructional objectives,&amp;#34; &amp;#34;applications,&amp;#34;
&amp;#34;Homework,&amp;#34; etc. The only thing I never formally wrote out was a
&amp;#34;medial summary.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over time, my lessons got better but my lesson plans looked worse and
worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were times a lesson plan might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/lesson-plans/plan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/lesson-plans/plan.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/lesson-plans/plan.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
OK, not exactly but as I developed at my craft, I didn&amp;#39;t need a laid
out script to follow line for line  rather, just a set of little
reminders and maybe some printed out code. If we were going to develop
a complicated algorithm or derivation, though, I would still write out
all the steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This doesn&amp;#39;t mean that as my career progressed I planned any less. It
might appear that I&amp;#39;m winging it but even if little to nothing is
written down, there is a plan and there&amp;#39;s always a lot of pre work
before class begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, to bring this back to TEALS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s interesting how what&amp;#39;s good in one context is not so much in
another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What TEALS is doing is great - they&amp;#39;ve got to get a lot of
technologists in to classrooms quickly but once there, they&amp;#39;ll be with
real, hopefully experienced teachers. What they&amp;#39;re doing gets them
ready to go. It&amp;#39;s a starting point, not an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, when I see scripted curriculum being sold as the
special sauce, be it in CS teacher &amp;#34;training,&amp;#34; Teach for America
summer prep or in the name of charter school uniformity, I run the
other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s prepare curricular  materials for important programs like TEALS
and for beginning teachers just starting out but let&amp;#39;s not confuse a
scripted lesson that can be delivered by one and all to be anything
close to the work of a master educator and craftsman.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robots platforms and practicalities</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/robot-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/robot-survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I received an email from a friend the other day asking me about a
particular robotics platform she recently saw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve played with robotics on and off over the years ranging from
building them from (not using) scratch using Atmel chips and programming them in
assembly to using Arduino based platforms to using pre-built robot
platforms. They&amp;#39;re really cool and since they interact with the real
world you can do all sorts of interesting and motivational things with students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve done these on my own as a hobbyist and also with students either
individually or in small groups, but never as part of a class I had
been teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest reason is that the classes I&amp;#39;ve taught are already so
packed full of CS goodness that we can&amp;#39;t even get everything done
that&amp;#39;s theoretically on the syllabi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other has to do with practical concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Equipment costs - Let&amp;#39;s say we can get our platform at $100 a pop. I
just can&amp;#39;t see a public school with 34 kids in a class getting one per
student or one for every two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s the robot to student ratio and how much actual access do
the kids get? If they&amp;#39;re designing  building, do they all get to
design and build? Same question with coding and operating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there&amp;#39;s space – if we&amp;#39;re talking about a mobile platform as
opposed to something that sits on the desk and is near stationary, we
have a problem. The classrooms I&amp;#39;ve taught in can barely hold the
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are also issues with breakage, loss, theft and long term
maintainability - will we be able to or even want to fill in with
compatible units in a few years as needed or will we have to reboot
the program from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All that to deal with before we even get to the fun of teaching and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m really curious about the experiences of those of you who do teach
using robots and similar platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you are such a teacher, could you please fill out this form or
leave a comment for anything that the form doesn&amp;#39;t cover?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1FlppDbeiK8uPxh_RkXoCbbdE_UDY_4qXmZWbXlZ0gGg/viewform?embedded=true&#34;&gt;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1FlppDbeiK8uPxh_RkXoCbbdE_UDY_4qXmZWbXlZ0gGg/viewform?embedded=true&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;760&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;500&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34; marginheight=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34; marginwidth=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;&amp;gt;Loading…&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navajo Math Circles</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zalafilms.com/navajo/&#34;&gt;Navajo Math Circles&lt;/a&gt;, a
documentary on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mathcircles.org/&#34;&gt;Math Circle&lt;/a&gt; put in place to support and enrich the
currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment
programs. I&amp;#39;m most familiar with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nymathcircle.org/&#34;&gt;New York Math Circle&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m friends
with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in
their summer program for a couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over in the southwest, these Math Circles have been bringing together
students, frequently across great distances each day to explore
problem solving and creativity through mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As someone who&amp;#39;s worked hard to bring educational opportunities to the
have nots, I love the program. Some of the highlights include the kids
working on open ended problems, focusing on process and techniques
more than specific results, working both collaboratively but also
developing self sufficiency, and more. I also love the fact that
they&amp;#39;ve started teacher math circles to help to bring some of that
math circle magic to the everyday classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I enjoyed the film and recommend you check it out to see what&amp;#39;s
possible and I want to share my two big takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, early on in the film, one of the people running the program
talked about developing a math enrichment program through and with
Navajo traditions and culture. This is HUGE and I feel it&amp;#39;s something
we&amp;#39;re losing. America is so diverse from coast to coast and here in
New York City you can see radically different ways of life living
right across the street from each other. Everyone pays lip service to
&amp;#34;making the work interesting and relevant to the student&amp;#34; but few
people walk the walk. These folk do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Second, I left the documentary with a sour taste in my mouth. Not
because of the program but because the Navajo Math Circle project and
projects like it are scraping together what little resources they can
to try to do what the school systems should be doing to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we move to scripted lessons, national standards, curricula dictated
or at least influenced by large private concerns and standardized
tests, our schools are moving further and further away from community
and local culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the documentary, one student pointed out that in math class, they
have to use the textbook. They learn the process and then have to
solve the problems. In Math Circle, there are no textbooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, the students in from the Math Circle did some Q&amp;amp;A. I asked
them to elaborate - what&amp;#39;s the difference between there Math Circle
experiences and their in school ones. I got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Math Circle is fun!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think that says it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know many great teachers who try to bring culture and community to
their classes. One of my son&amp;#39;s best teachers, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.heinemann.com/authors/828.aspx&#34;&gt;Paula Rogovin&lt;/a&gt; did it all
the time. Many of my friends and colleagues try to do so as well but
the powers that be make it harder and harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Until we win back public education it&amp;#39;s important to support programs
like Math Circles (and, if I do say so myself, programs like our own
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cstuy.org&#34;&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;) and it&amp;#39;s also critical that we work to try to bring community
and culture to our regular classes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As curricula changes, what&#39;s falling through the cracks?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/semaphores/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/semaphores/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Edit:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just a brief note to clarify a couple of things. As indicated in the
comments, this post isn&amp;#39;t  about what&amp;#39;s appropriate for HS CS. It&amp;#39;s
more about what kids have after they finish their education - be it
high school, college, code school, or other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of my thoughts are the results of pondering on the exacerbations
of friends after interviewing people for entry level positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The two examples are just to illustrate the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Original Post:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I enjoy reading blogs. It&amp;#39;s one of the ways I keep current. Not only
in terms of what&amp;#39;s going on in CS Education, but also trends in CS -
academic or professional as well as on a range of other topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the blogs I enjoy is authored by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/b0rk&#34;&gt;Julia Evans&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;#39;t know
Julia, but we do have some mutual friends. I&amp;#39;ve enjoyed her &lt;a href=&#34;http://jvns.ca&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. She
does a nice job talking about any number of systems related
issue. I&amp;#39;ve tried to leave comments a few times but for some reason,
my comments always end up deleted or otherwise not showing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One recent post, one on &lt;a href=&#34;http://jvns.ca/blog/2016/03/29/thread-pools-part-ii-i-love-blocking/&#34;&gt;concurrency&lt;/a&gt; got me thinking. Since the comment
I left there didn&amp;#39;t take, I thought I&amp;#39;d write about it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a nice post but the thing that caught my eye was when Julia
said that she &amp;#34; didn&amp;#39;t know what a semaphore was until I read this
code and I was like OH THIS IS AMAZING AND SO USEFUL AND WOW.&amp;#34; I was a
little surprised, semaphores seem to be one of those basic concepts
that you just know but that is, of course incorrect. I first learned
about semaphores in my honors Systems class with my mentor, the late
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Dewar&#34;&gt;Robert Dewar&lt;/a&gt;. We started from test and set and worked our way up. I
had two other undergraduate classes that at least mentioned the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then again, I knew that many undergrads would never get a good
treatment of concurrency so I tried to build a bit in to the System
Level Programming  course I designed while at Stuy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking - according to her linked in, Julia was a CS
major at McGill - a university that I hold in high regard but either
semaphores were never covered or their treatment didn&amp;#39;t make enough of
an impact to be worth remembering. What topics do we cover in our
classes that kids just let fall to the wayside and what topics do we
end up losing as curricula change and we don&amp;#39;t have an eye on the big
picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One big one is memory management. When APCS and college 101 classes
went to Java, memory management went out the window. Not a problem, as
long as memory issues are covered in some other course. Unfortunately
the don&amp;#39;t seem to be. You can make a case that kids don&amp;#39;t need to
understand memory management or anything about garbage collection but
I&amp;#39;d argue that while one might never have to do their own memory
management a good CS person should have some understanding of what&amp;#39;s
going on under the hood or as my friend Gerry says &amp;#34;never use a
technology you couldn&amp;#39;t write yourself.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another biggie that I lived through was the IBM PC era. Prior to the
mid to late 80&amp;#39;s when the IBM PC ruled the world, kids learned about
CS on timesharing systems. Once the PC took hold, every kid learning
programming or studying CS was working on their own machine. They had
full access to everything and the machine just supported a single
thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, it was nice since you could easily play with low
level programming and hardware but on the other hand, a hole
generation didn&amp;#39;t learn about the complexities of multiple users and
multiple processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Early in my career I designed courses and only later did I realize
that you can&amp;#39;t just design a course, you have to look at the full arc
of a students education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think it&amp;#39;s interesting to think about what concepts are getting left
on the side of the road and I wonder if the big players driving CS
education spend any time thinking about this bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IDE or the Cloud</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-04-12-ide-or-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-04-12-ide-or-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-orgheadline1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;orgheadline1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-orgheadline1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This weekend, I had a conversation on Twitter with my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/roybahat&#34;&gt;Roy Bahat&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-conversation=&#34;none&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky&#34;&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt; Mike, unrelated, what do you think of &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/BT1ublbajF&#34;&gt;https://t.co/BT1ublbajF&lt;/a&gt; ?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Roy Bahat (@roybahat) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/roybahat/status/718835740738650112&#34;&gt;April 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/roybahat&#34;&gt;@roybahat&lt;/a&gt;Maybe I&amp;#39;ll blog about my thoughts about online environments vs local installs&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky)
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/718837282334240768&#34;&gt;April 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/roybahat&#34;&gt;@roybahat&lt;/a&gt; Agree with this but there are many issues. I&amp;#39;ll try to write more later. Now going to see my son in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/umgass&#34;&gt;@umgass&lt;/a&gt; prod of Pinafore.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/718838508689993728&#34;&gt;April 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another friend had just asked me about IDEs vs local installs for learning enviromnents the day before.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, should we use cloud based IDEs when teaching CS or should we use
local installs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There isn&#39;t a single right answer but I thought I&#39;d share some of my thoughts here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m hoping this is helpful to both those of us in the trenches as well
as maybe some platform developers out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some times, you don&#39;t have a choice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the web based side, does your school have the bandwidth. We&#39;re not
only talking about the pipe to the outside world but also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/14/nyregion/bronx-science-bans-cellphones-from-wi-fi-as-students-devour-it.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;wifi within
the school&lt;/a&gt;.  If kids can&#39;t reliably get to the web based environment,
it&#39;s not a viable option. On the other hand, cloud based software will
always be up to date and properly configured and kids can use them
from home or pretty much anywhere they have a connection.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other side we have local installs. This can also present
problems. Is the teacher allowed to install locally? Does he or she
know how to do it? Who&#39;s going keep all the machines up to date and configured?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Assuming we can get past the technical issues we can start looking at
the education side of thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the web based side, you&#39;ve got a silo. This can be both good and
bad. In an intro class, using a tool like &lt;a href=&#34;http://codesters.com&#34;&gt;Codesters&lt;/a&gt; can keep the cost
of entry low, allow students to share work online and allow teachers
to make use of their curricular materials. If you can&#39;t tell, I&#39;m a
big fan of Codesters and the Codesters team. The limitation is that
you have to use their simplified interface and toolset.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some web based IDEs like &lt;a href=&#34;http://koding.com&#34;&gt;Koding&lt;/a&gt; offer more flexibility - one tool with
many languages as well as deployment. The cost is complexity. With
Koding, you&#39;re basically running a virtual machine in the
cloud. You&#39;ve got their web based IDE and a terminal shell so it&#39;s not
as complex as doign everything from scratch locally but it&#39;s not as
structured as Codesters and is more of a general purpose site rather
than one focussed soley on learning.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then you have &lt;a href=&#34;http://repl.it&#34;&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt;. This looks to be a great platform for
experienced programmers to play with and explore new languages but I&#39;d
be concerned about using it with beginners. It looks like they&#39;re
rolling out some teacher tools so this might be worth revisiting soon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any case and with other web based products, you&#39;re living in the
providers silo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I&#39;m a command line wonk and confessed Emacs geek so I&#39;m
generally wary of an online environment without an exit strategy to
real world tools. Eventually, if all development moves into the
browser as platform then this problem goes away, but for now, you&#39;re
not going to have the expressive power and flexibility that a local
install gives.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Local installs let you use more powerful and flexible tools either
alone or in combination.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Keeping kids out of silos also makes it easier for them to learn new
tools, languages, and techniques.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since I like generic tools, I&#39;m not a fan of big professional IDEs
like Eclipse. I&#39;m an Emacs geek but Atom, Sublime Text, and Vim are
all good as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are also an assortment of beginner IDEs like Dr. Racket and I&#39;m
a fan with these for beginners as long as there&#39;s an exit strategy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For completeness, I should mention that if I weren&#39;t an old school
Emacs guy, I might check out something like JetBrain&#39;s IDEs. They&#39;re
much lighter weight than something like Eclipse but still full
featured. Somewhere between a true general purpose, customizable,
programmable editor and an all encompassing IDE.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
In general, I use online enviromnents with my classes early on when:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&#39;re pretty much identical or equivalent to the installed version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They provide some value added (&lt;a href=&#34;http://codingbat.com&#34;&gt;codingbat&lt;/a&gt; for example) so they&#39;re not
being used as a development environment but for some other purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They help with student collaboration (such as cloud9 or Koding.com
for more advanced kids).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any case, it&#39;s imporant that our kids aren&#39;t locked into any IDE be
it web based or local.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our kids that go on to more advanced CS studies will certainly need to
break out of sheltered world of a learning IDE and we&#39;re not doing
them a service if we shelter them too long.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our other kids also benefit from seeing beyond these restrictive
environments. A student might learn to code in Python in one of our
classes, but if we do our jobs right, that student might be writing a
little Javascript to automate Google Docs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can&#39;t tell you how many people I&#39;ve seen go through online coding
courses in a web based enviromnent only to be unable to do anything
outside of that enviromnent.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, we want our kids to be empowered to grow on
their own. All of the things I&#39;ve talked about here are merely
tools. Each has it&#39;s place. It&#39;s up to the teacher to make the roadmap
and to lead the student down the path.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevOps, or You don&#39;t know what the F you&#39;re doing!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-31-devops/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-31-devops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having just concluded almost a quarter century at one job in one
place, I&#39;ve been reflecting on a number of things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I accomplished, what I&#39;ve failed to accomplish, highlights,
low lights and everything in between.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve also learned a lot over these twenty five years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One thing I learned is DevOps and System Administration.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back around 1993 or 1994 Stuy wasn&#39;t really on the internet. Yes, we
were able to scam stuy.edu even though we were a high school and yes
we did have a class B address block but no one really had access.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Somehow, Bruce, a student of mine at the time and I ended up with the
job of getting Stuy onto the internet. Bruce was one of our superstar
kids and people thought I had extensive experience setting up and
running networks. Truth be told I messed around a bit but there&#39;s no
way I would have hired myself for the job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nonetheless, we were off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We were able to take one of the RS/6000 AIX workstations that were
supposed to be used as CAD stations and repurposed it as a server. We
made email accounts for everyone and were off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Neither Bruce nor I really knew what we were doing but we figured
things out. I learned a lot from him and I&#39;d like to think he also got
some benefit out of working with me. Fortunately, we seemed to have a
knack for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Linux-System-Administration-Handbook-Edition/dp/0131480057/ref=pd_sim_14_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;dpID=61%2B57ajucML&amp;amp;dpSrc=sims&amp;amp;preST=_AC_UL160_SR117%2C160_&amp;amp;refRID=164V89GZMZM2X9M2S8AH&#34;&gt;finding the answers&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Of course, we had our moments. Once, we got a critical patch
announcement from IBM. It said that if we needed the patch and didn&#39;t
apply it were were in big trouble but if our machine didn&#39;t need it,
applying the patch would kill our system. It was unclear whether we
needed the patch or not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After about a half hour research, we determined that we didn&#39;t need
the patch.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But applied it anyway :-(.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
D&#39;Oh.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a brief set of panic attacks and a bunch of fumbling around, we
did manage to restore things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, Bruce and I ran the system for a year or so and as I said, I
learned a lot. Now, Bruce was close to graduating so I was starting to
worry that I&#39;d have to figure this all out myself soon. That was a
seriously frightening thought.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I figured it would be good to bring in a couple of new super smart
students. As it turns out, Jon was one of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At one point, there was some problem and Bruce and I were going to
head to the office to try to figure it out. Jon asked if he could come
and watch. I thought that was a great idea so I agreed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We all went to the office and Bruce and I went to work. After about
fifteen minutes, Jon blurted out:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&#34;I just figured how you guys do it!!!&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&#34;You guys have no idea what the F you&#39;re doing!!!!!&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We all cracked up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He was absolutely right. We had no clue. We didn&#39;t know what we were
doing but we had become pretty good at figuring things out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Truth be told, that really is the norm. If you already knew how to
solve the problem, well, then it really wouldn&#39;t have been a problem
to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, you learn to figure it out. It&#39;s something I learned not to be
afraid of a long time ago. I hope that it&#39;s something I&#39;ve been able
to convey to my students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debugging deployment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-23-debugging-deployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-23-debugging-deployment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
SoftDev students are hard at work on their final projects. By now,
they all have fairly complex code bases. This limits how much I can
help them with debugging.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are some problems, though, that they have to contend with that
even with experience, are hard to spot. Notably because the very
tools you use to debug these errors are part of the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last week, this happened twice. Both cases were brought to me by
really strong students which just goes to underscore how insidious
these problems can be.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Here&#39;s a fake code snippet of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://flask.pocoo.org/&#34;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; application that illustrates
both problems.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 1: &lt;/span&gt;from flask import Flask, render_template
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 2: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 3: &lt;/span&gt;app = Flask(__name__)
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 4: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 5: &lt;/span&gt;@app.route(&#34;/&#34;)
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 6: &lt;/span&gt;def index():
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 7: &lt;/span&gt;    return &#34;hello&#34;
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 8: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt; 9: &lt;/span&gt;@app.route(&#39;/test/&amp;lt;some_data&amp;gt;&#39;)
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;10: &lt;/span&gt;def test():
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;11: &lt;/span&gt;    picture_url = build_url(some_data)
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;12: &lt;/span&gt;    result = api_test(picture_url)
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;13: &lt;/span&gt;    do_something(result)
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;14: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;15: &lt;/span&gt;if __name__ == &#34;__main__&#34;:
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;16: &lt;/span&gt;   app.debug = True
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;17: &lt;/span&gt;   app.secret_key = &#34;some secret key&#34;
&lt;span class=&#34;linenr&#34;&gt;18: &lt;/span&gt;   app.run(host=&#34;0.0.0.0&#34;, port=8000)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
First, the &#34;easy&#34; one. The student was trying to deploy the
application. We use &lt;a href=&#34;http://gunicorn.org/&#34;&gt;Green Unicorn&lt;/a&gt; to deploy our applications,
ultimately on &lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalocean.com/&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; servers in the cloud.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The student was using the correct command:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-shell&#34;&gt;gunicorn -W 4 -b 0.0.0.0:8000 app:app
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
but it wasn&#39;t working. It ran, but whenever he went to the site, it
came back with an error.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He had to change:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;if __name__ == &#34;__main__&#34;:
app.debug = True
app.secret_key = &#34;some secret key&#34;
app.run(host=&#34;0.0.0.0&#34;, port=8000)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
to
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;app.secret_key = &#34;some secret key&#34;
if __name__ == &#34;__main__&#34;:
app.debug = True
app.run(host=&#34;0.0.0.0&#34;, port=8000)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Normally, when developing and testing our applications, we use the
test server that&#39;s bundled with Flask. The line that reads
&#34;app.run&amp;#x2026;&#34; takes care of this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When running the application as a &#34;main program&#34; - &#34;python app.py&#34; the
if statement is true and it runs the indented lines, setting the
secret key which is required for session management.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When running under &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;gunicorn&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;gunicorn&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; server loads the
application as a module and then runs it. In this case name isn&#39;t main
so it never sets secret key and so we have a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Pretty subtle and even though we did cover this in class, it comes up
pretty rarely so it&#39;s not an easy catch.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there was this problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The setup for this one&#39;s a little more complicated. The group was
using a facial recognition api. You provide the API with the url to an
image, it fetches it and does recognition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s also important to note that when Flask is running, it will serve
files from a static directory, so, if I&#39;m running my flask server on
myhost, port 800 and you stored an image named picture.jpg in the
static directory, going to:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;verbatim&gt;
http://myhost:8000/static/picture.jpg
&lt;/verbatim&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
would get that image.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The group did things right. They ran the Flask test server to serve
the static files and then wrote a small python program to test the
api:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;picture_url = build_url(some_data)
result = api_test(picture_url)
do_something(result)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Everything worked fine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But, when they put this code in as a route in their web app (as in the
top code fragment), it froze.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They couldn&#39;t figure it out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The code worked as a &#34;stand alone&#34; but not in the web app.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once again, the built in Flask development server.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The development server runs in a single thread / process. This means
it can only do one thing at a time. When they ran their test as a
separate program, the api they used made a request to their app to
serve up the static picture file and it worked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When they ran from the Flask application itself, their app made a call
to the web api (line 12) and then blocked while waiting for the
response. The web api tried to request the image from the Flask app
but it was blocked &amp;#x2013; &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;deadlock&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Again, the solution was to run the web app using a server that could
handle multiple requests - gunicorn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once again, that solved the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both of these problems were fairly subtle and very hard to catch -
even with experience. I remember the hours I lost when I was learning
this stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some times kids get caught up in algorithms or poor code design but
sometimes, it&#39;s just the tools.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cellular Automata for Pathfinding in NetLogo</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-17-maze-ca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-17-maze-ca/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;link href=&#34;//cdn.rawgit.com/noelboss/featherlight/1.3.5/release/featherlight.min.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;//cdn.rawgit.com/noelboss/featherlight/1.3.5/release/featherlight.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
.smaller {height:200px;width:200px}

.center {text-align:center;}
.frame {width:600px;height:800px;}

&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;center&#34; href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-start.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-start.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-orgheadline1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;orgheadline1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-orgheadline1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/2016/01/15/shift-image.html#.Vpvy4x8SrmE&#34;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt; we took a look at implementing a Cellular Automaton in
NetLogo to do some simple image manipulation. We just scratched the
surface. In class, the kids write pretty nice Photoshop Light
applications.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we&#39;ll look at some more ambitious problem solving - using a
Cellular Automaton to find a path through a maze.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-orgheadline2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;orgheadline2&#34;&gt;Part 1 - finding possible paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-orgheadline2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ll use the image above as an example and a live model with all the
code is at the end of this post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each square of the maze is a
NetLogo patch. White square represent possible paths, Red is our
entrance, green our exit. As we explore the maze, we&#39;ll color the
cells yellow.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Remember, in  a Cellular Automaton (CA), each cell makes a decision as to
it&#39;s next state based on information about its neighbors (up, down,
left, and right only in this case).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if every cell is looking around at it&#39;s neighbors, most cells
don&#39;t have enough information. The only white cell that might be on
the path from entrance to exit is the one next to the entrance - it
might be on the path.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This leads us to the first step of our CA rule set:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-netlogo&#34;&gt;; if I have a green neighbor, I might be on the path, turn yellow
ask patches with [pcolor = white] [
if any? neighbors with [pcolor = red] [
set pcolor yellow
]
]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(click images to enlarge)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-1.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-1.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next time through, we notice that a cell might be on the path if it&#39;s
white and it has either red or yellow neighbors.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-2.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-2.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-3.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-3.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-4.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-4.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Eventually, we end up with a yellow abutting green - the exit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-found.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-found.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Notice that each yellow cell is also numbered. The number indicates
how many steps it took to get there from the entrance. The
implementation is trivial:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start by giving each patch a variable &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;step&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and starting it at 0.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a cell is about to turn yellow, it should look at it&#39;s yellow
or red neighbors, ask for their &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;step&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; value (they&#39;ll all be the
same - think about why), and set it&#39;s &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;step&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; value to one more
than that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ll use these step numbers to recover the actual shortest path.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-orgheadline3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;orgheadline3&#34;&gt;Part 2 - recovering the shortest path.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-orgheadline3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can now use the yellow patches with the step numbers to find our
way back.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;re going to build a solution set.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&#34;org-ol&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;start with an empty solution set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take the only green cell not in the solution set (let&#39;s call it &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;G&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;G&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&#39;s yellow neighbor with lowest step number to turn
itself green (that cell will be &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;G&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; next time around).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;G&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; into the solution set (leaving the new green cell as
the only green cell not in the solution set).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat 2 - 5 until we&#39;re back at the entrance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;



&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-back-1.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-back-1.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-back-2.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-back-2.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; data-featherlight=&#34;/img/maze-ca/maze-solved.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;smaller&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze-solved.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is one of my favorite intro topics. It&#39;s using a CA - something
normally just presented as a toy idea, to solve a real problem. It
reinforces parallel processing and foreshadows all sorts of pathfinding
ideas to come.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Below is the complete NetLogo program. You can look at the code by
clicking on the code tab at the bottom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To run:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;setup&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; sets up all the variables and clears the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;buildmaze&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; builds a random maze.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;solve&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; is a toggle to run through an entire solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;step&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; single steps through the CA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;reset&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Resets all the variables and recolors the maze to
unsolved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The other buttons are toggles for drawing your own maze.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;center frame&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&#34;center frame&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/maze-ca/maze.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cellular Automata, NetLogo and real problems</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-15-shift-image/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-15-shift-image/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
.center {text-align:center;}
.frame {width:640px;height:800px;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;https://ccl.northwestern.edu/netlogo/&#34;&gt;NetLogo&lt;/a&gt; in our intro course for years. It&#39;s a
wonderful programming environment. Many of you recall the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logo_(programming_language)&#34;&gt;Logo&lt;/a&gt;
programming language. NetLogo is like Logo but instead of programming
a turtle, you write a program that&#39;s run by multiple, perhaps hundreds
of turtles and also by the world the turtles live on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of the reasons we like it are that it&#39;s:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An easy accessible textual programming language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Makes building a graphical interface trivial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;great for modeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comes with tons of demo models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And now, with the latest version, NetLogo programs/models can be
deployed as web sites. All you have to do is save your program as
&#34;NetLogo Web&#34; and put it up on a observer somewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you haven&#39;t you should download and install NetLogo, run it, then
go to the file menu and look at the built in models.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also enjoy playing with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cellular_automaton&#34;&gt;Cellular Automata&lt;/a&gt; and NetLogo&#39;s a wonderful
platform to play with. The turtles live on a grid of patches and just
like the turtles, the patches will all run your program over and over.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The patches make perfect cells for a cellular automaton and you can
implement a rule set in your patches.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
NetLogo even comes with a bunch of built in demo models for Cellular
Automata including &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life&#34;&gt;Conway&#39;s Game of Life&lt;/a&gt;, probably the most famous CA.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, Conway&#39;s Game of Life is somewhat cliche and while
I find it fascinating, it doesn&#39;t really solve a practical problem, at
least on on the surface.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I was looking for something more practical to do and something
where we could explore some deeper CS concepts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Image manipulation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In class, we make a Cellular Automaton where each cell or patch is a
pixel in an image. In NetLogo, you can do this with the
&#34;import-pcolors&#34; command. Lower down, I have a demo that just manually
colors patches - the web version of NetLogo doesn&#39;t yet support that
command.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Task 1 - what if we want to shift the image over? The kids come up
with a solution pretty quickly: &#34;We can just have each patch ask its
neighbor for its color.&#34; Here&#39;s the code they try:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-netlogo&#34;&gt;; ask each patch to set its color to the color of the
; patch at relative location -1,0
to shift-naive
ask patches [ set pcolor [pcolor] of patch-at -1 0]
end
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To see what happens, scroll down to the NetLogo model below, click on
setup and then hit the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;shift-naive&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; button a few times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It doesn&#39;t work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What&#39;s going on?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s a synchronization issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Suppose we have the following three cells in a row:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/shift-image/image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;image1.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If cell 3 asks cell 2 it&#39;s color before cell 2 asks cell 1&#39;s color, we
get the desired result:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/shift-image/image2.png&#34; alt=&#34;image2.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But if cell 2 asks cell 1 for it&#39;s color first then cell 3 will
actually get cell 1&#39;s color:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/shift-image/image3.png&#34; alt=&#34;image3.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So now we have the students thinking about synchronization and
parallel processing and they don&#39;t even know it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The solution&#39;s pretty easy, break the problem up into two steps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, have every patch ask its neighbor for its color and then once
everyone knows their neighbor&#39;s color, then change:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-html&#34;&gt;patches-own [next-color]

to shift-correct
; figure out my next color
ask patches [ set next-color [pcolor] of patch-at -1 0 ]
; then switch to it
ask patches [ set pcolor next-color]
end
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can run that by clicking &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;setup&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; again and then &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;shift-correct&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; a
few times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There&#39;s some of the beauty of NetLogo - we can get kids to think about
some deep concepts while playing with an easy to use, fun, interactive
environment with a real textual programming language.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stay tuned for part 2 when I&#39;ll talk about creating a cellular
automaton that can solve a maze.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;center frame&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&#34;center frame&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/shift-image/shift-image.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Coding - getting beyond superficial syntax</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-01-different-languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-01-different-languages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day, Alfred Thompson put up a piece about &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/12/code-in-different-languages.html&#34;&gt;coding in multiple
languages&lt;/a&gt;. Alfred references a post written last May by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robunderwood.com/2015/05/31/code-syntax-compared-part-1/%0A&#34;&gt;Rob Underwood.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both pieces are worth a look.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rob is trying to illustrate many of the superficial similarities in
popular languages.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the comments on Alfred&#39;s blog, both Alfred and I alluded to coding
in an appropriate style for the language.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For me the issue is even bigger.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Learning to code is all the rage and places to learn are popping out of
the woodwork.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In classes, in schools, with teachers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drop in programs in schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programs run by coding schools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moocs and other online resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer and weekend programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And probably more. All of these options are giving more and more
people a way to learn to code.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&#39;s great, but it also raises concerns given that very few people
involved in CS education have both strong teaching and CS backgrounds.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I&#39;m starting to see are the results as I meet young people coming
out of all of these programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, what I&#39;m frequently seeing, at best, is very
superficial coverage of syntax.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve seen kids who would have no basis for understanding that the
ramifications of this Python code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;a = 30
def f():
a=20
print a

print a
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and this Javascript code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-javascript&#34;&gt;a = 30;
function f(){
a = 20
console.log(a);
}
console.log(a);
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
are very different.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It gets worse when I meet kids who &#34;know C&#34; because they were exposed
to constructs like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-c&#34;&gt;for (i=0;i&amp;lt;10;i++){
// code goes here
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think the most common issue come from kids being &#34;taught&#34;
programming using javascript which seems deceptively simple but is
really rather deep.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s important that as CS becomes more mainstream that we make sure
that we have teachers and programs that are teaching the real deal. It
can be fun and accessible but it does require teachers that know their
stuff and are willing to continue to learn.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Do our kids deserve any less?
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code - because I&#39;m an idiot</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/advent/advent.png&#34; alt=&#34;advent.png&#34; width=&#34;480px&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish our kids believed us when we tell them that we have the same
programming troubles as they do. We stare at code for hours not seeing
problems that could be a simple as passing the wrong value. We spend
an inordinate amount of time trying to see the problem and then
realize that we just forgot something silly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At this point, it&#39;s common for us CS teachers to tell each other &#34;I
figured out the problem I was having &amp;#x2013; it&#39;s that I was an idiot.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last time, I talked about &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; and how I was somewhat behind
the curve. In part because I started late and in part because I&#39;ve
been using it as an excuse to learn some Clojure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here&#39;s how I burned over two days on &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com/day/6&#34;&gt;Day 6&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem is pretty straight forward. You have a 1,000 x 1,000 grid
representing a light board and you have to repeatedly do operations on
smaller rectangles on that grid. Turning individual lights on and off,
if you would.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I were doing this in a language like C, I&#39;d probably just take a
big block of memory and loop through the instructions but since I was
working in Clojure, I thought I&#39;d try to do something in more of the
functional mode, that is, with immutable data types.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a while, I was getting the feeling that it was going to be too
slow so I shifted to just modifying a big block of memory.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Try as I could, I couldn&#39;t get it to work. I was sure my algorithm was
fine - it wasn&#39;t a hard problem, but I couldn&#39;t get the right answer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a while, I started looking at existing solutions and they were
basically the same as mine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was stumped.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Two days after the start, I figured it out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No matter how hard you try, if your problem specifies the data in the
form &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;row1,col1 row2,col2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, you&#39;re not going to get the right answer
if you decide that the input is in the form &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;row1,row2 col1,col2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;D&#39;Oh&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ok, after that the problem was pretty trivial.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hopefully I&#39;ll have some time to do problem 7 and beyond this weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If there are any Clojure people out there, I&#39;m putting my solutions up
on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/adventofcodeclojure&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; - I&#39;d love some feedback on how to get more idiomatic.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Other People&#39;s Code</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-11-other-peoples-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-11-other-peoples-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-orgheadline1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;orgheadline1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-orgheadline1&#34;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The coding on their project is reminiscent in many ways of an Ed
Sheerhan song. It left me in tears and very confused as to what the
author was trying to accomplish.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#x2013; a student commenting on their most recent project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-orgheadline2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;orgheadline2&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-orgheadline2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had some fun last week. Well, OK, I had some fun. The SoftDev
classes had just finished a little project. Basically, a blogging
platform. Something that would tie together all the tools we&#39;ve been
using. Flask, user management, an SQL database (SQLite), and a nice
looking front end.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was also the first real group project so the teams have started to
learn how to work together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After some project demos, it was time for part two: NOSQL. We explored
MongoDB and then it was time for the project - clean up the
previous project through the use of techniques like template
inheritance and convert the database backend to MongoDB.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The catch? Each group would take another groups project and use that
as their starter code. The rules? They could modify and refactor but
they couldn&#39;t rewrite.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It threw the groups for a loop but I ultimately think they had
fun with this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards each group gave a write up to their starter group. What
made their life easier, what made it harder. We then circled up for
discussion as a class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was terrific.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, it was great that we&#39;ve gotten to a point where everyone feels
comfortable giving each other constructive criticism. We&#39;ve gotten to
the point where the class is a team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Beyond that, I&#39;m hoping that everyone got a lot out of the exercise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As each group talked, common themes arose:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consistent commenting is good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;variable names matter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unused code and files can be misleading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overall code structure, file names, and locations are important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and much more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;re now going to start a discussion of coding style, standards, and
documentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve got to say that I&#39;m very happy how this little experiment worked
out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview questions and tests</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-04-tests-and-interviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-04-tests-and-interviews/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The StuyCS Family mailing list was host to an interesting discussion
today. One of our younger members asked if the practice of giving
technical problems during an interview was going to follow him
throughout his career or if it goes away for more senior applicants.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An interesting discussion followed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It reminded me of a time I was talking to a few senior engineers at a
large tech company. A couple of younger engineers were with us along
with a new hire. The youngsters started talking about the new hires
technical interview questions. One older engineer light heartedly
asked another &#34;I don&#39;t recall any tricky technical questions, how
about you?&#34; &#34;I don&#39;t recall any either&amp;#x2026;&#34; and on around the table.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course these senior engineers had track records that stretched for
miles.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never liked those tech interview questions. If you just took
algorithms, you&#39;ve got an edge and it really seems to be more of a
test of &#34;have you seen this problem before&#34; rather than a true test of
ability.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I much prefer those few companies that give &#34;take home assignments&#34; or
use other ways to determine fit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The tech interview reminds me of the pop quiz or a poorly designed
test. If you just ask the question that the kid doesn&#39;t get, the kid&#39;s
in trouble. A kid could know how to handle 90% of the work but if the
question is that last 10%, zero credit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As teachers, we end up using many forms of assessment and try to
develop an overall picture of a student.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Companies should try to do the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why to companies still use these technical interview questions?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Quite simply because they can.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A company might miss out on a number of great candidates by using a
bad technical question but they will probably get at least a
reasonably strong hire that passes the test. For the company, mission
accomplished.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As teachers, we can&#39;t do that. I&#39;m not given a class of 32 kids and
asked to pull out a couple of software engineers. As teachers, we&#39;re
supposed to pull everyone along.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Alda on Teaching Science</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-20-alda/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-20-alda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scale, scale, scale. Scripted lessons. Online resources, Moocs. No
excuses schools. All of these are modern trends in education. None of
these are about good education. It&#39;s really demoralizing reading
article after article devaluing true master teachers and real
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, last night was a real pleasure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I attended a talk, given by Alan Alda on communicating science. The
talk was sponsored by &lt;a href=&#34;http://academyforteachers.org/&#34;&gt;The Academy for Teachers&lt;/a&gt;. I grew up watching
Hawkeye on MASH and more recently Arnold Vinick on The West Wing but
Mr. Alda has really been keeping himself busy in the world of
education. Check out what he&#39;s doing at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.centerforcommunicatingscience.org/&#34;&gt;Alan Alda Center for
Communicating Science&lt;/a&gt; at Stony Brook University.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At it&#39;s core, Mr. Alda&#39;s talk was about teaching. Making a connection
with your students and engaging them. The exact opposite of many of
the current ed reform trends.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mr. Alda talked about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.centerforcommunicatingscience.org/the-flame-challenge-2/&#34;&gt;the Flame Challenge&lt;/a&gt; where he challenged
scientists to teach 11 year olds all about &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Chemical_History_of_a_Candle&#34;&gt;a candle&lt;/a&gt; without dumbing it
down. Communication.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He also talked about story telling. At one point he had a volunteer
from the audience carry a glass across the stage. He then had her do
it again, but this time with a full glass telling her &#34;if you spill a
drop everyone in your village will die.&#34; The difference in audience
attention was striking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mr. Alda also talked about using improvisational games to help
students open up as well as about &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curse_of_knowledge&#34;&gt;the curse of knowledge.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of my favorite parts of the talk was when an audience member asked
for a few teaching tips. He replied that he hates tips because out of
context, without the connection to the class, they&#39;re
meaningless. Mr. Alda used as an example:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Imagine that you&#39;re about to give a piano recital at Carnegie Hall
and you asked for a few tips.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you&#39;ve never played before, those tips aren&#39;t going to help you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m asked for CS teaching tips all the time, and Mr. Alda very much
captured my feelings on the subject. My friend and Colleague Jim
Cocoros also captured the feeling when he reminded me that the only
&#34;tip&#34; he gives new teachers is &#34;be yourself.&#34; I couldn&#39;t agree more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a delightful and a refreshing evening. I very much appreciate
and admire what Mr. Alda is doing beyond his acting and while I very
much hope he&#39;s able to extend his reach to more high school teachers
as he continues to work on communicating in science.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking under the hood</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-17-under-the-hood/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-17-under-the-hood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just had an interesting conversation with &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisgrant.co/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt;, one of our &lt;a href=&#34;http://cstuy.org/&#34;&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;
mentors. Chris is working with one of our more advanced groups of
hackers - they&#39;ll be creating a web based app that with ultimately be
deployed as mobile using &lt;a href=&#34;http://phonegap.com/&#34;&gt;PhoneGap&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The question he had was &#34;&lt;a href=&#34;http://angularjs.org/&#34;&gt;Angular.js&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://backbonejs.org/&#34;&gt;Backbone.js&lt;/a&gt;.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Chris and I have had this conversation before. I was explaining at the
time why I preferred to use Backbone.js over Angular in my SoftDev
classes. Part of the reason is that the current version of Angular is
already deprecated while the new version isn&#39;t ready for prime time
yet. This means I&#39;d be teaching to a dead end. More importantly, Angular
is a much higher level framework than Backbone. There&#39;s a lot of
&#34;magic&#34; going on. Just a few short lines of code and you&#39;re done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Backbone is much closer to the metal. It does less work for you so it
let&#39;s me drill down with the kids all the way to the source. This way
the kids understand what&#39;s going on under the hood. As my buddy &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/gerryseidman&#34;&gt;Gerry&lt;/a&gt;
says, &#34;never use a tool you couldn&#39;t write yourself.&#34; I personally
like low level tools like Backbone.js. If you have to get a job
done quickly, it might not be the right tool, but for teaching,
it&#39;s terrific.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think Chris was surprised when I said that a higher level tool like
Angular could very well be appropriate for our Saturday Hackers and
that I&#39;d certainly support whichever direction Chris wanted to go in
with his team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why  might it be right in this case?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mostly because the hackers only meet once a week. In our Saturday
sessions, we want our kids to learn, but we also need to create an
environment where they can continue to progress on their
projects. Some times, compromise is needed. Angular will let them get
up and running within the constraints of our program and the hackers
will still learn a lot, particularly with people like Chris mentoring them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&#39;s the balance we strive to achieve - a good amount of real CS but
tempered with the realities of a once a week program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We could go the way of many other CS programs out there and
just use tools that do 90% of the work but we like to think we have a
higher standard and I think that&#39;s what makes our team of teachers and
mentors special.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grading Autograders</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-16-graders/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-16-graders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day codehs made an announcement about their new
&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/codehs-product-updates/these-are-the-autograders-you-ve-been-looking-for-bda0fa8fd8a&#34;&gt;autograder&lt;/a&gt;. Fellow CS Teaching veteran Alfred Thompson had his say up
on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/10/autogradersfor-good-or-for-evil.html&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; where he talked about &lt;a href=&#34;https://computinged.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s comment on
autograders leading to less creative assignments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I very much agree that autograders, due to their rigidness lend
themselves to less creative projects, but thought I&#39;d write up a few
of my own thoughts on autograders.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost, &lt;b&gt;I HATE GRADING&lt;/b&gt;. It&#39;s one of the worst parts of
my job and grading projects is &lt;b&gt;really&lt;/b&gt; hard to do well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You&#39;d think an autograder would be a panacea.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In addition to them being very nit-picky &amp;#x2013; got an extra space in your
output? &lt;b&gt;FAIL&lt;/b&gt;. Wrong number of significant digits? &lt;b&gt;FAIL&lt;/b&gt;. Didn&#39;t
handle all those &#34;trick&#34; cases? &lt;b&gt;FAIL&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since autograders typically check your output against a correct
solution, it&#39;s going to be limited in what it can grade right and
wrong and what&#39;s more, it&#39;s very limited in the feedback it can give.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These are some of the limitations that lead to less creative
projects but that&#39;s not my beef with the autograders.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why do we give assignments? To assess students? Yes, but also to
inform our instruction. We need to grade the assignments ourselves
because those assignments tell us about our students and teach us how
best to work with them. What&#39;s more, we really don&#39;t just want to see
that finished product, but rather, we want to see the process as
well. Autograders can&#39;t help here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do use autograders &amp;#x2013; &lt;a href=&#34;http://codingbat.com/&#34;&gt;codingbat.com&lt;/a&gt; and our own locally developed
&lt;a href=&#34;http://bert.stuy.edu/pbrooks/SchemingBat/scheming.py&#34;&gt;Scheming Bat.&lt;/a&gt; I use them for small homeworks and class assignments
early on. For bigger stuff, I do it myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For advanced classes (AP and beyond) we&#39;re all about the GitHub. Not
only can I grab the projects at any time but I can also see how
projects were developed - logs, diffs, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vynl/vynl-v0/graphs/contributors&#34;&gt;graphs&lt;/a&gt;. All give me insight
into how the students working. Add in class lab time when I get to
interact with the kids and I&#39;ve got a good sense of my student
computer scientists.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In our intro courses, where they&#39;re not ready for GitHub, we use
Dropbox for sharing and collecting assignments. Not quite as good but
we can still see a lot.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, if a teacher doesn&#39;t look at a student&#39;s work
directly, a teacher isn&#39;t going to know everything there is to know
about a student. I can&#39;t imagine a top English teacher not reading a
student&#39;s essays. We&#39;re no different.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s time consuming and generally no fun but it&#39;s a big part of &lt;b&gt;real&lt;/b&gt;
education.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting kids up to fail - CS edition</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-17-setting-up-to-fail-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-17-setting-up-to-fail-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We talked about setting kids up to fail in math. What about CS?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, it&#39;s a little subtler.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started thinking about this after a conversation with one of my
graduates about Harvard&#39;s famous CS50. Since that conversation, I&#39;ve
spoken to a number of my kids that have gone through CS50 and most
seem to say the same things:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don&#39;t really teach anything
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The kids rely on a group member who already knows stuff or will
learn all the stuff on their own
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it weren&#39;t for my StuyCS background my group would have really
struggled.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and things like that. I was then told that after CS50 kids go on to
Functional Programming in OCAML and they drop like flies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Doesn&#39;t sound like a recipe for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;re seeing this at multiple levels and we&#39;re seeing it because very
few places seem to have a plan. A multi year path taking kids from
start to finish. It&#39;s something we&#39;ve done and I&#39;m proud of it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that if we look carefully, we&#39;ll start to see what my
graduates reported happening more and more. Traditional CS sequences
can be pretty unforgiving and unless colleges put in a sensible ramp
up and recognize that not all CS and related majors should go on to
grad school we&#39;re going to have a high rate of kids initially thinking
that CS is for them and then dropping. I do suspect it will get better as colleges
recognize that there&#39;s more than one type of CS major.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It will be interesting to see what happens on the high school
level. Will we see what we&#39;ve seen in math - two years on the first
level course then dump the kids into something like APCS A or will we
see something more sensible?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Where this really gets me is with all those after school and summer
programs. One give away is when a program claims &#34;learn to &lt;span class=&#34;underline&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;underline&#34;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in 4
weeks,&#34; &#34;our kids learn more than in an AP class&#34;, or something similar.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My team and I have had to &#34;rescue&#34; kids from a number of
them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These programs take a number of forms:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using simplified environments that export to mobile
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gluing together libraries with minimal code
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working with an extreme amount of coaching in a short period of
time.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, none of these things are necessarily bad but so many of these
programs are designed and run by non-educators.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, the kids go through the programs, think they know the real deal,
and are hammered when they enroll in a real CS class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve seen it happen. There was even an article a couple of years ago
which then went on to blame the teacher in spite of the fact that the
program boasts that thier kids &#34;learned more than in APCS.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, all these programs have to do is make sure the kids make
something exciting and that they&#39;re happy. There&#39;s no real
accountability and the guy at the next level will shoulder the blame.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So there you have it, setting kids up to fail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s something I think we&#39;ll have to be more aware of and on guard for
as CS becomes more mainstream.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shipping a product</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-19-shipping-product/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-19-shipping-product/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in April, I was at the second annual &#34;Dream It, Code It, Win It!&#34;
awards. Some of our kids had submitted work and were selected as
awardees in the high school division.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was great to see &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Cahnja&#34;&gt;Jack&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davcahn&#34;&gt;David&lt;/a&gt; Cahn there. Jack and David were
both members of winning high school teams last year and they were back
as college winners this time around.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was great to see them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Cahn brothers spent some time talking to the current crop. They
mentioned one thing that really confirmed that I&#39;ve been on the right
track with my SoftDev class - they said it was their most valuable
experiece at Stuy because they learned how to ship a product. To take
something, as a team, from idea to delivery with all the bumps along
the way. Now, obviously, we don&#39;t do everything - there are no
questions of funding for instance and I think we cover a lot of great
CS but giving the kids a chance to learn to take a project from idea
to delivery and all that entails was a big part of the design of the
course.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With that in mind, I just finished evaluating projects and here&#39;s a
sampling:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-2&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Stuy kids live all over the city. Nadia, Aida, and Sydney solved the
problem of where to meet your friends when you live on opposite sides
of town:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/i_xDQg35T20&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-2-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sec-2-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34; id=&#34;text-2-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live demo: &lt;a href=&#34;http://meetup.jumpingcrab.com/&#34;&gt;http://meetup.jumpingcrab.com/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/apiccato/meetup&#34;&gt;https://github.com/apiccato/meetup&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Miranda, Leslia, and Anya built a Chrome plugin and server to
summarize articles:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pvRf7fPlV6Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-3-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sec-3-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34; id=&#34;text-3-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Server: &lt;a href=&#34;http://104.236.53.73/&#34;&gt;http://104.236.53.73/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chrome plugin: &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/dmbibehpblbnkacpmiecigdkcomfkhkm/&#34;&gt;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/dmbibehpblbnkacpmiecigdkcomfkhkm/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mchaiken/summarize&#34;&gt;https://github.com/mchaiken/summarize&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-4&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and Philipp, Richard, Steve, and Ziwei created an anonymous author
attribution system:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XksrKfxEprg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-4-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sec-4-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34; id=&#34;text-4-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/I-A-I/authorensics&#34;&gt;https://github.com/I-A-I/authorensics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-5&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not a SoftDev project, but for good measure, here&#39;s Natan and
Angelika&#39;s Ballroom Dance project - apparently they&#39;re the first two
to actually do a SONG and dance and they&#39;ve both got the pipes:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_xjHFdrJ4jQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were lots of other great projects all up on github:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/student-work-spring-2015&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/student-work-spring-2015&lt;/a&gt; albeit in a
rather disorganized form.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So proud of the work they all did this year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jazz Hands!!!!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-11-jazz-hands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-11-jazz-hands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/jazz-hands/jazzhands.gif&#34; alt=&#34;jazzhands.gif&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The StuyCS Semi Formal, Clyde &#34;Thluffy&#34; Sinclair, and other assorted
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/2015/03/08/antother-day-stuycs.html#.VXmHfN_08bw&#34;&gt;silliness&lt;/a&gt; - one of the reasons StuyCS is a family is that we try to
have fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Jazz Hands day was the latest.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I got the idea at JonAlf&#39;s wedding. The wait staff were all wearing
white gloves - all of a sudden it hit me - Jazz Hands!!!! and Jazz
Hands day was born.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of our Junior and Senior CS students, around 350 or so, along with
their teachers would wear white gloves on a specified day. The rules
were throughout the day, in any class, provided there were two or more
CS Jazz Hands students in the class, whenever:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a student gave a good thoughtful answer to a question
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or the teacher made a particularly strong point
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The kids would give a Jazz Hands salute.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Imagine, some kid gives a great answer and 1/3 of the class all of a
sudden does Jazz Hands!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/jazz-hands/jazzhands2.gif&#34; alt=&#34;jazzhands2.gif&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, this was an event that I wouldn&#39;t actually be able to
see as the havoc would be wreaked in other classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By the time we got to the end of the day, I knew we were on to
something.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Word on the street was that a bunch of teachers thought it was
hilarious. Apparently one teacher pulled the math chair into her class
so she could see.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then we had at least a few teachers that didn&#39;t get into the spirit
and actually lodged complaints.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let&#39;s see, we had students, via a non-verbal form of feedback,
indicate that they were totally engaged by acknowledging what they
felt was a good point.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Disruptive?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Imagine that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don&#39;t know what makes me want to fine tune this event more - the
positive feedback or the complaints.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
``
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking stock and tracking progress</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-11-taking-stock-self-assess/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-11-taking-stock-self-assess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When starting the spring semester, students are frequently a little
rusty. They just had a high intensity month of study, tests, and
projects. That was followed by a week of nothing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I like to start with something lightweight that gets them coding again
and ramps them up to speed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In SoftDev I started with a brief overview of the HTML5 canvas and
then gave them a small homework assignment to do something fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also remind the kids to self assess where they are and how they&#39;ve
developed as a programmer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I get a little tired of education &#34;experts&#34; espousing nonsense like you
have to have each talk each day or that you need to assess each kid
multiple times a period. That&#39;s nonsense. With 34 kids in a 40 minute
class and 150 kids a day, that doesn&#39;t fly. Besides, so many concepts
take time to develop, learn, and absorb.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yes, you can get some instant and short term feedback but a lot more
is revealed over time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m attaching a small sampling of their homework assignments. It was
basically a one day assignment to do something fun with the HTML5
canvas and indeed, it looks like they had fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I asked the kids to reflect on what they did now and what they could
do a semester, two, and three semesters ago.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the beginning they would have had no idea how to approach any of
these. A year ago, they would be a major project. Now, they can knock
these out as a homework assignment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once you take a step back to look at how much a student can grow in a
year or so you have to marvel at the results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At a place like Stuy, the kids frequently and unfairly judge themselves against
super prodigies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m hoping by looking back at what they could do then vs now they&#39;ll
appreciate how awesome they are.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All sources at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/submissions&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/submissions&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy&amp;#x2026;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unnumbered-1&#34;&gt;Chain reaction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unnumbered-2&#34;&gt;click to start the reaction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;unnumbered-3&#34;&gt;by Nadia and Sophie&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe height=600 width=&#34;80%&#34;
src=&#34;https://cdn.rawgit.com/stuycs-softdev/submissions/master/6/canvas/sophie-nadia/canvas.html&#34;
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unnumbered-4&#34;&gt;MakeOver Party&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unnumbered-5&#34;&gt;Take a picture and apply virtual makeup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-5&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;unnumbered-6&#34;&gt;by Veronika and Miranda&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-6&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe height=800 width=&#34;80%&#34;
src=&#34;https://cdn.rawgit.com/stuycs-softdev/submissions/master/7/canvas/miranda-veronika/canvas.html&#34;
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unnumbered-7&#34;&gt;3D Depth Perception Pong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-7&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unnumbered-8&#34;&gt;Follow the ball and keep it in the well&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-8&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-9&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;unnumbered-9&#34;&gt;by Natan&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-9&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe height=800 width=&#34;80%&#34;
src=&#34;https://cdn.rawgit.com/stuycs-softdev/submissions/master/6/canvas/NZamansky/index.html&#34;
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-10&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unnumbered-10&#34;&gt;Can&#39;t really describe this but I love it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-10&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-11&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unnumbered-11&#34;&gt;Use WASD to move DW around&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-12&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unnumbered-12&#34;&gt;by Fish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-12&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe height=800 width=&#34;80%&#34;
src=&#34;https://cdn.rawgit.com/stuycs-softdev/submissions/master/6/canvas/fishy/dyrlandland.html&#34;
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kids these days -- they don&#39;t know nuttin</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-15-kids-know-nuttin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-15-kids-know-nuttin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I took part in a round table discussion on Ed Tech and Tech
Ed, the latter being more, as they say, my wheelhouse. Afterwards a
few of us were chatting and a friend observed that when she first
started to talk to high school kids she was shocked that they really
didn&#39;t know the local tech players - neither names nor companies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, another friend was helping me organize an event for
high schoolers. He started to go down a list of well known tech names
and was surprised when I told him that the kids wouldn&#39;t know them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first time I experienced this, it was just as big a surprised to
me. I was setting up a big high school event at Foursquare (&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/2012/03/31/checking-in-with-family.html#.VLfzl9-c1CU&#34;&gt;post here&lt;/a&gt;)
and was shocked to learn that practically non of the attendees had
heard of the company.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This would never have been the case in the 90s or even the early
2000s. What happened?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have a theory.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don&#39;t think it&#39;s just due to the fact that CS is a hot subject
now. It was hot during the 90&#39;s bubble. I&#39;m sure the fact that a wider
range of kids are being exposed to CS is part of this phenomenon but
I don&#39;t think it&#39;s the biggest reason.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think CS kids back then knew more &amp;#x2013; more of the players, more of the
tools, more about the systems because they had to. In some ways, and I
know I&#39;m vastly overstating things, it&#39;s &#34;too easy&#34; now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back in the day, if you wanted to put your thoughts on line you had
to:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learn html
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maybe some PHP, Perl, or Python
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You probably had to learn a bit about hosting a server
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you had to deal with registering a domain name
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, you just go to blogger or tumblr.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back then, if you wanted to communicate, you had to learn how to learn
the dark art of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat&#34;&gt;irc&lt;/a&gt;, now you have Google chat.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back then, you want to share photos, you had to learn how to make a
gallery. Now, Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And of course the list goes on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even programming required that you know something about the filesystem
and the basics of working in an operating system. Now between IDEs
both local and cloud based, you can learn all about programming and
never actually create a stand alone program that operates outside of
the IDE sandbox.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back in the day, if a kid was into CS they had to learn more than
just the in class toolset and this in turn forced them to be in touch
with the tech community both products and players.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m not saying the &#34;good old days&#34; were in fact that good and I love
most of the progress we&#39;ve made. Just noting the cultural difference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It means we should pay more attention to educating our classes on tech
culture, the good, the bad, and the ugly.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Little details we take for granted</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-21-little-details/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-21-little-details/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unnumbered-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m getting ready for my AP classes this morning. We&#39;re building a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/2011/12/03/wheres-waldo-text-style.html#.VG8qtt-c2Ak&#34;&gt;word search generator&lt;/a&gt; and we&#39;re at the point where we need to read a
list of words from a file
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, I&#39;d better make sure I can do it. We&#39;re using the java
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;scanner&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, mostly because it&#39;s easy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First cut:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;wl&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;[] &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;) {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;words&#34;&lt;/span&gt;));
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; (sc.hasNext()){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; = sc.next();
System.out.println(s);
}
}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Oh yes, I forgot the
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
import java.io.*;
import java.util.*;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Oh, and also the fact that I&#39;ve got deal with exceptions when working
with files:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;words&#34;&lt;/span&gt;));
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; (sc.hasNext()){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; = sc.next();
System.out.println(s);
}
} &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;){
System.out.println(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;Can&#39;t open file.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;);
System.exit(0);
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But we don&#39;t want to wrap our entire program in an exception:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;words&#34;&lt;/span&gt;));
} &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;){
System.out.println(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;Can&#39;t open file.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;);
System.exit(0);
}

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; (sc.hasNext()){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; = sc.next();
System.out.println(s);

}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Now it doesn&#39;t work because the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Scanner sc&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; might not exist after the
try catch block (if an exception occurred), so we need:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; {
sc = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;words&#34;&lt;/span&gt;));
} &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;){
System.out.println(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;Can&#39;t open file.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;);
System.exit(0);
}

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; (sc.hasNext()){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; = sc.next();
System.out.println(s);

}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
And now this doesn&#39;t work because &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;sc&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; might not have a value so we
finally get to the working version:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ff00ff;&#34;&gt;java&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color: #ff00ff;&#34;&gt;io&lt;/span&gt;.*;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ff00ff;&#34;&gt;java&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span style=&#34;color: #ff00ff;&#34;&gt;util&lt;/span&gt;.*;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;publ&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;ic c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;lass&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;wl&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;[] &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;) {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ff00ff;&#34;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; {
sc = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Scanner&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;words&#34;&lt;/span&gt;));
} &lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;){
System.out.println(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;&#34;Can&#39;t open file.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;);
System.exit(0);
}
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ffff; font-weight: bold;&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; (sc.hasNext()){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ffff00;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; = sc.next();
System.out.println(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #00ff00;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;);

}
}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Really simple program but that&#39;s a long list of things that can go
wrong along the way. Nothing big, but each a stumbling block for a
beginning student that doesn&#39;t have the wealth of experience that
someone like me has.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had an interesting discussion with one of my seniors the other day
on this subject - all the base knowledge that experienced programmers
have that students don&#39;t and how we have to approach teaching so that
students are supported and not frustrated by these little but
important speed-bumps that they&#39;ll hit along the way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope to write more about this soon, but for now I&#39;ll leave you to
ponder the issue.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Complexity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-17-hidden-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-17-hidden-complexity/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve said it many times:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Never use a tool you couldn&#39;t write yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That is - make sure you understand what&#39;s going on under the hood.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In AP we&#39;ve been playing with ArrayLists. The problem for today?
Create an ArrayList with consecutive integers and then write a routine
that will randomize the ArrayList.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For example, you might start with this ArrayList:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
0,1,2,3,4,5
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and end up with
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
3,5,1,4,2,0
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First cut, the students grabbed a random element from the ArrayList,
removed it, and added it to the end of a new list. Then repeat until
the original list is empty and the new one is randomized. Then return
the list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;shuffle1&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;();
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; (l.size()&amp;gt;0){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; = rnd.nextInt(l.size());
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;v&lt;/span&gt; = l.remove(i);
result.add(v);
}
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; result;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looks good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Version two was much the same but after it removed a random value, it
added it to the end of the same ArrayList:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;shuffle2&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;();
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;=l.size();s&amp;gt;0;s--) {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; = rnd.nextInt(s);
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;v&lt;/span&gt; = l.remove(i);
l.add(v);
}
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; l;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then it was time to time. Both seemed pretty quick but as our data set
grew things seemed strange:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;c4&#34;&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;2&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;6&#34; rules=&#34;groups&#34; frame=&#34;hsides&#34;&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;left&#34; /&gt;

&lt;col  class=&#34;left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;100,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;2 seconds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;200,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;7 seconds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;400,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;26 seonds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;re just looping through an ArrayList, what&#39;s going on? When we
double the size of the list, it should just take double the time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since the class already wrote their own ArrayList implementation, they
were quick to realize that every time we removed an item from the
original Array, we were doing a linear or O(n) operation. That means
our algorithms, which look linear, are in fact O(N&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Can we do better? You bet. They just changed the remove and add to
using get and set. Instead off removing an item and re-inserting it,
just swap the randomly selected item with the last element:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;shuffle3&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;){
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;();
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;=l.size();s&amp;gt;0;s--) {
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; = rnd.nextInt(s);

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt; = l.get(i);
l.set(i, l.get(s-1));
l.set(s-1,tmp);
}
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; l;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No removes so no hidden linear component.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The run time?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;c4&#34;&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;2&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;6&#34; rules=&#34;groups&#34; frame=&#34;hsides&#34;&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;left&#34; /&gt;

&lt;col  class=&#34;left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;100,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;.15 seconds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;200,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;.16 seconds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;400,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;.17 seonds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In fact, it took data sets in the size of millions before we even
broke more than a couple of seconds.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The algorithm looks the same but understanding what goes on under the
hood can make a big difference.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forty minutes to the punch line or &#34;we&#39;ll never look at functions the same way again&#34;</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-12-decorators/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-12-decorators/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-unnumbered-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unnumbered-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-unnumbered-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How many times do we teach something and leave the kids thinking:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&#34;what&#39;s the point of this?&#34; &#34;When will I use this?&#34; or even just the
plain old fashioned &#34;that&#39;s weird.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s pretty cool when a lesson starts out that way but you get to the
payoff by the end of the class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we started exploring some advanced python.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We started by showing that you can assign functions to variables or
pass them as parameters:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;inc&lt;/span&gt;(x):
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; x+1
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;dec&lt;/span&gt;(x):
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; x-1

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; = inc
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; f(5)

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;flist&lt;/span&gt; = [inc,dec]

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; flist[1](5)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We then looked at closures in python:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;makeAdder&lt;/span&gt;(n):
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;inner&lt;/span&gt;(x):
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; x+n
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; inner

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;add3&lt;/span&gt; = makeAdder(3)
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;add5&lt;/span&gt; = makeAdder(5)

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; add3(10)
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; add5(10)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea that we can make a function that builds and returns a
function. When we call &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;makeAdder(3)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, the 3 is passed as parameter
n so the inner function reduces to &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;return x+3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and then we return
that inner function. When we later run it: add3(10) it adds
10+3. makeAdder(5) works similarly but passing a 5 in for n instead
of a 3.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even a somewhat clunky way of doing class type abstractions:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;make_counter&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;private &#34;instance&#34; data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;has to be a list due to weird python scoping rules&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; = [0]

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;public methods&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;inc&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;[0]=count[0]+1
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;dec&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;[0]=count[0]-1
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;reset&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;[0]=0
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; count[0]

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;send back a dictionary so we have access to all the methods&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; {&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;inc&#39;&lt;/span&gt;: inc, &lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;dec&#39;&lt;/span&gt;: dec, &lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;reset&#39;&lt;/span&gt;: reset, &lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;get&#39;&lt;/span&gt;: get}

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;c1&lt;/span&gt; = make_counter()
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;c2&lt;/span&gt; = make_counter()

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;we&#39;ve got to use the clunky list notation &lt;/span&gt;
c1[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;inc&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
c1[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;inc&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
c1[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;inc&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; c1[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;get&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
c2[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;inc&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; c2[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;get&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
c1[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;reset&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; c1[&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;get&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]()
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Up to now the students are able to see how this works but the why is
unclear.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So now we&#39;ll look at where this is useful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let&#39;s suppose we have routines like the following. It returns a
string:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; random
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;get_name&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;names&lt;/span&gt; = [&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;tom&#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;sue&#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;harry&#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;lisa&#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;sarah&#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#39;horatio&#39;&lt;/span&gt;]
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; random.choice(names)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
get&lt;sub&gt;name&lt;/sub&gt; and routines like it might be scattered throughout our
code. Let&#39;s suppose, for some strange reason, we want to double the
name every time we use it. A &#34;traditional&#34; way of doing this might be:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;dble&lt;/span&gt;(f):
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; = f()
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; name+name

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; dble(get_name) &lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;returns something like tomtom&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here, we pass a function which returns a string and then dble returns
that string repeated twice. The problem here is that if we&#39;ve got
get&lt;sub&gt;name&lt;/sub&gt; all over our code base, we have to find it and change each
instance to &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;dble(get&lt;sub&gt;name&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What if we write it as a function that returns a function:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;doubler&lt;/span&gt;(f):
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;inner&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;=f()
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; name+name
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; inner
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, in this case, we can do something like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;make a new function that wraps get_name in &#34;inner&#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;when we call inner, it returns the string twice&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; = doubler(get_name)
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;and then later&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; f() &lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;will print something like tomtom&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The cool part is that we can also do this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a0522d;&#34;&gt;get_name&lt;/span&gt; = double(get_name)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And then whenever we call our new &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;get&lt;sub&gt;name&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; we end up calling the
wrapped function.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was the first A-ha. We don&#39;t have to change get&lt;sub&gt;name&lt;/sub&gt; all over our
code base - we only have to change it once.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once we write a function like doubler, instead of re-assigning
get&lt;sub&gt;name&lt;/sub&gt; as we did above, we can do the following:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;@doubler&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;get_name&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #b22222;&#34;&gt;rest of code as defined above&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span style=&#34;color: #228b22;&#34;&gt;@doubler&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0000ff;&#34;&gt;demo&lt;/span&gt;():
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #8b2252;&#34;&gt;&#34;hello&#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The second example will have demo return &#34;hellohello&#34; whenever we
invoke it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A Python decorator is merely shorthand for calling a wrapper type
function like doubler.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was the second A-ha moment &amp;#x2013; we can write functions that
transform functions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ll cover more decorator and closure plumbing tomorrow and then
start doing some fun stuff with these concepts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wait, I know that!!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-23-i-know-that/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-23-i-know-that/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I&#39;m doing my job right, by the time my kids graduate they can learn
on their own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s like when two years ago, before starting her summer internship,
Batya listed all the tools and technologies she had to work with. When
I pointed out that she hadn&#39;t ever used any of them before and asked
how she was going to deal with it, she replied &#34;I&#39;ll figure it out.&#34;
And she did.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the summer, Dina told a similar story about her
internship and how she knew she&#39;d figure everything out because of the
solid background she got by going through StuyCS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I loved both these stories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But getting the kids there takes time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, in my AP classes, I assigned three &lt;i&gt;codingbat&lt;/i&gt; problems. I
decided to go objects first this time round so we haven&#39;t done any
language constructs. The problems were simple String manipulations but
I added one that needed conditionals.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we went over them. Most of the class solved the assignment and
most had either no trouble or had to do just a little work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I asked what about that last problem might have caused some
difficulty.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They couldn&#39;t figure it out, it seemed pretty straighforward. After a
number of guesses, one student  said:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&#34;Wait, we don&#39;t know ifs&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That was it. They didn&#39;t realize that they had taught themselves
something new.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This, of course, doesn&#39;t just happen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They&#39;ve seen conditionals in all sorts of guises.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scheme:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-scheme&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; boolean_expression
True_part
False_part)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
NetLogo:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;example&#34;&gt;
if boolean [True part]

and

ifelse boolean [True part][ False part]
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and Python:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;org-src-container&#34;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #483d8b;&#34;&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt;:
s1
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;elif&lt;/span&gt; bool2:
s2
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #a020f0;&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
s3
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and so on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So they new the concept, from there it was just details.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some said they just wrote it and it worked. Some said they looked up
sample code. Most didn&#39;t think they were doing anything new.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was pretty awesome.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s still a long road before they graduate, but we&#39;re getting there.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - Outreach</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-20-ship-outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-20-ship-outreach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;



&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ve got a few more topics to cover in the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Building a SHIP&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
series. We still have to cover:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Crew
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curricular Choices
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The long term plan
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Site and funding
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-2&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But for today, we&#39;ll talk outreach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Outreach proved to be particular challenge for SHIP. Our entire crew
is made up of teachers. That meant that we couldn&#39;t communicate with
schools during business hours. That made things particularly tough.  I
could send emails after hours or set up emails to be sent at specific
times during the day, but we couldn&#39;t call while at our day jobs. As a
result, this led to a vary long communication loop and we could never
be sure that information about SHIP was getting to the right people.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We did have a small number of non-teacher volunteers and they were
invaluable but they had limited knowledge from the teaching side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we had the volunteers try to call schools during the day and we
followed up by emailing a flyer and link to a web site. We tried to
emphasize that we needed help from the schools in finding the right
students &amp;#x2013; that is students who might not have even considered
something like SHIP but where we could potentially turn them on to
something new.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of this, we did get over 200 applicants for our 48 slots. I
have no idea how this compares to similar programs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-4&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were many terrific applications, but there were some head
scratching situations. There were some incomplete applications which I
attribute to students who weren&#39;t really interested in the program,
but I was surprised by two things on the student side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, sme times we needed a little more information from a student so we
sent an email to the addresses (primary and backup) that they listed
in the application. Some times students got right back to us. Other
times it took days or even weeks. In one case, we weren&#39;t able to
accept the student because he didn&#39;t get back to us until after the
selection process was over. I know that not everyone reads or responds
to emails promptly but I was surprised since these were cases of
students who wanted to partake in our program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another thing that surprised me is that we almost lost a couple of
students because they thought the program would cost too much. We
tried to make it as clear as possible that we offered financial
assistance and in many cases could cover all fees but apparently we
weren&#39;t as clear as I had hoped.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-5&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The one &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;really big&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; shock to me involved
recommendations. We required our applicants provide one email
address for someone that agreed to write a recommendation letter and
allowed for a second, optional one. We then contacted these
recomenders. If we didn&#39;t hear back, we sent reminder emails and asked
the applicants to prod the recommenders as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had a return rate of about 10%. This cut across type of school
(public, private, parochial, and charter) and grade (rising 9 through
12). As a teacher myself, I know of some colleagues who don&#39;t actually
write recs they agree to write but I was shocked that we only heard
back from 10%. The end result was that we could use a recommendation
to help an applicant but we didn&#39;t feel that it was fair to penalize a
student just because a teacher didn&#39;t send in a rec.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-6&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final though on outreach, it should get easier for us over
time. SHIP is going great and next year, we&#39;ll be a known quantity to
schools. We should also have our cadre of shipmates helping spread the
word and of course, we want them back for another summer of more
advanced work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>