<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emacs on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/emacs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Emacs on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 08:11:52 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/emacs/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 63 ClojureScript</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-63-clojurescript/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 08:11:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-63-clojurescript/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been playing with ClojureScipt for my web projects recently and really like it. Much more fun than any of the JavaScript frameworks I&#39;ve used.
Still, getting started was somewhat difficult due to the number of options in tooling and uneven documentation and learning resources.
Here&#39;s a video that shows how I use Emacs for ClojureScript development but the focus of the video is on how to get started with ClojureScript and Emacs takes a back seat other than an example of my workflow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 62 Magit Forge</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-62-magit-forge/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 12:25:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-62-magit-forge/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I started looking at Magit as a &#34;git dashboard&#34; instead of as a &#34;git interface&#34; it&#39;s been yet another Emacs killer app to me. I just recently started playing with forge which allows Magit to interface and interact with git &#34;forges&#34; like GitHub. This allows you to work on issues and pull requests without ever leaving Emacs.
Here&#39;s a video on how easy it is. The video doesn&#39;t show this but the first time you fire forge up it will prompt you for credentials.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 61 - org-msg</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-61-org-msg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 05:00:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-61-org-msg/</guid>
      <description>By living in Emacs I get a consistent interface across all sorts of tasks - programming, lesson planning, making presentations, preparing documents, and yes, even email. I&#39;ve been using mu4e as my Emacs email client for a while now. Currently, I&#39;m using Emacs for my work email and Gmail for personal. I&#39;ve been thinking of going whole hog to mu4e and possibly migrating from Gmail to a new email provider for the personal stuff but there are still a few pain points with Emacs email:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 60 - Restclient</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-60-restclient/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2019 11:57:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-60-restclient/</guid>
      <description>I started to work on a web application the other day. It&#39;s nothing special but if I ever finish it, it will be a pretty complete project. The backend will be a REST API and I&#39;m planning on writing the frontend in Clojurescript.
The problem with developing a web application like this is that you can&#39;t really write the front end until you have enough of the backend to provide data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 59 - markdown</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-59-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2019 11:57:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-59-markdown/</guid>
      <description>Org-mode is my markup of choice. I spend the vast majority of my time working on text files working in org-mode. Since GitHUb started rendering org-mode files in their site I&#39;ve also used org-mode for things like Readme files in my projects. I even force it on my students at times. When I make an assignment, I seed it with an org-mode file that they have to modify - that is - fill in things like their names, group members etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 58 - lsp-mode</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-58-lsp-mode/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 11:57:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-58-lsp-mode/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been wanting to check out lsp-mode under Emacs for a while now. LSP stands for Language Protocol Service. The idea is that you have a standard interface between your editor and some language server. If you program in multiple languages and each has an LSP server you end up, in theory, with a simpler configuration and a consistent interface.
This certainly sounds more appealing than how we did it in the old days where you have some ad hoc configuraiton for each language you work in.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 57 Dired Narrow</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-57-dired-narrow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 11:57:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-57-dired-narrow/</guid>
      <description>One of Emacs power features that I&#39;ve never quite gotten into is dired, the Directory Editor. I&#39;ve already done a video on the package. It&#39;s really cool and I do use it at times but I still haven&#39;t started using it for my day to day.
Well, I just started using a couple of packages that might change this. They&#39;re part of a set of dired addons that you can check out at the dired hacks page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 56 - Dictionaries</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-56-dictionaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 16:58:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-56-dictionaries/</guid>
      <description>One of the great things about Emacs is that it&#39;s not just for writing programs. Sure, you can set it up as an IDE for just about every programming language under the sun but that&#39;s just the tip of the iceberg. I use Emacs for just about all my text processing. This includes writing blog posts, reading and writing emails, creating lesson plans and pretty much anything and everything having to do with text.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 55 - Irony Completions</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-55-irony-completions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 08:27:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-55-irony-completions/</guid>
      <description>Last year I put together a post and video on some basics of Emacs for C++ development. In the video I didn&#39;t quite get completions fully working. I also used ggtags in that video but find myself using dumb-jump more frequently.
Here&#39;s a quick video showing how to set up irony-mode which uses libclang for completions. It&#39;s pretty slick. Now the only thing I think I&#39;m missing is header file completions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 54 Org Tables</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-54-org-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 11:34:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-54-org-tables/</guid>
      <description>As you know I use Emacs for all sorts of things. In addition to coding, I use it for email, my schedule, note taking, and much much more. As part of my job at Hunter, I read and evaluate some of the Macaulay Honors College applications. I also have to evaluate all the applicants to my CS honors program. I described how I use Org-mode and Emacs to help with that here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 53 Emailing Org Agenda</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-53-emailing-org-agenda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 08:55:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-53-emailing-org-agenda/</guid>
      <description>I use both org-mode and Google Calendar for scheduling. I like Google Calendar because: It&#39;s pretty universal so I can issue and accept calendar invites. It works well with my phone and other mobile devices. The rest of my family doesn&#39;t live in Emacs :-(.   I prefer using org-mode beacuse: Emacs I prefer, for the most part, to control my data.  I partially sync the two platforms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 52 - Eyebrowse</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-52-eyebrowse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 14:35:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-52-eyebrowse/</guid>
      <description>I was originally going to do a video on how I set things up so that I get an email every morning with my org-mode agenda but that&#39;s going to be something of an ordeal. I have to create a droploet on Digital Ocean, set up SyncThing and a mail server and lots of other things.
I&#39;ll get to that video at some point but in the meantime I saw this thread on the Emacs subreddit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 51 - Day to day work with org-mode</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-51-dtd-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 17:30:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-51-dtd-org/</guid>
      <description>I can&#39;t believe that I haven&#39;t made a video since the beginning of summer!!!
Part of the reason is that I haven&#39;t had any video ideas that have motivated me and the other reason is that the Fall is my busiest season.
In any event, here&#39;s the latest installment.
Take a look at how I use Emacs and more specifically org-mode for my day to day work. Sometimes I use the fancy power tools but to be honest, most of the time, I stick to the basics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Series</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 19:02:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs/</guid>
      <description>Link to current configuration: https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs Introduction Video 1 - Setting up the package manager Video 2 - Intro to Org Mode Video 3 - How to think about Emacs Video 4 - Buffers Video 5 - Windows Video 6 - Search / Swiper Video 7 - Navigation / avy Video 8 - Autocomplete Video 9 - Themes Video 10 - Org init files Video 11 - org-reveal / reveal.js Video 12 - Python, Flycheck, Jedi Video 13 - Python, Yasnippet Video 14 - Thoughts on Using Emacs Video 15 - Macros Video 16 - Undo Tree Video 17 - Small packages Video 18 - narrowing and iedit Video 19 - moving to a live config Video 20 - Yanking Video 21-web-mode Video 22-emacsclient Video 23 - capture 1 Video 24 - capture 2 Video 25 - Tramp Video 26 - Google Calendar and Org Agenda Video 27 - Shell and eshell Video 28 - Rectangles Video 29 - elfeed 1  Video 30 - elfeed 2 - Hydras  Video 31 - elfeed 3 - macros Video 32 - C++ Video 33 - Projectile Dumb-jump Video 34 - ibuffer and emmet Video 35 - blogging Video 36 - A Touch of Elisp Video 37 - Treemacs file browser Video 38 - dired Video 39 - mu4e Video 40 - Atomic chrome Video 41 - Pandoc Video 42 - Git Gutter and Timemachine Video 43 - Music Video 44 - pdf Video 45 - Company or Autocomplete Video 46 - auto yasnippets Video 47 - Magit Video 48 - silversearcher Video 49 - mu4e conversation Video 50 - presentations Video 51 - Day to day with org-mode Video 52 - eyebrowse Video 53 - Emailing org-agenda Video 54 - Org Tables Video 55 - Irony Completions Video 56 - Dictionaries Video 57 - Dired Narrow Video 58 - lsp-mode Video 59 - markdown Video 60 - restclient Video 61 - org-msg Video 62 - Magit Forge Video 63 - ClojureScript </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>