<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hunter on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hunter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hunter on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 17:34:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hunter/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College Winter Codefest 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 17:34:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s great to see how much Hunter CS has developed since starting here there years ago. The latest endeavor is Winter Codefest. During the fall I was approached by one of my students who had asked an older Hunter CS student about their portfolio and found that the senior&#39;s portfolio was lacking. This student said we should do something to help encourage younger students to build that portfolio.
The result was Winter Codefest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a feeling of community. Students aren&#39;t on campus every day and come from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&#39;t have a CS &#34;hang out&#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&#39;re scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
I&#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 in review - Hunter Undergraduate CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</guid>
      <description>I usually don&#39;t do year in review posts. At Stuy, not much changed year after year so I never felt it worth summarizing the past and projecting the future. At Hunter, now that I&#39;m a couple of years in, projects are really picking up steam so I think it&#39;s worth talking about them.
One of my two major missions at Hunter was to build a CS Honors program and raise the profile of Hunter&#39;s undergraduate CS program in general.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College - Honors CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 It&#39;s been a while since my last post and a while since I started at Hunter.  Time to share a bit about what I&#39;ve been up to.  One of the better kept secrets in New York City is Hunter College&#39;s computer science program. It&#39;s been around for years and it&#39;s been that way for years. In fact, when I was looking to get my masters degree back in the mid nineties I carefully researched all of the area&#39;s MS in CS programs.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>