<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lessons on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/lessons/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Lessons on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 07:48:14 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/lessons/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I Speak Jive</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-speak-jive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 07:48:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-speak-jive/</guid>
      <description>When I wrote about the HighWebEd I mentioned John William&amp;#39;&amp;#39;s talk on Agile. He spoke about how the movie Airplane! was filmed in an Agile manner and gave as an example the development of the &amp;#34;jive&amp;#34; scenes.  &amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34; src=&amp;#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zdCjbJ6NEfc&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34; allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;  Apparently the creative team had a script but it wasn&amp;#39;t working. The first pair that read for the role, Norman Gibbs and Al White had their owned take.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium and other blog sites you might get the idea that you&amp;#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful lessons they&amp;#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.  It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that worked for them or things they think will work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There&#39;s always something to learn (from your students)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</guid>
      <description>One thing I&amp;#39;ve learned from teaching is that there&amp;#39;s always something new to learn. For the kids, yes, but I&amp;#39;m talking about for the teacher.  The other day, I taught a lesson I&amp;#39;ve taught many times. Find the mode of a data set. That&amp;#39;s the problem that they solve but the lesson is really about run time complexity, hidden complexity and using data structures in alternate ways.  I blogged about this before so you can get an earlier take there although the code isn&amp;#39;t formatted correctly due to blog conversions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>