<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:59:55 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/post/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:59:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</guid>
      <description>Thanksgiving weekend is also reunion weekend. I&#39;ve been on and off invited to Stuy reunions over the years. Not as often it seems as some teachers but more often than others. I always do my best to attend. I have very fond memories of many students and many classes over many years and think a lot about them so feel very honored whenever I&#39;m invited to one of these.
In the past each class due a reunion did its own thing - some club or bar usually in Manhattan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Sorting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 20:04:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I saw a facebook post asking for thoughts on teaching sorting. The question was specifically not about motivations like having the class act out sorts or sort cards but rather about the coding.
I&#39;ve been meaning to write about this since last summer when I attended Owen Astrachan&#39;s talk on the same subject.
Early in my career when teaching sorting I developed the n^2 sorts as standalone routines just as they&#39;re presented in most books but as I gained more experience as a teacher, I changed it up to build the sorts (at least some of them) from existing concepts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 19:43:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</guid>
      <description>I spent this past Saturday morning up at the Microsoft building in Times Square. What was I doing there? Aankit Patel invited me to check out the professional development that he and his team organized for the teachers involved in the assorted CSforAllNYC programs that his office runs.
Wow.
Lots of great things going on. I was only able to stay for a couple of hours but I spent some time in two rooms run by TEALS, a room of BJC teachers, a group working with p5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An experiment with code review</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 17:09:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes professional practices don&#39;t work well in the classroom and sometimes they do. One professional practice that does work well is code review - reading and reflecting on other peoples code.
I&#39;ve had my students do code reviews in the past but this time I did things differently. Here&#39;s what I did and here&#39;s how it went
Two weeks ago my students completed a lab. The lab involved reading in a poorly indented C++ program and spit out a properly indented one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Teachers Teach</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/let-teachers-teach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 08:57:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/let-teachers-teach/</guid>
      <description>Mark Guzdial&#39;s post the other day about direct isntruction struck a chord with me. Right up front, Mark said:
  The research evidence is growing that students learn better through direct instruction rather than through a discovery-based method, where we expect students to figure things out for themselves.  Quite a surprise to the teachers who have been beaten over the head with &#34;everything must be discovery&#34; in recent years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local Tech and Local Learning</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/local-tech-local-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 11:08:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/local-tech-local-learning/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I took twenty four of my first year students up to Catskills Conf. As usual it was a great weekend. I particularly enjoyed this years talks.
I found one talk particularly engaging. Jordan Koschei gave at talk titled Digital Terroir. Terroir refers to the natural envorinment in which a wine is produced - the ground, the climate, everything. It&#39;s why wine (and foods) produced in one location taste differently than the same things mamde elsewhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 53 Emailing Org Agenda</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-53-emailing-org-agenda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 08:55:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-53-emailing-org-agenda/</guid>
      <description>I use both org-mode and Google Calendar for scheduling. I like Google Calendar because: It&#39;s pretty universal so I can issue and accept calendar invites. It works well with my phone and other mobile devices. The rest of my family doesn&#39;t live in Emacs :-(.   I prefer using org-mode beacuse: Emacs I prefer, for the most part, to control my data.  I partially sync the two platforms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 52 - Eyebrowse</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-52-eyebrowse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 14:35:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-52-eyebrowse/</guid>
      <description>I was originally going to do a video on how I set things up so that I get an email every morning with my org-mode agenda but that&#39;s going to be something of an ordeal. I have to create a droploet on Digital Ocean, set up SyncThing and a mail server and lots of other things.
I&#39;ll get to that video at some point but in the meantime I saw this thread on the Emacs subreddit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catskills Conf -  Knitting for Good 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 17:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</guid>
      <description>Two weekends ago I took a group of my first year students up to Catskills Conf, an annual event that I describe as &#34;light tech conference with a focus on diversity and inclusion meets summer camp.&#34; I&#39;ve written about the event before if anyone&#39;s interested in more details. As in past years, Devorah ran her knitting for good project. In each of the first two years of the project, attendees of Catskills Conf learned how to know and collectively knit, crocheted and assembled a blanket for Project Linux which provides hand made blankets to children in crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Scripts To Freestyle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2018 17:35:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</guid>
      <description>I just read this post by Bethany Crystal - Going off script.
Bethany writes that while she normally essentially scripts important presentations, this time she went more off the cuff.
It made me think about how I teach and a disturbing trend I&#39;ve seen in CS education and education in general.
I&#39;ve never strictly used a script for teaching. When I started I did use very detailed lesson plans. Back then I was teaching math.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 51 - Day to day work with org-mode</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-51-dtd-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 17:30:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-51-dtd-org/</guid>
      <description>I can&#39;t believe that I haven&#39;t made a video since the beginning of summer!!!
Part of the reason is that I haven&#39;t had any video ideas that have motivated me and the other reason is that the Fall is my busiest season.
In any event, here&#39;s the latest installment.
Take a look at how I use Emacs and more specifically org-mode for my day to day work. Sometimes I use the fancy power tools but to be honest, most of the time, I stick to the basics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman - part 3</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 17:25:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/</guid>
      <description>Parts 1 and 2  Part 1 Part 2  Part 3 In the first two parts of this set of posts I wrote about the motivation and design a question answering system that can answer &#34;who&#34; queries like &#34;who played Spiderman&#34; or &#34;who shot John Lennon?&#34; It&#39;s not perfect. When doing the Spiderman query, chances are the desired answer will be at or near the top of the list of most frequently appearing names but so will &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 16:04:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</guid>
      <description>Parts 1 and 3  Part 1 Part 3  Part 2 When we left off last time we used a search engine API to gather a whole bunch of documents with the term &#34;played Spiderman&#34; or &#34;who played Spiderman.&#34; Now we have to process these documents to answer the question. Fortunately, the documents are basically just big strings of text.
Since we&#39;re doing a &#34;who&#34; query we want to find all the names in all the documents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 1 or my Nifty Assignment (that was rejected)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 17:16:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</guid>
      <description>Parts 2 and 3  Part 2 Part 3  I wasn&#39;t going to teach this lesson today. I was planning on starting a multi day project starting with an exercise in specification writing and design.
Beforehand though, we had to talk about classes. One of my students asked if probability and/or statistics were really important for CS. I started to cite a few examples and then decided to segue into this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compile Each Concept</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2018 14:46:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;ve all been there:
  Student: Teacher, I need help  Teacher (comes over)  Student (shows screen listing three bazillion errors)  The student has just written pages of code and finally decided to try to run it only to end up with pages of errors.
Error messages can at times be hard to read for beginners but to see and truth be told, they frequently don&#39;t even read them but over the years I&#39;ve developed a practice that I&#39;ve found helpful as a software developer and if students adopt the same practice it can save them a lot of time and effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a feeling of community. Students aren&#39;t on campus every day and come from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&#39;t have a CS &#34;hang out&#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&#39;re scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
I&#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Globals Breaks And Returns, oh my</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 15:48:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</guid>
      <description>Never use global variables Never break out of a loop  These are two &#34;best practices&#34; that are frequently touted in early CS classes both at the high school and college level.
They came up a couple of times yesterday. Once in the Facebook APCS-A teachers group and once on Alfred Thompson&#39;s blog.
Alfred post was topically on global variables. Actually it was deeper than just global variables. It&#39;s also about how students progress - what they can figure out at various stages of progress and how what seems like a good idea early on the path to computer science doesn&#39;t seem so great later on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the students know more than the teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 16:07:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;ve heard it many times with computer science - &#34;the kids know more than the teacher.&#34;
On the one hand, the truth is that this isn&#39;t so much the case. Kids might use computers all the time but they don&#39;t necessarily know much about them or about computer science (link 1, link 2). Then you have students who think they know all about CS but really don&#39;t. They might have picked up a bit of coding somewhere but more often than not, the knowledge is pretty superficial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve written before about why Hunter College CS is so important for NYC and I&#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors CS program - a program in which students receive a scholarship along with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have made a lot of progress over the past two years and each year I roll out new special activities and events for my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS vs CT vs Coding</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 12:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s been a lot of buzz recently concernting Computational Thinking (CT) vs Computer Science (CS) vs Coding / Programming on the interwebs.
 Some of the questions and concerns that I&#39;ve seen recently include: What is CT?? Will rich schools get CS and poor only CT? Will rich schools get CS and poor on coding?  The first question is a big one and as a community we haven&#39;t answered it yet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium and other blog sites you might get the idea that you&#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful lessons they&#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that worked for them or things they think will work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What CS should we teach in HS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 16:54:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to chime in on Alfred Thompson&#39;s post last week on what to include in a HS CS class but was working on moving blogging platforms so didn&#39;t get a chance so I&#39;ll say a few words here.
If you&#39;ve been here before you probably know I&#39;m not a fan of the standards and I certainly am no fan of the College Board and the AP program so what&#39;s my take?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post again</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/firstpost/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 17:21:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/firstpost/</guid>
      <description>The new site is live. I&#39;m now running a Hugo based blog. I set it up using the Mainroad theme which seems to support everything I want.
Out of the box Hugo supports org-mode with pretty much all of its niceties like:
 code highlighting org-mode structure (lists, tables) html can be directly embedded tags and categories  The Mainroad theme added:
 MathJax Analytics An easy menu widgets for the sidebar  It was pretty easy to customize and deploying to GitHub pages is pretty simple.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>