<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 12:08:35 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/post/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CS vs CT vs Coding</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 12:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s been a lot of buzz recently concernting Computational Thinking (CT) vs Computer Science (CS) vs Coding / Programming on the interwebs.
 Some of the questions and concerns that I&#39;ve seen recently include: What is CT?? Will rich schools get CS and poor only CT? Will rich schools get CS and poor on coding?  The first question is a big one and as a community we haven&#39;t answered it yet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium and other blog sites you might get the idea that you&#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful lessons they&#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that worked for them or things they think will work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What CS should we teach in HS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 16:54:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to chime in on Alfred Thompson&#39;s post last week on what to include in a HS CS class but was working on moving blogging platforms so didn&#39;t get a chance so I&#39;ll say a few words here.
If you&#39;ve been here before you probably know I&#39;m not a fan of the standards and I certainly am no fan of the College Board and the AP program so what&#39;s my take?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post again</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/firstpost/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 17:21:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/firstpost/</guid>
      <description>The new site is live. I&#39;m now running a Hugo based blog. I set it up using the Mainroad theme which seems to support everything I want.
Out of the box Hugo supports org-mode with pretty much all of its niceties like:
 code highlighting org-mode structure (lists, tables) html can be directly embedded tags and categories  The Mainroad theme added:
 MathJax Analytics An easy menu widgets for the sidebar  It was pretty easy to customize and deploying to GitHub pages is pretty simple.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>