<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 08:00:08 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/post/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Do It First</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/do-it-first/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 08:00:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/do-it-first/</guid>
      <description>Reading Garth Flint&#39;s end of year post and Alfred Thompson&#39;s follow up had me thinking about a couple of things.
One was spurred when Garth wrote &#34;They also have to figure out the math before they code.&#34; This made me think about all the details we sometimes take for for granted. Things that are hard for our students that we just know. It&#39;s frequently math that we might find trivial but it could also be much simpler things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AP Classes, Placing Students, and First Topic Exposures</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/placing-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 13:27:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/placing-students/</guid>
      <description>Just like last year, I&#39;m taking in two classes worth of students in to my honors program. The challenge is that I can only teach two classes and I&#39;ve got to figure out what to teach and then which students belong in which class.
It basically comes down to one of two courses, our CS0 (CSCI127) and our CS1 (CSCI135).
CSCI127 is a first programming experience. The normal class is taught as a large lecture with small recitation/labs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Grades</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/predicting-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 12:03:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/predicting-grades/</guid>
      <description>Just saw this:
Evaluation metric idea: take snapshots of students&amp;#39; grades each week (specifically, the grade they actually see in your LMS). How well do these correlate with your final assigned grade? Were students getting good estimates?
&amp;mdash; Austin Cory Bart (@AustinCorgiBart) May 18, 2019 
It made me think of a couple of conversations I had with more senior teachers early in my career.
They&#39;d tell me &#34;by and large, you know what the kids are going to get after a few week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog For Self Professional Devleopment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/blog-for-pd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 07:12:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/blog-for-pd/</guid>
      <description>Lat day of the 2019 NCWIT Summmit. Got up crazy early, got back from my run and saw this when I checked Twitter:
A1: CSTA, Twitter chats like this one, @guzdial and @alfredtwo&amp;#39;s blogs among others. In all cases because those places start from assuming I&amp;#39;m a CS teacher, rather than starting from assuming I&amp;#39;m a teacher who is better at teaching something else. #csk8 https://t.co/6DO77fzq0j
&amp;mdash; Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) May 16, 2019</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hunter Daedalus Fall 2019 recruiting class</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 08:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</guid>
      <description>Now that high school seniors have all committed to their respective colleges I though I&#39;d share some information on Hunter&#39;s incoming Daedalus (honors CS) cohort.
I joke about the first cohort saying that nobody applied to the program. That&#39;s kind of true. I jointed Hunter a little over three years ago in late January. That was after high school seniors had already applied to college and at that time the program didn&#39;t exist.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Give me a break (and a continue)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/break-continue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 08:39:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/break-continue/</guid>
      <description>What can I do to discourage my students from using the &#34;break&#34;  statement?  That was more or less the gist of the comment and it elicited some good responses. This time the conversation was on Facebook but I&#39;ve seen this one and participated in it many times before. I never liked the question when presented as a &#34;how can I stop them&#34; one. I equally dislike when the offered advice is basically &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Technical Interviews And Diversity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/technical-interviews-and-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2019 11:27:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/technical-interviews-and-diversity/</guid>
      <description>I recently stumbled upon Laurie Barth on Twitter and noticed a couple of tweets about tech interviews and the hiring process, something I&#39;ve been thinking about recently.
Solid rant. I think the teach to the programming test market already exists. And it’s why interviewers who subscribe to these tactics get upset if a candidate admits they’ve seen the problem previously. Because it ruins the illusion that this is revealing how candidates think.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ebooks, Nypl and Process Starvation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 12:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m a big fan of E Ink e-readers. I had one a number of years ago. An Aztak EZ Reader. It was great. Small, cheap, and independent - that is, not tied in to Amazon or Barnes and Nobles and I found myself doing a lot more recreational reading with it. I still preferred paper for technical books but for easy reading there was nothing like having tons of reading options always available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seam Carving and Dynamic Programming</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/seam-carving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 13:51:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/seam-carving/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s spring break and for me that&#39;s always been a good time to explore some new ideas.
Here&#39;s one that some of you might like, particularly if you&#39;re teaching APCS-A or something similar.
Many APCS-A teachers do a unit on image processing using the picture lab (alternate resource). Image processing is a nice platform to explore two dimensional arrays. You basically use a 2D array of pixels (points) to represent an image.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code Review Revisited or research - the teacher version</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 11:36:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review-2/</guid>
      <description>Last semester I wrote about how I was introducing my students to code review. I thought it worked pretty well and was anxious to try it again.
Well, I did the lesson(s) again this past week and it looks like it&#39;s a keeper. The setup was pretty much the same with some hiccups due to using a new platform. Last semester I used plain GitHub public repos. This time, I&#39;ve been using GitHub classroom which I like very much but I forgot that I made this assignment use private repos which turned out to be a hassle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teacher PD at Grow with Google</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-at-gwg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 08:12:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-at-gwg/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday we held our third monthly Professional Development session for teachers of &#34;APCS-A, Similar, and Beyond.&#34; It&#39;s great to see that we&#39;re starting to form a core of a community of CS teachers teaching some of the more advanced classes as there is a core group that keeps coming back for more. Even better is the fact that we&#39;re gaining a couple of new teachers at each session.
Last time, we were at Digital Ocean, a cloud provide that has been very involved in education since their creation and has been a tremendous boon to my education projects over the years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implicit Curricula</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/implicit-curricula/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 16:23:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/implicit-curricula/</guid>
      <description>The state got back to us the other week on our CSEd programs. Still no approval.
One of the requirements is that we have 12 graduate CS credits in our program and that in those courses these five major areas:
 Algorithms and programming Computing systems Data and analysis Impacts of computing Networks and the internet  as described in the K12 CS Framework. Even though many of the items described in the framework fit better in an education side course NY is requiring that it&#39;s all covered in CS courses offered by a CS department.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 57 Dired Narrow</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-57-dired-narrow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 11:57:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-57-dired-narrow/</guid>
      <description>One of Emacs power features that I&#39;ve never quite gotten into is dired, the Directory Editor. I&#39;ve already done a video on the package. It&#39;s really cool and I do use it at times but I still haven&#39;t started using it for my day to day.
Well, I just started using a couple of packages that might change this. They&#39;re part of a set of dired addons that you can check out at the dired hacks page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busy Week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 07:32:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m glad it&#39;s Saturday morning. It&#39;s been a busy week. It looks like there&#39;s a couple more to plough through but hopefully then I can catch my breath over spring break.
Why so busy? It&#39;s the same old story - you&#39;ve got all those projects that you&#39;re waiting on and everything comes in at the same time.
To start off, it&#39;s college decision season. The high school seniors all know their options and are deciding where to go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing A Textbook</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/choosing-a-textbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 10:41:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/choosing-a-textbook/</guid>
      <description>Now and again there are requests on the assorted CS Education forums asking about which text book to use. These requests are usually for APCS-A. There are usually a number of &#34;I&#39;m very happy with ...&#34; replies but I thought I&#39;d take a bit of a deeper dive into what teachers might want to consider when evaluating a textbook.
It was never an issue when I started as a math teacher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adapting A Nifty Assignment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 08:20:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</guid>
      <description>The Nifty Assignments session at SGICSE is always a popular one.
Go to the site and you&#39;ll find links to all the assignments presented from 1999 to the present year.
On the one hand, it&#39;s a great resource. On the other, the assignments vary in nifty-ness depending on one&#39;s personal taste. To me, there seemed to be a run of nifty assignments that were really just &#34;take a generic assignment and fancy up the graphics&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 17:38:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</guid>
      <description>Got a new monitor today and wanted to share.
My old one was a 27&#34; Hanns G. Actually, the old ones - my old set up was 2 of them side by side. When I started at Hunter, I was given a piddly small monitor so I tried to buy my own 27&#34; Hanns G to bring in but they were no longer available. The 27&#34; jobs available then were much more expensive so my work monitor situation has been sadly lacking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Java IDES for teaching teachers.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:29:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</guid>
      <description>Since Hunter uses C++ as it&#39;s core language, I haven&#39;t used Java much in the past three years. That&#39;s going to change pretty soon. Once we start offering our CS teacher Certificate and Masters programs I&#39;ll once again start teaching with Java as that&#39;s one of the langauges that we want to prepare our teachers with.
That means deciding on a set of tools and so I&#39;ve been spending time evaluating Java programming environments with an eye on the beginner since not only do the teachers I work with have to be comfortable with the tool but more importantly they will have to be able to support the tool for all of their students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2019 - the keynotes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2019-keynotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 15:25:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2019-keynotes/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s that time of the year to write a series of blog posts about SIGCSE. I thought I&#39;d start with one on the keynotes.
There were four keynote speakers. Marie desJardins, Gloria Townsend, Mark Guzdial, and Blair Taylor. I wasn&#39;t at the first timer&#39;s lunch where Townsend spoke so I won&#39;t talk at all about that keynote.
I&#39;m also not going to summarize the talks. Andy Ko wrote up a terrific summary of his SIGCSE experience and did a much better job giving overviews to the keynotes than I ever could so I&#39;ll just refer you to Andy&#39;s blog post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March PD for CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 15:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</guid>
      <description>Back in December we ran our first PD session for CS teachers. This was to address the need for professional development for teachers who were more experienced in terms of computer science - we aimed this at people who were ready to teach APCS-A, similar, or beyond and also to start to build a community for these teachers.
We had trouble setting things up for February but we&#39;re good to go for March, April and May.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College Winter Codefest 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 17:34:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s great to see how much Hunter CS has developed since starting here there years ago. The latest endeavor is Winter Codefest. During the fall I was approached by one of my students who had asked an older Hunter CS student about their portfolio and found that the senior&#39;s portfolio was lacking. This student said we should do something to help encourage younger students to build that portfolio.
The result was Winter Codefest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Thomas Friedman&#39;s editorial on the College Board&#39;s Two Codes left me concerned</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 10:20:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</guid>
      <description>There was some buzz over this editorial about the College Board last week. The two codes every child needs - Coding and the US Constitution? Who could argue with that.
I&#39;m not going to disagree. Civics and CS are important and can&#39;t wait until college. The thing that left me chilled though was that nobody&#39;s paying attention to the fact that the College Board - a private entity with its own interests has so much influence over American education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I use Github Classroom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 16:42:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s been an amazingly unproductive weekend. Mostly because I&#39;ve been sick with the flu. It sucks but since the rest of the family&#39;s away anway at least I&#39;m not making everyone miserable.
I did manage to stage my next couple of classes and figured that writing this post wouldn&#39;t take too much energy since it&#39;s mostly a video.
Earlier, I talked about using GitHub and TravicCI and this time around I show how I use GitHub classroom to set up, disseminate, and collect assignments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech Jobs, Diversity, and Equity in the wake of the Amazon/NYC debacle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 11:14:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</guid>
      <description>I was planning on either following up on how I use GitHub classroom or commenting on the recent NY Times opinion piece on the College Board but the follow up, fall out, and polarization from the Amazon NY thing has been stuck in my head so I thought I&#39;d write a bit more about it.
Like my previous post, this isn&#39;t really about Amazon but rather about the long game, equity, and diversity and how a lot of people are fooling themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Amazon HQ2 in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-amazon-hq/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 17:57:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-amazon-hq/</guid>
      <description>That was the big tech news today. I know there was a good deal of vocal outrage about the deal but to be honest I was pretty surprised by the news. Normally deals like these get steamrolled through for better or worse.
I have decidedly mixed feelings about this. On the one hand, I have no problem with Amazon - I&#39;ve got a bunch of former students working there. Mostly in Seattle but at least one in NYC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Helps Me Help Students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-helps-me-help-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 18:55:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-helps-me-help-students/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I was reminded why I love GitHub in support of my classes. One of my students posted a question about our current lab. They posted a synopsis of the problem along with the error message.
Since we&#39;re all working on GitHub the student&#39;s work was already up online Since I started using GitHub Classroom I was able to quickly navigate to the repo. This might have been enough but to really in to the students work I cloned the repo and went into Emacs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use A Real Language</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 15:08:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</guid>
      <description>Why can&#39;t we use a real language!  This topic has been coming up a lot recently. Now I&#39;m not talking about the Drag and drop vs textual language thing. Let me be clear. To me a Drag and Drop language can certainly be a real language and many are. I also think they&#39;re terrific when used correctly. I just think they&#39;re frequently misapplied in later grades.
No, I&#39;m talking about people asking things like &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 09:40:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>Two of the hardest topics to make meaningful to students in APCS-A are inheritance and interfaces. It&#39;s not that they&#39;re super difficult topics but rather that they&#39;re not often needed, useful, or superior to not using them on beginner assignments. More often than not the motivation is a bit forced as are the assignments.
Inheritance is its own can of worms and to be honest, something I&#39;ve not found to be all that useful or necessary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Ap Registration - it&#39;s, um, for the kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 08:08:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon a thread over in the APCS-A Facebook group the other day. It seems that the College Board is making some changes in their registration timeline. In the past, students registered for the exam sometime in March with the exams administered in May. The new changes include requiring registration in November along with $40 late registration and cancellation fees.
The College Board is, of course, spinning this as for the student&#39;s benefit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Github Classroom and Travis CI</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 09:44:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been using GitHub with my classes since GitHub&#39;s early days. Over time I&#39;ve gotten my workflows down. I use a combination of shell scripts - many just written on the fly, GitHub organizations, and some naming conventions and protocols that have served me well.
A few years ago, the GitHub Education team started GitHub Classroom. I looked at it at the time. It was pretty cool but I had my workflow so I didn&#39;t adopt it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 56 - Dictionaries</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-56-dictionaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 16:58:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-56-dictionaries/</guid>
      <description>One of the great things about Emacs is that it&#39;s not just for writing programs. Sure, you can set it up as an IDE for just about every programming language under the sun but that&#39;s just the tip of the iceberg. I use Emacs for just about all my text processing. This includes writing blog posts, reading and writing emails, creating lesson plans and pretty much anything and everything having to do with text.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequencing Topics</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sequencing-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 16:06:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sequencing-topics/</guid>
      <description>Monday&#39;s the start of the Spring semester. Other than the 8:00am start I&#39;m looking forward to it. My 8:00am class is the honors/lab component that goes with CS1. I taught it last semester and during each of the past two years at Hunter. My second class is the follow up - more OOP / C++, data structures and some algorithms.
The material is old hat. I&#39;ve taught it in Java more times than I can count and also in C++ albeit many years ago.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 55 - Irony Completions</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-55-irony-completions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 08:27:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-55-irony-completions/</guid>
      <description>Last year I put together a post and video on some basics of Emacs for C++ development. In the video I didn&#39;t quite get completions fully working. I also used ggtags in that video but find myself using dumb-jump more frequently.
Here&#39;s a quick video showing how to set up irony-mode which uses libclang for completions. It&#39;s pretty slick. Now the only thing I think I&#39;m missing is header file completions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solve A To Solve B</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/solve-a-to-solve-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 19:36:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/solve-a-to-solve-b/</guid>
      <description>So many programming assignments involve a direct solution. Write a program to do this or write a problem to solve that. It&#39;s pretty typical. There&#39;s nothing wrong with assignments like these. They allow students to practice what they&#39;ve been learning and it gives them the opportunity to create some cool programs. All the same, I like it when there&#39;s an indirect problem. You&#39;re faced with a problem but in order to solve it you first have to solve some other problem</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts On Code And Beyond - Computational Thinking</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/thoughts-on-code-and-beyond-ct/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 17:48:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/thoughts-on-code-and-beyond-ct/</guid>
      <description>The theme of this year&#39;s To Code and Beyond was Computational Thinking. Mark Guzdial gave the keynote. While the talk isn&#39;t currently online, check out this talk that Mark gave last March. It&#39;s not the same but the second halves are and well worth a look.
In the first half, Mark talked about other types of &#34;thinking.&#34; Scientific thinking, engineering thinking and even historical thinking. All had a good amount of overlap with both each other and with computational thinking even as we haven&#39;t yet settled on what computational thinking actually is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 54 Org Tables</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-54-org-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 11:34:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-54-org-tables/</guid>
      <description>As you know I use Emacs for all sorts of things. In addition to coding, I use it for email, my schedule, note taking, and much much more. As part of my job at Hunter, I read and evaluate some of the Macaulay Honors College applications. I also have to evaluate all the applicants to my CS honors program. I described how I use Org-mode and Emacs to help with that here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is There a First Grade Machine Learning Achievement Gap?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-there-a-first-grade-ml-achievement-gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 15:24:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-there-a-first-grade-ml-achievement-gap/</guid>
      <description>Today was the fifth &#34;To Code and Beyond&#34; - a one day conference hosted at Cornell Technion and once again Diane Levitt put together a great show. The theme was Computational Thinking and the day consisted of a variety of talks, panels, and activities. I plan on writing about one panel in particular but for today I wanted to address something that came up as a question. One attendee asked a panel about the achievement gap - the fact that when the CS movement got started in NY some of the more innovative and interesting work was being done with some of our most vulnerable students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When does a new course really get developed</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/when-does-a-new-course-get-developed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 08:49:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/when-does-a-new-course-get-developed/</guid>
      <description>Following up on my last post I thought I&#39;d talk a bit more about course development. According to most powers that be it&#39;s all done ahead of time. Organizations and companies with curricula to sell package it all up ahead of time lesson by lesson unit by unit. When I create a new course at Hunter, they demand a sample syllabus during the approval process with a week by week outline, assignments reading and more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Owning The Curriculum</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/owning-the-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 19:41:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/owning-the-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>I spent a couple of days last week hunkered down working designing a CS Ethics course and of course it got me thinking about designing courses in general.
One of the topics I&#39;ve ranted on is my disdain for canned curricula. I&#39;ve never been a fan. This isn&#39;t to say I don&#39;t want to leverage other people&#39;s work. I&#39;ll take sample curricula, lessons, and all the resources I can get my hands on but I&#39;d never just deliver them as is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels in the Architecture - when they used to build schools like cathedrals.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 07:31:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</guid>
      <description>One of the side benefits of visiting high schools is that I end up going all over the city. This takes me to neighborhoods that I normally wouldn&#39;t have reason to visit. For a New York History wonk that can be pretty cool even if you just limit yourself to looking at the schools. A few of the schools I visited in the last couple of weeks before the new year were self contained whole building schools:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 09:55:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve never been much of a New Years person. I get up really early and so don&#39;t usually stay up late and more to the point, as any teacher knows, the year really goes from September through June with that really long much needed weekend that you regular folks call July and August tacked on to separate years.
This whole January first thing is really more of a half time break or perhaps an intermission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code, Data Structures, and Hidden Complexity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 15:17:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</guid>
      <description>Since 2015, Eric Wastl has gifted us each December with Advent of Code - a 25 day programming competition that I very much enjoy. This year I haven&#39;t been able to get to too many of the problems. I only completed the first two days on the day they were released, problem three a day late and then I didn&#39;t get back to the problems until almost 12/25 - the final day of the competition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting schools and talking tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 15:49:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</guid>
      <description>Back in September I talked about embarking on my Fall 2018 HS CS Tour. Since then I&#39;ve visited about a dozen schools. I&#39;d like to thank my friends who helped connect me to schools - particularly Aankit Patel and Diane Levitt.
Even though the original motivation for the visits was to get the word out about Hunter CS and the awesome things we&#39;re doing in the Hunter CS Honors program I always tried to make my talks about something that would be relevant for the entire audience and not just the few that were great fits for my program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Development - APCS-A, similar and beyond</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 08:56:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</guid>
      <description>A while ago I wrote about our plans at Hunter to run professional development for CS teachers. Specifically, running once a month sessions for teachers who teach APCS-A, similar and beyond.
The idea started as a joke but morphed into a legit idea.
I was talking to some friends about CTLE hours and how ridiculous the system is. NY State teachers need 100 hours of CTLE credit (PD hours) every so many years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sloan awards for excellence in teaching science and mathematics</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sloan-awards-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 12:52:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sloan-awards-2018/</guid>
      <description>I spent yesterday evening at the Cooper Union in their Great Hall, a place famous for Abraham Lincoln&#39;s speech that some say propelled him to the presidency.
I was there in the audience watching as the Sloan Foundation and the Fund for the City of New York awarded seven public school teachers with an ward for &#34;Excellence in the Teaching of Science and Mathematics.&#34;
I was their to see my friend Dave Deutsch, a long time public school physics teacher receive the honor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS For All The Time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs4allthetime/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2018 08:20:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs4allthetime/</guid>
      <description>A question that frequently comes up with respect to CS for All is what does it mean?
To me it means giving all students some fundamental exposure to computer science so that they can:
 Make use of those thinking skills, problem solving approaches, and practical tools regardless of their future paths. Provide a path for the subset of &#34;all&#34; that desire to further pursue computer science.  But even with this, how do you do it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email Policy</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 19:36:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-policy/</guid>
      <description>I saw this tweet the day along with the ensuing thread:
Seriously, who emails a professor with words like &amp;quot;u&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;plz hlp&amp;quot;? Am I allowed to put language in my syllabus that penalizes students for obnoxious, intentional misspellings? Maybe: -1% to your course grade multiplied by the edit distance of the word with its correction?
&amp;mdash; Austin Cory Bart (@AustinCorgiBart) November 30, 2018 
I wanted to reply but as usual, I decided to reply in a blog post so that it doesn&#39;t get lost in the Twitterverse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:59:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</guid>
      <description>Thanksgiving weekend is also reunion weekend. I&#39;ve been on and off invited to Stuy reunions over the years. Not as often it seems as some teachers but more often than others. I always do my best to attend. I have very fond memories of many students and many classes over many years and think a lot about them so feel very honored whenever I&#39;m invited to one of these.
In the past each class due a reunion did its own thing - some club or bar usually in Manhattan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Sorting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 20:04:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I saw a facebook post asking for thoughts on teaching sorting. The question was specifically not about motivations like having the class act out sorts or sort cards but rather about the coding.
I&#39;ve been meaning to write about this since last summer when I attended Owen Astrachan&#39;s talk on the same subject.
Early in my career when teaching sorting I developed the n^2 sorts as standalone routines just as they&#39;re presented in most books but as I gained more experience as a teacher, I changed it up to build the sorts (at least some of them) from existing concepts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 19:43:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</guid>
      <description>I spent this past Saturday morning up at the Microsoft building in Times Square. What was I doing there? Aankit Patel invited me to check out the professional development that he and his team organized for the teachers involved in the assorted CSforAllNYC programs that his office runs.
Wow.
Lots of great things going on. I was only able to stay for a couple of hours but I spent some time in two rooms run by TEALS, a room of BJC teachers, a group working with p5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An experiment with code review</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 17:09:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes professional practices don&#39;t work well in the classroom and sometimes they do. One professional practice that does work well is code review - reading and reflecting on other peoples code.
I&#39;ve had my students do code reviews in the past but this time I did things differently. Here&#39;s what I did and here&#39;s how it went
Two weeks ago my students completed a lab. The lab involved reading in a poorly indented C++ program and spit out a properly indented one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Teachers Teach</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/let-teachers-teach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 08:57:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/let-teachers-teach/</guid>
      <description>Mark Guzdial&#39;s post the other day about direct isntruction struck a chord with me. Right up front, Mark said:
  The research evidence is growing that students learn better through direct instruction rather than through a discovery-based method, where we expect students to figure things out for themselves.  Quite a surprise to the teachers who have been beaten over the head with &#34;everything must be discovery&#34; in recent years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local Tech and Local Learning</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/local-tech-local-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 11:08:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/local-tech-local-learning/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I took twenty four of my first year students up to Catskills Conf. As usual it was a great weekend. I particularly enjoyed this years talks.
I found one talk particularly engaging. Jordan Koschei gave at talk titled Digital Terroir. Terroir refers to the natural envorinment in which a wine is produced - the ground, the climate, everything. It&#39;s why wine (and foods) produced in one location taste differently than the same things mamde elsewhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 53 Emailing Org Agenda</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-53-emailing-org-agenda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 08:55:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-53-emailing-org-agenda/</guid>
      <description>I use both org-mode and Google Calendar for scheduling. I like Google Calendar because: It&#39;s pretty universal so I can issue and accept calendar invites. It works well with my phone and other mobile devices. The rest of my family doesn&#39;t live in Emacs :-(.   I prefer using org-mode beacuse: Emacs I prefer, for the most part, to control my data.  I partially sync the two platforms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs Episode 52 - Eyebrowse</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-52-eyebrowse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 14:35:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-52-eyebrowse/</guid>
      <description>I was originally going to do a video on how I set things up so that I get an email every morning with my org-mode agenda but that&#39;s going to be something of an ordeal. I have to create a droploet on Digital Ocean, set up SyncThing and a mail server and lots of other things.
I&#39;ll get to that video at some point but in the meantime I saw this thread on the Emacs subreddit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catskills Conf -  Knitting for Good 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 17:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</guid>
      <description>Two weekends ago I took a group of my first year students up to Catskills Conf, an annual event that I describe as &#34;light tech conference with a focus on diversity and inclusion meets summer camp.&#34; I&#39;ve written about the event before if anyone&#39;s interested in more details. As in past years, Devorah ran her knitting for good project. In each of the first two years of the project, attendees of Catskills Conf learned how to know and collectively knit, crocheted and assembled a blanket for Project Linux which provides hand made blankets to children in crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Scripts To Freestyle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2018 17:35:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</guid>
      <description>I just read this post by Bethany Crystal - Going off script.
Bethany writes that while she normally essentially scripts important presentations, this time she went more off the cuff.
It made me think about how I teach and a disturbing trend I&#39;ve seen in CS education and education in general.
I&#39;ve never strictly used a script for teaching. When I started I did use very detailed lesson plans. Back then I was teaching math.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 51 - Day to day work with org-mode</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-51-dtd-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 17:30:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-51-dtd-org/</guid>
      <description>I can&#39;t believe that I haven&#39;t made a video since the beginning of summer!!!
Part of the reason is that I haven&#39;t had any video ideas that have motivated me and the other reason is that the Fall is my busiest season.
In any event, here&#39;s the latest installment.
Take a look at how I use Emacs and more specifically org-mode for my day to day work. Sometimes I use the fancy power tools but to be honest, most of the time, I stick to the basics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman - part 3</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 17:25:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/</guid>
      <description>Parts 1 and 2  Part 1 Part 2  Part 3 In the first two parts of this set of posts I wrote about the motivation and design a question answering system that can answer &#34;who&#34; queries like &#34;who played Spiderman&#34; or &#34;who shot John Lennon?&#34; It&#39;s not perfect. When doing the Spiderman query, chances are the desired answer will be at or near the top of the list of most frequently appearing names but so will &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 16:04:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</guid>
      <description>Parts 1 and 3  Part 1 Part 3  Part 2 When we left off last time we used a search engine API to gather a whole bunch of documents with the term &#34;played Spiderman&#34; or &#34;who played Spiderman.&#34; Now we have to process these documents to answer the question. Fortunately, the documents are basically just big strings of text.
Since we&#39;re doing a &#34;who&#34; query we want to find all the names in all the documents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 1 or my Nifty Assignment (that was rejected)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 17:16:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</guid>
      <description>Parts 2 and 3  Part 2 Part 3  I wasn&#39;t going to teach this lesson today. I was planning on starting a multi day project starting with an exercise in specification writing and design.
Beforehand though, we had to talk about classes. One of my students asked if probability and/or statistics were really important for CS. I started to cite a few examples and then decided to segue into this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compile Each Concept</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2018 14:46:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;ve all been there:
  Student: Teacher, I need help  Teacher (comes over)  Student (shows screen listing three bazillion errors)  The student has just written pages of code and finally decided to try to run it only to end up with pages of errors.
Error messages can at times be hard to read for beginners but to see and truth be told, they frequently don&#39;t even read them but over the years I&#39;ve developed a practice that I&#39;ve found helpful as a software developer and if students adopt the same practice it can save them a lot of time and effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a feeling of community. Students aren&#39;t on campus every day and come from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&#39;t have a CS &#34;hang out&#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&#39;re scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
I&#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Globals Breaks And Returns, oh my</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 15:48:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</guid>
      <description>Never use global variables Never break out of a loop  These are two &#34;best practices&#34; that are frequently touted in early CS classes both at the high school and college level.
They came up a couple of times yesterday. Once in the Facebook APCS-A teachers group and once on Alfred Thompson&#39;s blog.
Alfred post was topically on global variables. Actually it was deeper than just global variables. It&#39;s also about how students progress - what they can figure out at various stages of progress and how what seems like a good idea early on the path to computer science doesn&#39;t seem so great later on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the students know more than the teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 16:07:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;ve heard it many times with computer science - &#34;the kids know more than the teacher.&#34;
On the one hand, the truth is that this isn&#39;t so much the case. Kids might use computers all the time but they don&#39;t necessarily know much about them or about computer science (link 1, link 2). Then you have students who think they know all about CS but really don&#39;t. They might have picked up a bit of coding somewhere but more often than not, the knowledge is pretty superficial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve written before about why Hunter College CS is so important for NYC and I&#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors CS program - a program in which students receive a scholarship along with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have made a lot of progress over the past two years and each year I roll out new special activities and events for my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS vs CT vs Coding</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 12:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s been a lot of buzz recently concernting Computational Thinking (CT) vs Computer Science (CS) vs Coding / Programming on the interwebs.
 Some of the questions and concerns that I&#39;ve seen recently include: What is CT?? Will rich schools get CS and poor only CT? Will rich schools get CS and poor on coding?  The first question is a big one and as a community we haven&#39;t answered it yet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium and other blog sites you might get the idea that you&#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful lessons they&#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that worked for them or things they think will work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What CS should we teach in HS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 16:54:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to chime in on Alfred Thompson&#39;s post last week on what to include in a HS CS class but was working on moving blogging platforms so didn&#39;t get a chance so I&#39;ll say a few words here.
If you&#39;ve been here before you probably know I&#39;m not a fan of the standards and I certainly am no fan of the College Board and the AP program so what&#39;s my take?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post again</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/firstpost/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 17:21:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/firstpost/</guid>
      <description>The new site is live. I&#39;m now running a Hugo based blog. I set it up using the Mainroad theme which seems to support everything I want.
Out of the box Hugo supports org-mode with pretty much all of its niceties like:
 code highlighting org-mode structure (lists, tables) html can be directly embedded tags and categories  The Mainroad theme added:
 MathJax Analytics An easy menu widgets for the sidebar  It was pretty easy to customize and deploying to GitHub pages is pretty simple.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>