<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>college on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/college/</link>
    <description>Recent content in college on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 08:25:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/college/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hunter Daedalus Fall 2019 recruiting class</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 08:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</guid>
      <description>Now that high school seniors have all committed to their respective colleges I though I&amp;#39;d share some information on Hunter&amp;#39;s incoming Daedalus (honors CS) cohort.  I joke about the first cohort saying that nobody applied to the program. That&amp;#39;s kind of true. I jointed Hunter a little over three years ago in late January. That was after high school seniors had already applied to college and at that time the program didn&amp;#39;t exist.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting schools and talking tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 15:49:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</guid>
      <description>Back in September I talked about embarking on my Fall 2018 HS CS Tour. Since then I&amp;#39;ve visited about a dozen schools. I&amp;#39;d like to thank my friends who helped connect me to schools - particularly Aankit Patel and Diane Levitt.  Even though the original motivation for the visits was to get the word out about Hunter CS and the awesome things we&amp;#39;re doing in the Hunter CS Honors program I always tried to make my talks about something that would be relevant for the entire audience and not just the few that were great fits for my program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve written before about why Hunter College CS is so important for NYC and I&amp;#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors CS program - a program in which students receive a scholarship along with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have made a lot of progress over the past two years and each year I roll out new special activities and events for my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter CS - a lot of progress in a short time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I was back on campus for an early orientation session for Hunter&amp;#39;s incoming Daedalus CS honors students. It was the first time all of us got to meet face to face. The students I met with will be my third cohort. I got to thinking how far we&amp;#39;ve come in under three years.  Hunter&amp;#39;s had a strong but little known undergraduate CS program for as long as I&amp;#39;ve known.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>