<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>College on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/college/</link>
    <description>Recent content in College on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/college/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve written before about why Hunter College CS is so important for NYC and I&#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors CS program - a program in which students receive a scholarship along with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have made a lot of progress over the past two years and each year I roll out new special activities and events for my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter CS - a lot of progress in a short time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I was back on campus for an early orientation session for Hunter&#39;s incoming Daedalus CS honors students. It was the first time all of us got to meet face to face. The students I met with will be my third cohort. I got to thinking how far we&#39;ve come in under three years.
Hunter&#39;s had a strong but little known undergraduate CS program for as long as I&#39;ve known. Much like any program, we&#39;ve got our strengths and weaknesses but you go through our program and academically you&#39;ll be as well prepared as from anywhere else.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>