<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/community/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunion Season</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/reunion-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/reunion-season/</guid>
      <description>Thanksgiving is reunion season. Stuyvesant and I&#39;m guessing other high schools traditionally hold their reunions, at least the five and ten year ones over the holiday weekend. It makes sense since grads who&#39;ve moved away might still be coming to town for family celebrations.
This year, I was invited to the Stuy07 ten year reunion. I considered crashing the Stuy97 20 year but it was at the same time and too far away.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teachers - we need you to blog</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/cs-teachers-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/cs-teachers-blog/</guid>
      <description>At this past year&#39;s CSTA conference, a few of us huddled in a corner voiced a very common lament - &#34;it would be great if more CS teachers blogged.&#34; It really would be. We&#39;re still a relatively small community and while there&#39;s some good conversation going on on mailing lists and on Facebook, those aren&#39;t easily discoverable or accessible and in the case of Facebook, there&#39;s a question of ownership and permanence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Educators StackExchange</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/cs-educators-stackexchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/cs-educators-stackexchange/</guid>
      <description>The CS Educators StackExchange is now in public beta. For those of you who are not in tech, StackExchange is a network of question answering sites. StackOverflow is probably the most famous - many peoples go to site for computer science and programming questions and answers.
During this period of public beta the site will be working on defining itself and also on developing a critical mass of users. I hope the site succeeds and I encourage everyone to check it out, ask questions, answer some and let&#39;s all see where this goes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knitting at a Tech Conference</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/knitting-tech-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/knitting-tech-conference/</guid>
      <description>This past weekend was Catskills Conf, one of my favorite events of the year.
Last year, Devorah joined me and also enjoyed the show.
If you know my wife, you know she&#39;s always knitting. Ok, not true, she&#39;s always knitting, spinning, weaving or performing some other form of fiber craft.
I can&#39;t complain. That&#39;s how I ended up with my Kandinsky, Dust Puppy and Yoda sweaters and my awesome Kang and Kodos socks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waking up in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/catskillsconf-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/catskillsconf-2016/</guid>
      <description>Waking up to a beautiful brisk morning at the Ashokan Center in the Hudson Valley.
Last year, Devorah and I attended the first Catskillsconf, a tech conference in Olivebridge, NY. It was an amazing and unique experience. I can only describe it as Tech Conference meets Summer camp. Where else can you hear talks by people like Dennis Crowley and an alos hear the music of Mike and ruthy.
This year, I gave another educaiton rant and to add to the fun, Devorah&#39;s been leading a knitting for Charity project and teaching attendees to knit:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can NYCIST become in leader in CS Education?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/nycist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/nycist/</guid>
      <description>I only learned about NYCIST last spring. They&#39;re the &#34;New York Consortium for Independent School Technologists.&#34; They had something of an open house that I attended. I heard about them from friend and fellow CS educator Saber Khan.
Last Thursday I spent an afternoon and evening with NYCIST members for a discussion of the state of K12 Computer Science Education in the City.
Most of my work has been with public schools and most of the teachers I know, public school teachers so it was great to make new friends in the Independent school community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impostor Syndrome - I&#39;m not good enough</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/imposters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/imposters/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been meaning to comment on these tweets for a while:
I went to high school with some scary smart people. Never made math team. Didn&amp;#39;t get into honors math. Thought I wasn&amp;#39;t good at it.
&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) June 30, 2016  @zamansky :D
that&amp;#39;s the thing though you can get such an inferiority complex by always comparing yourself to others https://t.co/LvaMjp1WVf
&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) July 1, 2016</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/end-to-act-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/end-to-act-1/</guid>
      <description>If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching career, then our family&#39;s West Coast swing was a nice way to pull down the curtain.
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she&#39;s interning at Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle for a couple of days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</guid>
      <description>Morgan Roderick pictures
https://www.flickr.com/photos/morganroderick/sets/72157660040372060/with/22362235148/
&amp;ndash;!&amp;gt;
   The Hudson Valley&#39;s a beautiful place, particularly during the Fall. We don&#39;t get up there as much as we should - usually just for apple picking and then for the New York Sheep and Wool Festival.  It&#39;s a region with great food, hiking, natural beauty, history and more.  So, what exactly is growing?  The Hudson Valley Tech community.  I first heard about what Hudson Valley was doing around Tech back at the August New York Tech Meetup.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StuyCS  family from coast to coast</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-02-11-tapia-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-02-11-tapia-2/</guid>
      <description>I think my one regret over the years is that I haven&amp;rsquo;t done much travel. So, when I had the opportunity to go to the 2014 Tapia conference, I jumped at the chance. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get to see too much of Seattle, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. Now I&amp;rsquo;ve more incentive to go back.
In addition to seeing new sites, it also gave me an opportunity to see friends that I don&amp;rsquo;t get to see too often.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NYTM &#43; StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-07-11-nytm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-07-11-nytm/</guid>
      <description>For those of that don&amp;rsquo;t know, the New York Tech Meetup it&amp;rsquo;s one of the things that help make the New York Tech Scene so awesome.
It&amp;rsquo;s a group of some 30k+ members and once a month, at Skriball Center at NYU they hold a meetup. It&amp;rsquo;s really quite an event. Members of the tech community demo their projects, there&amp;rsquo;s question and answer time, and afterwards theres a gathering for schmoozing amongst the crowd and the presenters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demo Night</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-06-27-demo_night/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-06-27-demo_night/</guid>
      <description>This past year, I was able to convince my administration to allow me to create a new course - Software Development. I really felt there was something missing in our kids CS preparation - missing both from Stuy&amp;rsquo;s program and from many youngsters college experiences.
I plan to do a few posts on the course, it&amp;rsquo;s design, implementation, and lessons learned, but for today, let&amp;rsquo;s look at the years culminating event:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investing in People</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2012-12-20-investing-in-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2012-12-20-investing-in-people/</guid>
      <description>A little over a year ago, I decided it was time to reach out to my alums, a group I refer to as the &amp;ldquo;Stuy CS family&amp;rdquo; and try to get us together. The most rewarding part of my job involves the relationships I&amp;rsquo;ve developed over the years but is was always between me and my alums and them to their classmates. This was an attempt to start building a network that spanned the years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni Day(s)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2012-11-25-alum-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2012-11-25-alum-days/</guid>
      <description>The day before Thanksgiving is always fun. For as long as I can remember, recent graduates descend upon Stuy. For the most part, they mull around the senior bar but we get our share up in 301.
This year was a little quiet but I got to see more than my share of graduates over the weekend as I attended the 2002 and 2007 class reunions. I&amp;rsquo;ve only been invited to a handful of reunions and really consider it an honor when I am.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Work</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2012-11-02-back-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2012-11-02-back-to-work/</guid>
      <description>On going back to work today Since school was still out due to Sandy, we ran a second online class yesterday. At the end of the session, which I&amp;rsquo;ll summarize below, I told the class what I wanted them to accomplish today and over the weekend. One student queried &amp;ldquo;you mean no class on Friday :-(?&amp;rdquo; Alas no &amp;ndash; while students aren&amp;rsquo;t reporting to school this morning, teachers are.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>