<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 18:52:08 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/community/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CSEvents.nyc</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 18:52:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago, a handful of CS Ed folks got together. One issue we discussed was that of finding CS related events both for students and teachers.
One of our conveners, Dan Fenjves of UPPERLINE CODE talked about possibly hosting a central site. Today, Dan announced http://csevents.nyc/. A site where organizers can submit and students and teachers can find upcoming events. Right now it&#39;s NY centric but it does list some events beyond the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CS Education Subreddit</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 07:37:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</guid>
      <description>Amy Ko posted this yesterday:
CSEd people: many have struggled to use Twitter for discussion. How about Twitter for broadcasting, but when replies turn to discussion, we use https://t.co/2oivuriOoU? It&amp;#39;s a better (albeit imperfect) platform for civil discourse. Subreddit mods @AustinCorgiBart @zamansky?
&amp;mdash; Amy J. Ko (@amyjko) February 21, 2020 
I&#39;d love to see more traffic there. For full disclosure, I&#39;m one of the moderators but in my defense, I&#39;m not much of a moderator and as Cory said, I too am happy to either keep moderating or to step aside.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presenting At CSTA 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 13:05:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</guid>
      <description>Presenting at CSTA 2020 I noticed a few tweets and posts from people announcing that they&#39;d be presenting at CSTA2020 - the big computer science teachers conference held every July.
A common thread in a few of these were trepidation&#39;s presenters. Excited to be doing this but nervous.
It&#39;s interesting that teachers, myself included, sometimes get nervous before presentations even though we present every day as part of our jobs. I know it&#39;s different as we have the same kids every day but even day 1 jitters each semester aren&#39;t the same as the presentation anxiety that some of us face.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicating With Students - maybe GitHub to the rescue</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 10:17:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/</guid>
      <description>Out of class student communication is always a challenge. There are plenty of options:
 Piazza Facebook group Slack, Discord, or other chat system Discourse, Vanilla or other discussion forum system Mailing list  but all have warts.
I shared my thoughts on a number of these options a while ago but thought I&#39;d update them now.
Most of my opinions hold form my earlier post. I was using and continue to use a mailing list as I can be pretty sure that students will get the email and they don&#39;t have to go to any outside site or application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni Anniversaries</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alumni-anniversaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 07:32:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alumni-anniversaries/</guid>
      <description>Two days ago, a teacher&#39;s comment on a frustrating situation made me mad.
Yesterday, I got to be part of something that made me very happy.
Last night, Devorah and I ventured out to Coney Island to celebrate the twentieth wedding anniversary of two former students. It&#39;s such a joy and an honor to be included in these types of life events and even more so to count the couple and so many other former students and friends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB World 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 19:35:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-world/</guid>
      <description>For those of you who don&#39;t know, MongoDB is a very popular NoSQL database. NoSQL is an overarching term describing databases that are not relational and don&#39;t implement Structured Query Language (SQL). In a relational database your data is stored in tables with columns - think spreadsheet where each row of the table is a record in the database. You link tables together via a common field or row name. NoSQL databases work differently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels in the Architecture - when they used to build schools like cathedrals.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 07:31:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</guid>
      <description>One of the side benefits of visiting high schools is that I end up going all over the city. This takes me to neighborhoods that I normally wouldn&#39;t have reason to visit. For a New York History wonk that can be pretty cool even if you just limit yourself to looking at the schools. A few of the schools I visited in the last couple of weeks before the new year were self contained whole building schools:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:59:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</guid>
      <description>Thanksgiving weekend is also reunion weekend. I&#39;ve been on and off invited to Stuy reunions over the years. Not as often it seems as some teachers but more often than others. I always do my best to attend. I have very fond memories of many students and many classes over many years and think a lot about them so feel very honored whenever I&#39;m invited to one of these.
In the past each class due a reunion did its own thing - some club or bar usually in Manhattan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a feeling of community. Students aren&#39;t on campus every day and come from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&#39;t have a CS &#34;hang out&#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&#39;re scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
I&#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my honors students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunion Season</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/</guid>
      <description>Thanksgiving is reunion season. Stuyvesant and I&#39;m guessing other high schools traditionally hold their reunions, at least the five and ten year ones over the holiday weekend. It makes sense since grads who&#39;ve moved away might still be coming to town for family celebrations.
This year, I was invited to the Stuy07 ten year reunion. I considered crashing the Stuy97 20 year but it was at the same time and too far away.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teachers - we need you to blog</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</guid>
      <description>At this past year&#39;s CSTA conference, a few of us huddled in a corner voiced a very common lament - &#34;it would be great if more CS teachers blogged.&#34; It really would be. We&#39;re still a relatively small community and while there&#39;s some good conversation going on on mailing lists and on Facebook, those aren&#39;t easily discoverable or accessible and in the case of Facebook, there&#39;s a question of ownership and permanence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Educators StackExchange</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/</guid>
      <description>The CS Educators StackExchange is now in public beta. For those of you who are not in tech, StackExchange is a network of question answering sites. StackOverflow is probably the most famous - many peoples go to site for computer science and programming questions and answers.
During this period of public beta the site will be working on defining itself and also on developing a critical mass of users. I hope the site succeeds and I encourage everyone to check it out, ask questions, answer some and let&#39;s all see where this goes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knitting at a Tech Conference</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/</guid>
      <description>This past weekend was Catskills Conf, one of my favorite events of the year.
Last year, Devorah joined me and also enjoyed the show.
If you know my wife, you know she&#39;s always knitting. Ok, not true, she&#39;s always knitting, spinning, weaving or performing some other form of fiber craft.
I can&#39;t complain. That&#39;s how I ended up with my Kandinsky, Dust Puppy and Yoda sweaters and my awesome Kang and Kodos socks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waking up in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/</guid>
      <description>Waking up to a beautiful brisk morning at the Ashokan Center in the Hudson Valley.
Last year, Devorah and I attended the first Catskillsconf, a tech conference in Olivebridge, NY. It was an amazing and unique experience. I can only describe it as Tech Conference meets Summer camp. Where else can you hear talks by people like Dennis Crowley and an alos hear the music of Mike and ruthy.
This year, I gave another educaiton rant and to add to the fun, Devorah&#39;s been leading a knitting for Charity project and teaching attendees to knit:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can NYCIST become in leader in CS Education?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nycist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nycist/</guid>
      <description>I only learned about NYCIST last spring. They&#39;re the &#34;New York Consortium for Independent School Technologists.&#34; They had something of an open house that I attended. I heard about them from friend and fellow CS educator Saber Khan.
Last Thursday I spent an afternoon and evening with NYCIST members for a discussion of the state of K12 Computer Science Education in the City.
Most of my work has been with public schools and most of the teachers I know, public school teachers so it was great to make new friends in the Independent school community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impostor Syndrome - I&#39;m not good enough</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been meaning to comment on these tweets for a while:
I went to high school with some scary smart people. Never made math team. Didn&amp;#39;t get into honors math. Thought I wasn&amp;#39;t good at it.
&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) June 30, 2016  @zamansky :D
that&amp;#39;s the thing though you can get such an inferiority complex by always comparing yourself to others https://t.co/LvaMjp1WVf
&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) July 1, 2016</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</guid>
      <description>If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching career, then our family&#39;s West Coast swing was a nice way to pull down the curtain.
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she&#39;s interning at Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle for a couple of days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discussion Silos</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-03-discussion-silos.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-03-discussion-silos.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 In response to the past couple of days where my friends and fellow CS Ed advocates Alfred Thompson, Rob Underwood, and I had a nice little discussion via our blogs, Alfred wrote this.  It&#39;s great when a number of voices in the community have an open discussion but one of the things I found myself lamenting was the fact that a lot of the discussion isn&#39;t truly accessible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halloween 2015 - the video</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-01-halloween-video-2015.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-01-halloween-video-2015.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 As a teacher, sometimes your gut tells you to do something and it turns out to be a really good idea.  That&#39;s what happened in October, 1994. I decided to dress up as Groo the Wanderer for Halloween. I never dressed in costume for school before and back then, no many did. A few students and very few teachers.  Afterwards, I noticed that my younger students - the ones that didn&#39;t know me that well yet, really loosened up and so a tradition was born.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inner voices</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-30-halloween-2015.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-30-halloween-2015.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} div.half {width:50%;} 

 It&#39;s Halloween again. This time, &#34;Inside Out.&#34;  No video yet, but stay tuned.  For the time being, enjoy some of our past madness:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</guid>
      <description>The Hudson Valley&#39;s a beautiful place, particularly during the Fall. We don&#39;t get up there as much as we should - usually just for apple picking and then for the New York Sheep and Wool Festival.  It&#39;s a region with great food, hiking, natural beauty, history and more.  So, what exactly is growing?  The Hudson Valley Tech community.  I first heard about what Hudson Valley was doing around Tech back at the August New York Tech Meetup.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Semi Formal</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-15-semi-formal.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-15-semi-formal.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
  Today marked the last day of classes and time for the 8th annual Stuy CS Semi Formal.  
  What&#39;s the Stuy CS Semi Formal? It&#39;s another bad idea that we refuse to let die. Eight years ago JonAlf joked that someone in class joked that they should have a party and they should all get dressed up. My thought? &#34;YEAH!!! LET&#39;S DO IT!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just another day at StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 .photo {width:60%;}   Last post was a little heavy so just a short fun one for today.  &#34;Just another day at StuyCS.&#34; That was the subject of the email Brian sent with the photo above. What&#39;s going on?  We&#39;re working on advanced JavaScript while also looking at Backbone.js.  Now, as sometimes happens, Batya, while in her CS class up at college, decided to open up a Google chat with me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions part 2 - My Stuy, Your Stuy</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-30-reunions-2.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-30-reunions-2.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 About a month ago, I was at my 30 year high school reunion. Yesterday I was at the class of 2009&#39;s 5 year one. Stuy 2004 also had their 10 year reunion last night.  It&#39;s always nice to be invited to reunions - I know it&#39;s largely dependent on who&#39;s on the organizing committee but it&#39;s nice to be remembered.  Last time I wrote about Stuy reunions I noted how similar they all are.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hi, I&#39;m Mike, I went to high school with....</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-16-weddings.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-16-weddings.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 That&#39;s how I introduce myself whenever I attend a former student&#39;s wedding. It leads to all sorts of confusion.  Even better was the time I was at the wedding of two former students. I had just dropped around 65 pounds and was wearing my hair differently. I sat at a table filled with former students that didn&#39;t recognize me &amp;#x2013; they had no reason to expect me, out of context and all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rich and Rich - two legends on opposite sides of the hall</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} .leftborder {border-left:1px; border-style:solid;} 
 We&#39;ll get back to CS content soon, but for now:  Last Tuesday was Election day - no students in the school - a day devoted to professional development. Traditionally, math team coaches from around the city descend on Stuy for a day full of lectures, discussion, and general catching up. I&#39;ve never actually attended these meetings. In the past, they were for math team coaches only and this year, I was actually allowed to do something with the CS teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evil</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-31-halloween.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-31-halloween.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 October 31, 2014. Twenty years after my first Stuy Halloween.  
 Little did I know that a goof of an idea would turn into a twenty year tradition. This year, I had a chance to team up with Natan in his senior year. Last time we had a Zamansky family duo for Halloween it was Batya cameoing in our Austin Powers - Dr. Evil sketch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions, StuyCS and community</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-25-reunions.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-25-reunions.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
  In a few hours Devorah and I will be off to our thirty year high school reunion. It&#39;s going to be a boat ride - reminiscent of those excursion day trips to Bear Mountain that Stuy had back in the day.  Having taught CS at Stuy for the last twenty plus years, I&#39;ve also been invited to my share of reunions as a teacher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An old tradition reborn</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-06-25-joesshanghai.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-06-25-joesshanghai.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 Yesterday, some of the seniors from the 301 crowd along with a few teachers had an end of year dinner at Joe&#39;s Shanghai. 
 While it&#39;s Famous for its soup dumplings: 
 I&#39;m partial to the braised pork shoulder: 
 We haven&#39;t had a 301 dinner in a long time, but I remember the crew, first unnamed, then using the moniker &#34;the Z-team&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I love about StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-20-wolfram.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-20-wolfram.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} .pic {height:500px;width:500px;} 
 One of the things I love about StuyCS is that we&#39;ve built a true Geek culture.  Last week, we had a last minute visitor - Stephen Wolfram. Well known for Mathematica and more importantly, Wolfram Alpha, without which our students wouldn&#39;t be able to complete all their homework.  The only problem was that we had about 24 hours from when the visit was confirmed til the talk was to take place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StuyCS  family from coast to coast</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-11-tapia-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-11-tapia-2/</guid>
      <description>I think my one regret over the years is that I haven&amp;rsquo;t done much travel. So, when I had the opportunity to go to the 2014 Tapia conference, I jumped at the chance. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get to see too much of Seattle, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. Now I&amp;rsquo;ve more incentive to go back.
In addition to seeing new sites, it also gave me an opportunity to see friends that I don&amp;rsquo;t get to see too often.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four to beam up</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-31-halloween.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-31-halloween.html/</guid>
      <description>Today was Halloween. This year we were the crew of the Enterprise. The original series, that is.
 
Overall, the school had a much more subdued spirit than past years but it was fun. Certainly more fun for me than the past couple of years.  For those of you that don&#39;t know - I have a long history of going all out for Halloween. Starting in October 1994 as Groo the Wanderer:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NYTM &#43; StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-11-nytm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-11-nytm/</guid>
      <description>For those of that don&amp;rsquo;t know, the New York Tech Meetup it&amp;rsquo;s one of the things that help make the New York Tech Scene so awesome.
It&amp;rsquo;s a group of some 30k+ members and once a month, at Skriball Center at NYU they hold a meetup. It&amp;rsquo;s really quite an event. Members of the tech community demo their projects, there&amp;rsquo;s question and answer time, and afterwards theres a gathering for schmoozing amongst the crowd and the presenters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demo Night</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-06-27-demo_night/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-06-27-demo_night/</guid>
      <description>This past year, I was able to convince my administration to allow me to create a new course - Software Development. I really felt there was something missing in our kids CS preparation - missing both from Stuy&amp;rsquo;s program and from many youngsters college experiences.
I plan to do a few posts on the course, it&amp;rsquo;s design, implementation, and lessons learned, but for today, let&amp;rsquo;s look at the years culminating event:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking it out of the school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-10-taking-it-out-of-the-school.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-10-taking-it-out-of-the-school.html/</guid>
      <description>Inspired by the likes of Jon Simantov and David Lerner as well as the greater Stuy CS family, a few of us have been working on CSTUY, Computer Science and Technology for Urban Youth. Yeah, we backed into the acronym. Let&#39;s bring Stuy CS out of Stuy so we can work on inspiring a wider range of students.  Well, last Wednesday we had our inaugural event. Hosted by NY TechStars (thanks Moisey), we invited 75 youngsters to an evening of talks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investing in People</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-20-investing-in-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-20-investing-in-people/</guid>
      <description>A little over a year ago, I decided it was time to reach out to my alums, a group I refer to as the &amp;ldquo;Stuy CS family&amp;rdquo; and try to get us together. The most rewarding part of my job involves the relationships I&amp;rsquo;ve developed over the years but is was always between me and my alums and them to their classmates. This was an attempt to start building a network that spanned the years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni Day(s)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-25-alum-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-25-alum-days/</guid>
      <description>The day before Thanksgiving is always fun. For as long as I can remember, recent graduates descend upon Stuy. For the most part, they mull around the senior bar but we get our share up in 301.
This year was a little quiet but I got to see more than my share of graduates over the weekend as I attended the 2002 and 2007 class reunions. I&amp;rsquo;ve only been invited to a handful of reunions and really consider it an honor when I am.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Work</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-02-back-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-02-back-to-work/</guid>
      <description>On going back to work today Since school was still out due to Sandy, we ran a second online class yesterday. At the end of the session, which I&amp;rsquo;ll summarize below, I told the class what I wanted them to accomplish today and over the weekend. One student queried &amp;ldquo;you mean no class on Friday :-(?&amp;rdquo; Alas no &amp;ndash; while students aren&amp;rsquo;t reporting to school this morning, teachers are.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandy Bridge and Screen Casting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-10-31-sandy-bridge.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-10-31-sandy-bridge.html/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s what the bridge leading across the West Side Highway over to Stuy during the storm. Hence the title with the weak tech reference.

The storm has kept the schools closed all week so it&#39;s as good a time as any to try to resurrect this blog.  As you can see, I&#39;ve moved from blogger to a Jekyll based blog hosted on Github. I&#39;m really liking the way it works but more on that at a later date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Favorite Year Teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher.html/</guid>
      <description>Sorry for the weak title and movie reference.
It&#39;s teacher appreciation week -- one of our lesser celebrated weeks. I&#39;m waiting for the annual letter we get from the chancellor. Given the level of teacher bashing over the last few years, I&#39;ve recently found their emails amusing.
I though I&#39;d take the time to thank a few of my most influential teachers. To paraphrase: whatever good I&#39;ve been able to do, it has been because I have stood on the shoulders of giants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuing the Journey</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-04-24-continuing-journey.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-04-24-continuing-journey.html/</guid>
      <description>Shortly after our event at Foursquare, I was chatting with Kevin Friedman (Stuy &#39;96). Kevin&#39;s startup is Cojourneo&amp;nbsp;and since it has an educational bent, he thought I might be interested in hearing about it.
I certainly was.
Rather than visiting Kevin, I thought it would be fun to have him come down after school, present Cojourneo to any students that wanted to stay late and then field questions.
Cojourneo is an interesting product.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checking in with the family</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-03-31-checking-in-with-family.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-03-31-checking-in-with-family.html/</guid>
      <description>&#34;...&amp;nbsp;the standardized courses don&#39;t shed much light on future opportunities and they make it hard for students to identify what they&#39;re most interested in. The CS department, on the other hand, is great at demonstrating all the things that are going on in the modern comp sci world.&#34;&amp;nbsp;-- Asa, one of our current CS students.Asa&#39;s comment was in response to an event we held last Tuesday. We brought 100 current students up to FourSquare&amp;nbsp;along with 100 of our CS alums for a mixer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Favorite Student</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-01-15-my-favorite-student.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-01-15-my-favorite-student.html/</guid>
      <description>Fred Wilson and me at #SOTC2012Last week I was given the honor of attending the State of the City address. The mayor was announcing a new school for the fall. An Academy for Software Engineering. This has been in the works for a while and has a long way to go but the announcement was a major step. The project really got its start a couple of years ago. I&#39;d been working hard for years prior trying to get the city to help me grow the program I developed at Stuyvesant, but until Fred got involved, there was no movement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talking Shop</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-06-talking-shop.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-06-talking-shop.html/</guid>
      <description>During my first few years teaching computer science, I frequently felt isolated. As pretty much the only CS guy I really didn&#39;t have any one to &#34;talk shop&#34; with. It&#39;s hard to bounce pedagogical ideas off of your colleagues when they teach subjects that are tangentially related, at best. I now consider myself extremely fortunate that I have four terrific friends and colleagues teaching CS with me. Now we have the same advantage that other teachers have enjoyed for years.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>