<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tech on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/tech/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tech on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 11:14:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/tech/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech Jobs, Diversity, and Equity in the wake of the Amazon/NYC debacle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 11:14:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</guid>
      <description>I was planning on either following up on how I use GitHub classroom or commenting on the recent NY Times opinion piece on the College Board but the follow up, fall out, and polarization from the Amazon NY thing has been stuck in my head so I thought I&#39;d write a bit more about it.
Like my previous post, this isn&#39;t really about Amazon but rather about the long game, equity, and diversity and how a lot of people are fooling themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Amazon HQ2 in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-amazon-hq/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 17:57:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-amazon-hq/</guid>
      <description>That was the big tech news today. I know there was a good deal of vocal outrage about the deal but to be honest I was pretty surprised by the news. Normally deals like these get steamrolled through for better or worse.
I have decidedly mixed feelings about this. On the one hand, I have no problem with Amazon - I&#39;ve got a bunch of former students working there. Mostly in Seattle but at least one in NYC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tech or the Teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</guid>
      <description>Every morning one of the first things I do is quickly glance at my emails and other notifications. I really should wait until I&#39;m more awake but old habits die hard.
As some of you know over the past couple of years I&#39;ve been making a series of videos and related post on using my editor of choice, Emacs. I&#39;ve done 48 videos, have over 2500 subscribers on YouTube and people seem to find some value from the series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</guid>
      <description>If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching career, then our family&#39;s West Coast swing was a nice way to pull down the curtain.
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she&#39;s interning at Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle for a couple of days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hillary and Student Loans</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I read over Hillary&#39;s briefing on her initiative on Technology and Innovation.
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have my doubts. My feeling is that she&#39;s pretty much aligned with the current administration education wise and the current administration has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public education.
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much like some of the others, I don&#39;t want to get into that today.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>