<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teaching on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teaching on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2018 17:35:56 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>From Scripts To Freestyle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2018 17:35:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</guid>
      <description>I just read this post by Bethany Crystal - Going off script.
Bethany writes that while she normally essentially scripts important presentations, this time she went more off the cuff.
It made me think about how I teach and a disturbing trend I&#39;ve seen in CS education and education in general.
I&#39;ve never strictly used a script for teaching. When I started I did use very detailed lesson plans. Back then I was teaching math.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium and other blog sites you might get the idea that you&#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful lessons they&#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that worked for them or things they think will work.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>