<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>teaching on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (teaching)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 08:28:56 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Yes, deadlines do matter</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/late-assignments/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 08:28:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/late-assignments/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been seeing a few threads lately talking about the virtues of
allowing students to hand in assignments late. Not just late but
pretty much whenever they want. This attitude seems to be related with
things like mastery or specification grading, which I believe in but
it&amp;#39;s not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The threads start with someone saying that assignments shouldn&amp;#39;t have
deadlines or some variant and the thread proceeds with a bunch of
people chiming in as to why a teacher who actually enforces deadlines
is an inhuman monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, before I dive in, I do think that a teacher should have some
flexibility with deadlines but allowing students to hand in anything
at any time is probably not a good idea in most cases and any teacher
or self styled educator who proudly proclaims that deadlines in all
cases are evil should just step off their soap box and maybe look more
into their own teaching practice. Of course, the teacher that likewise
says strict to the minute deadlines with no flexibility should do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at both sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Advantages of no deadlines
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The push here is that students have things going on outside of school
and an arbitrary deadline doesn&amp;#39;t account for this. Particularly over
the past couple of years students have had to contend with all sorts
of difficulties that could be unique or semi-unique to them or at
least they hit at different times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other push is that students might get certain concepts at
different times so a student might not be able to finish something
when originally assigned but could very well have mastered the concept
by the end of the term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, there&amp;#39;s the thought that those most susceptible to missing
deadlines are the most in need of support. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I agree with these issues and do feel that some deadline flexibility
is warranted or at least some mechanism to mitigate a missed deadline
or two or a bad grade and I certainly agree with the idea that the
important thing is that the student gets it at the end and not
necessarily that they get it when first introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, the idea of largely or wholly eliminating deadlines just
doesn&amp;#39;t fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Why deadlines matter
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The usual first response is that having no deadlines rewards bad
behavior. This can be true but it really depends on circumstances. On
the other hand there are some legit reasons for deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A big one is snowballing - some courses are compartmentalized. The CS
topics course I just taught was. Each unit was independent so in
theory any could be completed at any time. Here the snowballing is
just the overall amount of work. If completing one assignment say,
every two weeks is a challenge for a particular student, imagine when
they let the deadlines slip and then have to complete 6 at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s worse though in courses that do build. I taught data structures
last semester. You can&amp;#39;t build your linked lists without understanding
your pointers and you can&amp;#39;t build an open hash table without those
linked lists. If you can&amp;#39;t do the pointers you&amp;#39;re going to really be
at a loss for those other topics. This means making sure a student
&lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; successfully master what&amp;#39;s needed by the dealine &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; important
and not arbitarary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another reason is that, in spite of the no-deadline crowds
contentions, deadlines &lt;strong&gt;do matter&lt;/strong&gt; in the real world. You&amp;#39;re not
getting on that plane once the door at the gate closes. Likewise, I&amp;#39;m
sure you&amp;#39;d be pretty unhappy if your house burned down because the
fire department had to finish their dinner before heading over to put
out the blaze. Also, try getting into college if you miss the
application deadline. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Usually, deadlines are more flexible and the penalties for missing
them are less severe but they do indeed exist. If you miss a client
deadline you might lose the client, if you don&amp;#39;t pay your bills,
eventually the collectors will come for you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even without the penalties there&amp;#39;s also a matter of respect - not just
for the teacher but also for your classmates. Putting aside the legit
reasons for missing deadlines, some students will indeed either be
lazy on not focused or might just be taking advantage of a more
lenient teacher. This student is then given more attention from the
teacher - since teacher time is limited, that&amp;#39;s going to be at the
expense of the other students - not fair and not cool. If the reason
for missing a deadline is legit, then no problem but as we all know
there are plenty of people who&amp;#39;ll take advantage of any system that
lets them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another big reason for deadlines that&amp;#39;s never talked about is that
many students want and/or need them. Over my 30+ years as a teacher,
I&amp;#39;ve tried strict deadlines, no deadlines and everything in between. I
can&amp;#39;t tell you how many students have told me that they needed
deadlines to keep them on task and in fact, deadlines with internal
targets to meet helped even more. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, one has to consider the teachers workload and schedule. It&amp;#39;s
time to drop the &amp;#34;hero teacher&amp;#34; bit. Teachers &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; have a work
life balance and that means not being available to handle student
issues 24/7. I hate grading and it takes me a lot of time and
effort. When I grade, I set up my systems to be efficient and I get
into a grading groove. If a student hands in something late, even with
a good reason, it breaks my flow and takes me much longer and also
ties me up in other ways. Sure, if I taught at an &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; private
school and only had a dozen kids in a class I could make all sorts of
accommodations but when you teach 5 of 34 every day somethings got to
give. The teacher also has their own deadlines - students must know
this or that before the AP or standardized test and of course the big
deadline - getting those grades in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
What do I do?
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, where do I ultimately fall on this? I do believe in deadlines but
I believe in some flexibility. I also like to have enough information
on my students so that by the end of the term I can assess them even
if one or two things are missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Are my deadlines hard? Not really - anyone can ask for an extension
but my two requirements are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have to have shown that up to the request they&amp;#39;ve tried to
make some headway on the project. This is easy since I use Git and
GitHub so I can just log at their logs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They speak to me about the extension before the deadline and by
this I mean as soon as there might be an issue, not the evening
before the project is due. I encourage them to speak to me even if
they think there might be an issue to get my okay and then, more
often than not, they don&amp;#39;t use the extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some teachers don&amp;#39;t like the fact that I require that the student
actually talk to me about an extension and that they do it in what I
consider a timely manner but I think at some point the students must
advocate for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, how does it work for my classes? I think pretty well. I&amp;#39;ll take
almost any reason - sickness, family event, lots of other things due,
something&amp;#39;s unclear or almost anything else. We discuss it and come up
with a fair extension. I usually ask &amp;#34;what do you need&amp;#34; in terms of
time, resources, and in some cases help and then I try to give that
plus a cushion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what do you think? Are you part of the no deadline crowd? What am
I missing? Got other strategies and techniques? Let&amp;#39;s hear them as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When is remote better</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/whats-better-remote/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 08:13:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/whats-better-remote/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
With my first classes of the semester coming up on Monday I thought
I&amp;#39;d write a bit about what worked better remote than in person. When I
say better I mean specifically, worked better for me given my
situation. I think they worked better for the class but I can&amp;#39;t say
with any certainty given the length of the educational feedback loop
and other factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My in person teaching situation is as follows. Last semester I taught
2 in person classes (plus one remote). Both were in computer
labs. Minimal distance between the kids. Everyone had to have set
assigned seats and masks had to be on at all times. As the instructor,
I was allowed to remove my mask but I never would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, here we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
feeling safe
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Big one. Remote felt safer. It doesn&amp;#39;t really matter if it was safer
or not. This is a case of perception being reality. Since I felt less
safe - particularly at the start of the year before the students were
vaccinated, I can say for sure that I wasn&amp;#39;t as effective. If the
students didn&amp;#39;t feel safe I&amp;#39;m sure their learning also took a hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For all the dings on remote teaching, we all felt safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
participation
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my personal opinion, my classes last semester went from what I hope
were good classes to not so good lectures. Since students wore masks
and don&amp;#39;t project their voices in any case, student participation was
really tough. It would turn into asking students to repeat their
answers multiple times and to project louder and louder. It didn&amp;#39;t
help that windows had to be open and we&amp;#39;re in the heard of NYC with
all the associated street noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, remote participation is no great shakes. It&amp;#39;s really easy for a
student to just tune out but at least it was possible. Students could
be called on or could volunteer and between the Zoom and our Zulip
chat, there were far more opportunities for students to be involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, once we&amp;#39;re safe and mask free, in class will probably be better
than remote for this but for now, I can&amp;#39;t say that it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Group work
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Group work in person was pretty much impossible. Even though there was
little distancing between the students, they had to stay in their
assigned locations. On Zoom we had breakout rooms and on our Zulip,
group chats. In normal times, in person would blow away remote but
something reasonable on zoom and zulip was far better than nothing in
person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Working with individuals / small groups
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also couldn&amp;#39;t really work well with individual students (or small
groups if we were able to set them up). Online I could do a breakout
visit or an individual or group chat. Again, something being better
than nothing. The one place where in person was better is that, while
it was limited, I could eaves drop on the kids - look over while they
worked. It was limited because I didn&amp;#39;t want to get too close and also
for the reasons cited above but it was something. Can&amp;#39;t do that with
Zoom. Interestingly enough, Big Blue Button - an opensource Zoomalike
does have an eavesdrop on breakout rooms feature as it&amp;#39;s made for
teachers but last I checked the overall platform was not quite ready
for prime time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Polls
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another big win for remote was the use of the Zulip chat. Emoji polls
replicate the use of a clicker but with more power and flexibility and
less overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can also give a question and have them all type a response but
not hit  the &lt;strong&gt;enter&lt;/strong&gt; key. The can then all post at once. You can do
similar things with hand signals in class but this is much more
flexible and robust. Big win.
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Discussion of student work
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, the chat platform gave us the ability to discuss more
student&amp;#39;s work. Typically, in class you can only look at one or two
student solutions for a given problem but using the chat, you can
stretch out the discussion. A typical strategy is to have  everyone
post their initial answer/response/whatever and then over the course
of time have each student comment on at least two other student
posts. Yes, this has it&amp;#39;s kinks but it&amp;#39;s a nice way to get more
students to look at more other student&amp;#39;s work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Takeaways
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the beginning of last semester, I felt that we should have at least
started online - particularly with the students potentially
unvaccinated. Looking back, I think it would have been better
overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Truthfully, the ideal would have been to do remote until students were
vaccinated then allow professors to mix and match as best suits their
classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we ever get past this and back to regular old school in person
classes, sure, that beats remote for instruction overall but remote
does have it&amp;#39;s moments. On top of that, good remote can beat crippled
in person and sometimes there are other good reasons for a remote
option such as why I want my teacher prep program to remain online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there it is. Where I think remote teaching outshone in person for
me over the last year. As a college istructor I have more flexibility
than a K12 teacher so can mix in remote practices that I feel work
better. I&amp;#39;m hoping that over time those that set the K12 structure
would make it similarly possible at that level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning a good class into a bad lecture</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/inperson-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 08:11:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/inperson-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been teaching in person for about a month now so I thought I&amp;#39;d
give a quick update on how it&amp;#39;s going. I&amp;#39;ve written before about my
feelings on how Hunter started the semester (TL;DR - I was very
displeased) but that&amp;#39;s not the point of this post. As of today, I
believe every student has been required to be stabbed at least once
and on October 11, all students must be fully vaccinated to be on
campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, off to the report. Going in person sounds great but now that I&amp;#39;m
doing it, I&amp;#39;m having second thoughts. Let&amp;#39;s leave safety precausions
out of it, I&amp;#39;m having second thoughts just in terms of how the current
situation and related restrictions have affected my teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the low down. Students are supposed to wear masks at all
times and I wear mine as well. We&amp;#39;re supposed to socially distance but
that&amp;#39;s not possible given class and classroom sizes. Students are also
supposed to keep the same seed all the time, ostensibly for contact
tracing should anyone test positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, day one in person was important - I still haven&amp;#39;t met my
students from last year in person and I&amp;#39;d really like to. This years
students, at least I&amp;#39;ve seen all their foreheads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s actually an issue. At least for me, the masks make it MUCH
harder to know my students. Can&amp;#39;t get to know a face when you can&amp;#39;t
see two thirds of it and names are going to be even harder for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Online, at least for those who put on cameras, we could at least see
each others full faces and expressions. Zoom doesn&amp;#39;t carry the same
nuance as in person but neither does a masked face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The masks have another negative. You can&amp;#39;t hear anyone. I do my best
to actively project but students rarely do. This leads to me having
students repeat themselves multiple times and I also have to adopt a
conference speaker approach of repeating and projecting what the
student said so everyone can hear. This absolutely kills interactive
discussion and even question answer chains. It really pushes a lesson
more towards a lecture which, well, sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The social distancing and keeping seats also negatively impact the
environment. I can&amp;#39;t get in with my students like I usually do. Even
when in lecture mode, I&amp;#39;ll move to different locations of the room for
a variety of reasons - that&amp;#39;s pretty much out. I also can&amp;#39;t just get
in close to support students. Likewise, group work can&amp;#39;t happen in the
same way. They can kind of sort of work with their direct neighbor but
I can&amp;#39;t have them work with each other as I&amp;#39;d do under normal
circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. I won&amp;#39;t compromise safety for convenience but the
safety protocols do a good job in turning a good class into a bad
lecture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Online is also lousy in many ways but as long as the students are
willing you can all see each others faces and you can do all sorts of
interesting groupings and group work. I think my code review lesson
worked pretty much as well and maybe even better online last year than
it did in person the year before but I&amp;#39;m really at a loss on how to do
it as effectively in person in a few weeks with the safety
precautions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ideally, I&amp;#39;d like the freedom to mix and match. We were in person week
one, but let me decide when we&amp;#39;ll be in person and when we&amp;#39;ll be
remote. Let me use the best platform for any given lesson. This would
be a bit of a drag on the students depending on how their instructors
scheduled things but if students could use the rooms that they&amp;#39;d be in
person for as locations to work remote from it wouldn&amp;#39;t be too bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, the ideal would be to trust the teacher and let them do
what&amp;#39;s best for their students but as we all know, that&amp;#39;s never the
way. Regardless, the interesting thing to me is that while I was
clamoring for a safe in person return, the truth is, given sensible
safety precautions, in person might just not be the best way to go. At
least not all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calling an audible</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 13:48:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/audible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Be ready to call an audible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was advice I got during my third year teaching. I had just
transferred from Seward Park to Stuy and was being observed for the
first time by my former teacher and now supervisor Richie
Rothenberg. I forget exactly what the lesson was on - something with
coordinate geometry I think. The lesson was okay but it wasn&amp;#39;t going
over well with the class. I was teaching at too low a level for my
audience. I could feel it as I was teaching but as I was pretty
inexperienced I wasn&amp;#39;t confident in changing things up on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, Richie and I debriefed. He said the lesson was
satisfactory - the magic word you need on any observation but that it
could have been much better. I had only been teaching at Stuy for a
few weeks and even though I was a Stuy grad I hadn&amp;#39;t had time to get
my head around where the students were at. Richie said that sometimes
you just have to call an audible. For a young teacher, easier said
than done. In addition to not having a great handle on my students yet
I also wasn&amp;#39;t confident in flying without a net. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is why it&amp;#39;s so important for teachers to really know their
stuff - both the content and how to teach it. It&amp;#39;s why I&amp;#39;m concerned
when I see so many leaders in CS education pushing scripted curricula
and PD based training to fully &amp;#34;prepare&amp;#34; CS teachers in just a few PD
sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First time through, particularly when you&amp;#39;re voluntold to teach a new
class you just want to survive. Follow that script, learn with your
kids and get through. You&amp;#39;ll grow and the kids will be richer than had
you not gone through the fire with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two or three years down the road, however, if you&amp;#39;re still just
following the script you&amp;#39;re doing your students a disservice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, having subject knowledge doesn&amp;#39;t mean you have all the
answers but it lets you call that audible when a class needs something
that is not in the lesson plan or lets you talk about multiple
positions on subjects with no single best answer like coding style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And then calling an audible isn&amp;#39;t always about making a lesson more
advanced. It can also be about sensing what a class needs at that
time. This is something I learned from Bruce Baskind at Seward
Park. I&amp;#39;ve lost touch with Bruce but he was a mentor and a friend when
I started this teaching thing and without the support I got from Bruce
and a handful of others back at Seward, I wouldn&amp;#39;t have made it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes, you&amp;#39;ve got to turn off the academics. A class might need a
team building exercise or maybe just something fun. They might just
need to turn off school for part or all of the period. Sure, you burn
a lesson but sometimes that&amp;#39;s what the kids need and at the end of the
semester, they&amp;#39;ll be further along for it. I&amp;#39;d sometimes take a block
of class time and do Story Time - literally right out of grade
school - usually something from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.personal.psu.edu/faculty/k/u/kuc14/sunny/Children%20Literature/The%20stinky%20cheese%20man/stinky%20cheese%20man.pdf&#34;&gt;The Stinky Cheese Man&lt;/a&gt; like &amp;#34;The Really
Ugly Duckling.&amp;#34; In some ways it&amp;#39;s related to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG&#34;&gt;Halloween Stuff&lt;/a&gt; I
used to do at Stuy. Those were preplanned but that was all about
relationship building with the class - the non academic stuff that
supports the academics the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As this post is beginning to wander I think I&amp;#39;ll stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up - a specific audible I called that, at least for one student,
turned into a very memorable lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Day one back in person</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/day-one-in-person/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 06:46:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/day-one-in-person/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday was my first day of in person teaching since early
March 2020. It was,â€¦ interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was looking forward to actually seeing my  students in person but as
I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/32-years/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, i wasn&amp;#39;t comfortable given Hunter&amp;#39;s
current COVID policy and Delta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll be happier come mid October when 100% of students on campus will
be vaccinated but at least for now, mask compliance is high. I only
had to talk to one student in a hallway to remind him to put his mask
back on and the only other non-masked person was a staff member (too
far away for me to address) who had it under her nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In class distancing was not possible at all and I wasn&amp;#39;t happy with
that and this will certainly cause me stress for the next couple of
months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The positives? Actually meeting my students. I went through all of
last year not seeing any of them in person and in fact have only met
one face to face so far. That was just a couple of weeks ago at an
event we both attended. That was great. Even with cameras on there&amp;#39;s
no comparison with what you can pick up and communicate through body
language remote vs in person. Just not the same. A secondary positive
were the low-tech tools. I haven&amp;#39;t found a Zoom based whiteboard
solution that I like. There&amp;#39;s something to be said for a whiteboard
that&amp;#39;s up all period that can be modified not only by me but by other
members of the class along with the projected screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about the negatives? In addition to the general health questions,
both physical and mental there were a few other things I noticed. Day
one for me is always more lecture oriented. I have to give them a lot
of material - policies and procedures, syllabus information,
etc.. That&amp;#39;s not to say that the students aren&amp;#39;t involved at all but
my first day classes are usually ones where I talk more and they talk
less. When I talk, I like to roam the room. Move to different
locations - get their eyes on different parts of the room with
different students. It&amp;#39;s a small thing but something that makes a
difference. I couldn&amp;#39;t comfortably do that. Similarly, when they were
working, I wasn&amp;#39;t comfortable with my traditional circulation
routine - given that we don&amp;#39;t know students vaccine status, I didn&amp;#39;t
want to get in close with them. This also reinforces my question from
my last post about student collaboration and group work. These are
things that actually work better remotely. Breakout rooms are flawed
but they&amp;#39;re something and you can&amp;#39;t really do groups in a small
classroom while keeping distant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s next? As I said at the top, I&amp;#39;ll be more comfortable come mid
October when we&amp;#39;re all vaxxed. Until then, I&amp;#39;ll take it a day at a
time. I&amp;#39;ll probably schedule some of our classes to be remote
regardless of policy if I think that the remote tools make more sense
for a particular session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Gonna take it one class at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>\(2^5\) Years Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/32-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 13:02:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/32-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
  src=&#34;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&#34;&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was looking over my TRS statement the other day - that&amp;#39;s Teacher&amp;#39;s
Retirement System and noticed that next week I&amp;#39;ll be starting my 32nd
year teaching. That&amp;#39;s \(2^5\) or 10000 - 5 bits so I guess you can&amp;#39;t
call me a two bit teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two and a half years at Seward, over 20 at Stuy, and the rest at
Hunter College. I&amp;#39;ve had a lot of last days before school starts but
this year is different. I&amp;#39;m betting that&amp;#39;s the case for a lot of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mentioned about burnout and not feeling any joy when I wrote about the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/&#34;&gt;CSTA conference&lt;/a&gt; but we&amp;#39;re also starting a new year in a strange place
due to the pandemic. On the one hand we have vaccines but on the
other, we&amp;#39;ve got Delta. I&amp;#39;m scheduled to teach my undergraduate
classes in person and to be honest, I&amp;#39;m not 100% comfortable. Will
that affect my teaching? I guess we&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then we have practical concerns. My students should all be distancing
so how will that affect group work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I&amp;#39;m writing this I just got an email from Hunter saying that
students will have 45 days post FDA approval to get vaccinated. The
wording seems to contradict the previous policy that in order for
students to enter campus they had to be vaccinated. This is concerning
to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started teaching I was always nervous before the first day back
and then again for the first day teaching. Mid career it was more of
an excited nervousness. Ultimately the nerves went away and while I
sorely needed vacation in June by September I was looking forward to
seeing my students again. This year it&amp;#39;s mostly nervousness, discomfort and
uncertainty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t write this merely to complain but rather to share. I figure if
I&amp;#39;m feeling this way so probably are others. We&amp;#39;re not alone.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve got some CS and teaching content posts lined up and plan to start
with them next week as things get back in the swing but for now, good
luck to everyone starting back up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Science is not (inherently) fun</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 09:56:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-fun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw a tweet the other day by a CS teacher. They were talking about
how much easier it is to teach CS because it&amp;#39;s fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They went on about how they get to create cool problems which makes it
so much easier to teach than other subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve heard this a lot over the years particularly from teachers who
are into gaming - &amp;#34;CS is fun because you can create games.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sorry but I have to disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;300&#34; src=&#34;https://external-content.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=https%3A%2F%2Fmedia1.tenor.com%2Fimages%2F2394618fcb9a02e206f313155848d2d3%2Ftenor.gif%3Fitemid%3D5765989&amp;f=1&amp;nofb=1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. I think CS is fun (and I&amp;#39;m not a game person) but
just because I find it fun doesn&amp;#39;t mean it&amp;#39;s inherently fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I used to think like those teachers posting but one day, early in my
career I was observed by my principal. She liked the lesson but
focused in on one thing. At one point I mentioned that we could use a
specific new technique and that it was &amp;#34;cool.&amp;#34; She asked me &amp;#34;why is it
cool?&amp;#34; and more importantly &amp;#34;why should it be cool for them?&amp;#34; That got
me thinking. It was cool to me for a variety of reasons but the truth
was that in a class of 30 high school students, what&amp;#39;s cool for one
person is probably not cool for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That observation stuck with me. Something that&amp;#39;s cool for some of us
isn&amp;#39;t for others. A teacher and some students might love making games
but it does nothing for me and for many students. Same thing for the
general building stuff or solving problems. The set of things that will and won&amp;#39;t
motivate students in a CS class is a large one indeed. Now, this
doesn&amp;#39;t mean don&amp;#39;t do, for instance, games but rather understand that your students
will have a wide range of interests so if you do a unit that focuses
on games, maybe do other things in your other units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A second issue I have with the &amp;#34;CS is fun&amp;#34; thing is that it implies
that it&amp;#39;s all fun and games and not work. This is particularly a
problem transitioning from a CS0 to a CS1 class. If you don&amp;#39;t set up
the transition correctly students will find CS1 much more challenging
and harder and if it&amp;#39;s too hard or too challenging that&amp;#39;s not
fun. Besides, even if the class is fun, which should include being
challenging at the right level there will be times where things are
just not fun and that&amp;#39;s even with the best teacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The final thing that I find off putting about all the &amp;#34;computer
science is fun&amp;#34; posts. I think it&amp;#39;s unfair to other teachers and other
subjects. History can be tremendous fun - stories, adventures,
mysteries, predictions and more. It can be taught through traditional
lessons, role play, art music and the list goes on. English? That&amp;#39;s
also stories, adventures, mysteries etc.. Physics? How about show and
tell how the world works? To say we have the monopoly on fun is not
true and unfair. We currently don&amp;#39;t have the burden history which
strictly dictates what, how, and when we teach but we&amp;#39;re getting there
quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that CS will be inherently fun for some just like any
other subject and the specifics of what and how a class is taught and
to whom can greatly influence the level of fun. A strong teacher who&amp;#39;s
passionate about games teaching a game development elective will
probably be fun for most or all participants but if it were a required
course, not so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS is our field, we find it fun and interesting and we want to bring
our passion to our students. That&amp;#39;s all good but let&amp;#39;s remember that
it&amp;#39;s not special and we&amp;#39;re not special. The same can be said for other
subjects and other teachers and we have to remember that it&amp;#39;s not
about our passions but rather those of our students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Styles</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-styles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 08:31:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-styles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
My friend Emmanuel lamented over on Facebook on &amp;#34;Learning Styles,&amp;#34; or
more specifically on how it&amp;#39;s still given credence. We all chimed in
in agreement but not an hour later I saw a Twitter thread where
education thought leaders extolled the virtues of Learning Styles all
over again. I pointed out that it&amp;#39;s a great example as to why so many
teachers scoff at &amp;#34;the research&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;research backed practices.&amp;#34;
We&amp;#39;ve seen it all before. We&amp;#39;re told we have to teach one way or we&amp;#39;re
failures only to be told a few years later that we have to do
something else. It&amp;#39;s not necessarily the research (although I question
a good deal of what I&amp;#39;ve read) but also the interpretations and
implementations. There are just too many factors that are never
considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One factor that I&amp;#39;ve rarely seen mentioned but one I think about
frequently, particularly as I work with teachers is &amp;#34;teaching styles.&amp;#34;
I&amp;#39;m not talking about any deep science here but we know that teachers
are people and people have tendencies, strengths, weaknesses, and
preferences. These are factors that are so important to teaching but
rarely considered. It&amp;#39;s always &amp;#34;teach this way&amp;#34; and never what works
for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Think about how ridiculous that is. In what other field do we ignore
the individual strengths, tendencies and even comfort level of the
professional. In sports, we know that there are &amp;#34;player&amp;#39;s coaches&amp;#34; and
&amp;#34;disciplinarians&amp;#34; and players and teams might take better to one or
the other. Likewise, a coaches act can grow stale over time as the
team evolves. Similarly a great coach works their system to the
strengths of the players and doesn&amp;#39;t rigidly try to make players
conform to a system where they just don&amp;#39;t fit. Now that doesn&amp;#39;t mean
that a coach won&amp;#39;t try to develop a players weaknesses or try to move
towards their favored system but the greats look at the skills and
personalities of all involved. It also doesn&amp;#39;t mean that you can&amp;#39;t
evolve. Former NY Giants coach Tom Coughlin was a rigid
disciplinarian and almost lost the team and his job prior to their Super Bowl run
in 2007. He evolved - became more of a players coach. He didn&amp;#39;t change
his stripes. He was still a stickler for rules and details but he
brought in a new human dimension to his coaching game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to teaching. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While you want teachers to have a large set of tools in the box they
are going to be better with some than with others. Of course you can&amp;#39;t
ignore the students and how they respond but it&amp;#39;s not a one way
street. Take my friend Jim. He&amp;#39;s one of the best two or three natural
teachers I know. I describe him as &amp;#34;the teacher I aspire to be.&amp;#34; He&amp;#39;s
amazing. Stylistically though he&amp;#39;s what I call traditional teacher
dominant. He presents, there are questions comments and answer, seat
work. Pretty old school stuff. He doesn&amp;#39;t fit the constructivist mold
nor the cooperative one but he&amp;#39;s the best. I remember talking to our
principal a number of years ago. They said &amp;#34;I can&amp;#39;t bring
superintendents and DOE officials to Jim&amp;#39;s class when they visit and
want to see what we&amp;#39;re doing. He&amp;#39;s great but they just wouldn&amp;#39;t
understand and we&amp;#39;d get a lower school rating.&amp;#34; He&amp;#39;s the best but he
doesn&amp;#39;t fit Danielson. Now before you give me the &amp;#34;but it doesn&amp;#39;t
count, he teaches at Stuy&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ll share that prior to teaching at Stuy
he taught at an overall low performing neighborhood school and
experience notwithstanding, he was the best then too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What makes Jim the best? He has his preferred style and he adjusts to
what his students need. He&amp;#39;ll take an assortment of tools out of his
belt - some discovery stuff here, some group work there but he&amp;#39;ll work
it in to augment his strengths rather than being something he&amp;#39;s not
and as a result being inauthentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For my part I too am traditional teacher dominant. I&amp;#39;m not anywhere
close to Jim&amp;#39;s level. I consider myself an above average in class
teacher who brings other things to the table and makes up for it with
honesty, sincerity, and loyalty. I&amp;#39;m 100% &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a Danielson teacher
nor am I a cooperative learning one which was all the rage when I
started my career. I&amp;#39;ll try to get new ideas and learn new techniques
and pick and choose and overall it&amp;#39;s worked pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this is to say that when teaching teachers or coaching them,
don&amp;#39;t try to turn them into you or into John Keating, Jaime Escalante,
or what have you (note to self, write up teacher movie rant some
day). Help them to look at who they are and what they bring to the
table. Mix that with the needs of their students and the cosntraints
of their teaching situation and help them to be the best they cab be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teaching styles, for lack of a better name is too frequently missing
from the education equation. It&amp;#39;s totally removed by those who want
scripted curricula and cookie cutter instruction and barely mentioned
anywhere else but teaching styles are an important component of great
teaching and I wish more people acknowledged this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deadlines And Commitments</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/deadlines-and-commitments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 13:50:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/deadlines-and-commitments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A few days ago I was part of a Twitter discussion on assignment
deadlines. I noticed a tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Not sure who needs to hear this, but stop taking off points for late assignments. Itâ€™s not helping students learn responsibility, and itâ€™s not making your job easier. Itâ€™s only making your class inequitable. ðŸ’¯&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sydney Jensen (@sydneycjensen) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sydneycjensen/status/1309946435056611335?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 26, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I disagreed. I wasn&amp;#39;t necessarily against floating or open deadlines
without deductions but rather, they made my life more difficult and
weren&amp;#39;t in the best interest of my students. That said, they could
very well be appropriate for Sydney and her&amp;#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today I saw some emails on the SIGCSE list on the same topic. One
caught my eye - the poster talked about giving extra credit for early
submissions. These were likely unrelated discussions since the twitter
participants were not CS educators and I think the SIGCSE discussion
was mostly of college level CS instructors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, it was a sign. I was meant to write a blog post on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, what&amp;#39;s my policy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For homework or small every day assignments I grade for attempt, not
correctness. You either made an honest effort or you didn&amp;#39;t. I
encourage students to help each other but ask they cite where and when
they got help. When all is said and done, if you&amp;#39;ve done most of the
homework you get the full homework percent of the grade. If you miss
one here or there, no big deal. If you miss a whole bunch, you&amp;#39;ve got
a problem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For projects, I have hard deadlines with a deduction for lateness. If
time and circumstance permits, I&amp;#39;ll give a project and we&amp;#39;ll have a
discussion and set the due date together. Also, if a student talks to
me ahead of time about some issue, I&amp;#39;ll almost always give a penalty
free extension. On the other hand, if they come to me last minute, I
usually won&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I grade, and I &lt;strong&gt;hate&lt;/strong&gt; grading, I get into a groove so grading a
project later does inconvenience me and it&amp;#39;s also not doing the
student any favors - we&amp;#39;ve moved on to the next set of topics but I
don&amp;#39;t have the project which is an assessment of how the student was
doing up to that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is this bad? I don&amp;#39;t think so. While many deadlines are arbitrary,
students do have to learn to get things done and as long as the
deadline is reasonable there shouldn&amp;#39;t be a problem. Since I&amp;#39;m
flexible if a student has a particular issue even more so. One
tweet on the thread said that since some students aren&amp;#39;t comfortable
asking a teacher for an extension it was unfair but I think you have
to draw the line somewhere. One students might not ask for an
extension and just be late and another might not ask and kill
themselves to meet the deadline but in either case, I don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s
unreasonable to expect the student to advocate for themselves
particularly when they can start the conversation either in person or
via email and in private. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, is having open deadlines all good? Probably
not. Some students will game and abuse the system. Not all, but
certainly some and those students will gain an advantage in terms of
grades. Now, in an ideal world. we wouldn&amp;#39;t care about grades but in
the current reality if student one gets a fair B+ while student two
exploits loose deadlines nad gets an A-, guess who&amp;#39;s more likely to
get into that selective college? There&amp;#39;s also the problem of
snowballing and falling behind. If a student is a week late on
something that reinforces or clarifies the next topic that student is
now falling behind on that next topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also have the final looming deadline of end of semester or end of
year which further complicates matters. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, who&amp;#39;s right? Who knows. Overall, I think what I do works for me
and my classes. It&amp;#39;s a system that&amp;#39;s evolved over three decades and
will continue to evolve. Every year is a potential tweak and every new
situation, like when I came over to Hunter was cause for
re-evaluation. On the other hand, I know teachers who have open
deadlines and it seems to work for them and their students so they
should keep on keeping on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about that extra credit for early projects? This is one that
sounds good but I don&amp;#39;t like it. I think this one is potentially
really inequitable. It sounds good until you remember that students
all have different schedules and different obligations. If you give
students one week to complete an assignment starting monday, even if
they all have roughly the same workload, it will be distributed in
different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One kid might front load their courses into Mon-Wed so they don&amp;#39;t have
to commute Thursday and Friday. That student will never be able to
finish an assignment early because they&amp;#39;ve left there homework time
for later in the week. Same thing for a kid who works evenings rather
than weekends. There will be other kids where their schedule favors
finishing early. This sounds like a great idea but it will really only
favor a select few and not necessarily because they&amp;#39;re doing things
&amp;#34;the right way.&amp;#34; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s the answer on due dates? As usual we get a resouding &amp;#34;it
depends.&amp;#34; I just gave an assignment last Monday and over Zulip we
collectively decided that a fair deadline would be a week from
today. I don&amp;#39;t expect any extensions will be needed but if I&amp;#39;m
approached I&amp;#39;ll probably be flexible as I&amp;#39;ve always been. My policy
seems to be working well so I&amp;#39;m sticking to it for now. If yours works
for you, do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarter Century Courses</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/quarter-century-courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 07:09:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/quarter-century-courses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was talking in our Curriculum Development class last week about the
courses I&amp;#39;ve created over the years. From the first computer graphics
course to the current teacher education courses. JonAlf pointed out
that we missed an &amp;#34;important&amp;#34; occasion last spring - the twenty fifth
offering of my computer graphics class at Stuy. I haven&amp;#39;t taught it in
almost 10 years but it&amp;#39;s been running continuously for a quarter
century since it first ran back in the mid 90s. Systems will hit that
mark this year and the intro course I designed a couple of years from
now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking back at all the courses I&amp;#39;ve designed and taught it&amp;#39;s
interesting to see what I got right, what I got wrong, and why. Some
courses evolved slowly over time. The intro course fits that bill. On
the other hand, Systems had a complete reboot a few years in and has
been reasonably stable since. Interestingly enough Graphics has
probably been the most stable over the years. That&amp;#39;s not to say that
it hasn&amp;#39;t been tweaked here and there but overall, it&amp;#39;s largely the
same now as it was a quarter century ago. It&amp;#39;s been re-evaluated many
times but it just turns out that when I was teaching it I felt that it
was still hitting the right notes and my successor seems to feel
similarly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Funny because graphics was designed with the least thought of all of
my courses. I probably didn&amp;#39;t feel that way at the time, but it&amp;#39;s
true. I had only been teaching around 5 year - a beginner at best and
didn&amp;#39;t really know what I was doing. Even 10 years in you&amp;#39;re still an
advanced beginner in terms of teaching. Most teachers, if they don&amp;#39;t
burn out, hit there stride at 15 - 20 and after that become truly
experienced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I basically created graphics because I was teaching 4 APCS/AB classes
and one geometry and &lt;strong&gt;hated&lt;/strong&gt; grading proofs!!!! I needed to create one
more CS class. I decided on graphics because I knew I could teach it
and thought the students might enjoy it. Systems was created using
similarly deep contemplations. I got better and spent much more time
and effort designing future courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the graphics class I had a few choices to make but not many. The
students mostly only knew Pascal from APCS so the language wasn&amp;#39;t an
issue like it would become later on and since we were working on DOS
machines running Turbo Pascal there wasn&amp;#39;t any option to use any fancy
library like OpenGL. The course basically started with the ability to
draw a point and then went though: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lines&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lines in 3D and 3D transformations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;polygons (triangles)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A motion description language interpreter (stack and tree based
shape hierarchies)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lighting and shading&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ray tracing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motion description language piece had an entire unit that was
really an intro to compilers / interpreters. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In retrospect, the course really did make sense. It was taught to
second term seniors so it was a terminal course. It combined the
programming, algorithms and data structures from APCS, math they
did in trig, precalc (and baby calc), and a bit of physics. It as also
project based and they wrote programs that made pretty pictures so
that helped stave off senioritis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the course has remained largely the same, there has been some
evolution. When Systems students started learning C we ended up
supporting that as well in graphics and now the course is more
language agnostic. We also played with topics and unit length. We
spend less time on the compiler piece now and treat that more like a
black box and have at times looked at additional topics like texture
mapping. There&amp;#39;s also been a good deal of work put in to safety nets
and scaffolding. When you have a course where the main assessment is
one BIG semester long project you&amp;#39;ve got to make sure students don&amp;#39;t
end up falling into a hole they can&amp;#39;t climb out of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not a surprise that the first couple of courses I designed -
graphics and systems were somewhat arbitrary. Graphics turned out to
be a solid design and just needed some fine tuning but Systems got a
complete reboot. Over the years, I learned more about curriculum
design and feel pretty comfortable designing new experiences now. Of
course, this is thirty years into my career as a teacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe I&amp;#39;ll talk about the design of other classes here in the future
but for now, you can look at one of my first student&amp;#39;s graphics
project and read about it &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/class-legends/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ca_8q3ct6J4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Cameras For Remote Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/multiple-cameras-for-remote-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 11:05:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/multiple-cameras-for-remote-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We used Zoom for remote classes over the summer but at this point,
I&amp;#39;ve also used &lt;a href=&#34;https://codingrooms.com&#34;&gt;Coding Rooms&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://bigbluebutton.org&#34;&gt;Big Blue Button&lt;/a&gt;, and Google meet as
well. They each have their own strong points and failings but all are
limited in terms of sharing multiple cameras and screen
components. All will let you share your camera or share your screen
and when you share you screen you can either share it all or a single
window. Zoom is the only one that seems to allow for easy camera
switching but it&amp;#39;s still pretty clunky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why do I want to switch cameras? Because I can&amp;#39;t draw us ing a mouse or
touchpad. I&amp;#39;ve gotten myself a Wacom tablet but am still not
particularly proficient at it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I got myself one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000TTIP40/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o00_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&#34;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; to use as a document camera. It worked
but as I said, switching between the webcam and document camera was
clunky at best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
OBS to the rescue!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://obsproject.com/&#34;&gt;OBS&lt;/a&gt; Studio is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsproject.com/&#34;&gt;Open Broadcaster Software&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s a cross platform
streaming studio. You can set up any number of devices and then
compose them into scenes. I use it for recording my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs&#34;&gt;Emacs&lt;/a&gt; videos. It&amp;#39;s
easy to set up devices for every camera you own plus monitors and
individual windows. It only took a minute or so to set up a scene with
me in the corner and my desktop: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/obs/desktop.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One for my document camera: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/obs/doccam.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And one for my desktop with the doccam overlayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/obs/mixed.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can switch between them by clicking on which I want. I can also
select a transition like fade. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is all great for recording or streaming to a service like Twitch
but what about using with meeting software? It turns out that you can
set up OBS to act as a virtual camera. There are plugins for Mac and
Windows. You can find them by searching for them but for Linux, I
followed this video and it worked perfectly: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Eca509IDLdM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also found this video if the above one doesn&amp;#39;t work: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zaJSkj-dLoI&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zaJSkj-dLoI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I set up the virtual camera as per the video and then selected it as
the camera on both Zoom and Coding Rooms and it worked perfectly. It
should work on the other platforms as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is HUGE. Now, instead of explicitly sharing my screen I can hacve
my screen as my image and quickly and easily switch over to another
window, a document camera or anything else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re teaching remotely using a conferencing platform I recommend
you check this out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting the new semester</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-semester/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 08:56:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-semester/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Thursday was the first day of the new semester. The big change was
that my classes were done remotely but there were also some other
differences. Other changes were that I only met one of my two CS
classes on Thursday. That&amp;#39;s my CS0. I&amp;#39;m also teaching a recitation for
CS1 which only meets once a week. I&amp;#39;ll see those students as well as
my CS0 students for a second time on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I opted to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://codingrooms.com/&#34;&gt;Coding Rooms&lt;/a&gt; instead of Zoom since Coding Rooms has a
nice built in REPL. We had a couple of students drop a couple of times
and I had to reload once but even that&amp;#39;s no worse than typical Zoom
performance. It&amp;#39;s funny how once one product becomes &lt;strong&gt;it&lt;/strong&gt; everything
that&amp;#39;s different is labeled as harder and whenever there&amp;#39;s a hiccup
it&amp;#39;s so much worse. The truth is, I&amp;#39;ve now used a bunch of platforms
and none is harder than the others - you just have to look to
different places. For example, in Zoom, you &amp;#34;raise your hand&amp;#34; by
clicking in one place and in Coding Rooms (or Big Blue Button)
another. Neither is inherently better - just different but people seem
to think that the non Zoom one is worse just because Zoom got so hot
so fast. Likewise, other platforms periodically drop people and crash
but so does Zoom. This is all a digression but it&amp;#39;s something that
bothers me. Zoom does some things really well but then again so do the
other platforms I&amp;#39;ve been playing with. So far, there&amp;#39;s no silver
bullet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As you might imagine, class had a different feel. I think it went
pretty well but it&amp;#39;s certainly going to be harder to build a sense of
community. Since there was a good deal of class logistics to cover we
didn&amp;#39;t really get to play with the Coding Rooms REPL but I&amp;#39;ll report
on that soon. I&amp;#39;ll also mention that we&amp;#39;re going to see about using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zulip.com/&#34;&gt;Zulip&lt;/a&gt; instead of Slack for chat both in class and out. Like Zoom,
Slack is the de facto standard but Zulip seems to have a few distinct
advantages: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s open source&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can self host it (and it&amp;#39;s free if you self host)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s built around threads so I suspect it will be easier to deal
with discussions both synchronously and asynchronously more easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disadvantages are that there aren&amp;#39;t as many integrations, most
notably there&amp;#39;s no Giphy and it&amp;#39;s not the eponymous chat
platform. Note that it&amp;#39;s not that I don&amp;#39;t like Slack but was driven to
look for alternatives because I don&amp;#39;t have a budget and the free tier
has limited history and I believe integrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other big change this semester involve our K12 CS teacher
certification program. Our summer cohort kicked off there next two
classes on Thursday afternoon and evening - Ethics in Computer Science
and Curriculum Development for CS. I designed both courses but am not
the official teacher. Topher and JonAlf who worked the summer with me
are each taking one but I&amp;#39;m going to be very involved. We also had
four students start in our Masters program. I&amp;#39;ll be writing about all
of this over the course of the school year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Spent most of yesterday getting ready for Monday - setting up the
Zulip server, GitHub repos and GitHub classroom and the like. As
usual, I&amp;#39;m a slow starter but hopefully by mid next week will feel
like I&amp;#39;m in the swing of things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - index post</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 20:03:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-index/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Since we ended up with an eight post postmortem on our CS Teaching
Certificate summer intensive I thought I&amp;#39;d add add an index page. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are links to each post: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-recap-intro/&#34;&gt;Introduction - program overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods/&#34;&gt;On pedagogy - CS teaching methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-topics/&#34;&gt;Topics in Computer Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods-choosing/&#34;&gt;Deciding on which methods to teach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-topics-curriculum/&#34;&gt;Commentary on selected CS topics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-tools/&#34;&gt;Tools for remote instruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-community/&#34;&gt;Building a community of CS teachers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-successes-and-failures/&#34;&gt;The good, the bad, and what&amp;#39;s next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wrote a few posts as the summer intensive was running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-week-1/&#34;&gt;Week 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-week-2/&#34;&gt;Week 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/merge-over-zoom/&#34;&gt;An unplugged activity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We start up again in a couple of weeks so look for more updates on the
program then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - the good, the bad, and what&#39;s next.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-successes-and-failures/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 12:00:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-successes-and-failures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Looking back, what worked and what didn&amp;#39;t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall, things went very well. We were extremely happy with the
cohort&amp;#39;s growth and performance and based on feedback received they
were happy with the program so far. I&amp;#39;ll also say that while they&amp;#39;re
not finished yet, I can honestly say that every one of them would be a
boon to any school in the city in need of a CS teacher (but they&amp;#39;re
not available since they&amp;#39;re all already teaching CS at their
respective schools :-)). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before we started we felt good about our combination our program -
designed by teachers for teachers. Strong pedagogy combined with deep
CS content. Now that we&amp;#39;re done with the summer, I think it&amp;#39;s safe to
say that both our design and implementation is sound. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That doesn&amp;#39;t mean the program was perfect. We lost one student along
the way. That was unfortunate but sometimes the fit isn&amp;#39;t there. There
are also a few things we&amp;#39;d like to tweak. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hunter-teacher-cert/pre-acceptance-prework&#34;&gt;pre-work&lt;/a&gt; - we required it due to the compressed nature of
the summer. Next time around it&amp;#39;s going to be available earlier and
with more support. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also want to do a better job with early pacing but now that we&amp;#39;ve
had our first rodeo we can do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The one nut we haven&amp;#39;t cracked is that due to the teachers experience
combined with the pre-work there are some early learning / teaching CS
issues that didn&amp;#39;t and won&amp;#39;t come up naturally as the students are
beyond them before our first day. Things like issues that come up when
introducing variables or functions. We could just insert them as a
unit but that breaks the class flow. I&amp;#39;m still noodling that one but
for now they&amp;#39;re probably good topics for a school year PD. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The cohort will continue with two more courses starting up in just a
couple of weeks. One is an Ethics in CS class that I&amp;#39;m really excited
about and the other is Curriculum Development. The Curriculum
Development class has been a personal project. I had to take three
different graduate curriculum development courses over my career and
didn&amp;#39;t learn a single thing about designing curriculum in any of
them. Years ago, before I had any clue I&amp;#39;d be building this program I
told myself that if I ever did design and teach any education courses
I&amp;#39;d do a curriculum development course and it would be good. Well, her
it is. We&amp;#39;ll look at the standards and standard offerings but the crux
of the course will have the students designing curriculum. Since the
course is integrated with the NY State required field work they&amp;#39;ll
also be implementing what they build with their students. It should be
pretty cool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On top of all this, we also have four students starting in our Masters
in CS Education program. Those four are just starting their journey
towards becoming teachers. They&amp;#39;ll take general pedagogy courses in
teh Fall and Spring and then join with our next cohort in the summer
to start the CS and CS Ed part of our program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a long road to get here but now we&amp;#39;re here - preparing CS
teachers for NY city and state. When I came to Hunter this was one of
my two major initiatives. The thought was that regardless how bad the
powers that be screw CS education up, if you have great teachers,
students have a chance. At Hunter we&amp;#39;re preparing those great
teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - building a community</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-community/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 07:11:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-community/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
What so many non-teachers just don&amp;#39;t get is culture and community can
be so much more powerful than curriculum. The problem is, culture and
community are harder to create, curate, and maintain and the results
don&amp;#39;t always show up on standardized tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can&amp;#39;t force community or culture  in a classroom but you can try
your best to foster it. It&amp;#39;s ultimately up to the class as a
whole. It&amp;#39;s like I tell groups who come to events I organize. I can&amp;#39;t
make an event awesome, all I can do is bring everyone together and set
the stage. It&amp;#39;s up to us all to collectively make the event work. More
often than not, it does. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For our part, we did what we always do. We did our best to be open and
honest about what we were doing, how, and why. We sincerely tried to
listen to input and we worked to make ourselves available to our
students. We also looked to set our class tone as informal but
serious, and hopefully fun. We could take time for tangents but
remembered when it was time to get back on task. It&amp;#39;s the typical
balance a teacher seeks to create and maintain. There was no magic on
our end, we did what we always did - we were ourselves. It probably
helped that there were three of us and could already play off each
other Marx brothers style (oh, who am I kidding, more three stooges)
but all a teacher can really do is open the door. The other thing we
did was provide the tools - Slack and GitHub Discussions (even though
it didn&amp;#39;t take) and we did pre-load Slack with channels both serious
and not so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class walked through. They decided to engage and that started the
ball rolling. Of course we still had our part to play. If they posted
something, we had to respond, or at least be an active part in the
discussion. Now, understand, we didn&amp;#39;t respond as &amp;#34;part of the job.&amp;#34;
That would be fake and they&amp;#39;d know it. We&amp;#39;d respond because we&amp;#39;re also
part of the community. We wanted them to be part of it and we wanted
to be part of it. That&amp;#39;s what community is all about. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While community and class culture is something that&amp;#39;s always
important. In this case, I think it&amp;#39;s even more important. New York
City and State, like the rest of the country has very few CS teachers
that are both strong in CS content and in CS pedagogy and since NY
State just started approving certification programs, including ours,
there are currently no state certified CS teachers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When they finish the program, this cohort should be among New York&amp;#39;s
first certified CS teachers but even now, they have more CS content
knowledge and pedagogical content knowledge than most of the people
teaching CS. They&amp;#39;re also all experienced teachers in general. This
group can seed a community of CS teachers with strong
backgrounds. It&amp;#39;s on them to go back to CS4All in and run professional
developments and to work with us at Hunter to host events as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m sure I&amp;#39;ve already said how terrific the group is and how honored I
am to work with them and as a community we&amp;#39;re well on the way. Even as
I&amp;#39;m writing this post, I&amp;#39;m seeing new messages appear on our community
Slack discussion school openings and this is well after our summer
program has ended. They&amp;#39;re already becoming resources for each
other. In a couple of weeks, for their students, and soon for the rest
of the teachers in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - tools for remote instruction</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 06:07:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Our summer intensive was supposed to be in person but COVID-19 changed
that in a hurry. We had to scramble to redesign and figure out how we
were going to run things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We decided to go with the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom for live meetings &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slack for chat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git and GitHub&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub classroom for assignments &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub repos for code distribution, class website and resource
sharing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub discussions for off hour and long form discussion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Zoom is a great platform it was lacking in a few areas so we
also ended up using: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://padlet.com&#34;&gt;Padlet&lt;/a&gt; as a collaborative writing space for groups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assorted whiteboarding tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We used Zoom as you might imagine - big zoom for direct instruction
and whole class work and lots of breakout rooms. Screen sharing worked
great but the whiteboarding was less than ideal so we turned to screen
sharing with other tools. The big things missing from Zoom were a
collaborative writing/drawing space and flexibility for breakout
rooms. I would have loved to be able to spy on a breakout room or have
more fluidity between them but it still did a pretty good job
considering Zoom wasn&amp;#39;t designed for education. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bigbluebutton.org/&#34;&gt;Big Blue Button&lt;/a&gt; is an open source alternative to Zoom. It&amp;#39;s design for
teaching so it has some of the features that Zoom lacks but it&amp;#39;s not
quite there yet in terms of quality and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Instead of the Zoom chat, we decided to use Slack. Zoom&amp;#39;s chat only
works while Zoom is up and there were times when the cohort was
working &amp;#34;offline.&amp;#34; Also, slack gave us both threads and different
channels as well as arbitrary private chats. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition to the general class chat we had channels like #git-fu, #java-fu, #fall-is-coming to discuss COVID-19 and the public schools,
#attendance  and a bunch of others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Funny thing - this was the first time any of us had strong Slack
adoption. We&amp;#39;ve tried it before but never got buy in. This time we
did. Maybe because we were together morning through afternoon and when
we broke we were still in the same physical location with out
computers nearby. In any event, Slack was used for both in class and
out of class communication and is still being used now albeit at a
lower volume. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Slack also gave us a place, besides the zoom to build
community. Having some fun channels like #duckygram and #cs-educationy-goodness  set a light tone. Every day, Alex would wait
until right before our start to put a gif in the #attendance channel
each day outdoing the ridiculousness of the rest of the class. It was
the cohort that made the community but Slack as a platform helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m wondering if a I&amp;#39;ll get better buy in with my undergrads in a few
weeks as we&amp;#39;re starting the semester online but at least for this
cohort, it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My only problem with Slack is the price. I have zero budget which
leaves us with the free tier. That means limited integrations  and
limited history. I might check out some self-hosted options like Zulip
and Rocketchat to see if they&amp;#39;re viable alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We originally planned to use GitHub discussions for longer form
communication. It hit most of the buttons for me â€“ threaded
discussion, reply via email, customizable alerts. All good. It&amp;#39;s
lacking tags and search but it looked like it could be a viable long
form discussion platform. We kicked off with it but the class voted
with their feet. They kept going back to Slack so while GitHub was our
main platform for code, GitHub discussions fell by the wayside as
Slack won the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Along the way we learned some tricks. Even though Topher was paid for
teaching two courses, JonAlf two, and I was just officially
supervising and coordinating, all three of us were pretty much on all
the time. Ones strategy that developed was having one of us man Slack
while another ran the Zoom. I might be running a Zoom based activity
while Topher or JonAlf would answer questions or highlight and
emphasize key points on Slack. I don&amp;#39;t know yet if it helped the class
educationally or was a distraction but we all liked the
flow. Something to look at further. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also had to figure out how not to double or triple respond to
questions. We each adopted an emoji and when a question was asked,
whoever got there first would mark the thread with that emoji letting
the others know we had it covered. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another skill we mastered was the &amp;#34;slack-moji&amp;#34; poll - pre-staging
Slack polls and content to cut and paste over. Actually, there&amp;#39;s a
cool remote class tool, &lt;a href=&#34;https://prismia.chat/&#34;&gt;Primsia&lt;/a&gt; (formerly babylon.hosue) which is much
better at that than Slack but it isn&amp;#39;t up 24x7 and is more set up for
a teacher actively managing class discussion rather than a free form
chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d love to see Big Blue Button grow to be a suitable Zoom replacement
as it&amp;#39;s better suited for education and I&amp;#39;m hoping that Zulip proves
to be a good free alternative to Slack but regardless of specific
tool, the combination of video conferencing, chat, long form message,
and whiteboarding make up a pretty good remote classroom. It would be
nice if collaborative coding was easier but there aren&amp;#39;t that many
options there. &lt;a href=&#34;https://repl.it&#34;&gt;Repl.it&lt;/a&gt; is awesome but we decided to have them develop
on their local machines and adding a tool like &lt;a href=&#34;https://floobits.com/&#34;&gt;Floobits&lt;/a&gt; would have
been too much to ask for most of the cohort. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We think it all went pretty well. If given the option next summer, I&amp;#39;m
leaning towards a hybrid program as even without COVID-19, remote is
easier for many teachers for geographic and school scheduling
reasons. I figure open in person and maybe do one day or a couple of
half days a week on site and the rest remote. I think we&amp;#39;ll talk about
it as a cohort once the Fall begins and can start thinking about
cohort 2.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS teachers - Curricula don&#39;t add richness, teachers do</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-topics-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 07:25:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-topics-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve frequently been asked for curricula. I&amp;#39;ll hear from a school or
someone otherwise involved in a school or education and they&amp;#39;ll ask
for a course they can drop in and teach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I explain it doesn&amp;#39;t work that way. A syllabus or curriculum is only
so good. A great curriculum with a bad teacher will still be bad but a
great teacher can do a lot to salvage a horrible curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A curriculum only goes so far. At it&amp;#39;s most sparse, it&amp;#39;s a list of
topics. At the other end we frequently see worked out prescribed
lessons that can be a boon to a beginner but in the end constrains
great teachers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a side note, this was something I noticed years ago when touring
elementary schools for my own children. We saw one school where
everything was in lockstep - every classroom looked basically the
same. Every teacher taught the same subject at the same time as every
other teacher each day and what they taught and how they taught it was
tightly controlled. We opted for  a school where the teachers were
much more free to actually teach. The school in question was well
regarded and the more we dug in the more we realized that the
strictness the principal imposed helped bring the bad teachers up to a
certain level and got most students through the standardized tests but
there was no joy. Great teachers weren&amp;#39;t allowed to teach. It was a
perfect example of a Bloomberg era stat mill. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway back to CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was thinking about this while we watched the summer cohort&amp;#39;s topic
presentations. Three of the topics were ones that I teach annually -
AI Search, NLP, and Cipher decryption. Some of the others I&amp;#39;m planning
on mixing in next year. The presentations and supporting materials
were all terrific but in every case, the teachers chose to spin and
emphasize aspects different to those I would emphasize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the case of the cipher decryption lesson, the cohort emphasized the
machine learning type aspect. I spin the lesson more towards a
recommender system. Neither is better or worse. My guess is that we
each selected aspects that were exciting to us and riffed on
those. Similarly the other groups brought up nuances and emphases that
differed from mine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was terrific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you look at a syllabus, the search topic might just say &amp;#34;Depth
First Search.&amp;#34; It might be in the recursion section of the class and
thus lead you to teaching a recursive solution or it might be in
the data structure / stack section and lead you to implement your own
stack. If the curriculum is fleshed out it&amp;#39;ll give more specifics but
will it talk about states and state space? How about implicit data
structures? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s so much richness to a well taught course that&amp;#39;s never captured
by a curriculum and that includes tangents, side stories and limitless
discoveries. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I talk to my students decades later it&amp;#39;s usually not those lines
on the syllabus they remember but the richness that lives in the ether
of a well taught class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So cool that our certification program created an environment where
we&amp;#39;ve been able to mix the spices from so many different chefs and
each of us is leaving with something new and richer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - what to leave in, what to leave out</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods-choosing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 07:37:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods-choosing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Teachers always make decisions in their courses - what to leave in,
what to leave out. I&amp;#39;ve seen programming and data structure classes
where everything is written from scratch and others where a few things
are explained and the students just use built in types like the
java LinkedList  or Arrays.sort() method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do too much from scratch and you&amp;#39;ll never finish the curriculum. Do to
little and the students won&amp;#39;t really understand what&amp;#39;s going on and
walk a path towards being programmers or coders rather than computer
scientists. Most teachers work somewhere between the extremes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We not only had to make these decisions for our CS content but also
for our methods. We decided to leave out two particular
methods that are very popular - pair programming and Parsons
problems. We did mention both in passing and did a little talk on pair
programming but the treatment was far less than say live coding,
subgoal labeling or the many other teaching techniques we decided to
explicitly cover. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why did we leave out these two topics? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Partly pragmatism and pragmatism is something that&amp;#39;s always left out
when talking about teaching. Let&amp;#39;s look at Parsons problems. If you&amp;#39;re
unfamiliar with them, they&amp;#39;re basically scrambled code
fragments. Students have to put them in order. They&amp;#39;re cool puzzles
and a nice change of pace. but you have to create them and get them to
your students. That didn&amp;#39;t fit all that well with us. By the time we
got to content that would benefit from Parsons problems our pace or approach
didn&amp;#39;t really fit using them. It&amp;#39;s also worth noting that we haven&amp;#39;t
seen any good online Parson problem generator systems which would be
both a boon to problem creation and potentially distribution and
assessment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There just wasn&amp;#39;t that much bang for the buck in giving them more than
lip service. Since our cohort was composed of experienced teachers, we
were confident that they can find the appropriate Parsons problems
resources and use them where appropriate in their classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On pair programming we had similar pragmatic issues - it didn&amp;#39;t fit
all that well given how tight the program was and we had to figure out
how bet to do it remotely on the fly. We also knew that the cohort had
all been to at least some NYC CS4All training and so were at least
exposed to the idea. Still, we, or more accurately, Topher, who&amp;#39;s had
great success getting student buy in did do a brief talk on the
subject. Some of the things we covered were: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to motivate pair programming in a collaborative way&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What activities can you give the navigator while the driver&amp;#39;s
setting up the environment to involve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How in the &amp;#34;real world&amp;#34; some developers love PP and some hate it
and that there are many variations on the theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;d not always going to get student buy in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last point is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; important. Teachers are going to try things
that don&amp;#39;t always work and unfortunately, the system of evaluation
doesn&amp;#39;t promote such necessary experimentation. What&amp;#39;s more every time
you go to a professional development or training session or head
something online it&amp;#39;s about how the presented did it and it worked
perfectly and if you follow the same recipe it&amp;#39;ll work for you. It
might, but then, it might not. It&amp;#39;s all about building the toolbox of
tricks and using them when appropriate and even then, not every lesson
is going to be John Keating or Jaime Escalante on the big screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, in the end we made choices. We&amp;#39;re they the right ones? I think
so. Next time around the cohort will be different and the
circumstances a little as well. Will we make the same choices? Maybe,
we&amp;#39;ll have to wait and see. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teacher Certification - Topics in CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 07:13:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Officially, the last course of the summer was &amp;#34;Modern Topics in
Computer Science.&amp;#34; The idea was that K12 CS teachers on the one hand
need depth beyond the typical terminal high school course, hence data
structures and also breadth so that they could create electives, mix
teasers in to the regular courses, or help precocious students with
independent or semi-independant explorations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If someone was teaching this in a typical fall or spring semester
course, they&amp;#39;d probably have a list of topics and spend a couple of
weeks on each. We wanted to do it a little differently. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The original thought was to integrate some of the topics in with the
earlier computer science but there weren&amp;#39;t too many opportunities due
to the compressed nature of the program. Instead, a few days before we
wrapped up data structures we gave the cohort a list of potential
topics and asked them to select one. Since the cohort had all already
been teaching CS and had differing content backgrounds we also
encouraged them to choose a topic not on the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When it was time for them to begin work on the topics part of the
intensive, they all shared their desired topic. Fortunately, things
worked out. We ended up with two solo students and a bunch of small
teams. The teams were tasked with learning about the topic and
designing a lesson or unit covering it. This could be for their
current students or some other hypothetical group. Each group would
also have to create a program or programs to show an implementation
and or use of the topic. Once they chose their topics, we picked a few
out of the remaining selections as topics that we&amp;#39;d present. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next few days were Topher, JonAlf and I delivering our topics and
the cohort working in groups. When they worked, we&amp;#39;d drop in and
support. The final two days consisted of the groups presenting their
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The topics they selected were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Mining&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public Key Encryption&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natural Language Processing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classic AI - Decision Trees&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SQL / Cyber Security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visualization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning / Cipher Decryption&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genetic Algorithms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classic AI - Search&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We weren&amp;#39;t sure exactly what to expect but we were blown away both in
terms of the CS content as well as what they prepared in terms of
lessons and units. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since this is just year one of the program we thought we&amp;#39;d get ahead
of the game and set up a site where we could host and share these
units and other resources so check them out &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hunter-teacher-cert/Teacher-Resources/blob/master/README.org&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We didn&amp;#39;t have a strict format for the cohort to use so each one is a
little different but each link&amp;#39;s README.md file will get you started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said, we were blown away by their work but super proud that we
also have the bonus of being able to make their work available to the
general CS Ed community. If you&amp;#39;re looking to create a unit in any of
these, check them out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - adding methods to our madness</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 06:47:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Our summer intensive was, well, pretty intensive. We met all day every
day for a month and knocked out four classes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming (CS1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Structures&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever took or taught a summer session class, you know that time
is tight and generally you cover a little less than in a fall or
spring semester class. N credits in 5 weeks just isn&amp;#39;t the same as
those same N credits spread over 13. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How did we recapture some time? First, we had some pre-work and second
we integrated some of the courses. We couldn&amp;#39;t really do it with
programming and data structures and we were less successful at
integrating the topics than we liked but it made the most sense with
methods, in fact, I think the methods part of the class was more
successful as a result of it&amp;#39;s integration with the other subjects
than it would have been as a stand alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s what we did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We first thought about covering methods as we taught topics - that is,
present something using some teaching technique, cover the topic and
then also dive in to the technique. This turned out to be a
mistake. The teachers that came in with a strong CS background  seemed
fine but for the ones newer to the subject matter, it was too much at
once. We had to alter course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So we did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We continued to model various methods and sometimes made a side remark
here or there but focused on the CS. After a few days in, we were
ready to spend a day on pedagogy. We broke the class into groups and
had them reflect on the content we taught - how did we teach it? Why
did we approach it the way we did? Did it work? This led to some rich
discussion of both CS teaching techniques and teaching in general. We
were very happy with how it all went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then went back to content but added more side bits here and there
about the teaching methods - as they became more comfortable with the
CS we were able to integrate more methods talk in with the CS talk. At
our next formal pedagogy lesson, we again talked about new techniques
that were modeled but also looked at alternative approaches and
took a deeper look at our individual cohort members student
populations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of the methods we discussed included: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Live Coding &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subgoal labeling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make predictions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modifying existing code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;code tracing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;diagramming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;scaffolded assignments (code skeletons)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubber Duck Debugging&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code sharing (presenting)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;writing implementations of library code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;slack techniques (reacts polls, channels, ) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;thought-grooming/sparking warm-up Qs/tasks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;relevant quotes at warm-up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and more but the list doesn&amp;#39;t really do the discussion justice. Take
&amp;#34;live coding&amp;#34; for example - that&amp;#39;s not just writing code in front of
the class. There&amp;#39;s a rich discussion here - how do you narrate? Is it
truly live or from a note sheet? How about discussing workflow while
modeling it? How about live coding subgoals? The actual class is much
richer than just &amp;#34;live coding.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition to integrating methods into the teaching of content, we
also merged it with the topics course for some of the assessment. For
topics, each group created a class or unit on some area of CS and
included in the documents they prepared and presentation was a
discussion of how it might bet taught. I know that they all came in as
experienced teachers so weren&amp;#39;t starting with nothing but man, they
knocked it out of the park. I&amp;#39;ll be talking more about the topics in a
later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll probably say this a lot in my summer intensive wrap up posts but
it was such a treat working with a cohort of great educators and also
to have two of the best teachers I know to work with as the teaching
team.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing teachers to teach CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-recap-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 06:16:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-recap-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that the summer portion of Hunter College&amp;#39;s Advanced Certificate
in Teaching Computer Science is over I thought I&amp;#39;d do a
postmortem. That is, a few posts about what we did and how it all
went. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, though, an overview of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Advanced Certificate program is geared towards teachers who are
currently certified in another subject area who wish to earn an
additional New York State teaching certificate in Computer
Science. Aspiring teachers - people who don&amp;#39;t currently have either a
Masters degree or any teaching certification can enroll in our Masters
in Computer Science Education program. We&amp;#39;re starting a small cohort
of five on that in the Fall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The certificate program consists of a bunch of graduate classes plus
field work which is required by the state. Over the summer we covered
four of the classes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming - essentially a CS1 type course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Structures - since K12 teachers should go deeper than the last
HS course which is typically APCS-A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topcs in Compute rScience - since K12 teachers need a wide breadth
of CS knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods - since teachers need to know how to teach CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall, we&amp;#39;ll continue with Ethics in Computer Science and
Curriculum Development which also includes the field work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For this summer we started with a cohort of 22 practicing teachers but
lost one along the way. They all came from different schools and we
had all five boroughs represented. Most of the teachers worked in high
schools but we had some middle school representation and in terms of
current certifications, we had at least math, special ed, and science
represented but that&amp;#39;s something we didn&amp;#39;t officially track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Staffing wise, it was me along with two of my long time collaborators
JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver and Topher Mykolyk. JonAlf and Topher are two of
the best educators out there and part of my former core team at
Stuy. That team is the biggest thing I still miss having come over to
Hunter. They&amp;#39;re quite simply the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The program ran basically all day every day during the month of
July. we knew it would be tight so we also added on some pre-work
which made sure all participants had some experience with Java prior
to our official start. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
More will be revealed over the next few posts but I&amp;#39;ll spoil the
ending - I&amp;#39;m super proud of our 21 participants - while they still
have more work to do to earn their certifications, if I ran a school,
I&amp;#39;d love to have any of them teaching my CS classes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not planning on writing much about the programming and data
structure classes except possibly through the methods eye because both
of those courses are pretty well established and cut and dry but I do
plan to write at least the following: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methods course &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on the methods course &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topics course &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use of tools for remote teaching &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our overall philosophy in designing and running the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, stay tuned for more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Varying Remote Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/varying-remote-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 08:33:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/varying-remote-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
When we first went remote I jumped on Zoom. I already new the
technology and it most simulated a live class. Basically, it was the
best combination if quick, easy, and effective and we were under the
gun to get something going and give our students some sense of
normalcy and continuity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we settled in though, it made sense to try some different
things. One was the &amp;#34;lab packet.&amp;#34; A self contained document with
instructions and partial walkthroughs. One of my classes is already
set up to do a number of labs in this way so that was an easy thing to
try.  Basically it ended up being an asynchronous experience with me
being available using the usual suspects - Slack and email. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I tried something different this past Monday. It was synchronous with
me available on Slack but we didn&amp;#39;t use Zoom. I set up a series of
videos. Each video was fairly short and most had a small assignment at
the end. I asked the class to fill out a form after each
video/assignment. The topic was binary trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The whole process seemed to go well but I&amp;#39;ll report back once I&amp;#39;ve
finished going over the feedback emails I&amp;#39;ve gotten from the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m particularly proud of this video that I made for the class, enjoy:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OvwIyQJ-s40&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s okay, I Get It</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 14:13:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-get-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was reading Mary Clair Wright&amp;#39;s new &lt;a href=&#34;https://computationalthinkinginroom112.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; the other day. It&amp;#39;s always
great to see another teacher sharing publicly online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One line caught my eye in her &lt;a href=&#34;https://computationalthinkinginroom112.com/2020/04/07/ap-csa-enrichment-gone-awry/&#34;&gt;latest post&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;
Remote instruction is weird, I canâ€™t see them. I have to trust that they will message me with questions.
&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a real problem. It&amp;#39;s hard enough in a regular class where we
can pick up an all sorts of cues and use all sorts formal and informal
assessments but when the students are on the other end of a
teleconference or even more challenging an email or chat it&amp;#39;s even
harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also a reminder of how important those non verbal clues and
student feedback can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s great if we can create an environment where our students will ask
for help if they don&amp;#39;t know something but even under normal
circumstances there&amp;#39;s the danger of students thinking they get
it. If a student is totally lost they&amp;#39;ll usually know they&amp;#39;re totally
lost but after that, it&amp;#39;s not so clear. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A student might think they get it if they can basically follow along
with what&amp;#39;s being presented. It&amp;#39;s pretty easy to watch another student
or a teacher go through explaining a solution step by step and think
you really know what&amp;#39;s going on. Similarly they can read through an
example in a text or on a web site and think they understand. A little
better is when they can do the first couple of problems in the book
but those frequently mimic the samples and don&amp;#39;t require any
additional insight. Even in a traditional class a student can go week
to week like this and really think they understand things and then
they get hit over the head on a test or right before a big assignment
is due. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn&amp;#39;t the student&amp;#39;s fault. It&amp;#39;s hard to know what you don&amp;#39;t know
and truth be told, we don&amp;#39;t really teach our students how to study and
self assess. It&amp;#39;s also really hard for teachers to assess this even in
person. Now that we&amp;#39;re all remote it&amp;#39;s yet another huge red flag to
look out for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No solutions here today and no suggestions just yet another concern as
we continue to work to do right by our kids.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limitations Of Remote Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/limitations-of-remote-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:41:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/limitations-of-remote-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
While tools like Zoom, Slack and others are a tremendous boon as we&amp;#39;re
forced to do all our teaching remotely the limitations become apparent
as we settle in and try to go beyond the basics of an offsite meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review-2/&#34;&gt;code review&lt;/a&gt; day in my CS1 class. It&amp;#39;s a lesson that I enjoy
teaching and I think my students get a lot out of it. Today we had to
do it remote. The mechanics were largely the same:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pair off the kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have them write out a commentary on their partners code without discussion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pair off again&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have one review the others code but this time via discussion and
note taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get everyone together and discuss&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom supported all the basics. Splitting the class was pretty easy via
the breakout room interface and students were able to flag me when
they wanted to bring me in to their breakout. It was also pretty easy
to move newcomers into a room. There were some interface nits that
Zoom has to address like how when I entered and left a breakout room I
ended up losing part of the breakout window interface but I figured
out a workaround.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big difference and limitation was that I couldn&amp;#39;t just lurk. In
a live in person class, I get a top down view. I can basically see what all the
pairs are doing. I can&amp;#39;t get the details from a distance but I can
basically see what&amp;#39;s going on. I can also sidle over near a group to
see how they&amp;#39;re doing without being obtrusive. I can also see some of
the students screens and notebooks to get the gist of what&amp;#39;s going on
and focus in on individual conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can&amp;#39;t do these things with Zoom and I daresay you can&amp;#39;t with any
remote conferencing platform. When I wasn&amp;#39;t in a breakout room I was
alone in the main room. When I was in a breakout room it was obvious I
joined and that in and of itself changed the room dynamic. I also
couldn&amp;#39;t see anything the kids were writing on paper or on screen
unless they explicitly shared it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this changes the dynamic big time and limits my effectiveness
as a teacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t take this to mean I&amp;#39;m down on Zoom. I&amp;#39;m really loving the tool
and without it or similar products my students would be getting &lt;strong&gt;much&lt;/strong&gt; 
less during this crisis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s just a reminder that teaching is a contact sport and as much as
some people will tell you otherwise the best instruction is in person
in a small class with a knowledgeable dynamic teacher. We&amp;#39;re not
getting back there this semester but here&amp;#39;s hoping that we get back by
Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Necessity is the mother of invention</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mother-of-invention/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 18:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mother-of-invention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t expect to read a Fred Wilson post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2020/03/teaching-online/&#34;&gt;teaching online&lt;/a&gt; but
that&amp;#39;s what I found when I visited &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/&#34;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt; this morning. Don&amp;#39;t get me
wrong - I suspect that Fred has the makings of a great teacher, it&amp;#39;s
just not what I expected to find. There have been many posts about
education but I don&amp;#39;t recall any about teaching or more specifically
the art of teaching. I did find &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2011/07/teaching/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; though which actually speaks
to some of the thoughts today&amp;#39;s post got churning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fred describes what sounds like a typical &amp;#34;lecture style&amp;#34; lesson he&amp;#39;s
delivered numerous times. This time, it would be delivered via
Zoom. Now, Zoom is great but it&amp;#39;s harder to do an interactive
lecture - ie active learning online than it is to do in person which
is what I&amp;#39;m guessing led him to set up some starter Google sheets and
use these shared documents for an active project based class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the post, now that he came up with what sounds like
a much stronger approach. Fred wonders if he&amp;#39;ll ever teach this class
any other way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first thing I thought was that this would be even better in
person. I don&amp;#39;t know the specifics but I could think of a number of
ways of running this. All in person with time to work on the
spreadsheets is one. Giving some pre-work and the sheets and then pick
up somewhere in the middle is another. In person gives the feel - the
live interaction where a teacher can read the class but there&amp;#39;s no
reason why we can&amp;#39;t also leverage tech tools like shared Google
sheets in a live classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then I got thinking about necessity being the mother of
invention. Nothing stops us from changing things up, from trying
something in normal times but when the norm is disrupted sometimes it
spurs creativity or changes focus. I
try to continually evolve as a teacher but I&amp;#39;m no better than anyone
else and get caught in ruts. I force myself to try new
things. Sometimes they work and it&amp;#39;s great and sometimes &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/try-something-new/&#34;&gt;they
don&amp;#39;t&lt;/a&gt;. Live and learn. On the other hand, when all if a sudden you can&amp;#39;t do things the
usual way the brain works on alternatives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One example was the lesson where I
&amp;#34;invented&amp;#34; live coding. It was a direct result of a forced change -
for some reason, and I don&amp;#39;t recall why, I couldn&amp;#39;t do things the way I
wanted that day so I winged it. Years later, I was chatting with a
former student and he, out of the blue mentioned that that lesson had
a profound influence on him. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Right now, I&amp;#39;m teaching using Zoom, slack, videos and email. Not being
in a room with my kids sucks. I feel less connected and it&amp;#39;s much
harder to read the class. What am I doing? On the one hand, I&amp;#39;m not
trying to change that much at once as I want my students to have some
stability in an uncertain time but I am working on new things. The
nice thing is that whatever I come up with I can share with my fellow
teachers here and take with me back into the classroom. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was my big takeaway but the post also reminded me of why I turn
to teachers before I turn to &amp;#34;the research&amp;#34; or policy makers on how to
teach. Fred described the evolution of a lesson and a teaching
technique. What he essentially described is what teachers do every day
and we have to do it accounting for all the variables that the
research can&amp;#39;t. We teach multiple classes a day every day of the
week. We try things, assess the results, rinse and repeat. I get that
all teachers don&amp;#39;t do this but the good ones do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The final thought I had was with the reality that while coming up with
interesting active learning experiences is great it also takes a lot
of time and there&amp;#39;s not much time when you&amp;#39;re teaching five classes a
day five days a week to 150 kids along with grading, advising, and
everything else. This is why I tell young teachers that you always
want to evolve and improve but not every lesson is going to be a home
run and that&amp;#39;s okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s particularly important for teachers to remember this now as
across the nation they&amp;#39;re re-inventing their syllabi on the fly to
move from in person to online and they&amp;#39;re doing it without time,
training, and in some cases tools. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do the best you can and continue to develop your toolset. Not every
new online experience will be great but if they&amp;#39;re sincere, your kids
will know. In the end we&amp;#39;ll all be okay and back to normal but with a
whole bunch of new tricks up our sleeves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Problems</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 08:12:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I organize a monthly professional development session for CS
teachers. It&amp;#39;s targeted at teachers who are beyond the beginner stage
and don&amp;#39;t want yet another hello world blinky arduino scratch
workshop. Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, given the need for CS teachers we need
plenty of beginner workshops but we also need to take teachers to the
next level. I refer to my workshops as being for teachers of APCS-A,
similar, or beyond. Participants get three hours of CTLE credit and
thanks to our gracious hosts at &lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalocean.com&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; get to use a great space
and enjoy a free meal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I particularly enjoyed last weeks workshop for two reasons. One is
that we talked about &amp;#34;interesting problems.&amp;#34; This in itself is
interesting because different teachers find different things
interesting. For me, this time around, I was thinking of problems that
could be approached by beginners but had some interesting insight that
allowed them to look at the problem differently and solve it more
efficiently. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second reason I liked this session is because I wasn&amp;#39;t the only
one presenting!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started the session talking about the Happy Ladybugs problem - a
Hackerrank problem I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then passed off to Justin who talked about finding the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull&#34;&gt;convex hull&lt;/a&gt;
bounding a set of points. Justin talked about how you can relate this
abstract geometry problem to real world problems like bounding
neighborhoods as well as how this can be graphically motivated and
then moved to discussing &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull_algorithms&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;. Students can pretty easily come
up with a in inefficient O(n^4) solution and then Justin talked about
incrementally guiding them through alternate solutions ending with
something that runs in O(nlgn). At the end of the day we had a problem
that could be done in a variety of ways with students at different
levels of experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then moved to Barry&amp;#39;s presentation of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baphl.org/20/&#34;&gt;puzzle hunt&lt;/a&gt; problem he
adapted. It involved decoding, translation, number bases and Barry
uses it as a platform to work with stacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I finished the evening talking about three problems but we didn&amp;#39;t look
at solutions. These were teasers for next time when we also hope to do a
SIGCSE recap.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers Pay Teachers - part 2 - the report</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 10:03:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Continuing from yesterday, what about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.govtech.com/computing/Report-Most-Teacher-Created-Online-English-Materials-Subpar.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://fordhaminstitute.org/national/research/supplemental-curriculum-bazaar&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; on pay
and free teacher resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The report looked at three sources - one pay and two free. They came
up with a number of results but I think they largely missed the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Their bottom line conclusion was that &amp;#39;Overall, reviewers rate most
of the materials as â€œmediocreâ€ or â€œprobably not worth usingâ€.&amp;#39; They
also didn&amp;#39;t seem to find that neither the for profit or free sources
were universally better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The one thing I can agree with though is that a consistent rating
system for the types of resources found on these sites would be very
helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think the main problem with the report has to do with what they were
looking for. They concluded things like the resources didn&amp;#39;t line up
well with standards, didn&amp;#39;t have good assessments, didn&amp;#39;t address
cultural diversity and a few other &amp;#34;didn&amp;#39;t dos,&amp;#34;  As I said, I think they
missed the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It felt to me that the reviewers were looking for rote
experiences. Download a lesson and follow the script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of what reformers would have you think, that isn&amp;#39;t
teaching. A teacher new to a class might start with a well worked out
curriculum and largely follow it verbatim but as they develop their
chops they&amp;#39;ll want the curriculum and all related materials to become
their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A downloaded resource, taken as is, will likely not address a specific
classes cultural diversity, at least not more than in the general
sense because it was designed for the authors class and that&amp;#39;s a good
thing. It&amp;#39;s up to the person doing the downloading to take the
resource and then adapt it for their students in their situation. This
is why most of the items that the report considers bad to me are both
inevitable and fine. There is no universal lesson that you can cut and
paste to all schools. To expect it is rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the CS side, there&amp;#39;s a good amount of sharing of materials as well
as providers well, providing content. Some is free some not but there
is a lot available. Forgetting about whole curricula resources, three
lesson / experience sites  I&amp;#39;m
reasonably familiar with are the SIGCSE &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Nifty Assignments&lt;/a&gt; and now the
CSTA&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/cstaniftyassignments/&#34;&gt;corresponding project&lt;/a&gt; along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.engage-csedu.org/&#34;&gt;Engage CS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest problem with the Nifty sites is that they&amp;#39;re arranged
chronologically by the conference year they were presented. There are
no tags nor easy way to search.  Engage CS gives you some level of
searching like for course level, keyword, resource type, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The sites present resources in a format that&amp;#39;s superficially
 consistent but the truth is, once you get past the headings they can
 be written up in radically different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me, that&amp;#39;s not a problem. Each resource was written by some
educator with the intent of sharing but since each author is unique so
to will be the content they produce. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The real value of all these resources are to get ideas - lesson
motivations, code samples, project ideas etc.. Sure, I wish they were
more discoverable via search - better tagged and yes, even better
rated but the value is from reading what some other teacher has done
and then pulling out aspects that can work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve rarely used a Nifty Assignment nor something from EngageCS
explicitly but I have gotten value from both sites (CSTA Nifty
assignments are newer and I&amp;#39;ve been at all the CSTA sessions so
haven&amp;#39;t actually used the site). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Would I ever use a resources &amp;#34;as published?&amp;#34; Perhaps - if
it was really well aligned with how I do things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Would I pay? Probably not. I&amp;#39;m not against paying for resources from a
philosophical point of view. Charge a fair price and give a reasonable
assurance that what you&amp;#39;re selling has value and provide some value
beyond the free sites. I haven&amp;#39;t used Teachers Pay Teachers and
probably won&amp;#39;t look at Amazon&amp;#39;s thing when it&amp;#39;s launched but to me,
they would have to bring value in terms of curation and search. If
they do at a fair price, then they may be worth using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started teaching there was no public internet. None of this
existed. Teachers kept binders or books of lesson plans and if you
were lucky you could borrow from a friend or colleague. New York&amp;#39;s DOE
at one point had a few teachers in each subject area submit lesson
plans for &amp;#34;lesson books&amp;#34; which they published for each core
subject. My chairman wrote some of the math ones and those materials
largely got me through my first year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we have an embarrassment of riches. That comes with the price
that we have to actually read and evaluate all of the materials we&amp;#39;re
presented with but I&amp;#39;ll take today&amp;#39;s resources over what I started with
any day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers Pay Teachers  - part 1 - should they</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 08:43:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There was a bit of buzz a couple of months ago when Amazon announced
an online marketplace for educational resources. It wasn&amp;#39;t a new
concept - on the pay side, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.teacherspayteachers.com/?msclkid=a426c2c1625613061bc19ce4cdcb6a0a&amp;amp;utm_source=bing&amp;amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Search%2520-%2520Branded%2520-%2520Desktop&amp;amp;utm_term=teachers%2520pay%2520teachers&amp;amp;utm_content=Brand%2520Name&#34;&gt;Teachers Pay Teachers&lt;/a&gt; has been around for a
while and in terms of free, there are many online resources but
they&amp;#39;re not necessarily well organized or curated. What was the buzz?
Should teachers be charging their peers for class materials or should
they be providing them for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was going to blog about it then but never got around to it The other
day, someone posted &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.govtech.com/computing/Report-Most-Teacher-Created-Online-English-Materials-Subpar.html&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article which questioned the quality of both
free resources and pay ones. The article, based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://fordhaminstitute.org/national/research/supplemental-curriculum-bazaar&#34;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt; by the
Fordham Institute looked at ELA resources. The report also only looked
at Teachers Pay Teachers and two free sites - ReadWriteThink and Share
My Lesson excluding many other teacher resources that could be, for
all we know, better curated and more discoverable. As an aside, I was
turned off by the reports referring to their evaluators as &amp;#34;experts&amp;#34;
which is a description I personally would question. Still, there&amp;#39;s
some good fodder for thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll get to the report in the next post but for now let&amp;#39;s tackle the
question that started the initial buzz - should teachers be charging
each other for materials?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It depends. If you&amp;#39;re paid by a school to develop materials they
belong to the school. In NY you can take a sabbatical to build a
course so anything you build during that time would be DOE property
and therefore you couldn&amp;#39;t sell it. Same thing if you&amp;#39;re being paid
off hours to develop materials. The gray area comes when you&amp;#39;re lesson
planning. Most real planning and development happens outside of
school hours. In an typical school day teacher are typically
allocated around 40 minutes to do all their planing, grading,
and paperwork so realistically most materials as well as planing,
paperwork, and grading are done off hours. This being the case, I&amp;#39;m of
the belief that those materials belong to the teacher (although I&amp;#39;ve
met some DOE educrats who would disagree).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, should they sell it? Well, they have every right to. That said, my
personal feelings and practice is that if you&amp;#39;ve developed something
for yourself and have not spent extra time or effort to prepare it for
others then I think you should make it freely available to your
peers. On the other hand, if you spend extra time and effort to make
it useful for and usable by others then by all means charge if you&amp;#39;d
like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll tackle the report in the next post and we&amp;#39;ll look at some of the
resources available on the CS side.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using GitHub issues for class communicatoin</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/git-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 16:17:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/git-issues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last week I talked about using &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/&#34;&gt;GitHub issues&lt;/a&gt; as a mechanism for class
communication. I thought it might be helpful to follow up on it and
also felt that a video would be better than text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, here it is, 16 minutes on how you can use GitHub issues for class
communication. I don&amp;#39;t show examples of everything like @ tagging but
I think it shows some of the power of using GitHub and GitHub
classroom beyond just a software repo and versioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SNsjMKYoLr8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 1 - cleaning the data</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 16:18:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I run periodic professional development sessions here in New York with
my partner in crime JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver. I call them PD for &amp;#34;APCS-A,
similar or beyond&amp;#34; and they&amp;#39;re designed to fill a professional
development gap. We try to run them once a month but it&amp;#39;s a little
less frequent than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The NYCDOE has taken on the monster task of CS for all and since
they&amp;#39;re trying to get to everyone they have to run a bazillion
sessions but all at an introductory level. Beyond that, most PD is
tied to a curriculum, program, or product. We decided to run sessions
for teachers who are ready for more both pedagogically and content
wise while not affiliating with any specific provider. We&amp;#39;re just
about the CS and the teaching of CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday we had our first session of the year and the content topic
was text processing. Along the way, we used it as an opportunity to
highlight subgoal labeling as a teaching technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a lot you can do in both CS0 and CS1 with text and document
processing. By the end of yesterday&amp;#39;s session we had discussed a bunch
of possibilities based on the text processing technique known as a
&amp;#34;bag of words&amp;#34; which basically takes a text and just considers all the
words it contains. What are the words and how many times does each
word occurs. No consideration of order, grammar, or anything else. Just
words and counts. We also talked a bit about more advanced possibilities
like playing with an inverted index. I&amp;#39;ll talk about both of those in
a future post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For today, let&amp;#39;s talk about what we have to do before we even begin -
preprocessing the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We grabbed a bunch of texts from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gutenberg.org/&#34;&gt;Project Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically, &amp;#34;Moby
Dick&amp;#34;, a translation of my favorite play &amp;#34;Cyrano de Bergerac&amp;#34; and the
Book of Psalms from the Bible. I also made a copy of the first chapter
of &amp;#34;Moby Dick&amp;#34; so we had a shorter corpus to play with and typed up
the first scene of &amp;#34;Macbeth&amp;#34; - all thirteen lines of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s easy enough to read in the data in a language like Python:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;f &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;cyrano.txt&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
raw_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; f&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;read()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but if you&amp;#39;re using a bag of words you&amp;#39;ve got to do some cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, all Project Gutenberg texts contain a whole bunch of front
and back matter with lots of words. If you don&amp;#39;t get rid of them
you&amp;#39;ll get extra words in your bag. I forgot to do this and was a bit
surprised to see phrases like &amp;#34;Pay a trademark license&amp;#34; in the Book of
Psalms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s easy enough to just cut the tops and bottoms of each file off
with an editor and that&amp;#39;s when we can read our data into our program
and the fun begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First we had to turn everything into lower case;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; raw_data&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;lower()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and then the big part - we want to get rid of all the punctuation. We
first tried something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;stuff_to_remove &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;.:;&amp;#39;0123456789&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_letters &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; stuff_to_remove]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;join(cleaned_letters)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second line is a list comprehension. It iterates through each
letter in lower_data and copies it into the resultant list only if the
letter is not in our stuff_to_remove list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if we had &lt;code&gt;lower_data = &amp;#34;abc123def g&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt; we&amp;#39;d get a result
of &lt;code&gt;[&amp;#34;a&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;b&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;c&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;d&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;e&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;f&amp;#34;,&amp;#34; &amp;#34;,&amp;#34;g&amp;#34;]&lt;/code&gt;. We then use the join in line 3
to turn it back into a string &lt;code&gt;&amp;#34;abcdef g&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This worked pretty well but we found that there were problems. There
were characters that we didn&amp;#39;t account for like long dashes that
connected words and we didn&amp;#39;t have an easy way to put them in our
removal string.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This led to take 2. Instead of deciding what to throw away, let&amp;#39;s
decide what to keep;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;stuff_to_keep &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;abcdefghijklmnopqrstuvwxyz &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\t\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_letters &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; stuff_to_remove]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;join(cleaned_letters)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This worked better (and yes, I know I could have used isalpha() but I
didn&amp;#39;t remember it at the time) but still had problems. We had words
that were formerly separated by punctuation with no spaces that were
now combined into new invalid words. We also had things like chapter
headings in our text and other stray words that we probably wanted to
get rid of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this led to rich conversation among the teachers present and
can do the same in class. What do you clean? What do you keep? Is it
worth the effort to write all sorts of cleaning code to get rid of a
couple of stray bits of bad data or can we get the results we want by
leaving it in? There&amp;#39;s no universally right answer and that&amp;#39;s part of
the beauty of doing things like this with a class - it&amp;#39;s something
that can make them think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we made our final cleaning decisions it&amp;#39;s a simple matter to
convert the long string of text into a list of words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;wordlist &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; cleaned_string&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we&amp;#39;re ready to start building our bag of words but that&amp;#39;s a post
for another day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Ap Registration - it&#39;s, um, for the kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 08:08:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I stumbled upon a thread over in the APCS-A Facebook group the other
day. It seems that the College Board is making some changes in their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apcentral.collegeboard.org/about-ap/news-changes/ap-2019&#34;&gt;registration timeline&lt;/a&gt;. In the past, students registered for the exam
sometime in March with the exams administered in May. The new changes
include requiring registration in November along with $40 late
registration and cancellation fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The College Board is, of course, spinning this as for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3MCNEYCZWqw&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;fbclid=IwAR04Uuj7vpHoYU_8jMjw00YpAPXp7gi3MDGdTKhzpUXv7mI0OILW01KyzvA%0A&#34;&gt;the student&amp;#39;s
benefit&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At least a portion of the teaching community thinks otherwise and has
in fact started &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.change.org/p/demand-the-college-board-not-mandate-fall-ap-exam-requirements-and-deadlines&#34;&gt;this petition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me this is just another money grab by the College Board - an
organization that already has way too much influence over high school
education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s take a look at what the College Board actually brings to the
table. They offer an exam. A single exam in each subject offered
that&amp;#39;s supposed to in 3 hours encapsulate an entire years&amp;#39;s worth of
learning and from that, colleges might give  a student placement or
credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But you say &amp;#34;they offer so much more.&amp;#34; Do they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teacher&amp;#39;s have to submit syllabi and the college board approves
them. They offer samples but so do text book authors and third party
organizations. In my case I rolled my own. The teacher also develops
the course. Does the College Board provide materials? I guess, but so
do those same groups that provide curricula. The college board
certainly doesn&amp;#39;t define the subject. Last I checked Calculus, was
pretty well defined way before the AP program. So was 
Chemistry, and most other subjects. Actually, due to their outsized
influence they do define the subset of the subject in some cases and
we should really be questioning this influence. Finally, the teacher does
the actual hard job of teaching the class. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m  just not seeing the value added. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re already seeing schools require that students take the exam to be
in the class or provide &amp;#34;incentives&amp;#34; like a credit or grade bump for
taking the exam or even removing the AP designation from the
transcript if the student doesn&amp;#39;t take the exam. Doing any of these is
just plain wrong. By all means explain the advantages and
disadvantages of taking the exam but to essentially force a student to
fork over money and personal data to an outside independent agency is
just plain wrong. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But you say that students in many districts don&amp;#39;t have to pay. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is even more insidious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now it&amp;#39;s the taxpayer on the hook and the College Board has
successfully created an everlasting cash pipeline from the public into
private coffers while providing questionable value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t agree with me and think that these requirements or
incentives  are fine ask yourself this: If you had a child in a class
and the teacher said &amp;#34;your child has to sit in a room with a friend of
mine for three hours, give them $100 and personal data and I will give
your child a higher grade&amp;#34; you&amp;#39;d be outraged. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Spending three hours taking an external exam has no bearing on what a
student did or didn&amp;#39;t do in the class so the grades, credits etc
should be the same whether or not the kid took the AP exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s get back to the early registration changes. Currently kids
register for the AP exam in March. By then students might know what
college they&amp;#39;re likely to go to. They&amp;#39;ll know if the AP exam is of any
use to them. In November they don&amp;#39;t. I frequently lost some high
scores on AP exams because I had top students who were accepted early
to schools that didn&amp;#39;t award credit. I also lost a couple of low
scores of students that for whatever reasons had no chance at getting
a 3 or higher so opted not to sit for the exam. I guess the College Board came up
with a good way to get money for those kids without providing value in
return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there are block scheduled schools or other situations where kids
don&amp;#39;t start the class until after the new November deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, let&amp;#39;s talk a bit about the College Board&amp;#39;s claim that this is
all for the students. The video talks about students doing better if
they signed up earlier. I&amp;#39;m skeptical but even if it&amp;#39;s true, is &amp;#34;doing
better on the AP exam&amp;#34; the goal we have for our students. How about
learning our subject area or being inspired to continue on with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the video, teachers talk about how the kids are more motivated and
focused because the exam. This is getting to sound a lot like the
inane focus on high stakes test where the test is the goal. Is the
motivation that &amp;#34;you paid the $100&amp;#34; so it&amp;#39;s wasted if you don&amp;#39;t do
well or &amp;#34;the school paid $100&amp;#34; so we&amp;#39;ll guilt you into studying more?
Sorry, as teachers we can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m sure I&amp;#39;ll get some flak for writing this but I also suspect that
there are many teachers who agree with me that the College Board is
not looking out for students but rather themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Scripts To Freestyle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2018 17:35:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I just read &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@bethanymarz/going-off-script-b69345fc5904&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bethanymarz&#34;&gt;Bethany Crystal&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@bethanymarz/going-off-script-b69345fc5904&#34;&gt;Going off script&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bethany writes that while she normally essentially scripts important
presentations, this time she went more off the cuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It made me think about how I teach and a disturbing trend I&amp;#39;ve
seen in CS education and education in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never strictly used a script for teaching. When I started I did
use &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; detailed lesson plans. Back then I was teaching math. It
was also pre internet or at least pre internet as we now know
it. I had an account on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.panix.com/&#34;&gt;Panix&lt;/a&gt; and the internet did indeed exist but
you couldn&amp;#39;t just look for teaching materials. I actually remember
bringing a modem in to Seward Park one day and showing a bunch of kids
this up and coming thing called the internet. I showed them usernet
news, a gopher server and a couple of other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of teaching materials, you could buy sample lesson plans from
the teacher store near the Board of Ed in Brooklyn. These were books
that were compilations of mostly handwritten lessons. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I basically copied and modified them. I had an &lt;strong&gt;aim&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;do now&lt;/strong&gt; key
questions were written as were definitions and summary
statements. Of course there were numerous sample problems and
exercises, all worked out
in advance. It wasn&amp;#39;t quite a script but it was a very well fleshed
out guide &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I gained experience and also shifted from math which wasn&amp;#39;t my
passion to CS, my plans become sparser. I&amp;#39;d still write down
definitions, maybe some solutions and a list of key points but a lot
of the particulars were gone. I didn&amp;#39;t write out key questions or
solutions to all the problems in advance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As time went by the plans got sparser still. I&amp;#39;d still list the key
points I&amp;#39;d want to cover as well as notes on tricky parts of the
lesson but more often than not I&amp;#39;ll just go in with a bullet list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s my plan for a recent lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go over cipher soution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to we solve if already ciphered?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rotate 26 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about using stats&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frequency of letters - look up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find freq of letter in string then use distance formula against
model&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get frequencies from a book&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;try it in another language&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;#39;t get to the last two bullet items so that&amp;#39;s where we&amp;#39;ll start
off on Monday. This plan was all I needed but it in no way tells the
full story of the lesson to anyone but me. It doesn&amp;#39;t include the
motivation, ancillary stories and materials nor how the lesson was
developed or delivered. I knew how it would play out because I was
teaching it and for me these notes were more than sufficient. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All this is not to say that I don&amp;#39;t spend a lot of time planning my
lessons. I do. I just don&amp;#39;t create detailed scripts. I know what I
want to cover and how I want to cover it. Then it&amp;#39;s just got to the
class and go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A big advantage of this is something that Bethany mentioned in her
piece - the ability to &amp;#34;read the room.&amp;#34; This is a big part of
teaching. If you&amp;#39;re following a script, you&amp;#39;re not reading the room
and you&amp;#39;re probably not really teaching the class. You might be
following a script but your students certainly aren&amp;#39;t and once they
veer off program you&amp;#39;ve got to abandon your script or you&amp;#39;re not doing
right by the class. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having a direction but not a script makes it easier to &amp;#34;call and
audible.&amp;#34; That&amp;#39;s what led me to teach the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/&#34;&gt;question answering system&lt;/a&gt;
lesson the other day. It was unplanned but as a class we were having a
discussion and that&amp;#39;s where it led.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned, when I started out I couldn&amp;#39;t do this. I needed much
more detailed plans. That said, as a teacher gains more experience
they can better connect to their classes and do more for their
students by not sticking to the script, reading the room and adapting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brings me to that trend that disturbing trend. I&amp;#39;m talking about
pushing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2013/11/30/teacher-slams-scripted-common-core-lessons-that-must-be-taught-word-for-word/?utm_term=.6afd6d64f1c6&#34;&gt;scripted lessons&lt;/a&gt;. These crop up in charter schools and no
excuse environments and are typically used as ways of &amp;#34;compensating&amp;#34;
for teachers that don&amp;#39;t really know the subject area or how to teach
and to standardize teaching. To me it&amp;#39;s an attack on the teaching
profession. A script is great for a play. It&amp;#39;s great for a speech and
for some presentations but not for teaching. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I understand having something that&amp;#39;s more scripted to use when you&amp;#39;re
faced with novice teachers or teachers that are new to a subject area
but I fear that at times the scripted lessons are the end game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was talking to a friend a few years ago. He&amp;#39;s doing great work in the
CS Ed space and among other things, he develops curricula. I mentioned
to him that I loved his work (still do) but I was concerned that his
materials were becoming much more scripted. His reply was something
like &amp;#34;I agree with you in theory but the truth is most teachers aren&amp;#39;t
you.&amp;#34; I understood his point as most of the teachers that used his
materials were novices but I disagreed that they were &amp;#34;not me.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m
nothing special. I&amp;#39;m just a reasonably bright guy who works hard at
his craft. If I can teach script free so can anyone. Maybe not at
first, but certainly after time and we subvert our profession by
settling for less. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final note, at this point in my career I actually find it very
hard to use a script - even for a presentation. Over the last couple
of years, I&amp;#39;ve been spending my Falls visiting high schools to talk
about Hunter&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.huntercs.org&#34;&gt;Honors CS&lt;/a&gt; program. As much as I tried, I couldn&amp;#39;t
script a presentation. No matter what I did, when I got in front of
the students I just ended up doing my thing and talking to them. At
the end of the day I ended up working things backwards. Over my first
few school visits, I developed a set of key points that I kept coming
back to and finally ended up with a list of bullet points that I can
pretty much follow when I do the &amp;#34;navigating from high school to
college in tech&amp;#34; talk. I guess I&amp;#39;m now working in reverse. Starting
free style and working back to a script.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium  and other blog sites you
might get the idea that you&amp;#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The
internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful
lessons they&amp;#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in
professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests
for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that
worked for them or things they think will work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, for new teachers it can create an unhealthy illusion of what
really goes on in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that sharing of the good stuff is a bad thing but
the truth is that not every lesson is a masterpiece, not every teacher
is a super charismatic showman, and not all topics lend themselves to
creative teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I writing this now? Because I was planning lessons earlier
today and I&amp;#39;m at one of those places where I&amp;#39;m not going to be able to
deliver a whiz-bang lesson in my next class. One of my classes this
semester is for beginners so we&amp;#39;re building up language skills from
the ground up. Right now I want to do some loop applications but
there&amp;#39;s only so much we can do given what the students know. There are
reasons why I don&amp;#39;t want to do graphics with them right now. I also
haven&amp;#39;t introduced lists yet and don&amp;#39;t want to loop over strings yet
so I&amp;#39;m left with doing mathy stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ll look at Newton&amp;#39;s method for square roots. It&amp;#39;s
interesting for the math inclined and does let us explore issues with
floating point and accuracy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not going to be super exciting for everyone though and that&amp;#39;s okay. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could do lists first but I don&amp;#39;t want the kids to have to handle so
much new material so quickly. I&amp;#39;d rather keep the pace slower and work
with what they&amp;#39;ve just learned for a bit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could also do graphics but that adds a level of overhead I don&amp;#39;t
want to get into now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea is to look at the long game. A class runs a whole semester or
possibly a year. You&amp;#39;re going to have some special memorable lessons
and some mundane ones and that&amp;#39;s nothing to be ashamed of. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re still mostly going to see best practices shared online with only
a few brave souls sharing disaster classes and asking for help. That&amp;#39;s
just how the internet works. It&amp;#39;s not the worst thing in the
world. Just remember when you&amp;#39;re struggling to come up with a good
lesson or you&amp;#39;ve just taught a bad one that tomorrow&amp;#39;s will be
better. Judge yourself by your students long term development, not one
day at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>