<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pedgogy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/pedgogy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pedgogy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 11:36:27 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/pedgogy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Code Review Revisited or research - the teacher version</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 11:36:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review-2/</guid>
      <description>Last semester I wrote about how I was introducing my students to code review. I thought it worked pretty well and was anxious to try it again.
Well, I did the lesson(s) again this past week and it looks like it&#39;s a keeper. The setup was pretty much the same with some hiccups due to using a new platform. Last semester I used plain GitHub public repos. This time, I&#39;ve been using GitHub classroom which I like very much but I forgot that I made this assignment use private repos which turned out to be a hassle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An experiment with code review</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 17:09:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes professional practices don&#39;t work well in the classroom and sometimes they do. One professional practice that does work well is code review - reading and reflecting on other peoples code.
I&#39;ve had my students do code reviews in the past but this time I did things differently. Here&#39;s what I did and here&#39;s how it went
Two weeks ago my students completed a lab. The lab involved reading in a poorly indented C++ program and spit out a properly indented one.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>