<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teaching on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/teaching/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teaching on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/teaching/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium and other blog sites you might get the idea that you&#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful lessons they&#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that worked for them or things they think will work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD for people who know CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/</guid>
      <description>I saw a couple of tweets from Sarah Judd this morning:
A lot of CS Ed PD assumes you are new to CS. I really want CS Ed PD for people like us that came from a CS background and want to understand the pedagogy for CS in particular better. Do you know of some?
&amp;mdash; Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) June 27, 2018 
Yes! I love SIGCSE and CSTA. I just feel like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tech or the Teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</guid>
      <description>Every morning one of the first things I do is quickly glance at my emails and other notifications. I really should wait until I&#39;m more awake but old habits die hard.
As some of you know over the past couple of years I&#39;ve been making a series of videos and related post on using my editor of choice, Emacs. I&#39;ve done 48 videos, have over 2500 subscribers on YouTube and people seem to find some value from the series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Magic Bullets - Discovery Learning</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/no-magic-bullets-constructivism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/no-magic-bullets-constructivism/</guid>
      <description>The most recent NYC CSTA chapter meeting was &#34;How do I assess CS?&#34; I wanted to go but it&#39;s been such a crazy month I was just too wiped out. Fortunately, the meetup was recorded. I was able to watch the first half this morning while working out on my stationary trainer which leads me to today&#39;s rare Saturday morning blog post. The meetup consisted of two panels. The first was made up of K12 teachers who taught CS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</guid>
      <description>About a week ago New York State&#39;s new regulation creating a K12 CS teacher certification went live. Just the other day I was honored to be interviewed by Matt Flamm of Crain&#39;s New York in a follow up piece about it.
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs that lead to certification is HUGE. In my view, it&#39;s a game changer.
Let&#39;s Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refactoring</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/</guid>
      <description>One of my laments on teaching computer science is that students are rarely taught and given the chance to develop good programming practices. There&#39;s usually not enough time. Beginners work on small &#34;toys&#34; which don&#39;t lend themselves to good software development practices and later on, there&#39;s so much other material like algorithms, data structures etc. to teach and learn that programming practices usually amount to lines like:
  &#34;Make sure to comment your code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sigcse2018 Bootstrapworld on Creativity in CS classes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-bootstrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-bootstrap/</guid>
      <description>I really didn&#39;t know what to expect at the Creativity, Customization, and Ownership: Game Design in Bootstrap: Algebra session. I&#39;ve been a big fan of Bootstrep for years and looking at the authors, Emmanuel Schanzer&#39;s been a freind forever. I&#39;ve never met Shriram Krishnamurthi in person but am looking forward to it. We&#39;ve traded emails and blog comments. I&#39;d like to consider him a friend and I certainly respect him and his work even though we frequently disagree around the edges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools can shape how we think</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-4-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-4-6/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been having fun with this years Advent of Code competition. So far, I&#39;ve been able to keep up but with I expect that to change in another couple of days since I&#39;ll be traveling for the weekend.
After solving a problem, I like looking over some of the other solutions on the Advent of Code subreddit. Even with similar agorithmic solutions there&#39;s a decent amount of variation in the actual code and solutions in different languages can look radically different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts On A Hackathon</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thoughts-on-a-hackathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thoughts-on-a-hackathon/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I was one of the judges at StuyHacks. A one day hackathon at Stuyvesant run by and organized by the students. I don&#39;t have attendee stats but there were kids from all over the city and at least one team from New Jersey. The youngest student that I met was in sixth grade and the oldest were high school seniors. The judging was at the end but I decided to stop by earlier to see how the hackers were doing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Interesting Problems - Happy Ladybugs</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/</guid>
      <description>We all love interesting problems. The trouble is that it&#39;s hard to find suitably interesting problems for students when they&#39;re just learning the basics. In the very beginning the problems practically dictate the solution:
 loop over a list and add all the elements or calculate the sum of a list of integers. Determine if number is prime Convert a word into pig-Latin  It&#39;s not that there&#39;s no thought involved in solving these but the students already know the mechanics of solving these by hand so it&#39;s a direct translation into a program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Idioms</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms/</guid>
      <description>I just read Jeff Yearout&#39;s recent post titled The Beginner&#39;s Garden of Concepts. Not directly related but it got me thinking about programming idioms.
I&#39;ve been using the phrase &#34;programming idiom&#34; for years to describe a short useful recurring code construct. I didn&#39;t realize that it was officially &#34;a thing&#34; until doing a web search on the phrase years later.
As our students grow from newbies on I think it&#39;s helpful for them to see recurring and related patterns and programming idioms gives us a name to apply to many beginner patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Term New Tool - Thonny, a Python IDE</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-tool-thonny/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-tool-thonny/</guid>
      <description>Last year I wrote about repl.it, an online IDE that supports multiple languages. At the time it had some rudimentary classroom support and since I started using it, repl.it has become better and better. I used it last year with my class because I had to start the year in a lab where I couldn&#39;t easily install my own software. I&#39;ll continue to use repl.it - mostly for it&#39;s ability to schedule publish and manage assignments but when possible, I like having my students work locally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theseus&#39;s Curriculum</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseuss-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseuss-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>With the school year starting I was originally planning on writing about my class rules.
Instead I think I&#39;ll riff on Alfred Thompson&#39;s post today titled Curriculum is Hard. I&#39;m guessing I found curriculum design and development daunting decades ago but at this point in my career it&#39;s something I enjoy. In any event, Alfred got me to thinking - when is a curriculum your own?
If you grab a curriculum complete with lesson plans, assignments; the whole kit and caboodle and you use it verbatim it&#39;s clearly not your curriculum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching APCS-A for the first time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</guid>
      <description>I got an email from a friend the other day. Among other things, he mentioned that he would be teaching APCS-A for the first time this year. He&#39;s a little trepidatious. He knows his stuff but he hasn&#39;t really done much using Java.
I was going to respond in an email but thought I might share here instead.
  TL;DR - for all you APCS teachers who are new or new to Java - learn  your core CS, lean on your resources and support and it&#39;s OK to tell  your kids &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three strikes and you&#39;re out or third time&#39;s a charm</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/</guid>
      <description>Brenda Wilkerson, Director of CS and IT education for Chicago public schools was one of the keynote speakers at this year&#39;s CSTA conference. During her talk, she made a comment about it taking three times through to get it right so if you&#39;re working hard and struggling in your first year of teaching CS, it&#39;s not the time to give up. Learning to teach takes time.
She&#39;s absolutely correct. I saw this in myself and I&#39;ve seen this in many other young teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teacher-eval/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teacher-eval/</guid>
      <description>Another set of tweets god me thinking:
How do we help school administrators help and evaluate CS teachers? asks @lsudol of @CSForAll #csta2017 Many don&amp;#39;t understand CS
&amp;mdash; Alfred Thompson (@alfredtwo) July 10, 2017 
If the current system is any indication, checklists are not the answer
&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) July 15, 2017 
I get the intent. CS teachers should be evaluated by people who have some clue about the subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teachers - teacher first or content first</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</guid>
      <description>Is it easier to take CS people and teach them to teach or is it easier to take teachers and teach them CS?
The question gets batted around from time to time.
This time via twitter:
Some think it&amp;#39;s easier to teach a teacher to teach CS than to teach a CS pro to teach. @alfredtwo is not one of them https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ
&amp;mdash; Diane Levitt (@diane_levitt) July 3, 2017</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disclosing Bugs - requiring a project roadmap</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/disclosing-bugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/disclosing-bugs/</guid>
      <description>Over on Facebook, a fellow CS educator 1 made a comment on something he wanted to try with his students this summer: having the students pre-disclose bugs when they submit their projects.
The post was asking for any links to &#34;the literature.&#34; I can&#39;t speak to that but I I&#39;ve done something similar to what the post was asking about so, as per usual, I thought I&#39;d write about it here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python - Editor or IDE</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/python-editors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/python-editors/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I read Garth Flint&#39;s latest post on choosing a Python environment for his classes. While our classes and populations are different it looks like Garth and I share a lot of thoughts on the subject.
I started to write a comment to leave on Garth&#39;s blog but since it was getting a little long I thought I&#39;d write it up as a post.
The question of development environment can be an important one and can make a big difference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing a course with constraints</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/</guid>
      <description>One of the hats I wear at Hunter is to build a new CS Honors program and to bring my particular brand of insanity to Hunter College CS as a whole.
Yesterday was my last class for the semester so I thought I&#39;d write a bit about the course.
For the Fall semester, I taught an intro programming course to the entire cohort. For some in the cohort, this was their first exposure to CS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It feels good to be helpful</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/feels-good-to-be-helpful/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/feels-good-to-be-helpful/</guid>
      <description>I got some nice feedback today from a couple of disparate places. It was another reminder that being a teacher isn&#39;t just about the kids currently in your class but it&#39;s about who you are and everyone you interact with. It&#39;s not just about teaching a subject but rather about helping people get to where they can potentially go.
About a year ago I started putting together a series of posts and videos showing how I use Emacs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A free multi-state clicker with built in redundency</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</guid>
      <description>Last Friday, Mark Guzdial wrote about the woes of using clickers in a class. The amount of effort required to use his school&#39;s approved clicker technology sounds ridiculous so while we need tools to better engage students in large class settings we need better tools that can be integrated into our classes more easily.
I&#39;ve never used clickers. On top of stories like Mark&#39;s, there are a number of problems with using clickers in a public school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rookie Season Redux</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rookie-season-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rookie-season-redux/</guid>
      <description>Today was the last day of classes at Hunter thus ending my first semester of teaching at Hunter College.
I very much enjoyed the semester and my class and look forward to working with the same group when the spring term starts in a few weeks.
At the same time, even though I&#39;m a quarter century veteran teacher, in many ways this was like my rookie season all over again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First day back, or not</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/</guid>
      <description>The day after Labor Day. The day NYC teachers traditionally return to work. For the first time in a quarter century, I&#39;m not one of them.
It&#39;s weird.
Instead, I&#39;m in the second week of Hunter College&#39;s fall semester. So far so good on that front. I&#39;m getting to know my students, planning activities and overall having a good time.
But, I do have to reflect on some of the things I&#39;m not going to get to do this week:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</guid>
      <description>If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching career, then our family&#39;s West Coast swing was a nice way to pull down the curtain.
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she&#39;s interning at Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle for a couple of days.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>