<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Intro on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/intro/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Intro on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/intro/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Inverted Index Project</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/inverted-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/inverted-index/</guid>
      <description>I haven&#39;t spoken much about the class I&#39;ve been teaching this semester. It&#39;s an intro CS course - a programming heavy intro. I decided to use Python with a transition at the end to C++. The transition is to mirror Hunter&#39;s normal first CS course that ends with a C++ intro to prepare the students for next semester&#39;s CS course which is a more intense OOP class using C++ - the language we use in our core courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Madlib Madness</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-04-30-madlib_madness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-04-30-madlib_madness/</guid>
      <description>Earlier in the term, our intro classes spent a little time learning some basic HTML. We don&amp;rsquo;t spend a lot of time on it, just enough so that the students can present their work in a static web site. The end goal, though, was to programatically generate the web sites - there&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite as empowering to a student as when they can present their work to the world.
Finally, it&amp;rsquo;s all coming together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who won the election -- Quadratic to Linear Time!!!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-03-23-who_won_the_election-quadratic_to_linear_time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-03-23-who_won_the_election-quadratic_to_linear_time/</guid>
      <description>Last week was crazy. Busy, stressful, late night after late night. It ended, though, on a great note.
A young lady in my intro class found me in my office near the end of the day:
 Student: Mr. Z, I wanted to make sure to catch you before vacation!
Me: What&amp;rsquo;s up?
Student: I wanted to tell you that today&amp;rsquo;s lesson was AWESOME!!!!!!
 Wow. I&amp;rsquo;ve been teaching 23 years and that&amp;rsquo;s never happened before!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>