<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cs on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cs on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 16:04:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 16:04:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-2/</guid>
      <description>When we left off last time we used a search engine API to gather a whole bunch of documents with the term &#34;played Spiderman&#34; or &#34;who played Spiderman.&#34; Now we have to process these documents to answer the question. Fortunately, the documents are basically just big strings of text.
Since we&#39;re doing a &#34;who&#34; query we want to find all the names in all the documents. This leads to a class discussion on how to find names in a large string.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Played Spiderman part 1 or my Nifty Assignment (that was rejected)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 17:16:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/</guid>
      <description>I wasn&#39;t going to teach this lesson today. I was planning on starting a multi day project starting with an exercise in specification writing and design.
Beforehand though, we had to talk about classes. One of my students asked if probability and/or statistics were really important for CS. I started to cite a few examples and then decided to segue into this. Normally, I do this as a couple of lessons which leads to a project, we just did the first part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compile Each Concept</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2018 14:46:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/compile-each-concept/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;ve all been there:
  Student: Teacher, I need help  Teacher (comes over)  Student (shows screen listing three bazillion errors)  The student has just written pages of code and finally decided to try to run it only to end up with pages of errors.
Error messages can at times be hard to read for beginners but to see and truth be told, they frequently don&#39;t even read them but over the years I&#39;ve developed a practice that I&#39;ve found helpful as a software developer and if students adopt the same practice it can save them a lot of time and effort.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>