<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Csta on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/csta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Csta on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 05:03:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/csta/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Crochet at CSTA</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/crochet-at-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 05:03:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/crochet-at-csta/</guid>
      <description>Ok, probably more knitting but Crochet at CSTA was the line used in the newsletter and it sounds better.
As some of you know, my wife Devorah is all about the fiber arts. Knitting, spinning, dying, weaving, the works. We&#39;ve got a loom, two spinning wheels, two bobbin lace pillows, and bins and bins of deconstructed sheep, llamas, alpacas, and angora bunnies. I even got her some straw once to spin into gold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019 - Using GitHub as a CMS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 12:09:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</guid>
      <description>With ISTE ending, the next big event for CS treachers is the annual CSTA Conference. I first attended two years ago in Baltimore. Last year the conference, in Omaha was bigger and better in every way imaginable. I expect this year to be the best yet.
I don&#39;t go to a lot of conferences so I don&#39;t have much to compare CSTA with but I like the fact that it&#39;s is about half the size of SIGCSE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2018 - Funding and Direction</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018-future/</guid>
      <description>In addition to everything I wrote about last time there were a couple of other big announcements at this year&#39;s CSTA conference. Both announcements deal with funding.
First, there is a new class of CSTA membership. The free tier remains but now for $50 you can join CSTA+. This new level of membership comes with a bunch of extras that are probably good for K12 teachers but I doubt I&#39;ll use any of them.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>