<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Education on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Education on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 09:55:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/education/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 09:55:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve never been much of a New Years person. I get up really early and so don&#39;t usually stay up late and more to the point, as any teacher knows, the year really goes from September through June with that really long much needed weekend that you regular folks call July and August tacked on to separate years.
This whole January first thing is really more of a half time break or perhaps an intermission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sloan awards for excellence in teaching science and mathematics</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sloan-awards-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 12:52:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sloan-awards-2018/</guid>
      <description>I spent yesterday evening at the Cooper Union in their Great Hall, a place famous for Abraham Lincoln&#39;s speech that some say propelled him to the presidency.
I was there in the audience watching as the Sloan Foundation and the Fund for the City of New York awarded seven public school teachers with an ward for &#34;Excellence in the Teaching of Science and Mathematics.&#34;
I was their to see my friend Dave Deutsch, a long time public school physics teacher receive the honor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email Policy</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 19:36:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-policy/</guid>
      <description>I saw this tweet the day along with the ensuing thread:
Seriously, who emails a professor with words like &amp;quot;u&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;plz hlp&amp;quot;? Am I allowed to put language in my syllabus that penalizes students for obnoxious, intentional misspellings? Maybe: -1% to your course grade multiplied by the edit distance of the word with its correction?
&amp;mdash; Austin Cory Bart (@AustinCorgiBart) November 30, 2018 
I wanted to reply but as usual, I decided to reply in a blog post so that it doesn&#39;t get lost in the Twitterverse.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>