<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>class design on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/class-design/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (class design)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 12:18:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/class-design/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Organizing a topics course</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/organizing-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 12:18:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/organizing-topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m team teaching the CS Topics course this semester with my buddy
JonAlf. It&amp;#39;s the final course in our Advanced Certificate and Masters
programs in CS Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a fun course. The theory is that a K12 CS teacher doesn&amp;#39;t need to
know everything but should know a little about a lot. It&amp;#39;s a survey -
think of it as an intro unit in ten to twelve different topics in CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also something of a catchall. After this cohort, students
completing our program and in fact any NY state CS teacher
certification program will have to sit for and pass a new Content
Specialty Exam (CST) and while the exam hasn&amp;#39;t been released, best bet
is that it will cover draw from the NY State CS and digital fluency
standards. Between all our other courses we cover most of the
standards and &lt;strong&gt;far&lt;/strong&gt; more in many areas but there are a few topics that
just don&amp;#39;t fit. Also, some items from the standards are already covered in
courses like our Ethics course, but we can look at them from a
more technical point of view in topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The way I set up the course last year was that I taught the first
couple of topics - covering networks and networking and also
pragmatically generating web sites/applications with Flask. After
that, the students teach the topics and I support them in the
background. I cover the first topics to give them all the time and
support necessary to develop their lessons and I cover networking there
because there are a number of nit picky standards items I want to make
sure are covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When setting up and supporting the student groups the important thing
is to make sure that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The topics collectively cover everything I feel is important to be
covered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They deliver their topic at the right level as this is a CS class
not an education class. It&amp;#39;s got to be rigorous enough from the CS
point of view but at the same time accessible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With our first cohort, the class was integrated into the summer
program but last year was also a standalone during the Spring. It
worked pretty well but JonAlf and I decided to change a few things
this year. Part of this was in the hope that things run more smoothly
and the students learn and retain more and partly because I&amp;#39;m handing
off the program when I leave Hunter after the Spring and I want to try
these changes so we can give some specific recommendations for the
next program leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall the plan is the same but the big change is how we&amp;#39;re going to
overlap the topcis. Last year each week was self contained, this year,
we&amp;#39;re overlapping things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On any given week there will be a synchronous class delivered by a
student team. The week prior, that team will give an async
assignment - watch some videos, read some tutorials, work through some
exercises, whatever, that will lead in to the synchronous class. At the
end of the class, the group will give a homework assignment for the
next week. Also at the end of the class, the next group will assign
its prework async assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This means that between the synchronous sessions, each week the
students are working on two things. The prior week topic&amp;#39;s homework
and the forthcoming week topics prework. This should effectively
stretch each topic out to two weeks rather than a more intense one
week at a time. We&amp;#39;re hoping this leads to better weekly discussion
and better retention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other change we&amp;#39;re making is that the student teams have to grade
the homework they assign and also fill out a comment form about their
teammates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The peer evaluation form is needed because groups are much larger this
time around. Having the groups grade the homeworks should serve two
purposes. First, some teams missed the mark last time around. Many
assignments were great but a few were either too onerous  and a few
too trivial. The other reason is selfish - some of last years
assignments were a bear to grade and with 55 students, I don&amp;#39;t need
that. Of course, after they grade the homeworks, JonAlf and I also
have to go over them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These aren&amp;#39;t radical changes but I&amp;#39;m hoping they make for a smoother
class from a teachers point of view and a better experience from the
students point of view. If so, it&amp;#39;ll be all packaged for my
replacement. If not, well, things still worked pretty well last year
and shouldn&amp;#39;t be worse so that&amp;#39;s fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>