<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teacher Prep on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/teacher-prep/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (Teacher Prep)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 07:55:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/teacher-prep/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>But we don&#39;t have enough teachers!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/enough-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 07:55:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/enough-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A common refrain against requiring CS in our K12 schools is that we
don&amp;#39;t have the teachers and we won&amp;#39;t any time soon. Sure, we don&amp;#39;t
right now but we won&amp;#39;t if we don&amp;#39;t do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;300&#34; src=&#34;https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/736x/16/71/5c/16715cc71bd6c28da0b32f24afec5045--simpsons-quotes-los-simpsons.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The question to ask is &amp;#34;how long will it take&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;how do we get
there?&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at New York City. We&amp;#39;ve got approximately 1,000,000
students in our public schools. Let&amp;#39;s say that&amp;#39;s grades 1
to 12. That&amp;#39;s 83333 per grade. Let&amp;#39;s take one particular grade and see
how many classes. At 34 students per class we get 2450 classes. Since
teachers typically teach five classes that means to cover 1 class for
every student in one particular grade we&amp;#39;ll need about 500 teachers to
cover a full year class. 250 if the class is only one semester. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This if, of course, just back of the envelope calculating and we&amp;#39;d
need a good deal more to really do justice to teaching CS in K12 but
500 sounds like a reasonable critical mass to say &amp;#34;we&amp;#39;re teaching CS.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How long until we can get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Hunter we started our advanced certificate program a year
ago. The cert program is specifically for teachers licensed in another
area seeking to add the New York State CS credential. Our first cohort
graduated 21 and I can proudly say they&amp;#39;re all very well prepared to
teach CS in K12. They know their content and how to teach it. We&amp;#39;re
starting another batch in two weeks and a third cohort next summer. By
June 2023 we should have between 60 and 100 teachers certified. That&amp;#39;s
not bad. We&amp;#39;ll have a core group of teacher leaders three years from
our start. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How are we doing this? What&amp;#39;s the incentive for current teachers to
get this new certification? It&amp;#39;s an opportunity to really learn some
CS and how to teach it. All the training and PD based models just
don&amp;#39;t cut it long term. On the other hand, it costs a pretty penny -
21 graduate credits. True, those credits can be applied to salary
differentials but still. Also, while the state could just flat out
require the certification but they&amp;#39;ve put in a generous ramp up -
teachers will need the credential but not for a few year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest reason we&amp;#39;ve been able to get these teachers in is the
generosity of the New York Tech community. We&amp;#39;ve been able to provide
financial support to these teachers looking to be our leaders moving
forward. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Going with that, we have 4 students currently in our Masters program
with another 6 or so slated to start in the Fall and that&amp;#39;s with zero
advertising and outreach. I expect that in a couple of years, the
demand for the certificate program will wane while it accelerates for
the masters program. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re not going to have all the teachers we need in three years or
even in five but in three we&amp;#39;ll have a solid core. As other
certification programs come online the city will increase it&amp;#39;s teacher
training capacity and as we close in on 2026 when CS4All will expect
all schools to offer CS, we&amp;#39;ll have a good number of qualified
teachers to fill the need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sure, it&amp;#39;ll take a decade or longer to finish the job but you&amp;#39;ve got
to start with a plan and a vision and lots of support. At least in NYC
we&amp;#39;ve got all three.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching and Pedagogy - words and music</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teach-pedagogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 20:12:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teach-pedagogy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to give a little more context on &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-creds/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;#39;s post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In reading over the various comments on social media related to the
topic of required and desired CS teacher knowledge there are those
that fall on the content is king and pedagogy not so important and
others who think you don&amp;#39;t really need a deep knowledge of CS. I think
you need both and think current teachers need to be given a
reasonable but finite amount of time to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Whenever the topic comes up I think of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_and_the_Cruisers&#34;&gt;Eddie and the Cruisers&lt;/a&gt;. Tom
Berringer is playing a song - &amp;#34;On the Dark Side&amp;#34; for the band as the
band ridicules him. Eddie (Michael Pare) says &amp;#34;Not bad&amp;#34; to which a
band mate says - &amp;#34;he can&amp;#39;t sing, he can&amp;#39;t play and he can&amp;#39;t
write. What&amp;#39;s not bad?&amp;#34; to which Eddie replies &amp;#34;he&amp;#39;s got something we
need, words and music.&amp;#34; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ds-MR9OPiNU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Words and music - teaching and pedagogy. One isn&amp;#39;t enough - you need
both. You need the content but you also have to do something to bring
value to the kids beyond just dumping the content on the desk - it&amp;#39;s
why I&amp;#39;m so against scripted curricula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why do I think both sides are so important? I probably got here from
teaching at Stuyvesant for over 20 years. On top of that, I&amp;#39;m a Stuy
grad (&amp;#39;84), Stuy husband (Devorah, also &amp;#39;84), Stuy brother, and two
time Stuy parent. While Stuy has and had some good teachers, I got to
see a bunch of bad ones. I saw teachers who didn&amp;#39;t know their subject
areas and teachers who didn&amp;#39;t know how to teach. The rub is that at a
school like Stuy the kids will figure out what they need on their
own. You can put an unripe avocado on the teachers desk and the kids
will still pass all the exams. Sure, the kids pass but every kid
deserves a teacher that adds value to their lives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of the worst at Stuy were teachers for whom Stuy was their first
(and only) gig - they never really had to learn how to teach but for a
variety of reasons - all the kids pass the AP or in the case of
teachers that know content but not teaching, the &amp;#34;smart kids&amp;#34; like the
teacher because they &amp;#34;know stuff&amp;#34; - they think they&amp;#39;re good teachers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sorry, you have to add value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The best thing that happened to me when I started was when Stuy&amp;#39;s
chairman didn&amp;#39;t hire me. I ended up at Seward Park and that&amp;#39;s where I
started to learn my craft. Once at Stuy, I had to be careful not to
fall into the trap - you can become a good or even a great teacher at
a specialized school but, just like anywhere else, you have to work
for it. You have to really look at what and how you&amp;#39;re doing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this is to say that to add value to your students you really
have to know both the content and you have to know how to teach - you
have to add value. If you can be replaced by an avocado, you&amp;#39;re not
earning your paycheck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m not saying that the teachers who don&amp;#39;t know CS and are taking
on this new challenge shouldn&amp;#39;t be given time to learn the subject or
that raw teachers who know their subject shouldn&amp;#39;t be given time to
learn how to teach but you eventually have to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we&amp;#39;re okay with teachers who have to follow scripts for either
content or pedagogy for the long term then we&amp;#39;re devaluing our
profession. I&amp;#39;d like to think we add more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>