<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teacher prep on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/teacher-prep/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (Teacher prep)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 20:12:43 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/teacher-prep/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching and Pedagogy - words and music</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teach-pedagogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 20:12:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teach-pedagogy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to give a little more context on &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-creds/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;#39;s post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In reading over the various comments on social media related to the
topic of required and desired CS teacher knowledge there are those
that fall on the content is king and pedagogy not so important and
others who think you don&amp;#39;t really need a deep knowledge of CS. I think
you need both and think current teachers need to be given a
reasonable but finite amount of time to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Whenever the topic comes up I think of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_and_the_Cruisers&#34;&gt;Eddie and the Cruisers&lt;/a&gt;. Tom
Berringer is playing a song - &amp;#34;On the Dark Side&amp;#34; for the band as the
band ridicules him. Eddie (Michael Pare) says &amp;#34;Not bad&amp;#34; to which a
band mate says - &amp;#34;he can&amp;#39;t sing, he can&amp;#39;t play and he can&amp;#39;t
write. What&amp;#39;s not bad?&amp;#34; to which Eddie replies &amp;#34;he&amp;#39;s got something we
need, words and music.&amp;#34; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ds-MR9OPiNU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Words and music - teaching and pedagogy. One isn&amp;#39;t enough - you need
both. You need the content but you also have to do something to bring
value to the kids beyond just dumping the content on the desk - it&amp;#39;s
why I&amp;#39;m so against scripted curricula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why do I think both sides are so important? I probably got here from
teaching at Stuyvesant for over 20 years. On top of that, I&amp;#39;m a Stuy
grad (&amp;#39;84), Stuy husband (Devorah, also &amp;#39;84), Stuy brother, and two
time Stuy parent. While Stuy has and had some good teachers, I got to
see a bunch of bad ones. I saw teachers who didn&amp;#39;t know their subject
areas and teachers who didn&amp;#39;t know how to teach. The rub is that at a
school like Stuy the kids will figure out what they need on their
own. You can put an unripe avocado on the teachers desk and the kids
will still pass all the exams. Sure, the kids pass but every kid
deserves a teacher that adds value to their lives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of the worst at Stuy were teachers for whom Stuy was their first
(and only) gig - they never really had to learn how to teach but for a
variety of reasons - all the kids pass the AP or in the case of
teachers that know content but not teaching, the &amp;#34;smart kids&amp;#34; like the
teacher because they &amp;#34;know stuff&amp;#34; - they think they&amp;#39;re good teachers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sorry, you have to add value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The best thing that happened to me when I started was when Stuy&amp;#39;s
chairman didn&amp;#39;t hire me. I ended up at Seward Park and that&amp;#39;s where I
started to learn my craft. Once at Stuy, I had to be careful not to
fall into the trap - you can become a good or even a great teacher at
a specialized school but, just like anywhere else, you have to work
for it. You have to really look at what and how you&amp;#39;re doing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this is to say that to add value to your students you really
have to know both the content and you have to know how to teach - you
have to add value. If you can be replaced by an avocado, you&amp;#39;re not
earning your paycheck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m not saying that the teachers who don&amp;#39;t know CS and are taking
on this new challenge shouldn&amp;#39;t be given time to learn the subject or
that raw teachers who know their subject shouldn&amp;#39;t be given time to
learn how to teach but you eventually have to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we&amp;#39;re okay with teachers who have to follow scripts for either
content or pedagogy for the long term then we&amp;#39;re devaluing our
profession. I&amp;#39;d like to think we add more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>