<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Competitions on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/competitions/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Competitions on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/competitions/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Competitions and Hackathons</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hs-competitions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hs-competitions/</guid>
      <description>Today&#39;s the last day of spring break. After the weekend it&#39;s back to the grind. It really hasn&#39;t been much of a spring break. The rain and the snow made for very little spring and between working on the Hunter / CUNY2X Internship program and reviewing applications for my Hunter Daedalus CS Honors program there has been very little break.
Today was no exception - I spent much of the day working but I did take a few hours to head over to Cornell Tech on Roosevelt Island.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Prestigious Competitons And High Schools</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</guid>
      <description>The ACM recently announced this year&#39;s winners of the Cutler-Bell Prize in High School Computing. Over on his blog, Alfred Thompson noted that the winners were either from independent or magnet public schools. Alfred also noted that most of the winners of prestigious science competitions like the Regeneron Science Talent Search (nee Intel, nee Westinghouse) were from public magnet schools. In his post, Alfred ruminates on this and wonders &#34;how to we add the flexibility and support to more students at more schools?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>