<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Policy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/policy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Policy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 08:08:38 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/policy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Ap Registration - it&#39;s, um, for the kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 08:08:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon a thread over in the APCS-A Facebook group the other day. It seems that the College Board is making some changes in their registration timeline. In the past, students registered for the exam sometime in March with the exams administered in May. The new changes include requiring registration in November along with $40 late registration and cancellation fees.
The College Board is, of course, spinning this as for the student&#39;s benefit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a school for CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/creating-a-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/creating-a-school/</guid>
      <description>Do we really need CS focused high schools?
That&#39;s the question Alfred Thompson asked partly in reaction to my post talking about Bill Gates&#39; visit to AFSE, a NYC public school with a CS focus.
On both posts, Michael Preston shared some important and good points about AFSE as a starting point and gateway that helped lead to CS4All in NYC and also specifically about AFSE.
In response to Alfred&#39;s question I thought it was time I shared a bit about what I was pushing for AFSE back when I was involved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving control of NYC&#39;s specialized schools to a political appointee</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I shared my thoughts on Bill de Blasio&#39;s plans to &#34;fix&#34; the selection criteria for New York City&#39;s specialized high schools. If you haven&#39;t read the post, you can find it here.
I was going to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging today but there&#39;s more to the story.
In spite of what BdB stated, it&#39;s not enough for him to switch to another measure - the middle school state exam along with some modifiers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing Admissions to the NYC Specialized High Schools</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, Bill de Blasio, the current Mayor of New York City outlined how he would &#34;fix&#34; our specialized schools. The schools he was referring to were the &#34;big three&#34; of Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, and Brooklyn Tech and then five additional schools - The High School for Math Science and Engineering at CCNY, The High School for American Studies at Lehman, Brooklyn Latin, The Queens Arts and Science High School at York College, and Staten Island Tech.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should CS for All be implemented at the college level?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s been a lively discussion on pushback to CS for All at the K12 level over on Facebook. Mark Guzdial started a sub thread asking if CS for All should first be implemented at the undergrad level rather than K12.
It&#39;s an interesting question and as good as anything to get me out of my month long non-blogging rut.
Mark was right when he said that if Colleges implement CS for All, K12 will likely do so to follow - just look at AP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is there room for CS for All</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</guid>
      <description>A fear revolving around CS For All concerns where will the money come from and how will we fit in the new classes.
One suggested solution is to integrate CS into other subjects. I thought I&#39;d write today about why I don&#39;t think the fear is valid and while integrating CS into other classes can have value, it probably isn&#39;t a long term solution for CS education.
Let&#39;s start with the integration solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unfunded Mandates and CS For All</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</guid>
      <description>This morning, Mark Guzdial wrote about unfunded mandates and CS for All. Unfunded mandates frequently wreak havoc on schools in a number of ways but in the long run, I don&#39;t think it should have a severe effect on CS for All. Rather, it could have a big impact on the number of CS courses we offer beyond that.
Mark relay&#39;s a story from the Cambridge Rindge and Latin School where at the time many students wanted more CS classes but the school wasn&#39;t planning on hiring a new CS teacher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</guid>
      <description>About a week ago New York State&#39;s new regulation creating a K12 CS teacher certification went live. Just the other day I was honored to be interviewed by Matt Flamm of Crain&#39;s New York in a follow up piece about it.
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs that lead to certification is HUGE. In my view, it&#39;s a game changer.
Let&#39;s Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing the Absent Teacher Reserve (ATR) situation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</guid>
      <description>In the New York City department of education a recurring hot topic is the Absent Teacher Reserve or ATR pool.
A teacher or administrator in the ATR pool is a licensed, most likely tenured teacher not assigned permanently to a school. Each year these educators get shuttled from school to school and denied a chance to actually settle in a position.
The ATR pool was created under the Bloomberg administration. Prior to that, when there was an opening school transfers were basically seniority based and when school had too many teachers the least senior was excessed or basically out of a job until a school with an opening could be found.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</guid>
      <description>Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members of the New York State Department of Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A test result is just a test result</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>This past weekend was Catskillsconf - my favorite event of the year. I spent the weekend up in Ulster County with a bunch of my students. some great friends old and new, and Devorah. It was a great weekend but I was mostly offline.
As a result I missed a rather heated discussion in the CS Ed Facebook groups. The debate was over whether or not Strong AP CSP exam results are indicative of a good curriculum or good professional development (PD).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standards - Who are they for?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for/</guid>
      <description>The big push at last year&#39;s CSTA conference was the release of the new CSTA K12 standards. It seemed that every other session was pushing them in one way or another. I&#39;ve been meaning to share my thoughts about them or, more specifically, learning standards in general for a while but with announcement about federal funding for CS coming from the White House last week I thought it was time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the new Secret Sauce ever better?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</guid>
      <description>I read this piece earlier today on Nancy Bailey&#39;s blog.
TL;DR (although it really isn&#39;t too long so you should read it) - it&#39;s on Laurene Powell Jobs, her efforts to &#34;reform&#34; education and why she&#39;s misguided as are most of the well to do non-educators working hard to change and in many cases privatize public education.
Laura posts a nice list of simple, common sense ways to improve education. I&#39;ll repost them here:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cost of AP Exams</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</guid>
      <description>Now that I&#39;m back from vacation and summer&#39;s winding down I thought I&#39;d start getting back to more classroom related posts. I still have a few summer topics I want to write about -- standards and side projects in particular but I&#39;m also looking forward to talking more about the classroom since, after all, at my core, I&#39;m a teacher. When I saw this article in my inbox this morning I thought I&#39;d talk about it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on non educator  influences on CS Education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Mark Guzdial blogged about a NY Times piece discussing Silicon Valleys influence on education through Code.org.
Mark questioned the validity of the piece. If you don&#39;t read Mark&#39;s blog and you&#39;re in CS Ed you probably should.
I tried to leave a comment on Mark&#39;s blog - not about the NY Times article but rather my thoughts on why I think it&#39;s important that we remain wary and vigilant to industry and outsiders influence and impact on CS education and on education in general.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Ed advocates should pay attention to greater ed issues</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-and-all-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-and-all-ed/</guid>
      <description>For anyone involved in K12 CS education, the past few years have been a wild ride. When I first tried to make inroads in the DOE decades ago I couldn&#39;t get through the door. Now, CS Education is everyone&#39;s darling. It&#39;s really amazing. It&#39;s been a combination of grass roots efforts by teachers, non profit education efforts such as TEALS, advocacy of groups like Code.org and amazing individuals like Fred Wilson who has probably done more to move the needle of CS Ed in NY than any other 10 people combined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Certification - not a good idea</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/</guid>
      <description>You&#39;ve probably seen an image like this:
It&#39;s what you see when you try to access a secure web site but the web site itself certified itself as being secure.
When people see this on a professional site it sets off all manner of red flags. We feel much more comfortable when go to a site and we don&#39;t see that error. When we see the secure green lock in the url bar indicating that this site is certified through an external trusted source.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teachers - teacher first or content first</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</guid>
      <description>Is it easier to take CS people and teach them to teach or is it easier to take teachers and teach them CS?
The question gets batted around from time to time.
This time via twitter:
Some think it&amp;#39;s easier to teach a teacher to teach CS than to teach a CS pro to teach. @alfredtwo is not one of them https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ
&amp;mdash; Diane Levitt (@diane_levitt) July 3, 2017</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Retaining Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</guid>
      <description>Back in February, I shared my thoughts on losing CS teachers to the tech industy. TL;DR - I don&#39;t think it will be a CS Ed problem.
That said, I do think that it will be hard to find good CS teachers but the reason is because it will get harder and harder to find good teachers in general.
There are plenty of reasons why it&#39;s harder to become a career teacher but I don&#39;t want to talk about those today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mayoral Control - only when your guy&#39;s the mayor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/mayoral-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/mayoral-control/</guid>
      <description>The hot debate this past week in NY Education circles is Mayoral Control. When I started teaching, New York City schools were controlled by the Board of Education. The board appointed a chancellor. The system was supposed to balance community control as well as some centralized decision making. The system was created in the late 60s and was entrenched through my schooling. By the time I was a teacher I think it was pretty much a given that the system didn&#39;t work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will we lose CS teachers to industry?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/draft-will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/draft-will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</guid>
      <description>If we properly prepare CS teachers, won&#39;t they just jump ship and take  tech industry jobs?  I hear that a lot.
Tech pays big. Teaching? Not so much. Tech workers are respected and have flexible jobs. Teaching? Again, not so much.
Those chanting these refrains advocate the current simple teacher &#34;training&#34; - scripted lessons, minimal pedagogical content knowledge, even less real content knowledge. That will keep them in the classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should CS Ed be in bed with the College Board</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m guessing my views on this aren&#39;t very popular -that&#39;s OK, every community needs a curmudgeon.
A few years ago, I cautioned if we weren&#39;t careful, once the big players got involved, CS Ed would go the way of other disciplines, and not in a good way. It looks like indeed we&#39;re well on our way down that road.
I&#39;ve ranted before about things like non-profits, drop in and summer programs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s not one issue, it&#39;s the President and his enablers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/</guid>
      <description>Like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, I generally keep this site clear of political issues with the exception of those that are directly related to education.
Also, like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, this week has provided a reason to break with that tradition.
Many people, including some friends, all more eloquent than I have already posted, tweeted, and Facebooked about the behavior of our President and government.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selling out or getting a seat at the table</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/</guid>
      <description>The other day, a friend posited a question on Facebook (paraphrased):
  If called upon, would you take a job in an administration who&#39;s policies you strongly  disagreed with?  Would you go work for an administration that you reviled in order to get a seat at the table? To try to affect change from the inside or would you consider yourself a sellout or worse, publicly promote positions you disagree with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluate teachers like they do in the real world</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/evaluating-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/evaluating-teachers/</guid>
      <description>This old article has been reposted a few times in my circles over the past few weeks http://educationnext.org/facadeofexcellence/. It&#39;s from 2003 and complains about the lack of flexibility schools had back then with regard to hiring and salary. The article is old and out of date and the seniority system no longer holds for hiring but it does for lay offs. The salary scale from back then, though, is still in place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Hunter CS is so important to NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/</guid>
      <description>If you know me you know that my morning reads include a visit over to avc.com, Today, Fred&#39;s post talked about development and progress, evolution, if you would, in the city. Although not directly related, it got me thinking about gentrification.
To me, gentrification all too often seems to result in pushing out people and business that were there during the hard times.
We don&#39;t need to force out long time residents that can no longer make rent - we need to uplift communities with pathways to towards greater economic opportunity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Thinkers in Scotland</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m way behind on my Communications of the ACM. I generally only read them when I use my trainer in the mornings and with summer running and outside riding, I&#39;m still on the December 2015 issue.
This morning, I read a viewpoint by Jeremy Scott and Alan Bundy on a program in Scotland. If you&#39;re an ACM member, and if you&#39;re a CS practitioner, student, academic, or teacher you should be, you can read the piece for details.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federal Aid for Code Schools - is this a good thing?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</guid>
      <description>I saw this headline earlier today: The U.S. Just Made a Bold Move to Improve Diversity in Tech.
The article talks about a program by which a number of code schools will be able to accept federal student aid. I don&#39;t know if we&#39;re talking student loans or grants but I&#39;m not sure it matters.
The headline sounds great. I&#39;m not so sure that this is a good thing.
My thinking&#39;s evolved over the years but right now, everything tells me that public funds and for profit education don&#39;t mix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ed Disruption - why it&#39;s different</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I read this post by Eliot Horowitz, founder and CTO of MongoDB.
Eliot titled the post &#34;Innovate vs Appropriate&#34; and talks about the importance of knowing when to come up with something new vs when to use the accepted tool, technique, or method. Eliot, of course is discussing this as it applies to MongoDB and it&#39;s well worth a read but it got me thinking about the ever popular need to &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hillary and Student Loans</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I read over Hillary&#39;s briefing on her initiative on Technology and Innovation.
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have my doubts. My feeling is that she&#39;s pretty much aligned with the current administration education wise and the current administration has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public education.
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much like some of the others, I don&#39;t want to get into that today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PDF 2016 - How we lost the open web</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pdf2016-lost-in-the-silo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pdf2016-lost-in-the-silo/</guid>
      <description>I spent the last couple of days attending Personal Democracy Forum 2016, described on their landing site as:
  The world’s leading conference exploring and analyzing technology&#39;s  impact on politics, government, and society.  That&#39;s the reason why I haven&#39;t posted my latest Emacs video.
PDF is a great conference and raised a huge number of important issues. I&#39;ll probably blog about a few over the next few weeks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navajo Math Circles</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of Navajo Math Circles, a documentary on a Math Circle put in place to support and enrich the currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment programs. I&#39;m most familiar with the New York Math Circle. I&#39;m friends with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in their summer program for a couple of years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Coding or Cheating</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</guid>
      <description>I haven&#39;t been teaching this past semester. That&#39;s why I haven&#39;t been writing much about lessons. I miss working with students but that will resume in the fall and this semester has allowed me to get a jump on new projects.
It&#39;s also allowed me to look at some student issues from a bit of a distance.
One issue that keeps coming up is cheating.
Some of it, classroom cheating. my friend Ria recently asked a question on Facebook about it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A World Without Advanced Placement</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/world-without-ap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/world-without-ap/</guid>
      <description>Some good points in the Facebook comments on my last post. One notable comment was the fact that many teachers wouldn&#39;t be able to gain the traction needed to teach CS without an AP designation. This is true but also sad that we&#39;ve awarded such educational authority to a private company that&#39;s accountable to no one. Schools should run courses because they&#39;re good for kids not specifically because they&#39;re AP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Placement - Because We Don&#39;t Trust Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I ranted on about the College Board. This led to a Facebook hosted discussion which got me thinking a little more:
Advanced Placement exams basically exist because we don&#39;t trust our high school teachers.
I usually use phrases like &#34;society doesn&#39;t trust&#34; but let&#39;s personalize it this time -- for parents, think about whether or not you trust your kids teachers? Do you a large private, unaccountable organization more?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As curricula changes, what&#39;s falling through the cracks?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/semaphores/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/semaphores/</guid>
      <description>Edit: Just a brief note to clarify a couple of things. As indicated in the comments, this post isn&#39;t about what&#39;s appropriate for HS CS. It&#39;s more about what kids have after they finish their education - be it high school, college, code school, or other.
Some of my thoughts are the results of pondering on the exacerbations of friends after interviewing people for entry level positions.
The two examples are just to illustrate the point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NYC DOE - Doing what it can to keep opportunities away from kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cstuy-coi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cstuy-coi/</guid>
      <description>The difficulties I&#39;ve had with the city and DOE are pretty well documented by now.
Today I&#39;m going to tell you about my latest dealings with DOE and how they prevented my team from bringing free quality CS education to city students.
CSTUY&#39;s not running SHIP, its summer program this year.
That&#39;s not something I&#39;m happy about but part of me knew it might happen. What did surprise me, although it shouldn&#39;t have, was the role that the NYC DOE played in preventing it from happening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Awards for Educators</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awards/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awards/</guid>
      <description>There are all sorts of awards for teachers. The Presidential awards, NEA awards, National and State level awards, and more. There are also awards and honors given in more narrow areas like NCTM for math and our own ACM.
I&#39;ve haven&#39;t won any and never expected to. I&#39;ve never played well with the establishment.
It&#39;s ok though. For every honoree that I can point to and say &#34;there&#39;s a master teacher,&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become a CS Education Thought Leader - No Experience Needed</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-04-20-thought-leaders/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-04-20-thought-leaders/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, a friend asked if I knew any CS teachers that were available to work this summer. At the time, I didn&#39;t have anyone to recommend. We were still up in the air on running CSTUY&#39;s SHIP summer immersion program.
We ultimately decided not to run SHIP this summer. Mostly due to the fact that in my new position, I didn&#39;t have the time to do the necessary fund-raising and outreach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We&#39;re Number One!! We&#39;re Number One!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-19-were-number-one.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-19-were-number-one.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 I woke up this morning to an email from my principal &#34;Stuy is #1.&#34; This followed a bunch of Facebook posts by friends and alums of a similar vein.  It was all about a couple of reports, here, and here. It turns out Stuy is ranked #1. Woo Hoo. We&#39;re awesome.  Of course, everyone whooping it up now was quick to say &#34;all those rankings are meaningless&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview questions and tests</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-04-tests-and-interviews.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-04-tests-and-interviews.html/</guid>
      <description>The StuyCS Family mailing list was host to an interesting discussion today. One of our younger members asked if the practice of giving technical problems during an interview was going to follow him throughout his career or if it goes away for more senior applicants.  An interesting discussion followed.  It reminded me of a time I was talking to a few senior engineers at a large tech company.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers - boy do we suck!!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-03-teachers-suck.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-03-teachers-suck.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    Today was a &#34;professional development day.&#34; That means that instead of teaching, we were supposed to work on our craft.  Rather than the normal nonsense - forcing CS teachers to sit through common core math lectures or how to use the latest calculator, our host principal, Randy Asher, of Brooklyn Tech let us do our thing.  Basically, it was a bunch of CS teachers from two schools - Stuy and Brooklyn Tech, talking shop for most of the day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Appointed Experts</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-26-self-appointed-experts.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-26-self-appointed-experts.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 While looking over my tweet stream, I noticed this: RSVP today for the K-12 CS Education Panel, presented by @Uber + @FlatironSchool: https://t.co/nVBbSbRn9d pic.twitter.com/NAxowSIfff
&amp;mdash; Flatiron School (@FlatironSchool) October 26, 2015 
 So, on November 12, one can head over to Uber and listen to three experts talk about K12 CS Education. To quote the landing page: How can we engage our students in CS, and train our teachers to teach it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Alda on Teaching Science</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-20-alda.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-20-alda.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 Scale, scale, scale. Scripted lessons. Online resources, Moocs. No excuses schools. All of these are modern trends in education. None of these are about good education. It&#39;s really demoralizing reading article after article devaluing true master teachers and real education.  So, last night was a real pleasure.  I attended a talk, given by Alan Alda on communicating science. The talk was sponsored by The Academy for Teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grading Autograders</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-16-graders.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-16-graders.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 The other day codehs made an announcement about their new autograder. Fellow CS Teaching veteran Alfred Thompson had his say up on his blog where he talked about Mark Guzdial&#39;s comment on autograders leading to less creative assignments.  I very much agree that autograders, due to their rigidness lend themselves to less creative projects, but thought I&#39;d write up a few of my own thoughts on autograders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free labor for the College Board and more angst for the kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-13-psat.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-13-psat.html/</guid>
      <description>I won&#39;t be teaching my regular classes tomorrow. I&#39;ll be meeting all my kids but classes will only be 12 minutes long.  So, how will my colleagues and I spend the rest of the day?  Proctoring the PSAT.  This has always been a sore point with me. Back in the day, many schools, Stuy included, offered the PSAT on the weekend. If you wanted to proctor, you&#39;d come in and get paid a little extra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not in with the in crowd - concerns about NYC &amp;#35CS4All</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-18-in-crowd.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-18-in-crowd.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    Earlier this week, Mayor Bill deBlasio announced some ambitious CS Education Plans for NYC. I posted a response here. Now that a few days past, I thought I&#39;d clear a few things up.  First and foremost, I hope my concerns are unfounded and I hope the plan is a tremendous success.  What&#39;s got me bummed is not that I need to see my name in lights given that in many ways I&#39;ve been a CS Ed trailblazer (although who doesn&#39;t like a little ego stroking), rather that in my humble opinion NY has squandered a great opportunity and resource and as a results, kids won&#39;t get nearly all they could.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I should be happy but feel like I&#39;ve failed</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-15-failed.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-15-failed.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 The NY Times just posted an article - the mayor announced a 10 year deadline by which time all NYC public school students will be taking CS.  I should be happy.  I&#39;m not.  I feel thoroughly defeated.  As many of you know, I&#39;ve struggled for years to try to bring CS education to more kids and to train more teachers. You also probably know that over the years, I&#39;ve become pretty good at this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I have no faith in NYC Doing CS Ed right.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-22-nycdo.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-22-nycdo.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center text-align:center;    This post is in response to an email thread on the NYTM mailing list. I mentioned how the NYC DOE refused to even look at our program at Stuy let alone support us and help us get to more kids.  Rather than pollute an email thread, I said I&#39;d write up the story here.  I&#39;ve been at the CS Ed game for a long time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting kids up to fail - CS edition</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-17-setting-up-to-fail-cs.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-17-setting-up-to-fail-cs.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    We talked about setting kids up to fail in math. What about CS?  Well, it&#39;s a little subtler.  I started thinking about this after a conversation with one of my graduates about Harvard&#39;s famous CS50. Since that conversation, I&#39;ve spoken to a number of my kids that have gone through CS50 and most seem to say the same things: They don&#39;t really teach anything  The kids rely on a group member who already knows stuff or will learn all the stuff on their own  If it weren&#39;t for my StuyCS background my group would have really struggled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting kids up to fail - math class</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-11-set-up-to-fail-math.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-11-set-up-to-fail-math.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 &#34;Four in ten NYC high schools don&#39;t offer Algebra 2 and both Physics and Chemistry.&#34;  At least that&#39;s what this article and linked report say.  The implication is clear - many of our students don&#39;t have the opportunity to advance in math and the sciences.  The truth though is much more disturbing.  The reason why these schools aren&#39;t offering Algebra 2 is very simple - the kids aren&#39;t ready for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching to the test - APCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-07-25-teaching-to-the-test.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-07-25-teaching-to-the-test.html/</guid>
      <description>This image has been making its rounds.  Largest expansion is pretty clear but are the largest gain in 3+ scores mean a higher percentage of 3+ scores or merely the result of more test takers?  I&#39;m curious, but that&#39;s not what I wanted to talk about.  Looking at our AP results from this year we had: 
 For the past two years we&#39;ve been allowed to run 7 sections of AP Computer Science with about 30 kids per class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why don&#39;t we trust teachers or Rubber Room Light?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-24-grading-regents.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-24-grading-regents.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 It&#39;s Wednesday morning. I&#39;m sitting in an unairconditioned room. I really shouldn&#39;t be writing this since we were told &#34;NO ELECTRONIC DEVICES!!!&#34;  Where am I? Up at a school on East 96th street grading the geometry regents.  Back in the day schools gave exams then schools graded exams. Typically by committee. You&#39;d get a room full of math teachers, each teacher would take a problem or two and we&#39;d work through class envelopes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning takes time, hype doesn&#39;t</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/</guid>
      <description>or: what to watch out for in after school and summer programs  
CAVEATS:  In writing this post I do not mean to say that there aren&#39;t some great programs out there - there are. I also know that most of the programs I&#39;m aware are being developed by people who are really trying to do some good.  
  Since I wrote a post on my problem with drop in curricula on March 4 (http://cestlaz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s Expedient vs what&#39;s good - curriculum vs teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
  If we don&#39;t do anything then only schools like Stuy will have CS. 
  I heard that the other day. It was a comment relating to a number of efforts, both in and out of NY to get CS into the classroom.  These programs abound and up front let me say that they&#39;re all well meaning and have the best of intentions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Believing in what you&#39;re doing</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-25-good-idea-avc.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-25-good-idea-avc.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 The other day, Fred Wilson sent out a short tweet storm turned post on determining if an entrepreneur&#39;s startup idea is a good one. It&#39;s short. Take a minute to read it over.  At its core, the post and the comments talk about belief in an idea and it got me thinking about some things as an educator.  Tweet 7:   and you have to believe in yourself and your idea or nobody else ever will</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers, Rockstars, and the Godfather</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-12-14-rockstar-godfather.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-12-14-rockstar-godfather.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 In a recent post, Alfred Thompson referred to an earlier post where he mentioned rock star CS teachers. That&#39;s a term I&#39;ve heard thrown around a lot in the past few years. I&#39;ve heard some of my graduates referred to as rock stars - top tech people, and in fact I&#39;ve seen some of them courted for positions in a manner that a rock star might be accustomed to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on diversity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-12-07-thoughts-on-diversity.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-12-07-thoughts-on-diversity.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 Yesterday, my buddy Stan pointed me to this article: &#34;To address tech’s diversity woes, start with the vanishing Comp Sci classroom&#34;  It gives a reasonable overview of the gender issues in computer science education. The article talks about the drop in popularity of the old Advanced Placement AB course and its eventually being dropped as well as thoughts on how the current A course is pretty dry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VamVoom - Turning teachers into rubble</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-02-vamvoom.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-02-vamvoom.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
 Earlier today I saw a friend&#39;s Facebook post questioning the sanity of common core math. He had an issue with the way his daughter was being forced to work out problems. A few of us chimed in with our low op pinion on Common Core, others said they thought it was a good idea. I think the fact that my buddy was questioning it is a major strike against CC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teacher Ratings</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-02-mosl.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-02-mosl.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
  A while back I posted about the new teacher evaluation system in New York.  
  I originally wrote about the system here and a little more here.     Well, the results are in and I got my evaluation. What type of teacher am I? According to New York City I&#39;m &#34;Effective,&#34; which is basically run of the mill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>State test scores - don&#39;t fall into the trap</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-25-state-tests.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-25-state-tests.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} 
Test results are in:  The other week, the NY State third through eight grade high stakes test results were released. This was immediately followed by the usual spin an posturing. The reformers privatizers would claim things like &#34;These charter schools did better than those public schools&#34; while people like me would say &#34;Those charter schools have different populations&#34; and so on.     As you know, I&#39;ve never bought into the &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The new SAT - the more things stay the same</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-11-sat-the-same.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-11-sat-the-same.html/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} .large {font-size:200%} 
Plus ça change, plus c&#39;est la même chose 
 The more things change, the more they stay the same.  Last week we heard all about the new SAT. Going back to 1600 points, writing optional, and reworking the verbal section.  Immediate responses ranged from the usual fact that SAT doesn&#39;t correlate with college success to the idea that the motive was not to improve the test but rather to recapture market share from the ACT.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Show me the data</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-26-show-me-the-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-26-show-me-the-data/</guid>
      <description>Last time, I shared my thoughts on the recent coverage of AP CS statistics. Compiled and presented by Barbara Ericson and later reported on all over the place.
To summarize my point of view - yes there is a problem but some of the highlighted data points can easily be shown to be irrelevant and therefore can hurt the greater goal of access to great CS education for all.
This felt like the launching pad for a great class discussion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>At Last - CS Gender Equity in Multiple States!!!!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-11-badstats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-11-badstats/</guid>
      <description>Some buzz seems to have circulated on the data compiled by Barbara Ericson on AP Computer Science test takers in 2013. In addition to going to the source there was a piece in The Atlantic and in Education Week.
Some exciting results:
 In two states just as many girls passed the AP CS exam as guys!!!!! In two other states, just 6 more guys passed than girls!!!!! In yet another state, 100% of the girls passed, doing far better than the approximately 75% of the boys that passed!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Floating Points</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-30-huffpost-floatingpoints.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-30-huffpost-floatingpoints.html/</guid>
      <description>The other week I was invited by Brandon Diamond and Ilana Sufrin to participate in HuffPost Labs podcast - Floating Points.  I&#39;ve known Brandon for a while and he&#39;s a really awesome guy. He&#39;s a techie for sure but he also understands the importance of community building. Brandon and Ilana (also awesome but I haven&#39;t known her as long) are at HuffPost labs and also are working on important initiatives like Hacker Union.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m no longer an effective teacher - part 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-25-effective-teacher-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-25-effective-teacher-2/</guid>
      <description>Earlier I wrote about the new teacher evaluation system and why a teacher such as myself might now be considered ineffective and two ineffectives in a row can cost you your job.
Well, the New York City and New York State Departments of Education are the departments that just keep on giving. Here&amp;rsquo;s the latest.
This coming Wednesday, I won&amp;rsquo;t be teaching during my usual 8:00 to 10:15 block of three AP classes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The College Board Smorgasbord -Don&#39;t Overfill Your Plate</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-23-spectator-ap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-23-spectator-ap/</guid>
      <description>Each month, The Stuyvesant school paper - the Spectator invites a teacher to write a piece on, well, basically, whatever they want to. I did it this past month.
Here&amp;rsquo;s a reposting of the piece. The original can be found on the Spectator site.
Enjoy
&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve got 10 periods of class and no lunch.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve got four APs.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Can I also take Great Books, Multivariate, Physics C, and Software Development?&amp;rdquo; The goal of a Stuyvesant student: take as many electives and AP classes as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I might no longer be an effective teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-09-06-why_i_might_no_longer_be_an_effective_teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-09-06-why_i_might_no_longer_be_an_effective_teacher/</guid>
      <description>So here we are starting the new year and NY City is rolling out its new teacher evaluation system.
It was all over the news last year.
Ultimately, the state imposed the plan.
The city hailed the new plan as a way to fire under-performing teachers.
The UFT president hailed the plan as something that &amp;ldquo;is designed to help teachers improve their skills&amp;hellip;.&amp;rdquo;
My take? All three parties have thrown the students and teachers under the bus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That One Inspirational Curriculum</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-08-07-that_one_inspirational_curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-08-07-that_one_inspirational_curriculum/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few years, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a lot of people talk about curriculum.
&amp;ldquo;We need a curriculum that works for everyone.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;If we had a good curriculum, we could get CS in the schools.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t you just take someone else&amp;rsquo;s curriculum and scale things out?&amp;rdquo;
People miss the point. In my twenty some odd years as an educator and my forty five as a human (including 18 as a parent), I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard someone talk about that one inspirational curriculum that made all the difference in their lives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender stats</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-05-gender-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-05-gender-stats/</guid>
      <description>People keep asking me about how we&amp;rsquo;re doing with respect to gender balance and CS education at Stuy.
Rather than writing the same email again and again, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d summarize things here.
We&amp;rsquo;ve done rather well at Stuy. I might write more in depth at some point in the future but we don&amp;rsquo;t dumb anything down and we aren&amp;rsquo;t patronizing. I think much of the success can be attributed to:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Teachers - Evaluating schools</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-05-09-evaluating_teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-05-09-evaluating_teachers/</guid>
      <description>The Problem: The buzz word is &amp;ldquo;accountability.&amp;rdquo; Why are teachers special? Why don&amp;rsquo;t they feel they need to be evaluated like other professionals? Why do they feel they need a &amp;ldquo;job for life?&amp;rdquo;
Of course, the job for life line is nonsense &amp;ndash; teachers have tenure, but that&amp;rsquo;s just due process - not a guarantee of a job.
Friends in the private sector ask &amp;ldquo;if a teacher is doing a good job, why do they need tenure?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schools, Snake Oil, and the SOTU</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-14-schools-snake-oil-and-the-sotu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-14-schools-snake-oil-and-the-sotu/</guid>
      <description>Today I had the privilege of attending my second live State of the City address. Mayor Bloomberg didn&amp;rsquo;t spend as much time on education as he did at last year&amp;rsquo;s address but he did take a moment to give a shout out to charter schools. It gets old hearing the same false story about how charters are better than public schools. At least we have people like Gary Rubinstein and Diane Ravitch trying to set the record straight.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who&#39;s missing from the picture</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-12-whos-missing-from-the-picture.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-12-whos-missing-from-the-picture.html/</guid>
      <description>So, it&#39;s Computer Science Education Week. Full of rah rah events and everyone&#39;s gung ho about teaching computer science.
 You all know that CS Ed is what I&#39;ve dedicated most of my life to and maybe that&#39;s why I&#39;m &#34;not feeling it&#34; in terms of CS Ed Week. Let me explain.
 Yesterday there was a Twitter Conversation led by a &#34;national panel of thought leaders in the field.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>