<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CS Ed on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs-ed/</link>
    <description>Recent content in CS Ed on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 08:40:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs-ed/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Ed Podcast 3 -  Debugging</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-3-debugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 08:40:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-3-debugging/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt; Everyone knows that debugging is twice as hard as writing a program in the first place. So if you&amp;#39;re as clever as you can be when you write it, how will you ever debug it?  – Brian Kernighan &amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;  Debugging is what the third episode of the CS Ed Podcast was all about. Kristin Stephens-Martinez of Duke University speaks with Amy Ko of the University of Washington.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Ed Podcast 2 - Dan Garcia on test creation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 08:41:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-2/</guid>
      <description>Episode 2 of the CS Ed podcast had Dan Garcia talk about exam creation.  This wasn&amp;#39;t a podcast about the value of exams - in class, high stakes or otherwise. In fact Dan says in the podcast it would be great to &amp;#34;get grades out of the equation. Grades are gonna be an impediment to learning.&amp;#34; But recognizes that we have not say in this most of the time (and I&amp;#39;ll add that though I agree grades can and do perform a function) so we should be creative in terms of assessment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Riffing on the CS Ed Podcast - Episode 1 - David Malan</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 16:42:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-1/</guid>
      <description>I saw a couple of posts the other day about the CS Ed Podcast.  Kristin Stephens-Martinez of Duke interviewed (or will interview) six CS educators on a variety of topics. There are four posted so far:    David Malan    Dan Garcia    Amy Ko    Mark Guzdial    Before I started I thought I&amp;#39;d listen to a few and then share some thoughts but I found so much to unpack in the second episode where Dan talks about testing that I decided to share my thoughts on the first episode, then Dan&amp;#39;s and then see if find anything to comment on in episodes three and beyond.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>