<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cs Ed on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs-ed/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cs Ed on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 08:41:21 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs-ed/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Ed Podcast 2 - Dan Garcia on test creation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 08:41:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-2/</guid>
      <description>Episode 2 of the CS Ed podcast had Dan Garcia talk about exam creation.
This wasn&#39;t a podcast about the value of exams - in class, high stakes or otherwise. In fact Dan says in the podcast it would be great to &#34;get grades out of the equation. Grades are gonna be an impediment to learning.&#34; But recognizes that we have not say in this most of the time (and I&#39;ll add that though I agree grades can and do perform a function) so we should be creative in terms of assessment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Riffing on the CS Ed Podcast - Episode 1 - David Malan</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 16:42:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-podcast-1/</guid>
      <description>I saw a couple of posts the other day about the CS Ed Podcast.
Kristin Stephens-Martinez of Duke interviewed (or will interview) six CS educators on a variety of topics. There are four posted so far:
 David Malan Dan Garcia Amy Ko Mark Guzdial  Before I started I thought I&#39;d listen to a few and then share some thoughts but I found so much to unpack in the second episode where Dan talks about testing that I decided to share my thoughts on the first episode, then Dan&#39;s and then see if find anything to comment on in episodes three and beyond.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>