<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Git on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/git/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Git on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/git/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Pull Requests and Other People&#39;s Code</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/pull-requests/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/pull-requests/</guid>
      <description>One of the things I&#39;ve heard for years from former students - both those looking for jobs and those looking to hire is that colleges don&#39;t really do a good job preparing students for careers in tech. Sure they teach the algorithms and the theory but ther are a lot of missing pieces, particularly on the practical end. I&#39;m certainly not advocating turning CS programs into coding schools but there are many low cost opportunities to bring practical real world best practices in to the CS classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 42 - Git Gutter and Time Machine</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/using-emacs-42-git-gutter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/using-emacs-42-git-gutter/</guid>
      <description>One day I&#39;ll do a Magit video but since there are already some good ones out there I thought I&#39;d share a couple of other great git related packages.
The first is Git Gutter which adds markers on the side gutter of your buffer so you know what&#39;s changed since you&#39;re last commit. I pretty much use it exclusively for that visual but it can also be used to cmmit and revert individual chunks of your changes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Coding or Cheating</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</guid>
      <description>I haven&#39;t been teaching this past semester. That&#39;s why I haven&#39;t been writing much about lessons. I miss working with students but that will resume in the fall and this semester has allowed me to get a jump on new projects.
It&#39;s also allowed me to look at some student issues from a bit of a distance.
One issue that keeps coming up is cheating.
Some of it, classroom cheating. my friend Ria recently asked a question on Facebook about it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>