<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CS4All on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs4all/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (CS4All)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 19:35:57 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs4all/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>New York City has Certified CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/certified-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 19:35:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/certified-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m super proud to say that New York City now has state certified
Computer Science Teachers!!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/cs-cert.png&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a long road - really long if you consider I got started on
my CS Ed journey decades ago and there&amp;#39;s a long road ahead but we hit
a major milestone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started at Hunter a little over five years ago and creating teacher
certification programs was one of the goals. Back then, the state had
neither CS certification nor CS standards. The certification area was
created a year or so ago and the standards were just adopted this past
December. Hunter&amp;#39;s programs were approved December 2019 and we started
our first advanced certificate cohort last summer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Twenty one working teachers, all certified in another subject
area. They spent a big chunk of their summer with us all day every day
and continued on with classes and field work in the Fall. Many
finished last December while a few needed one more course which
they&amp;#39;re taking now. Earlier today on our Slack, teachers from that
cohort started sharing that they either received their state
certificates in the mail or that they looked themselves up on the
NYSED web site and confirmed that they were now certified to teach
computer science in the state of NY.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is big news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The entire cohort came in as strong teachers and they all grew
tremendously in terms of CS knowledge and their ability to teach
it. Now they represent the first of a growing group of certified CS
teachers - education leaders to provide a core of expertise in terms of
both CS content and how to teach it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m super proud of the cohort and super proud to be part of this. One
of the best parts for me have been meeting and working with these
great teachers and having this new learning network form - hopefully
we can keep it growing for years to come. Another is being able to get
the band back together - I was able to bring in my old partners in
crime JonAlf and Topher to teach and anyone who&amp;#39;s seen them teach know
that they&amp;#39;re the best. I couldn&amp;#39;t include our other co-conspirator,
Sam, because he was on sabbatical and couldn&amp;#39;t work but hopefully that
will change next time around. Not having a team at Hunter has been
really one of the few downsides so being able to work with my &amp;#34;go to
guys&amp;#34; again was a blast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also have our Masters program well underway so the pipeline of CS
teachers is starting to form. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is exciting news for New York City, Hunter and for me
personally. Long road ahead but as of today, a bunch of students in
NYC are being taught by state certified computer science teachers and
there will be more to come.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>