<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tools on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tools/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tools on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:29:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tools/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Java IDES for teaching teachers.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:29:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</guid>
      <description>Since Hunter uses C++ as it&#39;s core language, I haven&#39;t used Java much in the past three years. That&#39;s going to change pretty soon. Once we start offering our CS teacher Certificate and Masters programs I&#39;ll once again start teaching with Java as that&#39;s one of the langauges that we want to prepare our teachers with.
That means deciding on a set of tools and so I&#39;ve been spending time evaluating Java programming environments with an eye on the beginner since not only do the teachers I work with have to be comfortable with the tool but more importantly they will have to be able to support the tool for all of their students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I use Github Classroom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 16:42:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s been an amazingly unproductive weekend. Mostly because I&#39;ve been sick with the flu. It sucks but since the rest of the family&#39;s away anway at least I&#39;m not making everyone miserable.
I did manage to stage my next couple of classes and figured that writing this post wouldn&#39;t take too much energy since it&#39;s mostly a video.
Earlier, I talked about using GitHub and TravicCI and this time around I show how I use GitHub classroom to set up, disseminate, and collect assignments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Helps Me Help Students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-helps-me-help-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 18:55:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-helps-me-help-students/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today I was reminded why I love GitHub in support of my classes. One of my students posted a question about our current lab. They posted a synopsis of the problem along with the error message.
Since we&#39;re all working on GitHub the student&#39;s work was already up online Since I started using GitHub Classroom I was able to quickly navigate to the repo. This might have been enough but to really in to the students work I cloned the repo and went into Emacs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Github Classroom and Travis CI</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 09:44:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/github-classroom-travis/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been using GitHub with my classes since GitHub&#39;s early days. Over time I&#39;ve gotten my workflows down. I use a combination of shell scripts - many just written on the fly, GitHub organizations, and some naming conventions and protocols that have served me well.
A few years ago, the GitHub Education team started GitHub Classroom. I looked at it at the time. It was pretty cool but I had my workflow so I didn&#39;t adopt it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>