<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cseducation on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cseducation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cseducation on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2018 08:20:42 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cseducation/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CS For All The Time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs4allthetime/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2018 08:20:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs4allthetime/</guid>
      <description>A question that frequently comes up with respect to CS for All is what does it mean?
To me it means giving all students some fundamental exposure to computer science so that they can:
 Make use of those thinking skills, problem solving approaches, and practical tools regardless of their future paths. Provide a path for the subset of &#34;all&#34; that desire to further pursue computer science.  But even with this, how do you do it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TEALS Time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/</guid>
      <description>Everybody know&#39;s I&#39;m the Statler and Waldorf of the CS Education world.
https://media1.giphy.com/media/nPxVvyTWo1aIU/giphy.gif
I&#39;ve been known to be &#34;prickly,&#34; which is a nice way of putting it and I&#39;m openly critical of many programs out there.
One program, however, that I very much like is TEALS. They&#39;ve been around since 2009 founded by Kevin Wang, a former teacher. The basic idea was to have tech professionals go to a school on the way to work and team teach a CS class with one of the school&#39;s teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2017 - Recap</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/</guid>
      <description>As a high school teacher, I was never able to attend SIGCSE, the conference of the ACM&#39;s Special Interest Group on Computer Science Education. Between the number of instructional days I would lose and the cost, I could never justify going. Instead I looked over the proceedings and read many of the papers.
 Now that I&#39;m at Hunter, I was finally able to attend. This year in Seattle, the conference ran from Wednesday through Saturday.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2017</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow morning I fly out to Seattle for SIGCSE 2017. For those of you not in the CS Education space, SIGCSE is the ACM (Association for Computing Machinery) special interest group for computer science education.
I&#39;ve wanted to go for years but have never been able. It&#39;s hard for a high school teacher to miss a week in mid March, particularly in places with a school calendar similar to New York.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>