<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cseducation on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cseducation/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (cseducation)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cseducation/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>TEALS Time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Everybody know&amp;#39;s I&amp;#39;m the Statler and Waldorf of the CS Education
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://media1.giphy.com/media/nPxVvyTWo1aIU/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;https://media1.giphy.com/media/nPxVvyTWo1aIU/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;https://media1.giphy.com/media/nPxVvyTWo1aIU/giphy.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been known to be &amp;#34;prickly,&amp;#34; which is a nice way of putting it and
I&amp;#39;m openly critical of many programs out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One program, however, that I very much like is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;. They&amp;#39;ve been
around since 2009 founded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/KevinKWang&#34;&gt;Kevin Wang&lt;/a&gt;, a former teacher. The basic
idea was to have tech professionals go to a school on the way to work
and team teach a CS class with one of the school&amp;#39;s teachers. The tech
person would provide the CS expertise and the teacher would provide
the education chops. They&amp;#39;d both learn from each other and the
students from both of them. I didn&amp;#39;t know what to make out of it when I
first heard about them and in general, I am  pretty skeptical about drop in
programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After a couple of years, I started hearing from my former students. As
it turns out, a number of them had independently discovered TEALS and
become volunteers. They all talked about how rewarding the experience
was and how much the kids were getting that they wouldn&amp;#39;t have gotten
otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was sold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
TEALS has expanded considerably in the decade since they started. Now
they support multiple classes at multiple levels, have different
models from the original team teaching to a model where the volunteer
is more of a general tech / programming resource and the teacher is
more self sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most importantly, they provide quality training and materials to both
the teachers and the tech volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No drop in program can ever replace well prepared knowledgeable
teachers but in K12 CS very few of those teachers exist and it will
take us years to produce them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Until then, TEALS is one of the best programs to get CS education to
our kids and even when we do get there, their ability to connect
schools with volunteers and resources can&amp;#39;t be understated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re a tech professional and want to do some real good, volunteer
with TEALS - here&amp;#39;s a link to more information:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/volunteers/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/volunteers/&#34;&gt;https://www.tealsk12.org/volunteers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2017 - Recap</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;As a high school teacher, I was never able to attend SIGCSE, the
conference of the ACM&amp;#39;s Special Interest Group on Computer Science
Education. Between the number of instructional days I would lose and
the cost, I could never justify going. Instead I looked over the
proceedings and read many of the papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;m at Hunter, I was finally able to attend. This year in
Seattle, the conference ran from Wednesday through Saturday. I was
part of a panel on &amp;#34;Tools we can&amp;#39;t live without.&amp;#34; Over the next few
weeks, I hope to blog about a number of things I thought and talked
with people about over the conference including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The path I use to teach git and why GitHub a good teaching tool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(my talk).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The relationship of different CS Ed stakeholders - teachers,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;researchers, organizations, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching at the high school level vs college - perceptions and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The challenges of tech tool adoption in schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;#39;s going on in K12 CS Certification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe some other stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, some overall thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
The good
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As with many conferences, the &amp;#34;hallway track&amp;#34; along with receptions
sponsored by &lt;a href=&#34;https://csnyc.org/our-work/cs4all&#34;&gt;the CS4All consurtium&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tealsk12.org&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.org&#34;&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt; were terrific. I
was able to finally meet in person many people who I&amp;#39;ve only known
virtually and got to know many more as well. I left the conference
with a much larger address book and a long list of follow up
items. Being in Seattle, I also enjoyed being able to spend time with
people from &lt;a href=&#34;http://tealsk12.org&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.org&#34;&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt;, two of the CS Ed groups working hard
to do some real good (yes - I do like and support these guys even
though I call them out on things I disagree with, but that&amp;#39;s the
subject of another post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I attended sessions on CS certification, teacher preparation,
assessments, POGIL based instruction to name a few. They ranged from
valuable to interesting and to be honest, a couple of &amp;#34;what were they
thinking&amp;#34; but the overall experience was very much worth the trip. I
also got to speak to a number of wonderful students at the
poster sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The keynotes are also well worth a read (sorry if you don&amp;#39;t have ACM
digital library access). &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025045&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692&#34;&gt;Jeannette Wing&lt;/a&gt; talked about the importance of
probability and statistics in CS Ed, and aspects of  &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025047&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692&#34;&gt;Gail Chapman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s talk
&amp;#34;Inspire, Innovate, and Improve…&amp;#34; keynote and &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025046&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692&#34;&gt;Mitch Resnick&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s
&amp;#34;Fulfilling Papert&amp;#39;s Dream&amp;#34; both spoke to the educator inside me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
The bad
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest downside to me was that I found very little value added in
a number of the paper sessions over just reading the papers. Part of
this is probably because of my own over-inflated expectations given the
number of years I&amp;#39;ve waited to attend. Part of it though, was the fact
that sessions were so tightly packed that I didn&amp;#39;t have time to follow
up with presenters before having to run to the next
thing. Unfortunately, in some
cases, it was because the presenter merely
&amp;#34;read&amp;#34; the paper much as a professor sometimes just reads the slides
or the book to his class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Other thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One paper presentation I very much liked was &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3017701&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692&#34;&gt;Exam Wrappers: Not a
Silver Bullet&lt;/a&gt; presented by &lt;a href=&#34;https://michellecraig.github.io/&#34;&gt;Michelle Craig&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~bdstephe/&#34;&gt;Ben Stephenson&lt;/a&gt;. I
actually came in late since I was hustling over from the Code.org
lunch. The result was that I didn&amp;#39;t actually know what &amp;#34;Exam Wrappers&amp;#34;
were until well after the talk when I ran into &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jkhuggins&#34;&gt;Jim Huggins&lt;/a&gt;. Exam
wrappers, in short, are merely when you require the students fill out something
for some credit when picking up their exams. The funny thing is that
it&amp;#39;s a strategy that high school teachers have used for years without
a special name and we already knew the good and bad of it without the
research but that&amp;#39;s not what I want to get at here. What I loved about
the talk, besides the fact that Ben and Michelle are clearly strong
presenters is that this was a negative result that was being
presented. I also loved the fact that they didn&amp;#39;t present their
research as gospel but rather pointed out the strengths and weaknesses
of their approach - they made a case to what and why we should pay
attention to and what should be taken with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was a major breath of fresh air after being exposed to so much
education &amp;#39;research&amp;#39; over the course of my life that the author or
presenter felt was just as strong as a mathematical proof rather than
an indication based on a specific experience or small set of
experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also felt a little weird at times during the week when west coast people seemed
to know me. I know I&amp;#39;m a loud mouthed curmudgeon and I go on my
periodic ed rants but given the dearth of comments on this blog I was
really surprised to get as many as &amp;#34;great to meet you in person after
reading your blog&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;we know you and your work&amp;#34; all week. It was
weird and somewhat humbling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, another highlight f`or me was that I got to catch up with
some of family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-seattle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/sigcse-seattle.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/sigcse-seattle.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already planning to submit something to present at SIGCSE 2018 in Baltimore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2017</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow morning I fly out to Seattle for SIGCSE 2017. For those of
you not in the CS Education space, SIGCSE is the ACM (Association for
Computing Machinery) special interest group for computer science education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve wanted to go for years but have never been able. It&amp;#39;s hard for a
high school teacher to miss a week in mid March, particularly in
places with a school calendar similar to New York. NY city schools are
already closed for a week in February and then Spring Break is right
around the corner. If you&amp;#39;re teaching an AP course with the exam in
early May, losing a week in March is really not an option. Even if you
can take the time, you&amp;#39;ll probably have to foot the bill out of
pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;m at Hunter, I&amp;#39;ve got more flexibility in terms of schedule
and attending is probably even more important given my current roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m looking forward to the talks and events but probably even more
looking forward to seeing old friends, meeting new ones and seeing
face to face friends that til now I&amp;#39;ve only known through the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On Saturday I&amp;#39;ll be part of a panel (thanks &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cscheerleader&#34;&gt;Ria&lt;/a&gt;) titled &amp;#34;Tools we
can&amp;#39;t live without.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ll probably talk about the way I use git and
GitHub and how I get my students up to speed but there are lots of
tools I can talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I plan to write up a series of posts on how I use GitHub (and how it
evolved from other versioning systems) as well as thoughts about other
tools I&amp;#39;ve used and some I&amp;#39;ve struggled with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re going to be at SIGCSE drop me a line, I&amp;#39;d love to connect.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>