<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Csforall on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/csforall/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Csforall on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 16:54:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/csforall/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What CS should we teach in HS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 16:54:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-cs-in-hs/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to chime in on Alfred Thompson&#39;s post last week on what to include in a HS CS class but was working on moving blogging platforms so didn&#39;t get a chance so I&#39;ll say a few words here.
If you&#39;ve been here before you probably know I&#39;m not a fan of the standards and I certainly am no fan of the College Board and the AP program so what&#39;s my take?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Cs for All Worth Doing</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-cs4all-worth-doing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-cs4all-worth-doing/</guid>
      <description>Last time I mentioned the pushback on CS for All. While many people are all in for CS for All, resistance is coming from many areas. There&#39;s resistance from teachers of other subject areas, people who think it&#39;s merely job training for the tech industry (which it can be if done poorly), people who feel it will be implemented at the expense of other important subjects already on the chopping block like music and art, and others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should CS for All be implemented at the college level?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s been a lively discussion on pushback to CS for All at the K12 level over on Facebook. Mark Guzdial started a sub thread asking if CS for All should first be implemented at the undergrad level rather than K12.
It&#39;s an interesting question and as good as anything to get me out of my month long non-blogging rut.
Mark was right when he said that if Colleges implement CS for All, K12 will likely do so to follow - just look at AP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is there room for CS for All</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</guid>
      <description>A fear revolving around CS For All concerns where will the money come from and how will we fit in the new classes.
One suggested solution is to integrate CS into other subjects. I thought I&#39;d write today about why I don&#39;t think the fear is valid and while integrating CS into other classes can have value, it probably isn&#39;t a long term solution for CS education.
Let&#39;s start with the integration solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unfunded Mandates and CS For All</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</guid>
      <description>This morning, Mark Guzdial wrote about unfunded mandates and CS for All. Unfunded mandates frequently wreak havoc on schools in a number of ways but in the long run, I don&#39;t think it should have a severe effect on CS for All. Rather, it could have a big impact on the number of CS courses we offer beyond that.
Mark relay&#39;s a story from the Cambridge Rindge and Latin School where at the time many students wanted more CS classes but the school wasn&#39;t planning on hiring a new CS teacher.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>