<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cstuy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cstuy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cstuy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cstuy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>NYC DOE - Doing what it can to keep opportunities away from kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cstuy-coi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cstuy-coi/</guid>
      <description>The difficulties I&#39;ve had with the city and DOE are pretty well documented by now.
Today I&#39;m going to tell you about my latest dealings with DOE and how they prevented my team from bringing free quality CS education to city students.
CSTUY&#39;s not running SHIP, its summer program this year.
That&#39;s not something I&#39;m happy about but part of me knew it might happen. What did surprise me, although it shouldn&#39;t have, was the role that the NYC DOE played in preventing it from happening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing def hacks(&#34;Winter&#34;,2015)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-09-def-hacks-winter-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-09-def-hacks-winter-2015/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Last March, we (CSTUY) hosted our first hackathon - def hacks():  It was a tremendous success. Fifty students of all experience levels, a bunch of great mentors and judges - added all together and it was a terrific day.  I wrote about it here.  We&#39;re doing it again. We love last years hosts SumAll and are grateful that they continue to host our Saturday Hacking Sessions but we are also grateful to Facebook NY for allowing us to use their larger space for this edition of def hacks().</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions - iterating until it&#39;s right</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-26-hacking-sessions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-26-hacking-sessions/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}     Today we kicked off Hacking Sessions 2015. Saturday morning with sixty kids in a room brainstorming ideas. Soon they&#39;ll settle on teams and projects and we&#39;ll be off for a semester of exploring CS and tech.  The next couple of weeks will be a little chaotic with groups shifting, mentors figuring out which groups to work with and us, the instructors launching each team on its way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Help us create a Saturday Hacking Space for kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-12-kickstarter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-12-kickstarter/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    As many of you know, I&#39;m part of the team behind CSTUY, a non-profit dedicated to bringing the best CS education to kids who wouldn&#39;t otherwise have the opportunity.  Over the past two summers we&#39;ve hosted our highly succesful immersion program SHIP. We were also able to run a small Saturday program thanks to the generosity of SumAll who provided space, and other members of the StuyCS family who provided laptops and the funds we needed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What makes a great manager? - Open praise for my team</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-07-30-ship-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-07-30-ship-teachers/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Today was the last day of SHIP 2015, CSTUY&#39;s summer immersion program. I was blown away by the projects. The shipmates and the stewards all did tremendous work.  All through the reception parents would come up to me and rave about the job I did with the program. They&#39;d thank me, tell me how exited their child was every day, how proud they were of what they were learning and on and on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>def hack(2015)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-29-defhacks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-29-defhacks/</guid>
      <description>.center {text-align:center;} div.center {text-align:center;}     This past Saturday, 50 high school students, 10 high school mentors, and 10 more post high school mentors headed down to SumAll to participate in def hacks(2015): CSTUY&#39;s first hackathon.  The fifty participants, came from all over the city, Long Island, and New Jersey. They ranged from having never programmed to three or four years experience.  Projects ranged from web sites to full stack applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a High School Summer CS Program - SHIP</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-05-ship-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-05-ship-index/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    I wanted to do a couple more posts on the CSTUY summer program SHIP, particularly about getting funding and reflections but I think I&#39;ll just wrap things up with the school year starting.  Overall it was an amazing success and I&#39;m amazingly proud of the entire team (in no particular order):  Devorah, JonAlf, Sam, Yulia, Topher, Ethan, Leslie, Brian, Andreas, Natan, Miranda, Nadia, Fawn, Lise, Jessica, Angela, Benedict, Elise, Fish, and Derek.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - The Crew</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-16-ship-crew/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-16-ship-crew/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    The Crew       One of the most important, possibly the most important part of SHIP&#39;s success was the crew and that&#39;s what sets us apart.  I&#39;ve seen CS Ed organizations run by business people, lawyers, investors and more.The people developing curriculum are EdTech people, entrepreneurs and anything but seasoned educators. I&#39;ve seen programs developed, curriculum created and then the search for teachers commence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - Our partner - St. Joseph&#39;s College</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-08-ship-partners/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-08-ship-partners/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    From the day we filed the paperwork to create CSTUY, we knew we wanted to run a summer program. In fact, we started looking for a space during the 2012/2013 school year. We were hoping to run SHIP for the first time in the summer of 2013 but we all knew it wasn&#39;t really a realistic goal.     Our original plans required at least one classroom sized space, and up to three for full days for a month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - Outcomes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-05-ship-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-05-ship-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    SHIP ended last week. So, how did we do? Time to look at outcomes.  Outcomes can be tricky. There are lots of programs out there and they all claim amazing results. Unfortunately, it seems to me, that everyone&#39;s so concerned with good PR that, well, you know, lies, damned lies, statistics.     First you&#39;ve got claims like &#34;learn how to make a mobile app in under n weeks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can&#39;t wait for CSTUY SHIP Demo day tomorrow</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-30-ship-demo-day-tomorrow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-30-ship-demo-day-tomorrow/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Miranda and Nadia showing off their project    Tomorrow is the last day of SHIP and we&#39;ll be capping the whole thing off with a day of demos, science fair style.  Both the shipmates and the stewards will be showing off their work and I can&#39;t wait. I&#39;ve intentionally stayed away from the shipmates because I want to be surprised but I&#39;ve seen what the stewards have been doing and I can&#39;t tell you how proud I am of their work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - Toolset</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-28-ship-toolset/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-28-ship-toolset/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    We&#39;re almost at the end of CSTUY SHIP&#39;s first journey. The Shipmates and stewards will be showing off their work in another day or so and I&#39;m excited to see their finished projects.  But what toolset are they using.     With knew we would be working with two rooms of relative beginners. We needed something that allowed us to develop the shipmates CS skills while also having a low cost of entry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - Outreach</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-20-ship-outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-20-ship-outreach/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    We&#39;ve got a few more topics to cover in the Building a SHIP series. We still have to cover: The Crew  Curricular Choices  The long term plan  Site and funding       But for today, we&#39;ll talk outreach.     Outreach proved to be particular challenge for SHIP. Our entire crew is made up of teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - Guest Stars</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-17-ship-guests/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-17-ship-guests/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Cynthia Koo talking about UX    Much like the Love Boat had every week, at CSTUY SHIP, we too have our guest stars.  On the one hand, it&#39;s important to have a focused program that leaves the shipmates empowered to continue their CS studies on their own. That means the shipmates have to explore something with sufficient depth so that the learning sticks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a SHIP - the Stewards</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-10-ship-tas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-10-ship-tas/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;} div.left {text-align:left; padding:20px;} div.right {text-align:right;padding:20px;}   The Stewards: In size order.  And from the other side  Ok, seriously - here they are.    I thought I&#39;d share some thoughts on how we designed SHIP. I&#39;ll try to talk about curriculum choices, tools and more in the coming week but first, let&#39;s talk about our stewards.     When we first designed SHIP, we knew we wanted to run two rooms each with around 24 shipmates and two teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing to launch SHIP</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-03-launching-ship/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-03-launching-ship/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Some of our Ship Stewards (TAs) planning day one.     What&#39;s been happening since the close of the school year? We&#39;ve been getting ready to start SHIP - CSTUY&#39;s first summer program.  SHIP will be running starting this Monday through the end of July and should be a great adventure. Fast facts: We have 47 students and 14 student teaching assistants (stewards)  We have 4 amazing teachers, 1 mentor for the TAs, me, and one official program mom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing SHIP</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-04-07-ship-announce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-04-07-ship-announce/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   It&#39;s been a while since my last post.  That&#39;s mostly since I&#39;ve getting things ready for this announcement.  I&#39;ve talked about our non-profit CSTUY before. Well, we&#39;ve been hard at work getting things together for our first summer program: SHIP - Summer Hackers Immersion Program  We&#39;re really excited about this - taking our years of experience teaching kids at our schools and taking it to a wider audience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summing up at SumAll</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-01-sumall/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-01-sumall/</guid>
      <description>Our hackers have been coming down to SumAll every Saturday for a while now. It&amp;rsquo;s a great space and we&amp;rsquo;ve been given run of the office. That said, the hackers really had no idea what SumAll is all about.
Today, we had our first guest speaker. Davin Chew, founder and CTO of SumAll. Davin&amp;rsquo;s also a member of the StuyCS family, he was my student back in the nineties. When Davin heard we needed space for our Saturday program, he and the SumAll team graciously offered to host.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions Resume</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7/</guid>
      <description>Back to school last Thursday after almost two week off. Twenty four hours later - Snow Day. I know this sounds a bit hokey, but I really would have rather had school. I love a good snow day as much as the next guy, but after a big vacation, I was really ready to get back to work with the kids.
Saturday, hacking sessions were set to resume. Being in Manhattan, getting around was pretty easy but we&amp;rsquo;ve got hackers from all over the city from Staten Island to the Bronx.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions - putting it all together</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5/</guid>
      <description>Week 5.
Last week, I lamented over the difficulties with only meeting once a week. We went over a log of new material last week and I was happy when today rolled around and the hackers would be able to start putting things together.
When writing a web app, you&amp;rsquo;ve got to know about all sorts of things - for us it&amp;rsquo;s HTML, CSS, Python, and the microframework, flask.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions Week 4 - The challenges of once a week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4/</guid>
      <description>We just finished week 4 of CSTUY&amp;rsquo;s Hacking Sessions.
I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with how our hackers are doing - they&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch and even if they don&amp;rsquo;t realize it yet, are making great progress.
Meanwhile, as an instructor and program designer I&amp;rsquo;m noticing the differences between a once a week program and having a class every day (note - I&amp;rsquo;m not the sole designer or instructor. I have a great team - JonAlf, Sam, and Topher are three of the best teachers I&amp;rsquo;ve had the privilege of working with - this post, however, is based on my observations).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions - Week 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2/</guid>
      <description>Saturday was the second day of CSTUY&amp;rsquo;s Hacking Sessions. We started out wit a minor panic - none of the laptops could connect to the wireless!!! After a brief scramble, we finally gave up and gave our host a call (sorry Davin) and the problem was swiftly addressed. From there it was off to the races.
Last week we spent most of the session with mixers and setting up the laptops.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions Begin</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-20-hacking-sessions-begin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-20-hacking-sessions-begin/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday was my 46th birthday. How did I spend it? Well, 20 &amp;ldquo;Hackers&amp;rdquo; from 9 schools, 4 student TAs and a few of us teachers gathered at SumAll to kick off CSTUY&amp;rsquo;s first weekly program - Hacking Sessions (sometimes called Hackers Sessions).
  It was the first week so it was mostly mixers, setting up machines (installing Linux on 24 laptops takes time) and going over how we&amp;rsquo;ll be communicating but I&amp;rsquo;m really excited about the weeks to come.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>