<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cstuy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cstuy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cstuy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cstuy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>NYC DOE - Doing what it can to keep opportunities away from kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/cstuy-coi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/cstuy-coi/</guid>
      <description>The difficulties I&#39;ve had with the city and DOE are pretty well documented by now.
Today I&#39;m going to tell you about my latest dealings with DOE and how they prevented my team from bringing free quality CS education to city students.
CSTUY&#39;s not running SHIP, its summer program this year.
That&#39;s not something I&#39;m happy about but part of me knew it might happen. What did surprise me, although it shouldn&#39;t have, was the role that the NYC DOE played in preventing it from happening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summing up at SumAll</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-02-01-sumall/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-02-01-sumall/</guid>
      <description>Our hackers have been coming down to SumAll every Saturday for a while now. It&amp;rsquo;s a great space and we&amp;rsquo;ve been given run of the office. That said, the hackers really had no idea what SumAll is all about.
Today, we had our first guest speaker. Davin Chew, founder and CTO of SumAll. Davin&amp;rsquo;s also a member of the StuyCS family, he was my student back in the nineties. When Davin heard we needed space for our Saturday program, he and the SumAll team graciously offered to host.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions Resume</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7/</guid>
      <description>Back to school last Thursday after almost two week off. Twenty four hours later - Snow Day. I know this sounds a bit hokey, but I really would have rather had school. I love a good snow day as much as the next guy, but after a big vacation, I was really ready to get back to work with the kids.
Saturday, hacking sessions were set to resume. Being in Manhattan, getting around was pretty easy but we&amp;rsquo;ve got hackers from all over the city from Staten Island to the Bronx.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions - putting it all together</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5/</guid>
      <description>Week 5.
Last week, I lamented over the difficulties with only meeting once a week. We went over a log of new material last week and I was happy when today rolled around and the hackers would be able to start putting things together.
When writing a web app, you&amp;rsquo;ve got to know about all sorts of things - for us it&amp;rsquo;s HTML, CSS, Python, and the microframework, flask.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions Week 4 - The challenges of once a week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4/</guid>
      <description>We just finished week 4 of CSTUY&amp;rsquo;s Hacking Sessions.
I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with how our hackers are doing - they&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch and even if they don&amp;rsquo;t realize it yet, are making great progress.
Meanwhile, as an instructor and program designer I&amp;rsquo;m noticing the differences between a once a week program and having a class every day (note - I&amp;rsquo;m not the sole designer or instructor. I have a great team - JonAlf, Sam, and Topher are three of the best teachers I&amp;rsquo;ve had the privilege of working with - this post, however, is based on my observations).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions - Week 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2/</guid>
      <description>Saturday was the second day of CSTUY&amp;rsquo;s Hacking Sessions. We started out wit a minor panic - none of the laptops could connect to the wireless!!! After a brief scramble, we finally gave up and gave our host a call (sorry Davin) and the problem was swiftly addressed. From there it was off to the races.
Last week we spent most of the session with mixers and setting up the laptops.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Sessions Begin</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-10-20-hacking-sessions-begin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-10-20-hacking-sessions-begin/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday was my 46th birthday. How did I spend it? Well, 20 &amp;ldquo;Hackers&amp;rdquo; from 9 schools, 4 student TAs and a few of us teachers gathered at SumAll to kick off CSTUY&amp;rsquo;s first weekly program - Hacking Sessions (sometimes called Hackers Sessions).
  It was the first week so it was mostly mixers, setting up machines (installing Linux on 24 laptops takes time) and going over how we&amp;rsquo;ll be communicating but I&amp;rsquo;m really excited about the weeks to come.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>