<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Apcs A on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/apcs-a/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Apcs A on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 21:47:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/apcs-a/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Classes Or After school programs - which is more important for female retention in CS?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/classes-or-afterschool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 21:47:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/classes-or-afterschool/</guid>
      <description>This morning Mark Guzdial tweeted on his latest post:
Results from Longitudinal Study of Female Persistence in CS: AP CS matters, After-school programs and Internships do not https://t.co/GOzp3045Hp
&amp;mdash; Mark Guzdial (@guzdial) October 14, 2019 
I&#39;m glad Mark wrote about this as it&#39;s something that&#39;s important to both research and publicize but it&#39;s really not a surprise.
I&#39;m going to start by dismissing the statement that &#34;... participation in the Aspirations awards program were teh best predictors of persistence three years after the high school survey in both CS and other technology-related majors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 09:40:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>Two of the hardest topics to make meaningful to students in APCS-A are inheritance and interfaces. It&#39;s not that they&#39;re super difficult topics but rather that they&#39;re not often needed, useful, or superior to not using them on beginner assignments. More often than not the motivation is a bit forced as are the assignments.
Inheritance is its own can of worms and to be honest, something I&#39;ve not found to be all that useful or necessary.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>