<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misc on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (misc)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 19:40:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Retiring part 3 - What&#39;s Next</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 19:40:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Links to the three posts in this series:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re seeing this before the previous two posts, I&amp;#39;d encourage you
to read post 1 and 2 first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;What was accomplished at Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said at the start of these three posts, I do want to stay in the
game. Maybe take a break and definately slow down but I still think
I&amp;#39;ve got something to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m writing this so that you can have it in the back of your mind in
case a great match appears either soon or somewhere down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I posses a somewhat unique set of skills and experiences. A
thirty year teacher with a strong CS/Tech background, I&amp;#39;ve taken students
from blank slate to industry, created entire programs, and worked with
educators from early grades through college level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve also worked as a software engineer and have remained in touch and
connected with the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What might be appealing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Probably not full time and since I&amp;#39;ll be collecting my pension it&amp;#39;ll
be about fit much more than money. Still, I&amp;#39;d never say never on the
right opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d love the opportunity to travel more - even if just in the
region. I think that&amp;#39;s my biggest regret is that Devorah and I really
never had the opportunity or took the time to see the country or
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe if a company wants someone as a rep at conferences like all
those Ed Conference sponsors or who knows what else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d also be open to longer gigs elsewhere - a month, a semester, or
even a year on an interesting project where we can get to know a new
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know the big tech companies work with colleges to try to help them
do what I did with Daedalus at Hunter. Given that none of them have
people with the range of educational experiences and successes I
have, they could do far worse than engaging me to help with these
programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe some colleges, universities, or governments have a side project
and they could use someone like me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, I don&amp;#39;t know but figured this was a good way to get the
word out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, thanks for reading and keeping me in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, back to our regular blogging program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Links to the three posts in this series:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;What was accomplished at Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retiring part 2 - Accomplishments</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 15:35:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Links to the posts in this series
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re reading this before the previous post, I&amp;#39;d recommend going
back and reading that one first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;What I think I&amp;#39;ll be looking for next&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ve carved out a somewhat unique career. Never set out to be
a teacher and a couple of different turns here or there and things
could have been very different. When I started teaching, I thought I&amp;#39;d
probably, if anything  become a math chair and that was actually the
plan at Stuy until Richie Rothenberg, the math chair at the time
unexpectedly passed away in the late nineties. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Pre Hunter recap
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just a quick recap. I started my career as a Programmer Analyst at
Goldman Sachs back in the day. I&amp;#39;d say Software Engineer but that
title didn&amp;#39;t exist back then. From there I went into teaching for two
decades, mostly at Stuyvesant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Stuyvesant I built the CS program, created classes, trained teachers and
shepherded hundreds, perhaps thousands of students towards tech
careers. My continued relationships with these former students left me
in a unique position as someone with strong CS chops, strong teaching
and education chops along with professional programming experience and strong ties
to the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During this time, I played my part in getting the
ball rolling for K12 CS Ed. Certainly at Stuy but I&amp;#39;d like to think
beyond it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
The Hunter chapter
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Almost seven years ago, I came over to Hunter to work on two major
projects. One was to develop and run an undergraduate honors computer
science program at the college and the other as to create and run
computer science teacher certification programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Undergraduate CS Honors
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Prior to my joining Hunter, they already had a long established CS
department and program. It was (and is) both as good as any other
program out there and as bad. There were though, a few particular
issues. First, Hunter&amp;#39;s program was either unknown to high school
students or had a poor reputation due to the misconception that a
liberal arts school can&amp;#39;t do good CS and, at the tech company end,
Hunter was a total unknown. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter&amp;#39;s program was a typical college CS program in that it did a
great job preparing strong applicants for grad school but did nothing
to prepare them for tech careers and there was no connection with the
NY Tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started, top tech companies never recruited at Hunter and most
Hunter students never even applied for internships prior to
graduating - they didn&amp;#39;t know they were supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the past 7 years there have been tremendous changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My first cohort had 8 students. My latest has 64. My honors program and Hunter CS in general is
now a known CS destination in many NY high schools. Applications have
grown from around 50 to many hundreds and each year I field more and
more calls of students trying to decide between my program and other
top CS programs - I win some, I lose some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the exit side, my Daedalus students regularly end up at top tech
companies and the overall profile of Hunter CS is much greater and
more positive in the tech world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve created new classes that integrate software engineering practices
with traditional CS and built many unique partnerships and programs over
the past 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My trouble is that the Daedalus program is in full swing. It has to be
maintained but the job is basically done. At the same time, I don&amp;#39;t
have the ability to get the reforms I&amp;#39;ve brought to my program to the
greater Hunter CS population. Sure, I&amp;#39;ve gotten some initiatives
started that are available to all Hunter students but a lot of the
core stuff that I&amp;#39;ve worked into my courses are only available to the
Daedalus students and I don&amp;#39;t have a way of changing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I think I&amp;#39;ve done what I can do. The original goal was to create
this honors program and I think we&amp;#39;ve gone well beyond. Hunter, and
Daedalus in particular, has a higher profile with high schools and
employers and Daedalus students get the best of CS, the practical
software engineering skills they&amp;#39;ll need and unique partnerships with
the tech community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Teacher Certification
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My other major hat was on the K12 CS teacher side. First we had to
lobby the state to create the certification. I visited Albany a number
of times and spoke to my share of Regents but the real heavy lifting
went to Hunter&amp;#39;s President and the Dean of the Ed school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile, I created our masters and certificate programs while
doing my part in the whole K12 CS effort. I created new classes and
worked with some of my old teaching pals from Stuy to get ready to run
the program once the state approved everything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Three years ago everything got really rolling. Hunter had the first active
certificate and masters programs in the state. Thanks to the generous
support of Gotham Gives, we were able to start a cohort of 21 working
teachers towards CS certification. They were joined by 2 masters
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A year later, New York State had its first certified CS teachers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following year, again with support from Gotham Gives, this time
joined by Google, we started another 24 working teachers along with 5
more masters students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now in our third cohort we&amp;#39;ve got another 56 working through the
programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By the time our third year ends, we&amp;#39;ll have around 100 certified CS
teachers in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m equally proud of the fact that we&amp;#39;ve got five teachers from the
Fingerlakes region in our program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been pretty vocal over the years as to what I think a good CS
teacher looks like and I&amp;#39;m super proud that our brand of CS teaching
can now be found across the city and in fact across the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you
think about the number of students these teachers reach each year,
that&amp;#39;s pretty amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m equally proud of the fact that these cohorts are still in touch
and forming a new community of CS teachers in the city and state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that we&amp;#39;re rolling, what&amp;#39;s next? The program needs to continue to
run but I don&amp;#39;t see major changes. There are more things to get done
at Hunter and in the state. Things like getting the state to separate
HS from early grades in terms of certification and integrating some CS
teacher prep in our elementary school programs but, right now, I don&amp;#39;t
see a path for the former and don&amp;#39;t have the energy for the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Other hats
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve also done a number of other one offs or side projects while at
Hunter. Some of them have been:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was on the executive committe and a lead author in creating the
NY State K12 CS standards. Something I find ironic since I&amp;#39;m not a
fan of &amp;#34;state standards.&amp;#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mentioned earlier that I was a big part of Hunter winning and
administering the CUNY2X grant. Got to work with some great people
and that whole grant was huge in helping move the needle on Hunter
CS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was also fortunate enough to work on a project funded by the
Robin Hood foundation on CS in the primary grades. It also allowed
me to work with some great people while dipping my toes in CS Ed
research and early grade work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prior to Covid we were also well on our way in developing a nice
little K12 CS teacher community hosting monthxly meetups at tech
companies like Google and Digital Ocean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there it is, the major initiatives I&amp;#39;ve been working on at Hunter
and what I think I&amp;#39;ve accomplished. I&amp;#39;m proud of the work and in all
cases I think we went farther than we originally set out for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s next? I&amp;#39;m not entirely sure. I&amp;#39;ll share some thoughts in my
next post. I hope all my friends read it and keep an ear open if the
right opportunity presents itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Links to the posts in this series
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;What I think I&amp;#39;ll be looking for next&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>After 7 years at Hunter College and 33 in NYC public schools, time for a change.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 06:43:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been dropping mentions of this here and there for a while now but
I think it&amp;#39;s time to come out more formally -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m planning on retiring from Hunter at the end of this Spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This doesn&amp;#39;t mean getting out of the CS or CS Ed game entirely - I
could stay on in a part time capacity and, after some decompression I
think I still have things to offer but the plan is retire, collect my
pension, and then see where I can continue to be contribute to the
Ed/CS Ed scene. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why now? Largely burnout but there are a number of reasons. I&amp;#39;ll talk
about them below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also posting this with two other posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One talking about what I feel I&amp;#39;ve accomplished here at Hunter (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another talking about the types of opportunities I think I&amp;#39;ll be
looking for next (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d love it if people could read those - particularly the last one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the rest of this post, why it&amp;#39;s time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said, burnout is at the top of the list. What from? Largely from
having too much on my plate. When I started at Hunter, neither of my
programs existed. We started undergraduate CS honors (the Daedalus
program) the following fall and that grew at a consistent pace until
it was a full time job. The CS Ed program took longer to get running
since we needed to get the state to create the license and get our
programs through governance but once they started, that was another
full time job. Add to that the assorted other responsibilities that
ended up on my plate and I&amp;#39;ve been doing two to three full time jobs
for the past three or so years - not sustainable. For the burnout,
Covid and the state of the world certainly hasn&amp;#39;t helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What does burnout mean? Well, I&amp;#39;m not enjoying my classes. Sure, there
are fun times but I don&amp;#39;t get up in the morning looking forward to it
and in class, I&amp;#39;m as likely to get annoyed by something as not. Part
of this is that I have students who refuse to mask - something I see
as a direct sign of disrespect but there&amp;#39;s more. All in all, this is a
good sign that it&amp;#39;s time to get out or at least take a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another factor, and a big one is that I&amp;#39;ve accomplished everything
I&amp;#39;ve set out to accomplish at Hunter and then some. I&amp;#39;m normally not a
&amp;#34;goal guy,&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m more about process and journey but in the case of
Hunter, I also had a set of goals and I&amp;#39;ve gotten there and
beyond. There are new challenges at Hunter but not challenges that I&amp;#39;m
as excited about. More on this in my accomplishment post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I&amp;#39;ve got health and family reasons. Health isn&amp;#39;t anything
immediate but I do have indications of heart disease. Combine that
with the fact that my mom died when she was 72 and my dad at 44 and
well, now that I&amp;#39;m 55, if we can financially handle it, maybe it&amp;#39;s
time to give more time to myself and my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, Devorah&amp;#39;s also retiring - she put in the paperwork the other day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For those of you who read this blog, I&amp;#39;d love for you to keep your
ears open for potential next steps so I&amp;#39;d love for you to read my next
post on what I think I&amp;#39;ve accomplished at Hunter and what I bring to
the table and the one after that where I&amp;#39;ll muse about what I think I
might be able to get excited about and where I think I might be able
to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Links to this post  and the other two posts:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;Recap of what was accomplished at Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;What I think I&amp;#39;ll be looking for next&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crafting a new major for tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-major/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 09:42:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-major/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Hunter College, like most colleges and universities is facing
unprecedented demand for CS. It&amp;#39;s the hot major. Being a public
college, we have an obligation to provide the best education possible
to as many students as we can in our locality. This means we can&amp;#39;t
just put a GPA requirement or other cap on the major and we can&amp;#39;t do
things I&amp;#39;ve heard &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; schools do like essentially making
applicants apply to the major direct from HS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This had led to the usual problems - more large lectures, fewer
electives offered, challenges for space etc.. This is nothing unique
to Hunter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another problem, though is that Hunter offers a traditional CS major -
similar to the majority of institutions across the USA and the
traditional CS major is not really servicing many of our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unlike many other majors, the students in CS by and large want to work
in Tech. Unfortunately, most CS programs aren&amp;#39;t set up for this. Rather
they are set up with the assumption that all CS majors want to go on
to PhD programs which is most certainly not the case. Sure, CS
students learn programming and some other career useful things but
they also learn a lot that most ever use. Theory is important but not
as much as many have to study. Far too much proof, How about calc 2
and sometimes 3? Sure these topics can be useful and even important to
some but I&amp;#39;ve talked to countless tech people in the business world
ranging from entry level programmers to top executives and everyone in
between and by and large the CS major is poorly set up for the CS
career. What&amp;#39;s more, the only career that many CS majors only somewhat
prepares students for is programming and even then just to a certain
extent and there are many non-programming heavy tech opportunities out
there waiting for our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think many in academia acknowledge this as well. I&amp;#39;ve spoken to some
high up people at some of our most prestigious institutions and, at
least, privately, they&amp;#39;ve agreed with me on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it stands, not all Hunter CS students can get through the major and
for those that do, they&amp;#39;re just as well set up for career as graduates
of the &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; programs but truth be told, it&amp;#39;s not the institutions
that are setting them up well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter&amp;#39;s trying to do something about this. At recent department
meetings there&amp;#39;s been discussion of creating a new major - something
that maybe dumps the unnecessary stuff and replaces it with material
that is both more relevant to the students career while also providing
additional support in areas that the students need. The challenge is
to also keep the academic rigor at the same time and not just become a
jobs program for the flavor of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was a lot of talk asking &amp;#34;what do other colleges do and what are
they planning?&amp;#34; but I didn&amp;#39;t like that talk. Who cares what other
colleges are doing? Who says they&amp;#39;re doing it right. Every institution
has a unique situation. Hunter - a liberal arts college in the heart
of NYC which is part of the CUNY system should be figuring out what&amp;#39;s
best for itself, not what may or may not work for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I suggested talking to the tech community, particularly in NYC - what
jobs are out there now and what will be out there in the next decade
and how can we structure a program to inform students as to the
possibilities and to prepare them on their paths?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, I&amp;#39;ve got tons of former students in all areas of tech and
we&amp;#39;ve been talking for the past few weeks and trying to figure this
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Originally, some of the Hunter faculty were considering things like
network admin / sys admin type roles and thought to explore there but
that&amp;#39;s not what I&amp;#39;ve been getting from my network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A big obvious one was software engineering. This could be great for
those meant to follow the programming path but not for tech minded
people who don&amp;#39;t want to spend their days in code. Project management
kept coming up but there were more than a few concerns that to be a
great PM you really have to have some real world experience so a PM
major wouldn&amp;#39;t be serving students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another thing that came up was the idea that developers in many cases
do have more control over their infrastructure which would lead to
requiring knowledge in administering their own systems, some network
wherewithal as well as some knowledge of container technologies and
the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was also a lot of talk about which current major classes were
useful and which really weren&amp;#39;t and there was discussion of a lot of
other things like software architecture (something never taught but
much needed), technology integration, and things like soft skills
(presentations/writing) ethics and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also glad &amp;#34;the family&amp;#34; got the idea that we wanted to teach
academic classes and not just how to use tools. I was heartened this
morning when one of my former students recalled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the 90s when I was in your systems class I remember you
saying that you weren&amp;#39;t teaching us Intel Assembly. We were learning
how computers worked and that we were &lt;strong&gt;using&lt;/strong&gt; Intel Assembly as a tool
to explore to accomplish that learning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Made me feel good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all, I&amp;#39;m really grateful for my StuyCS Family (or as some say,
the StuyCS Mafia) - got all the info I needed from which I think I&amp;#39;ll
be able to craft a very strong and useful new proposed major. I don&amp;#39;t
think it&amp;#39;ll focus on just one possible career but I think it should
get a student ready for a variety of entry level tech jobs including
programming related ones. What&amp;#39;s more, it will educate them as to the
possibilities - something else current majors don&amp;#39;t usually do. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will the CS department like it? Who knows but I&amp;#39;m convinced that it
will be a great option for Hunter students if they do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>College Recommendation Season</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-recs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 20:42:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-recs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s fall so for HS teachers who taught juniors last year it&amp;#39;s
recommendation writing season. For many of those teachers, they&amp;#39;re
already well into the season with early decision deadlines being as
early as November 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Writing recs is one thing I don&amp;#39;t miss now that I&amp;#39;m working at the
college level. Sure, it was always an honor to be asked but it was a
lot of work. Now I&amp;#39;m on the other side and reading the recs. On one
hand, much easier but on the other hand, getting worthwhile
information from a college rec as an application reader can be its own
challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When reading recs, I see the same things that I knew were going on as
when I was on the writing side. Some teachers do a crap job and some
teachers put their all into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the bad side, you get the generic rec - pretty much the same thing
for every kid. We all know some teachers do this. From the reader
point of view, you see these a mile away and when a lot of kids apply
with the same teacher writing, it&amp;#39;s even worse. Sometimes this is
indeed lazy rec writing but other times it&amp;#39;s because the teacher&amp;#39;s
doing their best but just doesn&amp;#39;t have the material - I used to get
asked for recs all the time from that quiet kid who basically did a
good job but was quiet, and to be honest, somewhat generic in terms of
application portfolio. Nice enough kid but within the context of
class, not a lot to write. You know as a teacher that this is a good
kid who deserves to be represented and you&amp;#39;re porbably their best or
only option but there&amp;#39;s not a lot to write. It&amp;#39;s hard. Combine that
when, like me, you&amp;#39;re not a great natural writer and you can get a
generic rec even it you&amp;#39;re not trying to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the good side, you get writers who really write something unique and
descriptive for each kid. In order to try to do
right by my kids, I&amp;#39;d insist on having multiple weeks to write the
recs since I&amp;#39;d have to space them out - I couldn&amp;#39;t do more than one or
two at a sitting for fear of them becoming generic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any case, good recs take work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, I would always be very clear to my students. I&amp;#39;d tell them
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m making no effort at all to get you into any particular school.&amp;#34;&lt;/strong&gt;
I never saw that as the purpose of the rec. I&amp;#39;d tell them that my job
was &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#34;to paint a picture of them&amp;#34;&lt;/strong&gt; in the hope that the reader would
be able to determine if they were a good fit for a school. Afterall,
fit is what it&amp;#39;s all about. If an applicant or rec writer &amp;#34;fool&amp;#34; an
admission office into offering a bad fit, it won&amp;#39;t work out for
anyone. The majority of kids, in my experience end up in good places
and get good educations but the key is not getting in to the dream
school, the key is getting in to the right fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My son, in spite of an amazingly stellar application portfolio,
didn&amp;#39;t get into any of his first choice schools and went grudgingly to
Michigan - it turned out to be the best possible place for him. I
didn&amp;#39;t get in to my dream school back in the day and ended up at NYU
but that was indeed, the right place for me at that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s about fit and a rec can help paint a picture to see if there&amp;#39;s a
fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;ve been on the reading side for a number of years, that&amp;#39;s
what I look for. If I get a generic rec I don&amp;#39;t count it against a
student and if a rec isn&amp;#39;t well written I likewise try to look past
that. As I said before, I don&amp;#39;t consider myself to be a strong writer
so I understand the challenge. I do look for a rec to paint a
picture. Will this student be a good fit for my program. Will they
thrive and be a positive part of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, for teachers at schools where i have a track record, I&amp;#39;d
just as soon get short and sweet - &amp;#34;You remember so and so, well this
kid is like them but here are the differences&amp;#34; or even &amp;#34;Mike, you know
I&amp;#39;ve written for a dozen kids in the past - you WANT this kid.&amp;#34; That
track record is important because over time, I get to know the schools
and the teachers and if they&amp;#39;re honest with me, their recs weigh more
heavily. On the other hand, if I read a bunch of over the top reviews
and later it turns out that the students weren&amp;#39;t fairly represented,
then those writers lose credibility with me in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This has made a difference for kids in the past. Every year, it seems
that I reach out to rec writers directly where I&amp;#39;ve felt there was
something, a spark in the application but I needed to dig deeper to
make a case to advocate for the kid. Sometimes it worked out,
sometimes it didn&amp;#39;t but building the track record and history
certainly help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I can&amp;#39;t speak for anyone else or any admissions office - in fact,
I have nothing to do with the Hunter admissions process, I just have a
major voice in advocating for the students in my program and that is
indeed a very little corner of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, why did I write this? I was talking to a couple of friends who
stil teach high school and they were talking about rec writing and I
thought that even though I&amp;#39;m not directly involved in admissions and
in the greater scheme of things my program is very small and I&amp;#39;m just
one voice, I thought it might be interesting for teachers to read a
bit about how I look at and think about college recs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning 55</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-55/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 15:15:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-55/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, I turned 55 today. Another year older. The changes? Well, I&amp;#39;m
seeing more doctors and seeing them more frequently and to be honest,
I&amp;#39;d love to have a day or two without some small niggling ache or pain
but that&amp;#39;s life. Like many people my age, we&amp;#39;ve got our health issues
but I&amp;#39;m pretty active and managing mine (hey, I had a great 8 mile run
this morning :-) ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, 55 is a big one. Yeah, I know, it&amp;#39;s not 50 which ends in a 0
and is half a century so people seem to earmark it. It&amp;#39;s also not 62
or 67 when social security can kick in for most people. Nope. It&amp;#39;s
also not 65 when you get all those senior discounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fifty five, for teachers who started around when I did is that magic
age that, if you&amp;#39;ve put in enough years (which I have) you can retire
and start collecting unreduced pension benefits. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/&#34;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt; that I was starting to think about retirement as
a possibility. Of course, that doesn&amp;#39;t mean getting out of the game
entirely but if I go that route it means reducing my work obligations
be they at Hunter or elsewhere. Regardless of what I do, I think I
still have something to offer in terms of CS, the Tech Industry,
Education, and the intersection of the three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of what I decide to do, it&amp;#39;s been a tough few years, and
I&amp;#39;m feeling somewhat burnt out and it&amp;#39;s calming and relieving to know
that if I wanted to, I could now step back whenever it suits me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, now to do some hard thinking and have conversations about this
with family and friends (yes, dear reader, I&amp;#39;ll be reaching out to
some of you) while I work to make the experiences of my current
students as positive and rewarding as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masters of CS Education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/masters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 06:45:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/masters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was in the middle of writing a post on how early and often we should
be teaching CS in our schools but had to jump in with a quick hit
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As any reader here knows, Hunter was the first institution with state
approved CS Teacher Education Masters and Certificate programs. Siena
had the first Bachelors program (Hunter doesn&amp;#39;t have undergraduate
education programs that lead to state certification).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ve been graduating certificate students for a couple of years
now. Those are professional teachers - working under another
certification area who are earning the new New York State CS
credential. We now have around 40 certificate graduates who are either
state certified or qualified to be state certified if they haven&amp;#39;t
filled out the state application. It was cool that we were the first
but more importantly that NY is getting qualified CS teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We passed another milestone the other day. Our first two Masters
students graduated this past June and I just heard from one of them
that she now possesses New York State Certification to teach Computer
Science. She should be the first newly minted Masters grad to have
earned certification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another cool milestone passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I expect that in the coming years, the demand for Hunter&amp;#39;s certificate
program will go down as demand for the Masters program goes up. We&amp;#39;ll
see if I&amp;#39;m right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For now, just wanted to share a bit of cool news.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS - it isn&#39;t all that</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-all-that/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 11:52:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-all-that/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve dedicated my entire career - something like 32 years, to CS
education and the spread of CS education. So, while I try to be a
cheerleader I also think it&amp;#39;s important to call out things that we do
or say that are maybe not so great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I hope I don&amp;#39;t annoy too many people (or maybe I hope I do) with
this post and maybe a few more to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before diving into specific CS teaching methods, we started with some
general discussion. What is CS? Why study CS? Why it&amp;#39;s important to
offer etc. This is is really red meat for CS teachers so rich
discussion quickly ensued. Nothing particularly new, I&amp;#39;ve heard and
has been part these conversations so many times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of good stuff but there were a few things that always come up in
these conversations that I think are worth calling out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is creativity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is problem solving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is making mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is building projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students like CS, it&amp;#39;s fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&amp;#39;t bad things and in fact are almost always good
things. What I want to call out is that they&amp;#39;re not CS and certainly
not exclusive to CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big thing I don&amp;#39;t like about this is that the good things here are
not exclusive to CS and are not always in CS. CS can teach problem
solving but so can Math. Creativity? How about writing or the
arts. Making mistakes? Science? Math. and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the flip side CS doesn&amp;#39;t necessarily have these and other good
attributes. CS is generally perceived as fun but then again we&amp;#39;re CS
educators. Math teachers think math is fun. Likewise, as long as CS
classes are populated by students electing to be there and as long as
the content is lightweight it&amp;#39;s not surprising that many kids think
it&amp;#39;s fun. When standardized testing sets in and teachers are
pressured to cover more with less in less time, this will probably
change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I will not infrequently say that something I&amp;#39;m teaching is &amp;#34;inherently
cool&amp;#34; but the truth is it isn&amp;#39;t. There are plenty of things that I
might think are cool or neat or fun but that doesn&amp;#39;t automatically
mean all our students will feel the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Problem solving and creativity? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said before, just about every other field can be about these but
CS might not. Back when the code school / bootcamp boom started in the
Ruby on Rails days, those code schools taught neither problem solving
nor creativity. They taught rote pattern programming to create a very
specific type of application to solve a specific problem that was in
demand in the early days of the second internet boom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS also isn&amp;#39;t also necessarily taught in a creative way in the
K-College classroom. I&amp;#39;ve seen many classes where student create a
game but they all code it together and the creativity consists of
students deciding on the sprite to use for the player. Yes, this
allows for a controlled form of creativity on the visual part of their
project but not on the problem solving side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t mean to be down on CS. CS can incorporate all these good
things and more but I think it&amp;#39;s important to recognize that other
fields can be these things as well and CS might not be all we think
it&amp;#39;s cracked up to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS does, though have one edge over most other fields. As the new kid
on the block K12 CS education is not as highly regulated and
restricted as other fields. We don&amp;#39;t have standardized exams nor
standardized curriculum. The closest we have are APCS-A and
APCS-Principles. This means teachers are more free to teach what they
want how they want. This can be great with a well prepared, qualified
tearch or less great with a less ready one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As CS becomes more part of the system I expect teachers to have less
freedom in what they teach and how they teach. As a community we might
be able to steer the ship towards keeping the good stuff but then
again, we might not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s important, as a community of educators, that as CS becomes more
standardized that the teachers and not the curriculum providers, not
the standards makers, and not the gorillas in the room with the
oversized influence but none of the actual teaching or CS experience
have a voice to keep the good stuff and not go the way of other
disciplines that are no longer considered cool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You can&#39;t workshop a lesson</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/workshop-a-lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 10:02:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/workshop-a-lesson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
The other day, Natan scored tickets for us to see an interview with High
Jackman and Sutton Foster. We&amp;#39;ll be seeing them in &amp;#34;The Music Man&amp;#34;
come this fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was fun but it was the taping for a radio interview so nothing
earth shattering or surprising. Still, one thing stuck with me and got
me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jackman told a story about how, during rehearsals, he wandered down from
his dressing room to find  Foster was working with Jerry
Zaks, the director on &amp;#34;My White Knight.&amp;#34; He remained and observed,
entranced as Foster and Zaks spent an hour or so working on the song.
It reminded me of a Master Class taught by Maxim Vengerov, my favorite
current violinist that I caught on cable one day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It got me thinking about how horribly pathetic our model of teacher
observation, support and improvement is and that you can&amp;#39;t have a
master class for a lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The two things in teaching that would be closest to a master class
would be either teaching a mock lesson to a colleague or supervisor or
an observation. Mock lessons rarely occur outside of teacher
interviews but colleagues will observe each other. The problem is,
those aren&amp;#39;t Master Classes. In a Master Class, you have an immediate
feedback loop. You perform, stop, get feedback, rinse and repeat. When
teaching, you get some feedback at the end of the lesson and even if
it&amp;#39;s good you generally can&amp;#39;t implement any changes until next
year. If you&amp;#39;re lucky, next semester. Sometimes you might be able to
rush try things in a class later that day but usually not. Of course,
if and when you do try that change you likely won&amp;#39;t be getting any
feedback on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem is, you can&amp;#39;t stop the lesson in the middle becuase, you
know, the students and you certainly can&amp;#39;t then go back  and reteach
the last 10 minutes again to them to see if it&amp;#39;s better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although there are many similarities between teaching and performing
there are of course crucial differences. The bar for a performer is
pretty simple - will the audience get something out of the
performance - enough to think positively about it. That&amp;#39;s pretty much
it. To get there, Sutton and Zaks worked on a challenging song. There
wasn&amp;#39;t any audience feedback but rather they worked to achieve the
director&amp;#39;s vision. When Vengerov runs his class, he&amp;#39;s working with his
students on their interpretation of the work. These work in performance
becuase first, presumably they know what works with an audience and
second, an audience may very well go to something to see or hear an
artists interpretation. Personally, I&amp;#39;ll go to one violinist or
anther&amp;#39;s performance of a work specifically to hear their
interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When teaching the bar is harder to define, at least if you&amp;#39;re serious.
about education. My first chairman kept it simple. He said, when you
observe a class, just keep asking yourself &amp;#34;is learning going on?&amp;#34; And
then figure out where and how. I always liked that and always lived by
that.  Of course these days observations aren&amp;#39;t about learning but
about teacher evaluation using garbage metrics like Danielson where
it&amp;#39;s all about checking off the boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, good teachers do work to improve their lessons. They try
different techniques, work within the extremely slow feedback loop and
they work with their colleagues even though they&amp;#39;re never given the
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
None of this really means anything. Just something I found interesting
to ponder. Would a master class work for teachers? Maybe. Maybe you
could run a department meeting as one with one teacher presenting and
the rest of the department playing students, both good and bad. That
would actually be pretty interesting. If anyone tries this, let me
know.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put It In The Books</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/put-it-in-the-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 17:20:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/put-it-in-the-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Just finished entering grades closing out my 32nd year teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Whew!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a hard year for me and I&amp;#39;m sure even harder for the K12
teachers out there. Still this year I&amp;#39;m really missing what I was oh
so many years ago - a regular teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teaching from September through June is a beast and from my first day
on the job I had to work ten times harder than I ever had to as a
software engineer and was commensurately exhausted. In spite of what
the &amp;#34;real world&amp;#34; says teachers need their summers to recharge the
batteries. This isn&amp;#39;t to say that teachers don&amp;#39;t work over the
summer - they lesson plan, attend PD and in fact a bunch of them will
be with me, working towards their NY State CS teaching certification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m also technically on a school year contract so why do I wish I
was a regular teacher? Because once you enter those final grades, you
put the past to bed. Once I clicked on &amp;#34;post grades&amp;#34; in CUNYFirst I
thought about that. Early in my career, before I had to deal with
building Stuy&amp;#39;s CS program and otherwise getting involved in the
movement, once those grades were entered I was done. I could mentally
turn off. My responsibilities to student and school were done and I&amp;#39;d
have a couple of months before the next go around. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I noted that I should have been feeling that but wasn&amp;#39;t. Why not?
Because I&amp;#39;m still immersed in dealing with issues for my advanced
certificate program - working on scholarship issues, getting the
teachers, making sure they&amp;#39;re up to speed, finding instructors under
some draconian restrictions placed on me by both Hunter and the staet,
andto be honest, the self imposed stress of feeling responsible for
making everything work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a while since I&amp;#39;ve &amp;#34;just taught&amp;#34; and maybe would like to get
back to that but even then, all this is making me seriously think
about that possible (probable?) retirement in a year to scale things
back or change things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, ploughing ahead with the teacher certification program
this month to get things in order and then teaching through
July. Should get a week or two of downtime in August so that&amp;#39;ll be the
time to reflect on the year in depth. Until then it&amp;#39;s nose to the
grindstone.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Critical Mass Of CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/a-critical-mass-of-cs-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 13:38:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/a-critical-mass-of-cs-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A big difficulty with creating CS opportunities for all our students
is the lack of CS teachers. New York City addressed this problem with
their CS4All program - quick form PD to get teachers into CS
classrooms in a hurry. One can debate if that was the best way to go
but it enabled NYC to create a whole lot of CS classes in a very short
period of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, these teachers, by and large, only have that short form PD
so I&amp;#39;d argue that this isn&amp;#39;t a long term solution. I mean, you
wouldn&amp;#39;t want your entire language program taught by people who
barely knew Spanish 1  or Math taught by teachers how don&amp;#39;t know
beyond the basics of Algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A number of institutions, including Hunter are working on rectifying
this via our CS Education programs. Some programs are legit, and some
practically as superficial as the short form PD but the legit ones are
trying to address the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I want to talk about why Hunter&amp;#39;s Advanced Certificate program, a
program, that I might add, is currently accepting applicants for this
summer, is critical to the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Right now, you could place K12 CS teachers into one of the following
buckets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People with strong CS backgrounds. CS Majors or people with
industry experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hobbyists who learned some CS on their own and developed an
interest or passion for the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volunteers who are game for the challenge who heard about CS4All
and answered the call.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teachers who were voluntold who are taking one for the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of the home-brew CS programs in the city started with teachers
from the first two categories but currently the vast majority of
teachers teaching CS are in the last two. Eventually, CS classes in
NYC will all or mostly all be taught by qualified, certified CS teachers
but how we get there will make a difference in terms of the community
and culture we create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of the approved certification programs in NY state award either a
Bachelors degree or a Masters. That is, they&amp;#39;re designed for new
teachers just entering the profession. At Hunter we run a Masters
program. Our first cohort had 3 students, our second 6 and right now
there are 3 applicants for our third cohort. I haven&amp;#39;t done any
advertising or outreach but over time we&amp;#39;ll get more and more
applicants. It will be a slow process but eventually we&amp;#39;ll have
comparable numbers as for our math and science ed programs. I&amp;#39;d
imagine that other programs across the state will have a similar
growth curve. As these programs graduate teachers, the voluntolds and
volunteers that aren&amp;#39;t up to speed will return to their other
subjects. Some will continue to teach a section or two of CS which
is fine provided that by then their base of knowledge of CS and CS
pedagogy is well beyond the canned training that DOE currently
provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While eventually this will normalize, there is a problem. We&amp;#39;re
basically asking our new CS teachers to also be our master CS
teachers, our CS teacher leaders. They&amp;#39;ll have deep CS knowledge and
they&amp;#39;ll have studied the CS pedagogy so it&amp;#39;ll all be on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The trouble is that it&amp;#39;s hard enough surviving as a new
teacher. Asking them to be the master teachers and the leaders at the
same time is just not right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s where my Advanced Certificate program at Hunter comes in. Right
now, we&amp;#39;re the only such program in New York state. The program&amp;#39;s an
18 credit masters level program that teaches the CS and the CS
pedagogy but understands that the participants are already experienced
teachers in some other subject area. It&amp;#39;s a program that takes an
teacher who&amp;#39;s already experienced, albeit in another subject area and
fills in the CS content and CS pedagogy gaps. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mentioned earlier that I&amp;#39;ve done zero outreach for our masters
program and that&amp;#39;s because all my outreach has been for the Advanced
Cert. I think it&amp;#39;s vitally important that we  build a critical mass of
highly qualified CS teachers as soon as possible. Taking current,
experienced teachers and bringing them up to speed in CS and teaching
CS is the way to do this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other subjects already have their teacher leaders. In most schools, at
least in larger schools, there will be one or two &amp;#34;go to&amp;#34;
teachers. The ones that know the subject matter more deeply and how to
teach it, the ones who are up on the latest and greatest in the field
and in teaching, the ones who attend the conferences and bring back
best practices. I&amp;#39;m working to jump start that for New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, I&amp;#39;m not alone and our friends at &lt;a href=&#34;https://gothamgives.org/&#34;&gt;Gotham Gives&lt;/a&gt; and Google
are supporting our program by providing scholarships to pay the
tuition for qualified applicants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our first cohort graduated in May of 2021 and with that, New York City
(and state) had it&amp;#39;s first 21 certified computer science
teacher. They&amp;#39;ll be joined by 23 more two months from now. That&amp;#39;s 44
teachers that have both the subject knowledge and the pedagogical
knowledge to match in the system. Part of their scholarship agreement
is for them to give back. Take part in CS education efforts in the
city so they&amp;#39;re already helping to shape the community and culture of
K12 CS Education in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m hoping for an even larger cohort this year. Imagine if we could
get 60 or more into our program this summer. That would mean in three
short years we&amp;#39;ll have gone from zero to 100 qualified certified
teachers and we&amp;#39;ll be well on the way to that critical mass of teacher
leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we get closer to that critical mass of qualified teachers, interest
in programs like my certificate program will wane but at the same
time, there will be more demand from teaching newcomers for our
Masters program as there will be a career path for young CS minded
teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once again it&amp;#39;s the long game but that&amp;#39;s what it takes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re a New York City CS teacher and are looking for state
certification, come join us. All the information can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.huntercs.org/teacher_ed/summer-2022.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE2022 - Things I plan to blog about</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse2022-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 20:07:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse2022-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been up in Providence RI since this past Wednesday for
SIGCSE2022. The big Computer Science Educators conference. Also, my
first in person conference since pre-covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t sure how I was going to feel about this big in person
gathering but as it&amp;#39;s turned out, it&amp;#39;s been pretty comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So far, I&amp;#39;ve attended two terrific keynotes. One by Barbara
Liskov and the other Barbara Ericson, some really interesting sessions
and some less interesting ones and have had a great time discussing CS
education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big highlight has been seeing friends in person and being able to
talk. Sitting down for coffee with a friend or having a rount table
discussion around a well, round table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of those friends I was delighted to see was Alfred
Thompson. Alfred&amp;#39;s already sumarized his &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.acthompson.net/2022/03/sigcse-2022-day-1.html&#34;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.acthompson.net/2022/03/sigcse-2022-day-2.html&#34;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; day
experiences so there&amp;#39;s not reason for me to write much the same so I
figured I&amp;#39;d just quickly list out a few of my highlights and in
particular things I plan to write more about when I get back to NYC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Language choice for APCS. There was a panel that considered why
change to Python or why stick with Java. I didn&amp;#39;t attend this
session but talked at length about it with a number of people. It
had me reconsidering my opinions and I&amp;#39;ll certainly write about this
in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I saw an interesting talk by Sam Lau in which he discussed how
statisticians and computer scientists differed in their views as to
how and what should be taught in a data science course. This got me
thinking about developing CS offerings at the high school level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I attended the &amp;#34;It seemed like a good idea at the time&amp;#34; session for
the first time where teachers discussed their failures. This was a
&lt;strong&gt;great&lt;/strong&gt; session hosted by two more friends I haven&amp;#39;t seen since
pre-covid - Dan Garcia and Jim Huggins. One topic brought up there
was dealing with late assignments as well as alternative
grading. This too is something I plan to write about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PD For CS Teachers and teacher prep programs. This is clearly
something I care deeply about and there were some sessions on this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also spent a good amount of time catching up with my friends Jim
and Robin from Siena College. They&amp;#39;re doing some cool thing up there
so that&amp;#39;s another thing I&amp;#39;d like to write about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also had some good discussions with vendors in the exhibit hall as
well as some great hallway tract talks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My thoughts on the hybrid format of this conference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a big list - a lot of things to write about. I hope to get on
this when I get back to NYC on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the meantime, if you&amp;#39;re in providence for tomorrow&amp;#39;s last day of
SIGCSE, please find me and say hello!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First live conference in 2 years</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 08:13:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow I&amp;#39;ll be driving up to Providence Rhode Island for SIGSE 2022,
basically the largest computer science education conference out
there. I guess ITSE, a conference I&amp;#39;ve never attended, is larger but
that&amp;#39;s really EdTech with some CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The last in person conference I went to was two almost exactly two
years ago - also SIGCSE. I arrived in Portland and went to a
pre-conference session and on the morning of the big start, about three
hours before I ran my session, I saw an email saying we were
canceled. I flew home and a few days later we began our shelter in for
covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of the latest CDC release, SIGCSE is still requiring
masks. This is something I support. I have no problem taking a
conservative view on health, particularly at an event that brings
together people from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The sessions should be comfortable. Everybody will be vaccinated and
should be masked so it&amp;#39;s no different than attending a concert in
NYC. I am curious though about the lunches and big reception. Will
everyone just dump the masks for food since we&amp;#39;re all vaccinated? Will
there be some trepidation? We&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also curious to see the overall attendance. The last SIGCSE had
well over 1,500 attendees. What will this one be like? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are some sessions I&amp;#39;m really looking forward to. There are some
on K12 teacher preparation and professional development. I feel pretty
confident that the approach I&amp;#39;m taking at Hunter is the right one but
it&amp;#39;s always good to see what other people are thinking about and
trying - always happy to steal better ideas. I&amp;#39;m also looking forward
to some of the sessions that deal with teaching more advanced CS
concepts. This is something that&amp;#39;s lacking in CS Ed. The CSTA
conference which focuses on K12 is more about actual teaching but
since K12 CS is still in its infancy, most schools are still dealing
with intro level stuff and conferences like CSTA really have to work
to support our new teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most importantly though, I&amp;#39;m looking forward to seeing people that I
haven&amp;#39;t seen in a couple of years. Both those that I consider real
friends and also the many acquaintances I&amp;#39;m friendly with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also looking to see the breakdown of K12 and higher ed
people. Over the years the number of K12 teachers at the conference
has grown and it&amp;#39;s interesting to see the differences in the
camps. The teachers, by and large know far less CS but are much
stronger teachers while the professors know the topic but while they
might research teaching, they don&amp;#39;t nearly have the depth of teaching
knowlege that K12 teachers posess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a probably unfair oversimplification but you could say that teachers teach
the student and professors teach the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This can make for an interesting dynamic. I hope over time, the
teachers become stronger in the subject material and that the
professors realize that teaching is an art and a craft and that what
one does at an elite institution is worlds away from the inner city
middle school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, enough yammering. For those of you who&amp;#39;ll be in providence
this week, make sure to say hi. I&amp;#39;m sure we&amp;#39;ll all learn a lot and have
a blast doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Problem Solving And Crosswords</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/programming-problem-solving-and-crosswords/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 17:37:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/programming-problem-solving-and-crosswords/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I used to do the New York Times Crossword puzzle. I don&amp;#39;t remember
when I started - some time late in Eugene Maleska&amp;#39;s tenure as the
editor. I continued on a few years into Will Shortz&amp;#39;s puzzles. I
stopped when the Times wanted to charge me for both print and
online. I preferred reading the physical paper but liked printing the
puzzle from their online site. I was also pissed at the Times coverage
of a number of issues at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I picked up the puzzle again when Covid started and have only missed a
few days since. I&amp;#39;m pretty sure the puzzle is easier these days. Way
back when, I&amp;#39;d sometimes complete or almost complete a Saturday puzzle
but more frequently I&amp;#39;d just fill in a smattering of words. On this
run, I&amp;#39;ve completed every puzzle I started except one. I say the
puzzle must be getting easier because if anything, I&amp;#39;m getting dumber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was doing the puzzle the other day and it got me thinking about the
advice I give my students when I first meet them. I tell them it&amp;#39;s one
of the true secrets of success. Of course, I know it&amp;#39;s my job as teacher to tell
them these critical secrets and it&amp;#39;s their job as student to ignore
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I tell my students that regardless of when they do an assignment they
should read over it the day they get it. It doesn&amp;#39;t matter if the
assignment isn&amp;#39;t due for two weeks -  read it and give it a bit of
thought the day you get it. Even if you don&amp;#39;t work on the assignment
right then and there, your brain will start working on it in the
background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I do the crossword, particularly Friday and Saturday, but
sometimes other days as well, I start the puzzle with my first cup of
coffee. Sometimes I&amp;#39;ll get a good amount done but on those Saturday
puzzles, I&amp;#39;ll sometimes get stuck with the fewest of words. I&amp;#39;ll look
at clues and, well, have no clue and think &amp;#34;guess I won&amp;#39;t be finishing
this one.&amp;#34; At some point I stop - do something else. I check my email,
read some blogs in my feeds and a little later go back to the
puzzle. Invariably, I&amp;#39;ll read some clues that while opaque just a few
minutes earlier are trivial now. Hitting another wall I take another
break. I&amp;#39;ll come back after breakfast and fill in some more. So far,
this has just about always resulted in a solved puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking of a few things. One, the break is giving my
brain time to work in the background while focusing on something
else. It also lets me look at the puzzle with fresh eyes when I pick
it up again. A last little point that&amp;#39;s neither here nor there is that
it is a manner of perseverance (no, I won&amp;#39;t use that term grit which
I hate).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me this was a really clear and concise example of exactly what I&amp;#39;ve
been preaching to my kids for decades. Not only read the assignment
early but also when you hit a roadblock, take a break - clear your
head. Come back with fresh eyes. Work smarter not harder. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, I don&amp;#39;t think this example is more relatable to my kids
than the other ways I try to share this wisdom with them but I still
think it&amp;#39;s a great example.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pension Consultations</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pension/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 17:41:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pension/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Devorah and I just got off a Zoom pension consultation. Very
enlightening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m 54 so regardless, can&amp;#39;t retire for another year but Devorah hit 55
last November and the DOE can really kill ones spirit and grind you down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I&amp;#39;ve been pretty happy at Hunter but I&amp;#39;ve written before about
the fact that I&amp;#39;ve been feeling some burn out and have been basically
doing 2+ full time jobs myself at Hunter for the past few years and
that&amp;#39;s just not sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not saying I know what I&amp;#39;m going to do  but it&amp;#39;s important to know
your options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t sure what our retirement benefits would look like but when I
came in to teaching, looking at the older tier 1 teachers, I felt that
back then there was something of a societal pact, at least in NYC. As
a teacher back then, you weren&amp;#39;t going to get rich. In good times,
you&amp;#39;d do okay - not great but okay. On the other hand, in bad times,
you wouldn&amp;#39;t do terrible. You&amp;#39;d be able to have a decent home and
while you couldn&amp;#39;t jet set you&amp;#39;d be able to vacation reasonably and at
the end of it all, you&amp;#39;d have a comfortable retirement. Again, you
wouldn&amp;#39;t be rich, but you wouldn&amp;#39;t have to worry about making ends
meet either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the course of my career, I saw that pact erode, even in NY. Young
teachers don&amp;#39;t earn enough for the housing market and the workload and
work pressures have just exploded. For the newest teachers, the
retirement end of the deal has also gotten worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what does it look like for us after putting in and paying in for
30 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With 30 years in, it turns out that pension will net me just a few
hundred dollars less than my current net. It&amp;#39;s much closer than I
thought it would be. Devorah doesn&amp;#39;t do quite as well. Her difference
is greater but that&amp;#39;s because she hasn&amp;#39;t crossed the 30 year barrier
yet. If she stays one more year, she will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Add to that a substantial TDA and we&amp;#39;re actually in really good
retirement shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A lot of older teachers say they finally &amp;#34;had&amp;#34; to retire because based
on tax benefits and other factors, they were actually losing money by
not retiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Based on the differences I mentioned above we&amp;#39;re not there yet but
when you factor our housing, we might be, or if not it&amp;#39;s really
close. We currently live in what&amp;#39;s known as a &amp;#34;limited equity coop.&amp;#34;
It&amp;#39;s a coop but it receives local and state tax benefits. In return,
there are earning caps on the residents. We currently earn well over
the cap so pay a significant surcharge on our monthly maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we retire, our lower incomes will result in a much lower
surcharge or maybe it will remove the surcharge entirely - we&amp;#39;re
working on figuring that out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Depending on how that plays out we might actually be losing money if
we don&amp;#39;t retire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ll have to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said at the top. I&amp;#39;m basically happy at Hunter and I think I&amp;#39;ve
accomplished a lot so I&amp;#39;m not saying I&amp;#39;m out the door as soon as I can
walk. We&amp;#39;ve got to lower my workload but they&amp;#39;ve known that for a
while so hopefully are working to solve the problem. Devorah and I
also have to figure out what we want to do in our next phase. I do
know that regardless, I think I&amp;#39;ve still got something to give in the
CS Ed space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For any young teachers out there - make sure to max out on that
TDA. It seems like nothing at first but when you look back after 20 or
30 years it&amp;#39;ll surprise you - that + the defined pension are what
allow you to have a few years of leisure at the end of a life of
service. And don&amp;#39;t let anyone tell you that you don&amp;#39;t deserve it or
that it&amp;#39;s an entitlement. You&amp;#39;ve paid into it for your whole career
and are just getting back what you&amp;#39;ve earned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning 54</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 13:59:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, tomorrow, October 19, is my birthday. The big 5 4. Okay, maybe it&amp;#39;s not a
traditionally big one. It doesn&amp;#39;t end in a zero or a five but I think
it rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why? Because it&amp;#39;s one shy of 55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the magic age when I can retire collect my pension should I
choose to do so. It&amp;#39;s what you get when start young and put in over
30 years of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago I would have given an emphatic &amp;#34;no.&amp;#34; Now, I&amp;#39;m starting
to think &amp;#34;maybe.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ve written a few times here about feeling some
burnout and a lot less joy. Part of that&amp;#39;s covid and part of it&amp;#39;s doing
more than two full time jobs. Another factor is that by summer 2023,
actually, summer 2022, I&amp;#39;ll have pretty much accomplished everything
I&amp;#39;ve set out to do here. On top of this, Devorah will be able to
retire before I can so that also weighs in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. There&amp;#39;s a lot I like about Hunter and a lot I
still enjoy about my job but there&amp;#39;s stuff that&amp;#39;s just wearing me
down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of what happens, I plan to stay in the game in some
capacity. I want to figure out a situation where Devorah and I can
travel more - my one big regret, but I think I&amp;#39;ve still got something
to contribute to the CS Ed world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we can trim down my workload at Hunter and eliminate the things that
stress me out, I could be there a long time. If not, well, we&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the time being, I&amp;#39;ll enjoy tomorrow. Nothing particularly
special - normal work day followed by a family dinner. Actually,
whole family dinner is always special, just not unusual for us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No CSTA conference for me this year</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 17:08:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today is the start of CSTA&amp;#39;s annual conference. Like last year, it&amp;#39;s
virtual. Unlike the past few years, this year I won&amp;#39;t be attending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a big fan of the CSTA conference. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jakebask&#34;&gt;Jake&lt;/a&gt; and team have done an
amazing job growing the conference and it&amp;#39;s been a highlight of my
year every time I&amp;#39;ve attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could say that I&amp;#39;m not attending due to my schedule - I&amp;#39;m pretty
much spending all day every day during July teaching in my CS Teacher
Certification program and at the end of the day I&amp;#39;m wiped. This is
true but it&amp;#39;s not the only reason. The truth is, I&amp;#39;m pretty burned
out. Part of it is doing too many things. At this point, the
teacher education part of my portfolio is a full time job as is my
work with the undergraduate CS students and that&amp;#39;s not counting the
extras that have worked their way onto my plate. The other part of it
I&amp;#39;m sure is Covid. I&amp;#39;m writing this because  many teachers are
overworked and add in this past year of Covid and I&amp;#39;m sure many are
feeling the same as I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I love the CSTA conference but I&amp;#39;m just not feeling it. Same with a
lot of professional stuff - just not feeling the joy these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m hoping that come August I can turn everything off for a few weeks
and recharge a bit for next year and going back in person (safely)
will provide a boost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m betting teachers around the country are feeling rather burned out
so wanted to share publicly saying you&amp;#39;re not alone, it&amp;#39;s okay and
it&amp;#39;s okay to dial it back for our own mental and physical well being. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already looking forward to a better next year and  CSTA2022, hopefully in person.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Election Thoughts - feeling hope but still concerned</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/election-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 06:56:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/election-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t usually talk  politics on this blog but it is the news of the
day. We truly are at a turning point in this country and we should all
be concerned with the road we take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday the media outlets called the election for Biden/Harris. It&amp;#39;s
not over but I thought this would be as good a time as any to share
some thoughts and more importantly concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at some of the bad that we&amp;#39;ve got to pay attention to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
The Bad
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;70,000,000  voted for Trump.

That should be both sobering and
frightening. Some of these are rich selfish people, some are racist,
some brainwashed by Fox and AM talk radio but there&amp;#39;s also a huge
undercurrent of lack of decency.  

Trump has time and again shown these traits: bullying, ignorance,
protectionism, isolationism, ignorance, compulsive lying, misogyny,
divisiveness, racism and white supremacy.

A vote for Trump says that none of those were disqualifiers. A Trump
voter may fancy themselves not racist but are fine with a racist as
the American President.

This should be very concerning. 

Can we educate this group? Bring them over? We should not and can
not just all be friends and pretend nothing ever happened. If I&amp;#39;ve
got a friend who has any of the above traits I hope that I&amp;#39;d try to
bring them over from the dark side but our friendship would be over
if they just doubled down as Trump and Trump supporters have done
time and agian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Republicans leaders haven&amp;#39;t congratulated Biden/Harris

Republican leadership has shown no indication of recognizing or
wanting to work with our new Presiden. How will the Democrats react?
Will they &amp;#34;reach across the aisle&amp;#34; only to be burned again? This
would be a HUGE mistake. Sure, now is the time to extend the olive
branch but come January, if the republicans still want to go
scorched earth the Democrats must respond. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ain&amp;#39;t over til it&amp;#39;s over

Trumps team &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; the GOP are still forging ahead to contest the
election and some GOP leaders are telling states to forgo the will
of the people and quite simply give the election to Trump. Even if
this doesn&amp;#39;t happen this should terrify you. Even if all goes well
and we move on to a Biden/Harris presidency, these GOP leaders are
still in power and they&amp;#39;ve shown their true selves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Democrats still refuse to learn

I thought Biden&amp;#39;s speech was great last night. He hit all the right
notes but let&amp;#39;s see what the party actually does.

Right after the election I saw tweets from Democratic candidates
attacking the progressive wing of the party yet to my knowledge all
the candidates that actively campaigned on progressive issues
won. It wast he old school Democrats (that is, the ones who are
really 1980s republicans with better social positions) that had
difficulties. It certainly appears that most Americans want police
reform, health care that&amp;#39;s not contingent on employment or being
independently wealthy and I do dare say most don&amp;#39;t want to destroy
the planet. 

If the Democrats continue to ignore the future, ignore the working
and middle class, address income inequity and the aforementioned
progressive line items we&amp;#39;ll be back where we were in 2016 before
you know it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low turnout

Finally, on the bad side, even though the past few presidential
elections have had record highs for voter turnout we&amp;#39;re still under
50% which is just sad. We have to both address the GOP&amp;#39;s repeated
attempts to disenfranchise voters and get more people to the polls.

&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; I accidentally looked at US population instead of voting age
population. It&amp;#39;s actually more like 56% which is a great step
in the right direction but still not enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
The eh
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Senate is still up in the air but it doesn&amp;#39;t look like the Republicans
will lose control. It&amp;#39;s bad but I can&amp;#39;t say it&amp;#39;s a failure. It&amp;#39;s
certainly bad that Kentucky keeps sending McConnell to the Senate with
him possibly doing more damage than even trump but not a surprise. The
Democrats shouldn&amp;#39;t have lost seats in the house  but I haven&amp;#39;t dug
into those races carefully enough to say anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
The Good
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, there&amp;#39;s some good as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;close to 75,000,000 voted for Biden/Harris

That&amp;#39;s millions more than voted for Trump and they got support from
all corners. This is terrific. Biden wasn&amp;#39;t my first choice nor was
Harris but both have grown on me and it looks like a broad coalition &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blue wave?

While it may not seem like there was a blue wave, maybe there
was. Taking the senate was probably not a realistic goal and there&amp;#39;s
still a chance. You could say the Democrats lost some seats but
instead of comparing 2020 to the midterms, compare 2020 to 2016 when
the Republicans held the house. This plus looking at the states that
went or still could go Biden? Maybe there was a blue wave afterall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The world response

Certainly seems like our allies are happy with the results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a first dog

Nuff said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The response of the American people.

Parties in the streets all across the country. In New York, the
party started with the announcement and kept going through the
evening. 

I&amp;#39;ve &lt;strong&gt;never&lt;/strong&gt; seen anything like this before. Not even when Obama was
elected. I saw tweets talking about how this is the behavior you see
when dictators are overthrown. Well, there you have it.

This outpouring of emotion and relief never seen in our lifetime in
America This says a lot about where we are and where we were.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
What&amp;#39;s next?
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the question. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the parties don&amp;#39;t change nothing&amp;#39;s going to change and the parties
aren&amp;#39;t going to change unless the people force them to change. Groups
like &lt;a href=&#34;https://brandnewcongress.org/&#34;&gt;Brand New Congress&lt;/a&gt; are a start but we&amp;#39;ve all got to be active
supporting candidates (or running), calling out injustice, using our
position and platforms for those that can&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a rough four years and a super stressful election
season. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m still concerned about this election and very concerned
about our future but for the first time in a while I&amp;#39;m also hopeful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just remember though, hope without action won&amp;#39;t take us from hope to
reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>53 trips around the sun</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 20:36:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
In the 10 plus years of this blog I&amp;#39;ve never done a post on my
birthday. Okay, maybe I&amp;#39;ve written one &lt;strong&gt;on&lt;/strong&gt; my birthday but never
talked about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why this year?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No particular reason. Maybe because I&amp;#39;m getting older. I&amp;#39;m 53
today. Devorah will turn 54 in a month - from there one year until she
can retire. I can follow a year later. I&amp;#39;m pretty happy with what I&amp;#39;m
doing but it&amp;#39;s nice to know that in two years I&amp;#39;ll have a lot of
options on the table. I can stay the course or maybe look for new
challenges. By then, should things continue apace, my undergraduate
program will have been running and growing for seven years, I&amp;#39;ll have had
three cohorts of teachers go through my advanced certificate program
and I should even have my first Masters in CS Education graduates. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For today, it&amp;#39;s mostly business as usual. Plan is to head out for my
morning run, come back and teach class. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After that, I&amp;#39;ll head down to Varick Street to drop off my ballot. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to the rest of the day, we&amp;#39;ll see. I&amp;#39;ll probably spend most of it
trying to set up virtual school visits.  Looking forward to the family
dinner - Natan&amp;#39;s cooking tonight as he does often so I know it&amp;#39;ll be
tasty.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unplugging with Bob Ross</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/unplugging-bob-ross/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 08:56:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/unplugging-bob-ross/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img width=&#34;75%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/bobross/practice.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a long year since March. Many of us have not really been
able to leave NYC for a variety of reasons - financial, professional,
or family to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other than a couple of small escapes in the last two weeks we&amp;#39;ve been
home and working from home in our Manhattan apartment since this all
started. Early on we didn&amp;#39;t get out much and we still aren&amp;#39;t and that
does take its toll. You have to go out to shop but walking the same
streets over and over is a bit monotonous and far too few people seem
to understand that for masks to be helpful they have to cover both the
mouth and nose. Since recovering I do get out for a run most mornings
and that helps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I realized that one of the draining factors of being stuck in a NYC
apartment is that everything I was doing was on screens. I teach via
the computer and consume my news and communicate the same way. If I&amp;#39;m
working on a side programming project that&amp;#39;s more computer time as
well. If I watch some TV I&amp;#39;m just switching out one screen for
another. Even when I read which I&amp;#39;ve been doing much more of since the
outbreak it&amp;#39;s still on a screen!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Devorah doesn&amp;#39;t have this problem - between her knitting, spinning,
and weaving she&amp;#39;s got plenty of non-screen time. She always said I
needed a hobby and as usual, was probably right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about painting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/bobross/halloween.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Years ago, 1997 or 1998 I did Bob Ross for Halloween. It was an
absolute blast. I did a painting in each class and a couple by the
second floor bar. So much fun but I didn&amp;#39;t really know how to paint. I
watched the show a few times but that was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/bobross/halloween2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I never really did anything after that Halloween - oil paints are
messy, take forever to try, are hard to clean, and require the use of
hazardous solvents. I put the stuff away in a closet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to today - we have water mixable oils which remove the
toxicity issued and makes clean up easier and there&amp;#39;s now a wealth of online
resources to learn from. I thought I&amp;#39;d give it another go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even with just a little practice, I&amp;#39;m starting to get better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/bobross/mountains.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And while it&amp;#39;s all a work in progress,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/bobross/islands1.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/bobross/islands2.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But it&amp;#39;s been fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;75%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/bobross/trees.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Each time I paint it&amp;#39;s getting me away from a computer screen for an
hour or two and it&amp;#39;s been both relaxing and fun. The only downside is
that they still take forever to dry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scared teachers can&#39;t teach and scared students won&#39;t learn</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/scared-teachers-scared-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 13:23:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/scared-teachers-scared-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been reading a lot of takes on NYC schools reopening. We&amp;#39;ve had
daily conversations about it with our summer teachers but
conversations abound on Facebook, Twitter and everywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many salient points have been raised - given the DOE&amp;#39;s track record,
can they make things safe and will they? Can they be trusted? Given
that any policy needs all players to follow the rules - students,
teachers, and staff how can that ever happen? What happens when a
parent want&amp;#39;s their kid in school but wants to opt out of wearing a
mask? What happens if kids just straight out refuse? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there&amp;#39;s logistics and teacher workload - even if you have fewer
kids in school there will still be far too many on subway platforms
and who knows if they&amp;#39;ll be masked outside of the school
building. What about bathrooms and class changeovers? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there&amp;#39;s that little matter of teachers having to now, instead of
just five classes which is already too many could effectively be asked
to teach double or more - the result of splitting their classes into
live and remote. There&amp;#39;s also the way they want the live teaching to
work which basically reduces the in person instruction to a remote
experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What isn&amp;#39;t being talked about is discomfort and fear. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From what I can tell, a lot of teachers are afraid for their
health. Not mildly concerned, afraid. I don&amp;#39;t blame them. I would be
too. I&amp;#39;m betting a lot of students are also afraid of going back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How effective is a teacher going to be when they feel that any
interaction or even too much time in the wrong space might get them
sick or worse. Same for students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After 9/11 we relocated to Brooklyn Tech. It was surreal
and weird but it felt fine. I taught, they learned. We were pushed
back to Stuy too early. You could still smell the smoke from the
smoldering wreckage of ground zero and there were concerns about the
air quality. It was on a lot of our minds all the time we were down on
Chambers street. It was certainly on my mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know that I wasn&amp;#39;t teaching at anything resembling my normal level
and I&amp;#39;m pretty sure the kids weren&amp;#39;t learning nearly as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Eventually, the smoke cleared, they cleaned the building again (and
stole a lot of valuables) and set up sensors that at least seemed more
accurate and after a period of time we felt normal or at least close
enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, that was from a single event not an ongoing pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t believe for one second that NYC schools will be safe for
teachers and students in the fall but even if they were, if teachers
and students don&amp;#39;t feel safe, student learning will suffer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I get that there are downsides to staying remote but don&amp;#39;t fool
yourself into believing that just because you&amp;#39;re sending your kid to
school they&amp;#39;ll be socializing and doing all that good in person
stuff. They&amp;#39;ll be sitting in rows watching a projector and then
shuffled home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sure, remote is not as good as normal in person classes but don&amp;#39;t
blame teachers, blame the pandemic. These are exceptional times and
bad and unsafe  in person &amp;#34;solutions&amp;#34; are much worse than safety of
remote. At the end of the day, this pandemic will pass and we will get
back to in person. So what if a for a year students don&amp;#39;t reach some
arbitrary standard bar because remote is sub-optimal. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even if safe, scared teachers can&amp;#39;t teach and scared students won&amp;#39;t
learn.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PSA on CSTA (NYC)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/psa-for-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 11:43:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/psa-for-csta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Just a quick public service announcemnt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Up until now CSTA-NYC has been using Meetup to organize and advertise
events but now they&amp;#39;re moving over to using the CSTA site as their
platform. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re a CS teacher you should be a part of CSTA. There&amp;#39;s both a
free tier and a plus tier which costs $50 a year.  I&amp;#39;ve been a plus
member since that level became available. If you&amp;#39;re a NYC teacher, you
should join the CSTA NYC chapter. If you&amp;#39;re already coming to CSTA-NYC
events, you should still go to the CSTA web site and check to make
sure you&amp;#39;re part of the NYC chapter so that you don&amp;#39;t miss any
exciting announcements or events. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Read the tweet below for instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;NEWS: The NYC &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/csteachersorg?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@csteachersorg&lt;/a&gt; chapter is moving platforms from Meetup to CSTA&amp;#39;s membership site!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;1. Join CSTA at &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ze7ix0491W&#34;&gt;https://t.co/ze7ix0491W&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;2. Select &amp;quot;CSTA NYC&amp;quot; in the Member Area&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/cs4allnyc?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#cs4allnyc&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/diane_levitt?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@diane_levitt&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/csnyc?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@csnyc&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CSforAllNYC?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CSforAllNYC&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UpperlineCode?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@UpperlineCode&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@ed_saber&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/learningdrive?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@learningdrive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ronsummersnyc?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@ronsummersnyc&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/5KBHeErZPT&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/5KBHeErZPT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Tom O&amp;#39;Connell (He/Him/His)  (@mrtomocon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mrtomocon/status/1273276485638504455?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 17, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting Our Students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/supporting-our-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 12:22:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/supporting-our-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Austin Cory Bart put together a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://acbart.github.io//2020/06/10/race-in-cs1/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about supporting Black
students in CS1. Cory asked about this on the SIGCSE mailing list and
in his post he both breaks things down and shares all the resources
that he compiled from the ensuing discussion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a lot of good stuff both in the post and in the links but
there&amp;#39;s a lot to get lost in. As teachers we can sometimes affect
change at a department or school level but we can always make a
difference in our classes and with our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I titled this post &amp;#34;Supporting Our Students&amp;#34; and not &amp;#34;Supporting Black
Students.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m certainly &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; pulling any all lives matter BS but
rather reflecting back on something that shaped my approach with my
students and started to open my eyes and that specific experience for
me was an all students experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I cut my teach at Seward Park High School down on the Lower East
Side. It was a high poverty school and a very diverse one. I had
top flight honors students, criminal thugs, druggies, sweet kids whom
the system failed and everything else you can imagine. The main groups
were classified back then as Chinese and Hispanic and then Black then
White but within those groups there were subdivisions. Shortly before
I got the gig the school had brokered an in school truce between the
factions of Chinese gangs and while the term of the day was
Hispanic the students were from a variety of places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One day I was talking to a guidance counselor in the hall. We didn&amp;#39;t
know each other - I shanghaied her in another conversation - I had
something to ask. She said &amp;#34;wait - you&amp;#39;re Zamansky right?&amp;#34; Yep. &amp;#34;I was
wondering who you were, all the students want to be in your class.&amp;#34; I
was confused. I wasn&amp;#39;t super popular - I was just in about a year and
a half. I also wasn&amp;#39;t so good. I&amp;#39;d rate myself as an above average
very raw young teacher but that&amp;#39;s about it. She explained that I was
one of the only teachers where students from all the population groups
wanted to be in my class. The Hispanic students, for instance all
wanted to be in Pablo Chang&amp;#39;s math class, the Chinese in another
teachers but apparently I appealed to everyone equally. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started to think about why that might be the case and it got me
thinking about what I had learned in my short time teaching. Prior to
teaching I led a pretty sheltered life. I went to public school up
until college and had a pretty diverse group of friends but as a kid
you can be pretty oblivious to economic and race related
differences. As an adult I went to a private college, NYU, and started off
at Goldman Sachs. Not exactly a recipe for awareness. I quickly
realized that not all kids learned the same, thought the same and
going further, lived the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It taught me that it&amp;#39;s not merely about talking to your students, it&amp;#39;s
about listening to them. Given time and the chance, they&amp;#39;ll open up
and you&amp;#39;ll learn about their challenges. When it seems there giving
you a song and dance, don&amp;#39;t assume they&amp;#39;re trying to pull a fast
one. Give them the benefit of the doubt. You&amp;#39;ll get burned now and
again by a kid taking advantage but things have a way of coming clean
and if you don&amp;#39;t give the kid the benefit of the doubt you can
irreparably harm your relationship. Trust is key in
education.  Besides I&amp;#39;ve been burned way more by giving the benefit of
the doubt to people professionally than as a teacher and at the end of
the day I&amp;#39;d rather lose sleep angry over being taken advantage of than
lose sleep feeling guilty for damaging my relationship with a student
for the wrong reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you treat your students like people - young people but  people
nonetheless and earnestly listen and try to learn from them and learn
about them that&amp;#39;s your guide. I&amp;#39;m not saying I&amp;#39;m particularly good at
helping my kids - I&amp;#39;m your stereotypical socially awkward computer
geek but the more I listened the more I understood the individual
issues my students had to deal with. My Black students, my immigrant
students, my poor students and all the rest. Sure there were common
themes but every one has a unique story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While we teach our assorted subjects to our students really at the end
of the day more so than teaching any specific computer science I hope
to be a force for good in their lives and their development as
people. The best way I can do that is to listen, try to learn, try to
understand and then try to help and support.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers and Police</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 10:56:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Teachers and Police 
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been an ugly few days but perhaps in some ways a hopeful few as
people have been making their voices heard like never before in my
lifetime. We&amp;#39;ve seen and endless stream of videos of peaceful protest
and far too many instances of police officers overstepping their
bounds. I keep hearing about violent protesters but those videos seem
to be avoiding my feeds as are the videos of law enforcement going
after the looters who are a separate group from the protestors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not comfortable getting on a soapbox about race relations in this
country. I want and strive to be an ally but I think my place is to
listen and support not dictate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even so, we keep hearing about police accountability on one side that
they need their protections on the other. I thought I&amp;#39;d look at that
and compare the job of a police officer to that of a teacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
My experience
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one side, I&amp;#39;ve been a teacher for close to 30 years. On the
police side? I&amp;#39;ve never been a cop but I was an auxiliary cop for a
while. I stopped soon after I went in to teaching. I was able to do it
while on Wall Street but teaching is just so much harder and more
draining that I didn&amp;#39;t have the energy. As an auxiliary cop I got a
bit of an inside view. I didn&amp;#39;t patrol the bad parts of the precinct
much - Manhattan Valley,  but I did a bit. I also got to interact with
the police and was listening to police radio during my tours so knew
what was or wasn&amp;#39;t going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Key Requirements
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Police
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sixty college credits or military experience, pass a written and
physical test, psychological test and then the Police Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Teachers
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Masters degree, standardized tests, student teaching although the
quality ranges from rigorous preparation to fly by night TFA nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Perceptions
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Police
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one side you have police as heroes. This is probably to an
extend residual from 9/11 grouping them in with firefighters and
EMT. You&amp;#39;ll also hear that they face death every day and if there
weren&amp;#39;t protections like qualified immunity you&amp;#39;d never have anyone
sign up for the job. We also keep hearing that the &amp;#34;majority are good
cops&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;only a few bad apples.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other side, ACAB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
Teachers
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand you&amp;#39;ll hear we&amp;#39;re the backbone of society and should
be paid more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other, we&amp;#39;re glorified babysitters who do nothing for pay and
pension. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-9&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-9&#34;&gt;
Reality 
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-9&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This post isn&amp;#39;t really about teaching so I&amp;#39;m not going to dwell on
that side other than as a comparison but education going remote has,
if nothing else, proven that teachers are anything but lazy
goodfornothings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the police side, video evidence shows that a few bad apples do
indeed spoil the bunch and when both police commissioners and police
union chiefs and even mayors repeatedly lie, distort and omit you know
we need some real changes. I keep hearing about the police needing to
maintain order and acting reasonably but with all those body cameras
plus police officers specifically at protests to film and document I
haven&amp;#39;t seen anything backing the police line. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to the police facing death every day? Yes, there&amp;#39;s always the
possibility of a bad encounter but in my time with the auxiliary I
can&amp;#39;t ever remember hearing a call for &amp;#34;officer needs assistance&amp;#34; nor
vary many intense situations. Most of the job was being in the
community. In fact, it turns out that most police officers go through
their entire careers &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2017/02/08/a-closer-look-at-police-officers-who-have-fired-their-weapon-on-duty/&#34;&gt;never firing their weapon&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, teachers in many schools face violence or the threat
of violence and are under no circumstances allowed to even touch a
student. We are supposed to deescalate. Is there a reason why police
can&amp;#39;t do the same? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-10&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-10&#34;&gt;
On reform
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-10&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some people are calling for more training but I&amp;#39;m not one of
them. I&amp;#39;ve had corprorate, teacher, and city training. It&amp;#39;s all CYA
garbage. It doesn&amp;#39;t change behavior. Eric Garner was choked
in 2014. Chokeholds were banned by the NYPD in, I think around 1993
and you can bet that was in the &amp;#34;training&amp;#34; officers received. Training
reminds good people how to act. Training helps give you a tool if
you&amp;#39;re inclined to use it. Hire a thug and no training is going
to make them an angel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m more on the defund side but that doesn&amp;#39;t just mean cut the
budget. Here are a few things I&amp;#39;d like to see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beat cops - this is something that David Dinkins did with
Commissioner Brown and they never get credit. They took the cop out
of the car and put them on the beat. On foot. Make them part of the
community they&amp;#39;re policing. Once they went back into the cars they
were out of the communities. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better accountability - when the next contract comes around we need
our politicians to take a &lt;strong&gt;hard&lt;/strong&gt; line on accountability. Things like
community review boards, penalties for turned off cameras,
transparent records on police misconduct. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make police accountable for bad behavior - while police need due
process, in the rare times there&amp;#39;s any accountability it&amp;#39;s usually
in terms of a payout to the public. This doesn&amp;#39;t affect the police
because it&amp;#39;s paid by the taxpayer. Let&amp;#39;s change that. The city
contributes to police pensions. Let&amp;#39;s reduce that as needed to pay
for settlements. If not, how about start with the police salary
scale and adjust it annually to pay for settlements. Make those
responsible feel it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The sad thing is that unless the protests continue there might not be
change. I fear that we&amp;#39;ll get a few speeches and some surface changes
when we need fundamental change. The solutions aren&amp;#39;t hard but we
need people in power who will actually implement them. de Blasio came
to office claiming to be a progressive but he caved to the police
force at the first signs of resistance. We need to put up candidate
who will actually represent the people and make changes and then we
actually have to get out and vote them in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Before condemning try walking in their shoes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/privilege/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 19:20:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/privilege/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve got some CS Ed stuff I want to write but can&amp;#39;t bring myself to
writing about it today. I rarely post outside of my wheelhouse - CS,
Education and the intersection of the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t really think I&amp;#39;m qualified to say much about the current
crisis. The out of control police, racism, class warfare, a failed
government not only at the federal level but also in New York city and
state but maybe I can share something worthwhile from my narrow
experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been seeing too many posts and tweets about the protests
condemning any rioting. I&amp;#39;ve never promoted violence but still I
thought I might have something to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The important background piece is that for those of us who are white
and who grew up with some level if privilege, it&amp;#39;s hard for us to
really understand the what oppressed people suffer.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started life in a somewhat well to do family, I attended private
school through first grade, then my parents pulled me and my
siblings out for public school - somethingn for which I&amp;#39;m now
grateful. Shortly after, my dad got sick, lost his job and later passed
away. That left my mom raising 3 kids on a teachers salary. On the one
hand we had the apartment, on the other I wore hand-me-downs. I worked
my way through school and payed &amp;#34;rent&amp;#34; living at home not because I
wanted to but because we needed me to. So, we weren&amp;#39;t well to do but
although I didn&amp;#39;t realize it at the time, I possessed great privilege
both in terms of my skin color and also in terms of what my mom was
willing and more importantly able to sacrifice of herself for her
children. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I got older my schools, though public were less reflective of
society. Populations were pretty diverse but I was brought up in
something of an intellectual bubble and under the belief it was a
meritocracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After school and a stint on Wall street, I went to teach at Seward
Park. What an awakening. It was my first exposure to kids and families
living under far harsher circumstances than I. When I was a kid I
volunteered at a soup kitchen. I couldn&amp;#39;t reconcile the family that on
the one hand had to come to the kitchen for food while the family all
wore really expensive sneakers (I was wearing the $10 Alexander&amp;#39;s
special). As I got more exposed to &amp;#34;how the other half lived&amp;#34; I
learned that it was more complex. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I went into teaching on a whim, as my career progressed I
realized more and more how important public education was and the job
became more of a mission. At the same time, as I learned more and more
about the populations that I tried to serve so that I could support them
and try to really know their circumstances. I realized that it&amp;#39;s really
hard to &amp;#34;get it.&amp;#34; I also realized that the more removed you are, the
higher up you are on the ladder, the harder it is. That&amp;#39;s not to say
that there aren&amp;#39;t many well to do people with huge hearts trying to
and doing good it&amp;#39;s just that I feel that the further you are from the
ground floor the harder it is to really understand the issues that the
ground floor people have to live with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, this brings us back to the protests and the rioting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Separating out the protesters and rioters we really have 4 types of
rioters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Criminals - people who are going to riot and loot whenever the
opportunity presents itself. Remember Philly after the Eagles won
the Superbowl?  These people are just criminals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Riots resulting from police instigators - well, we should condemn
the police and not their victims and we&amp;#39;ve seen a bunch of video
evidence of this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Riots resulting from white agitatos - same as the previous point. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Riots from within the protest group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last group - group 4 are the only ones who are part of the
protest groups but let&amp;#39;s not be so fast to condemn them. It&amp;#39;s easy for
those of us of privilege to point fingers and say &amp;#34;shame on you,
protest peacefully&amp;#34; but where has that gotten them? We were talking
about this earlier and I was trying to remember an earlier victim of
police brutality. I was thinking of Rodney King 20 years ago but was
blanking on the name. Devorah rattled off names walking back the
years. Two decades, countless abuses and nothing changed with
peaceful protest. There comes a time when you feel you&amp;#39;re out of
options. It&amp;#39;s easy for us to point and condemn but very hard to
understand. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Am I promoting violence? No. I feel bad about innocents hurt and small
business owners who&amp;#39;s property has been damaged but what about the
lives that have been lost or destroyed due to police abuse and
government inaction and in fact government support?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are solutions. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.joincampaignzero.org/#vision&#34;&gt;Campaign Zero&lt;/a&gt; has a lot of info on how to reform
policing. We also have to fully fund schools and actually deal with
poverty rather than make it a crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t have any inspirational message here or any real answers. The
work goes on. I&amp;#39;ll continue my work in public education try to support
my students and understand them and their challenges more and more and
try to be a better ally to those less privileged than I. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Covid-19 Journey (so far)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 07:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t been posting much over the past couple of weeks and that&amp;#39;s
partly because we&amp;#39;ve been under the weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yep - Covid-19. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First things first - we&amp;#39;re all either recovered or well on the way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I&amp;#39;d write up our experience as it might be useful for
others who are going through similar. This disease is weird and seems
to affect people differently but three of us followed a similar path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of our current status, I&amp;#39;ve been symptom free for a few
days. My sense of smell hasn&amp;#39;t fully returned but it&amp;#39;s starting to and
I&amp;#39;ve been fever free for around two weeks. I&amp;#39;ve been using a pulse
oximeter  and that&amp;#39;s been reading normal. I still feel a bit off in
the evenings, haven&amp;#39;t been sleeping well and get a bit of a headache
but I think that&amp;#39;s mostly my inner hypochondriac and the headaches
from the poor sleep. Besides, the headaches feel different than when I
was having symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Batya and Devorah have been clear for a week longer than I&amp;#39;ve been and
Natan hasn&amp;#39;t yet shown any symptoms so hopefully he got it, built some
antibodies and is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Batya got it first then Devorah then me. The symptoms were largely the
same. As they say - flu like. Fever, chills, low energy, head or chest
congestion and loss of smell and taste. I never fully lost my taste
(but then nobody would accuse me of having good taste anyway) but it
did dull. Batya and I also got headaches. They were a little weird -
kindof between a regular headache and a migraine. We never had bad
coughs, just occasional ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The actual fever/chills part lasted for about 3 or 4 days each. Never
got as bad as a bad case of the flu and we never felt we had to rush
to the emergency room but we all essentially took some days off for
work. For me, it was mostly being lucky - my class days and important
meetings fell outside my sick zone and I was able to focus enough to
do the planning I had to albeit not optimally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We never relapsed but recovery was slow. After the fever passed, we
all went through the &amp;#34;I think I&amp;#39;m feeling better&amp;#34; stage where we still
had some congestion and were feeling &amp;#34;off&amp;#34; but we seemed to go in the
right direction. This seemed to last forever but at least for me, one
day a few days ago, I finally woke up feeling pretty good. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By all counts we&amp;#39;ve been lucky. Hopefully we&amp;#39;ll have some level of
immunity - we&amp;#39;re going to try to get antibody testing to see if we can
give plasma. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the things to watch out for if you do got through this is the
lethargy. I&amp;#39;ve been in a funk for most of the past month. I guess that&amp;#39;s
because of the difficulty in sustaining focus when actually sick and
the stress even when you&amp;#39;re feeling okay. Over this past weekend
when I was finally able to restart a number of projects is what&amp;#39;s
making me feel I&amp;#39;m really out of the woods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s been our Covid-19 journey. I hope posting this provides
another data point for people - what it&amp;#39;s like for those of us who are
getting it but have been lucky so as not to get it so bad. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hoping you&amp;#39;re all staying safe and healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email or USPS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-or-usps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 14:00:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-or-usps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
USPS is in financial trouble. That&amp;#39;s been pretty well documented
recently. Most reasonable people will recognize that the USPS is both
an important service and while it receives no taxpayer support would
be profitable were it not for the GOP imposing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.truthorfiction.com/is-usps-losing-money-because-of-a-2006-pension-law/&#34;&gt;unfair and unrealistic
pension funding requirements&lt;/a&gt; in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although I&amp;#39;m an ardent supporter of the post office and feel that
privatization of such an important intuition would be criminal today I
want to talk about some small repercussions of so many things going to
email rather than snail mail. Small in the greater sense but maybe
pretty big to the people affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in the old days college acceptances went out via old fashioned
paper mail. It took a bit of time but it was super reliable no matter
where you lived. Nowadays I&amp;#39;m pretty sure college acceptances are
still sent out via USPS but you can also find out online. That&amp;#39;s
terrific. The potential issue comes up for opportunities that are only
announced via email. This is the case for my program and also for a
number of other college and university honors program that I&amp;#39;m aware
of. Part of this is certainly due to timing as the window from getting
applications to confirming participation is very small but it&amp;#39;s still
unfortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past year, I&amp;#39;ve had a few cases of bad email addresses. For one
reason or another I had to reach out to a candidate only to get the
email bounced back. This isn&amp;#39;t really horrible as I&amp;#39;ve always been
able to hunt down a correct address either through Hunter or through
my friends teaching at the high schools. The real problem is that
students don&amp;#39;t always read or see all their emails. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had a student who applied for my program with an active email but
their high school school somehow sent over to Hunter one that the student didn&amp;#39;t
use. Had I not caught it by chance that student who&amp;#39;s now with us and
doing great wouldn&amp;#39;t be. In another case I was talking to a student
who by chance new another student who we offered a seat but never took
it. It came up in conversation that this kid was very unhappy at the
college they ended up going to. I asked why they didn&amp;#39;t take our offer
to be in the Daedalus program. We later found out that the student
never saw the offer. It either went to a non-used address or a SPAM
filter or was just buried in the inbox. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a problem. Not so much for those of us running these
programs - we&amp;#39;re going to fill with qualified, deserving
students. Rather for qualified and deserving students who miss out on
the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When something goes out via USPS we can be fairly certain it will at
some point in the near future be in the hands of the intended
recipient. USPS is really good at that. With email, we can&amp;#39;t always be
sure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passover 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/passover-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:59:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/passover-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday was the start of Passover and like many others we weren&amp;#39;t
able to physically gather with friends and family to
celebrate. Since the Talmud, unlike the NYC Dept of Education, doesn&amp;#39;t
seem to ban Zoom, like many others, we used Zoom to connect with
family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tonight we&amp;#39;ll do it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the meantime, I thought I&amp;#39;d share this small bit of research Natan
did a couple of years ago on a traditional part of the seder: &lt;a href=&#34;http://seccorecit.blogspot.com/2018/04/a-historically-informed-echad-mi-yodea.html&#34;&gt;A
Historically Informed Echad Mi Yodea&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest Post - Missing out on a great opportunity in education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 06:53:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Preamble
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never accepted a guest post before but when my friend and long
time colleague JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver said he had something to say I
was all for it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JonAlf&amp;#39;s one of the best teachers I know - he started at Brandeis HS and
has been at Stuy forever. Really sharp guy, great teacher, and really
perceptive. When he has something to say it&amp;#39;s 100% worth listening
to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To JonAlf - since I know this is one of my blog posts you&amp;#39;ll actually
read - you should set up a blog of your own. The community would be
all the better for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Missing out on a great opportunity in education
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
By JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the COVID-19 crisis, educators across the nation are
adapting to remote learning. Ive watched my colleagues work hard
putting together plans on how to deliver content, engage students and
assess their learning. Some, like myself, are combining multiple tools
in order to achieve these goals while others are using a single
platform for it all. I count myself lucky that the administration in
my school has given its teachers the leeway to select their own tools
instead of forcing a single platform on us. Last week, as I was
thinking through what my plan was going to be, a particular thought
kept nagging at me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We are facing an amazing opportunity in the world of education. Think
of how many lessons, worksheets, notes, examples, etc. are being put
out in some electronic form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Students will (hopefully) have access to the materials for their
classes, and teachers in the same school may also be able to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will never be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about the teacher three states away thats struggling to find good resources or new problems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will never be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about the student in a different district, perhaps one that has
shut down entirely, who just wants to learn and do some work in order
to help fill the days?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will never be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The internet gives us the ability to put all of these resources out
there to the public, and it pains me to think about how much of this
work is going to be hidden behind one platform or another. So many of
the educational technologies make it very easy to post work for your
class and very hard, if not impossible, to share it with other people
(youre school doesnt also have a license for XYZ?, sorry).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, there are many teachers out there that have no choice, they
are being mandated to use whatever the school decrees. There are
others, perhaps the less technically savvy, that are going to use
whatever they can get trained on quickly. Were all running a 2 minute
drill and working with what we have. I get that, and it is not a
teachers job to provide materials for everyone. That being said, If
you have the knowhow, or would like to learn, there are ways to make
your work publicly available. Last summer Mike and I ran a session at
the CSTA conference on using GitHub for just this purpose, and hope to
run a workshop on it this summer (For those interested, I made a brief
tutorial about how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KzSE_H3rfMs&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KzSE_H3rfMs&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For my part, Ill be putting everything on my class websites, if you
need any ideas for intro to cs in python heres my class:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/intro1-dw/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/intro1-dw/&#34;&gt;https://www.stuycs.org/intro1-dw/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. If yourre looking for advanced cs,
Ive got a computer graphics class here:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/graphics-dw/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/graphics-dw/&#34;&gt;https://www.stuycs.org/graphics-dw/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brazilian Carrot Cake</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/carrot-cake/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 15:55:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/carrot-cake/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/carrot-cake.jpg&amp;#34;/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not my normal post but these are not normal times. Besides, this isn&amp;#39;t
the first &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-05-02-flatbreads.html/&#34;&gt;recipe&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#39;ve posted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m one of those that will, as long as supplies allow, bake and cook
my way through our shelter in. Today I made Brazilian carrot
cake. It&amp;#39;s not quite the same as an American carrot cake as you&amp;#39;ll see
from the recipe below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, carrot cake rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Obviously since it contains carrot which is a vegetable, it&amp;#39;s healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t ice it and serve it before evening, it&amp;#39;s carrot bread and
therefore a healthy option for breakfast, brunch, or snack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Only when you add the frosting or icing does it become carrot cake and
hence dessert. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This recipe is the family recipe of one of my daughter&amp;#39;s coworkers. I
can only imagine it&amp;#39;s from some Brazilian grandmother and hence the
measurement of &amp;#34;3 large carrots.&amp;#34; It makes me think of recipes that
I&amp;#39;d get from bubbe or my mothers bubbe - &amp;#34;add 2 cups of sugar.&amp;#34; Of
course she was talking about 2 empty yartzeit glasses of sugar. I have
a relative who followed around here grandmother an before she added
any ingredient for a recipe put it in a standard measure to 
convert the recipe to something that we could make sense of today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Okay, now on to the recipe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Ingredients
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Cake
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 carrots, peeled and sliced)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 eggs (large)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 cup oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cups sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cups flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Brigadeiro sauce
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 can sweetened condensed milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 tablespoons of cocoa (or use some other chocolate and melt it in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Buttermilk Glaze
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I sometimes use this instead of the brigadeiro sauce&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2/3 cups buttermilk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 to 2 cups powdered sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Directions
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Cake
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Preheat oven to 350
Prepare pan (I line the bottom with parchment and grease)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix sugar, flour, baking powder in a bowl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blend carrots in a blender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add oil and eggs to blender and blend all together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fold carrot mixture into dry ingredients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pour into prepared pan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bake for ~40 mintues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Bigadeiro sauce (if using) 
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;combine all ingredients in saucepan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cook, stirring until thickened (about 10 minutes) 

You&amp;#39;ll know it&amp;#39;s thick enough when you drag your spoon across the
pan and you can see the bottom. It will thicken up considerably when
it cools so better if it&amp;#39;s looser rather than thicker.

spread on cake while warm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
Buttermilk glaze (if using)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;whisk together glaze ingredients until smooth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;poke holes all over cake with a fork or knife&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pour / spread glaze on cake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Career Directions - how a sad day changed mine</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/career-directions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 14:39:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/career-directions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was talking to a friend yesterday who had just started doing grad
work in school leadership. It got me thinking about my original career
plans and how you never know where you&amp;#39;re going to end up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, not my original original career plans. When I started on Wall
Street I had no idea what the future would bring. For all I knew, I
could have been a career professional programmer or even gone over to
the business side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started teaching, it was as a math teacher and back then, I
thought that if I were to do it for my career, it would probably be in
math with maybe a smattering of CS. I had reached out to DOE once
about a greater role for CS but this was in the very early 90s and was
summarily dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was September 1996. I had graduated my first class of CS students
having taught 4 sections of APCS-AB and one of Comptuer Graphics - a course I
created to get out of teaching Geometry. I had just started the
Systems course and given the culture of the school and the trends of
the times it looked like I&amp;#39;d be able to teach all CS for the
foreseeable future if I so desired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My friend and mentor Richie Rothenberg was the math chair. Richie, or
Doc as we sometimes called him started to talk to me about succession
plans. Richie was going to turn 50 that spring. In five years he&amp;#39;d
both hit retirement and his kids would be done with college. The plan
was to groom me as his replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sounded like a good idea. I enrolled in Hunter&amp;#39;s school leadership
certificate program and we were on our way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Early that spring, Richie called me in to his office and told me that
CS enrollment had skyrocketed. He was my boss but wanted to know if he
could be the other CS teacher, shadow me and follow my lead as the CS
guy. I was super psyched for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If things went to plan, Richie and I would have split CS for the next
few years while I took on a larger administrative roll and then when
Richie retired, I&amp;#39;d take the reigns. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If that happened I probably wouldn&amp;#39;t have pushed for more CS and
history or at least my history would have been very different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What happened?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
May 15 1997. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Richie, on his 50th birthday, driving home, suffered a heart attack,
crashed his car and passed away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was devastating. For me and for the school. I wrote a bit about
more about Richie &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher.html/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich.html/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t yet have my license and in any event wasn&amp;#39;t ready. The
principal chose Danny Jaye, another great friend and mentor for the
position. I&amp;#39;m pretty sure that up until then Danny had no real desire
to be department chair. He seemed happy ruling over his math reserach
domain and working int he dean&amp;#39;s office.  Danny would adopt the
moniker &amp;#34;doc&amp;#34; but we&amp;#39;d also refer to him as &amp;#34;The Maestro.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I would finish getting my supervisors certificate but would never use
it and ended up forging what has been my path in the CS Ed
space. Danny would not only take Stuy&amp;#39;s math department to new places
but also led revolutionary work in NY City and State in terms of math
education and their math teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Had that tragedy not occurred on May 1997, for better or worse I
probably never get involved in the greater CS Ed movement and only a
select few at Stuy end up benefiting from Danny&amp;#39;s work (and Danny, as
a side note is an amazing teacher - back in the day, he got my brother
Steve to both understand calculus and enjoy calc class).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Talking to JoAnn had me reminiscing about all of this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I still miss Richie and  tear up when I think about him but that is
the past. That event was horrific for Richie, his family and friends
but also changed a number of life trajectories. Funny how that works.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;m looking forward to in 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/looking-forward-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 12:45:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/looking-forward-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Happy new year to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been reading some prediction posts this morning on blogs and
social media. Big national and world level stuff. I&amp;#39;ve never been much
for predictions so I thought I&amp;#39;d share some more local and personal
things I&amp;#39;m looking forward to in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First a couple of big ones. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m just about to complete my fourth year at Hunter. Time really does
fly. It&amp;#39;s been a long road but late in 2019 NY State finally approved
our CS Teacher Certification programs!!!!  That&amp;#39;s big news. Some day
I&amp;#39;ll go into the frustrations and ridiculousness that caused a year
plus delay but now that&amp;#39;s all in the past and we&amp;#39;re good to go. We&amp;#39;ve
got a Masters program for aspiring teachers and a certificate program
for teachers who are already licensed in another subject area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The plan is to run a summer intensive in July and have our first
cohort through the program by the end of 2020. We have a real
opportunity here to get ahead of things and build a group of certified
master CS teachers in and for NYC. This can be relly big and is very
exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other big thing for me has to do with the other big initiative I
started at Hunter - the Daedalus CS Scholars program. The program has
been growing each year both in terms of students and in terms of
programs and student opportunities. The exciting thing for me is that
we&amp;#39;re about to have our first graduates. The Daedalus program didn&amp;#39;t
exist four years ago and now it&amp;#39;s a big part of Hunter CS and soon it
will be sending graduates out into the world. I&amp;#39;m super happy and
proud of what the students have done and continue to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both of these really excite me. When I started, I figured it would be
about five years to get things running smoothly so to have both in
existence in 4 is super cool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other things I&amp;#39;m looking forward to? I&amp;#39;ll be giving a talk at SIGCSE2020
in a couple of months on how to take your students from GitHub
neophytes to pull request masters and then a full workshop version at
CSTA2020. I&amp;#39;m stoked about going to both conferences and also to help
Devorah once again run her  &lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;Blanket Statement&lt;/a&gt; project at CSTA.  If I can get the
funding there are also a couple of other conferences I&amp;#39;d love to
attend. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also looked over the list of speakers for CSTA2020 (harder to
navigate for SIGCSE) and am really  excited to see many friends
present. Also noticed Mark Emry will be presenting and really hope to
see Mark in person after something like over a dozen years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the personal side of things, Batya moved into her own apartment
just before the new year and Devorah&amp;#39;s setting up Batya&amp;#39;s room as a
fiber studio so we&amp;#39;ll have some adjustments on the home front but all
good and all exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m sure there are other exciting things to come in 2020 but that&amp;#39;s
enough for now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waterfalls - a trip report</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/waterfalls/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 19:18:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/waterfalls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
No, this post is not about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model&#34;&gt;Waterfall development model&lt;/a&gt;. Devorah
and I had a chance to take a little vacation up north.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First stop, Niagara Falls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/ZO1ALFs-adEiSXZiaHi7CTDl3GjdFr6x2D2zTzdW8__EeUH9TYp56pkcV4xeXqRk9E3bw0FcqJL_BpXgxKBR4GaOmqKhYffd-htNgIo7_IG4uQmKNzqyF4XHgb_B9iNKfson0P-uAnbVR9pmD7QlRRGfgAV6Ud9R39FvhB84n60y2RJCc5juo0iovB1qP7uuw6zjxP-7NfXWFmNk-8qdEqj0WNiwg8T-AeEwF3sdpLeD1IF9fWQGAky7akDvraG5fRnvM9REg9FuLSqlOBc1eX4J7HNE36FRILibiuxBQjFhBM9CKRS78-4eHD-EBsrpRxj7rJ0ds65txkq7_yubpd_yYyWYIWnIH81iDPdgw2K8TWHBVZuVmpgnKvkkFQ-wTzDthdilc1fyhWLyEms88K7JLloU3dLtIcGIZVi0TV0eLYjrJdK0ElgpolPJCpiDSU6Ic2roDXpJPyicuSgQ43N2XEsFStaJ2907pUvVkdZ1LzwmRkuOvTjLzfgcrVQbSiyfMAr9ftIPDylrv7xlvP-CxlhMjtAApLCSylizPXEmz2HozTQQFIbSFcX60GMXXSlES2lJG2rfezLCc4IfAmRxQ71ee3aEKznydjCwBpe9FICZkqwywykyUWgYrShuEclPsqKctU9cYZSx0qYpiRF8Y9S2qzJdkO0YZScY9h94RRqRA_JRr6xdmfBbHso9o1ylyrVQJ_NDIJjXdKSnOMwLJQ=w1495-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-TOrr0_0Q98rMZniXAUfalKk-PoB5wc03jeP4M6GCcu-lVmNtSjq5CDX3XT7BzMpntm1wsCI6AFjwAg7ZD3JFrxehhNd0FPKWMesVPuisx6bf6jCskGbE16KbSY09BzrL_dyl9vJHg-TKWEfYwzlWRQ5cvsRlDSd4YRbY5D5zPAb5RQGJvMooPLt0GrPe8ecPBgFlpnlkLio_U4pkz6JH18jtl9CkvC2yZiXUHwi4g5j0zUdJ4wquoWWDoahG0MwizIjYcT3lBbKsSxCwG64647T7uRSvRcetDnWXUwUWYpwKa9cbVUBx4zi7IHXzA71fqkzyraY8YWgHIvfyFxjBWP9l8P5aONWtXcITqQoIVIWg5n-O-MlcfsVKU3YRUsnpwFX0-YpBKC_UpVqIXwRT9cEOEp359QpdKtcoJ9yUVOWpzf4M3owAcj4Q3cZmy1R0oZdcbpVH_YNcrjgWfr9PfhbyDyuzc4_NRLcME8xJYIPmCRbTis-I9KfKrRyGzdMnwjTR_bVzfuDgwmrPjZ_5HeJsev5-qBbvdfmvnEO3LgOwk2BsnbUFaNLUeJvWPPfhgwrLPcnagRUiDsDOvSewYY4VIc4XC_wmR7fmXJOlYPmoj6eQ-aQxKPDhq7eEMUzKJ7RLCEanYe9a1YKryvg12ySdTeA5YxR=w448-h336-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We did the Canada side 9 years ago when we did our Erie Canal bike
trip (you can read about that by checking out some of my early &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-08-05-erie-canal-day-1.html/&#34;&gt;blog
posts&lt;/a&gt;). This time, the American side. My take is that the Canadian
side is more polished and all private attractions - think Times Square
or Disney. On the American side, the town itself is somewhat run down
but the attractions are all state park making them well maintained and
affordable. We did the &amp;#34;touristy stuff&amp;#34; - Maid of the Mist and Cave of
the winds, both of which were well worth it and also things like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://parks.ny.gov/parks/105/details.aspx&#34;&gt;Whirlpool State Park&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nypa.gov/&#34;&gt;Niagara Power Project&lt;/a&gt; along with a few
other attractions. We got a nice dinner at the Niagara Culinary
Institute and an okay one in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurants-g48050-Lewiston_New_York.html&#34;&gt;Lewiston&lt;/a&gt;. There were a few things we
didn&amp;#39;t get to do and I&amp;#39;m not sure there&amp;#39;s enough to merit a return
trip but we really enjoyed the day and a half we spent at the falls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up was half a day at Old Fort Niagara about 25 minutes north of
the falls;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/fe73nED0eFzSJX9Se32R4CHtPPhOLMn6-gfsnBVH1seeBx20IpnavPSiigUow1t4O94nONeDn-M53hD1iSBR_sjqQlazR9QAECAYfPSmHRS5llPebxl6OkbWPCNCWt_hIDKe07UtWvT5isdRWyo9S9u5vXq3n7vESKkihfdl83oksWuAZBA3noPJ1HYbXLcDWsbIHPi66FLbzZITw1NRdOjNymQamUop5F6r7jOE7m0xh-q_laEupotVu8x8rtPinrZ42kpAHsdgjbBe7wtcccd3xQiP8vTmuB4wGsnrdZhhN1qgSrg-WMUEXfDRfClNARZy5EBhwiQ_-tboWVjhsxjomRbDVoMnxhVjSXHRc7Ipmd4wtxcJCBMXs-fUttvqLWtpPzVV3YqVY0DrmpVxTRPGX-JrBAr9zHZuPvQ8tCTK9HVJCUQ7PoITo3XL8mtp-npj4DeBiuleor9sexUwAcUddSVdaT6a93BLS0vfYzjDJ9ED_GlD-PVrhSEbH_dVBt9rBzG1nw5MCvwZ-I1BCXddRZkL__4djy8MrdjqMRX4VEbLY3Z3jAsa_txrny1gp3jb-E7apYU4QuW_LikZP9X4PSvXuVt_Dbj2qOKbzWH8WdWd3cS0jroEgsL-diQQwAJDeeUlcQJyDoM2FAfgfzUwSTZJD1oL=w1495-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/P5eGSb8exZx2H74LF3UFNAMcA_Px8vb0AjNCInbXIASUyzni0UU5Ij3hWodUAKIfkZHNx9dgWounHvTTeqrI1nF0N92Y1eObkff5ablIobpaky_9i_DGeqFj0iT8pdlvQhie8q9YZvV8AoegUUA40gWZHeVgatdtgw076smv4vBC8nqG_0aB5K4wDkH0qC__8JLCNq_AVns0QNbAsVn1GmppA31ZRhCCyGq8Y6igWOa084lOppPXTQF7pA7ZwdnyWNEx6YUncJ3XuU1cuDcwbQmIO8uek5DWDNpFSCuQRECtTadt_oFPMscsa7uPIyLwUTThvfWuhLSs0eo7zy-z-UcXDGwyZT8SH4WmlsdFtl9UW2n62TleBUZB2Q_LGzmGpqABofrjWSaCTQY-qwMV2xVq5IvV5-I-9na9myVWbgDFJajKkiCj5yLkBDkeh48kV_3fC6WMdJo_8byCJEoQkn5rAx3SwyOsdf7gcjZmECI57VNr8p-SmklEWEQso3unRW_rhHcBLWV819Z8fh-S8AxPVAomlcM9yWzunjkBpCTj5Q8fgjsek9ijaXQqY_RZqLOFXKNaMcQ6qbC8BrY2nXM2L2EUgyYFhq9He0xAurxmhgSHJRJJW9cftBnFjSZ2jusHRgJ6Zj0JAijmbBhgcQK9tXx4oJJ7=w841-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of cool history from both the war of 1812, revolution  and the French and
Indian war. We&amp;#39;re such a young nation so it was cool to see standing
structures from pre-colonial times.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there we drove in to Canada. On &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dougpete&#34;&gt;Doug Peterson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s suggestion we
stopped at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welland_Canal&#34;&gt;Welland Canal&lt;/a&gt; which connects Lake Ontario to Lake
Erie. It&amp;#39;s much wider than our own &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erie_Canal&#34;&gt;Erie Canal&lt;/a&gt; and ultimately connects
the midwest to the port of Montreal and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/7TAtafilPV9NvwDsHgAywreQFofk3e-tuQRVKhM0nCXK_aW64Qh3T1_CMkHAW5xCe_us69b6IoNZUzSSgCOKmZDlvZCdAHElozy0HMfS8OHjLRwZaUbmklXPtn51MqYq2DxE5tDIwqyUiX_PRyLqwqz_jEPVXtI8A-RHmixd2K2mzqEWS1y40fabhTEaEoDFdPQQUDmOXi8XW3ZvFh0Dtx3Z8tUGoauqQneHsiY6Elrb5i6GjT2igsCuZQl9GCzagN0_Tb9f0Jo9E0zoDM2LshVtw74rF-i6iEngMs_-tt_3_iA87jlYc_dR8h5fiNNCxf6NdNhj0gmlNd9xhJYJrRhvvJJXytE0wFpeNvcW6JWlZqN-vi1y9HrSVv5-qK5e4GaPEx4Qip-isIkkhanYMOyjbmU4OzPrepp7TLD-iCbwvtaRY0lP20_pIPcWNMakvZ2kYno13oIQkMaKxNwQE8kYYEpqwiYVhjxFVhFZ211q4iQpSA7czWzs-HKDAHaiBvsO5QybzD5MCfmqJJmKsJjm8mnmey6NLcJH0Yw5V2nqwiMvQjUs8_cpiNniGR_pNiQ_pg9eWpW669CrrbKVJtQQfHIn3bo8b6LT2I6p8oMdFr6Zn6LYl3fkck4BzE0hnKzjRTTf3ZYLvVGQRpUxyNFQ7OUHgehK=w841-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/KE4LGNqZnGWVGWzJtOq-hsRDucc4oAXZqT1uW8Y4qSwLs6Wj2ZFsl1OdT8-3UzRXFdw0tIUxq3jzPaD-6P8iBBPbY-vPcyynCaqM7AgEbQLCxtQ1Ihvpit4Kj7f_7w6jXCscTHTTi0pmRwswHvRbpw6bHQ2wsMb4IDVd-s8OWaJKqa-VDx4GTBtSjPugmHNahTMB3DO76BLUCBdAQkbHBU3FknzPRXhT5xX2wwTlVeIsJL4DUZoaRmwXtaA2nzi-akv5YPRxom4b4ilhH3MybebtbGrlaCRFYLjEaQvVXUFCamhm5B2wkmSZ3bFto3QwMGfiI_G03TsOg5_vf3GY1gQCKM5hety8C2ZIV-IcQg8wtt_RQIpiSf-hHSNrgKDLsdPoJMB8Z_nf8-mSZAtCi0JJb1DB0ExRJLGysLayt6oiQyITjf-WZKCrLDVaoWehjZ1kkV3BcZZumiEbwshAwLqrzh_5UGDmvGEO8YSRzC7Srhp0M2R5XO2VfeWrKjkVAqiLIoc_tih_tOl8YFf59fjo_--BcauaZI0rKu2q1NGPu0asL2PLwZBCD0RgIdJQwHJkA5MOxNhT3ReMKJaZ5r_MP5SCWJs8ICTYtg4wEVMUgPj6Wpj0ZriRDFj7iKYWz1wIy56f1sIxd1J11S1SOfdNhRBttvZzcrqpjVePm62HjV2Lyw6g50KgP1akI7pVqNgaxmZUBjTZbiudntIix2yt_A=w1495-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The image on the left is the cement barge St. Mary&amp;#39;s Cement II being
pushed by the pusher tug The Sea Eagle II. Using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marinetraffic.com/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; site I was able
to track it going over to Cleveland. That website is really cool - on
it you can track &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the boats. It also has an API so you can have
your students use it in class projects. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The image on the right is the same boat a couple of minutes later
after the lock emptied and lowered. Really cool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We settled in that evening in Hamilton Onntario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hamilton is known as the Waterfall Capital of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/lwrhZWCIFZfpSE2umVZZ970Soln9uv8pXztTajS_HL0cGDB_TWZy1TUVFpegO1t-_VgKXRPDn1xXl8A9XS2Y1kpPC0Zkwa0U4GL2zJsXgbebYkwv5OSzkdbd3vSCVPvBKg0tGp2q9ZSofLwQ14X6-r8wDV-qJaznFgy4kwDWFX2HDQCqgzToERtQNZwohM-_foWs4rFkuIlEp5JF_MnqDcRsJQvZIWIVQgMZ7C7zp4Na1Z73T_1h5IzZzEFZ3t2n7zjmVhNSL8mERoHjcMmsd1sEprre1uf5RTEoFWgAQCnoN4hDtyJPrO79zeCe_SKZGfH00m-Xn0gadFpm3r9msRaz4sI7Z1b8hvghxoN0ijeu39mQ9HhdTcuweJTioYmsFU35qNtjZuAWYxyEgQtiORVtzmzW9PFG27IiLFh7QuQcZK9FS5qsoXVcnU81-XdtiTgSrfqunfPk7zW7mc5NFhy8jxnt3-DcE0Pxi34BckLBme6wa-LsO1uyLQQ9KtPC174g9faDWQbHifEOiMcCG7VQGa1XBg7zlfdxi8b4Ts5NGzkQv3B1dMWXjP8CWEblxpMAMS_OQCNWwxLsOmZO-Z-7i3AZmaGat6d-tU0SevPv6P0ZDdxwIcvl5Zh8oswtuC3AMf6KDSbmCDsSVctRxUGURECXanyDW3wBMbYM6lqFKRYpcSCPzNknVDgrHYUboz3i6G9KHUbyx4lTJ46qrnypbg=w1495-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It didn&amp;#39;t disappoint. We didn&amp;#39;t get to the two biggest falls - Webster
and Tews but we spent a long day of walking the trails and did get to
see six or seven of them including &lt;a href=&#34;https://tourismhamilton.com/devils-punchbowl&#34;&gt;the Devil&amp;#39;s Punchbowl&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tourismhamilton.com/albion-falls&#34;&gt;Albion
Falls&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://tourismhamilton.com/felkers-falls&#34;&gt;Felker&amp;#39;s Falls&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s pretty cool that we&amp;#39;re still in the
city but are on these hiking trails. We could probably have done
another day or two just hiking the rest of the falls and another day
to see other local attractions like the botanical gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our last stop was &lt;a href=&#34;https://parks.ny.gov/parks/79/details.aspx&#34;&gt;Letchworth State Park.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Letchworth is truly a hidden gem just as the Ithaca area state parks -
Treman, Buttermilk Falls, and Taughannock but more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Beautiful waterfall and gorge views. You can go on a hardcore hike or
just drive from view to view. At the south end you&amp;#39;ve got the three
major waterfalls and at the north end the Mount Morris Dam. There&amp;#39;s
also some pretty good food at the Iris Inn which is at the south end
of the park. We didn&amp;#39;t stay there but if we go back, I think we will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you haven&amp;#39;t been and get a chance, you won&amp;#39;t be
disappointed. There&amp;#39;s a reason Letchworth is called the Grand Canyon
of the East. Not nearly as big or majestic but just as beautiful in
it&amp;#39;s own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Cp6aZxzJNS5ZZCMMu_CtIQNAB4p_M2_9T9qlROh7keHxJnIIsHik1QaupzyqXHqPVdYUD_S-FaJ25yiRtOcgL-YtL3oQbBDXG1zsQUy4hJtBPh2gRlRgNNPHwrtuYHMhEwflks6nqpyiQZtohN2Fxaz6-w95-YJlzV8ob4JJshVzrkAf9xTk3G0C6NDTMC9N1tdIMSr8-z8Y4M2HbsC8-T0YucUmJS4UyTJML4FaA4X9rbrKQKA5_biATYnfo56PDYunG6fPskH7qyfDOnZ-olp9NPzg3jEub5BThS5W2rZZ-8kgE0fmGUXecjd-bJf6ncIY9wmgA-PKH1xu-S6JykjWohbN37ADnc_3U3Phc3Hp71-qe9rZOfSk2HnD54xwz11ybH2i0n0_enfLWZGkm8n2u3LwzOsR-XenSw6yEqrBvexAq9khmn4xLHgBlajuuzYsP6XOOpNNKaNvScpTUEw4kWyHhyQZJMP6UUqT5mmxoNJ2Rg801fh-5qil69Lc-A7fjh5lQ2Hn1HVS5VCGYXRSnBeY6t70vGCbStiwl298Bb8l0rYHj-_bO6YSoDN1KzztcoNWgm-Y10KFyac5688H9cimISGzGBUhWFLy-EKnPHoulMINVy6ZXEu1Fa7TJS42nmQ7_9-FO8t0M8yZvAbJB3RFoHBZKhkOHedJBQWmEnbXYWKKWpWH1mlBU6ptcSrIWhnM-9jMZCA7vSQrMeYDpQ=w1495-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/fucLzS0UWdKXMzMHe9nIoGuqtG6T_qP31GM7uOa5ShlHJOWFwuXkvVbhUOVICBKP-x8lAxpf5vgu7UlU4_WB2Ynk9UuAgokLuKlFxqUBAM_h8TPq1NrtVmmi0oHABcPTv4UPlr5FwsZ8o2BcZpxVUkINOvQzqR8jY81qXzKCTU1gsy2adrW06HBk2FBxNEBnuNu0gBfjF1Oq4jcEcs2O4VNlpaXf9IGsWnCziwXFfXcQNp6WkjNwskGxffymEseUfjGzYoQzXs80OwrbKsHC0VYvnpwkj7CdZGlNOL6JQWMVV4F5_lw8THDmwjNYX1xczn2qHb51sdSRGqrADU2FSq478vsRwX37PmMP4VWct8KDEdQx-_2oRgrYNWlfVqXRAANZ4uQK9T3WXN0v0UnEtQlYkaotyjRhX95aeoPbdEz8z2VpjKfuu9rIOiuGW38RBKMLeA4723uFXAWVrp8e0FgbVBVAnSAx4TqO7BylD-QjHTZoX16QAVW3wbbeFXRwLjJCXs-QOuZrpa4s8Ks18YVvJn8WRrlGfLJmqVid1HupMlnMfpdE2SkYhhC29mu4tJRJn83kJkP85nPgeTj9P1oQG2kw2seyRDGpGiGud-EVOyq9zoaIZKm1TrlKONHEEwanWb44E-uO2hULcp_pAf1GJJF46pMsE-XjwZ7f0iUUkFwIxv9qWnrszyCYv74m0xvCfvjbGTj9V9yHVnDNVkdAEQ=w1495-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/9aFZ-ftnDFvn2QuZrwFuwBJgetPNxhPQ7rrNcrCM2VeF3JUyuq6TL26Cfal8v_PgpDjsrNWEiW_Mp6ug9u0hyEQzvd-4ZfMxNS6MAiNuk0TpIjgkX_ahfVrlcl0NF5YOAKVVl6wuzlXQFN7m4806ohTHQcgAELfF8ha7PIIgd-L6M4fr1MeC9MWmYuFeIAM3jKpsCI-yInJNUYHSec_mqFnHv4HBkvrC6HEH-pAy9HR-Xun1EWJBch0GOpp6QS0hdn5Maz26RUOCxcW1O8IzBIpORu1w-8qVFNl6b_ESwQvqcHpTOBZZ1aRlxGSs8pamafDhtldeS-e2ZOZ6JHHyIeuMVv7tATz7Aiwoapb_Giy7gtJme9A4In3O2dSj5OQKYVFksGIFeZJdQK7MkmhR7EFEqGXgfo4NOXMYXQgkSdIoFdFNSkk35M3UkebX5iWeVRHd1iGryW-Su5rLGqo-e4P6ZdAqBZo1aCFzpFLOBAxty48ckKd6qb9ONsBYBnclKArpJCM-QmxZ1tuEg052vk2_8VF1Hp5jPle9Eg7qHRZmvhRp4FLLR3lxMCnv4UVj_hv8ATcWlOmv0pQKiBSU7uaBE4z2FmesgAKMIF8jgib6uLiImD7T93qQ1ribKYTsE7Wk2TYdIX9FrsUqyKU9lV1-RvJFB1C_8-ous4_uGe1jpUZajOWS8Fd4AhPfkUd1yng6eqgM6XJccUadZAEgTUOvVw=w1495-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/bMS7PphU4bf6S3tNZ9SCow8vzFXB7SgHd8YV6GlqvKSqs2sQSvbspwSGZdMXpfm35WxNCfr1Pmt9_GZEx2KXBS0UGZJhOJj11S_a1yDQOFG-C2usQLrAwTwAFPABjORmI02lMjgp8QgrW3QI7N7SjZEupZoXmjAi9Np4IeejivDCe0wLqUKEfZIpi6rTh0_MpkH9UK3LZEtqBOqnHaE2T5qPMSy7WIZZGqtmLJxsTwQpBDAuzMuRiXcgoSWOs4LoO692zaKGhO65PSqmy6lJZC_hmspWN5mbrKIAgqswvNublAVcA8UfLDa2EtOHGG-sULUc-ZMmjK93TL6AVyTiOeOrEYgCWgDBzohSHgBvQaW8vMBvnu2foJ42h6r3TF9fapKyhXe1FH2qi9vlTu3Bs44WHrZi5rPTUt7acpCD2pdatg2r_b_0CKKP1MO0l7I1cq-1q162GqVyCON4aMN0xzFQ75CMUL_YOWX0LtjYSxRaCh6OkhtqwCOQpdELeoVO_qyF57zyFZxJEggHAB3awX_VA_TpzE-eEcGF0URM4QjT7JyR3D1-KC_HxesReBkDUn91YRCD522o0alO4468mPL4s4eAN1E4-rYb6wRYj7n0o0bPgUT1lg8TlSQPxl8ehy8q55_zijFvloje44O5Q9eC6xhYpWTRvIlaSpou5BT6LArf6_e4zVbms90m2Qst91CFUHLg20d3ARz_dMQpywcveg=w841-h1121-no&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ll probably head through this way again we still haven&amp;#39;t but want
to get to Toronto. When we do we&amp;#39;ll probably spend additional time in
Hamilton and Letchworth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now it&amp;#39;s back home and try to get in a few more restful days before
the semester begins.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Codeland 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 19:46:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent today at &lt;a href=&#34;https://codelandconf.com/&#34;&gt;Codeland&lt;/a&gt;, a one day conference in NYC designed for
developers in the early stages of their careers. Just as at CSTA, I
was there with the GitHub contingent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Codeland had talks and a keynote in a common auditorium, smaller
breakout workshops and a couple of small vendor areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent most of the morning upstairs in the GitHub lounge so I onl
caught part of one morning talk. Up in the lounge we, along with the
other vendors - IBM, Flatiron health, and Command Line Hero were
available to talk shop and hang out with conference goers. To be
honest, not too many people came by. I attribute that to the fact that
we were up on the ninth floor and the elevators didn&amp;#39;t work very
well. We were in a nice space with plenty of areas for conference
goers to relax, schmooze, get a snack and even play games but it was
too much of an effort to get to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also decided not to attend any of the workshops and stayed up in the
lounge. The workshops were targeted at new devs early in their career
so while some looked interesting to me, I didn&amp;#39;t want to take up a
seat from anyone who really could benefit from them,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, I relocated to the downstairs vendor area. That was much
better. Since it was right near both the snacks and the main
auditorium there was much more foot traffic. I also got to hear and
see all the afternoon talks since audio and video were available right
near where I was set up. They were pretty cool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, the best part of the conference was the ability to talk with
the conference attendees. On the one hand, I was there to talk GitHub
but I also had the chance to talk general tech with them. I got to
talk to people at all stages on their coding journeys. There were
undergraduate students studying CS, second career people either in
code schools or self learning, Former CS students who&amp;#39;s lives had gone
in other directions but now they&amp;#39;re looking to get back into tech and
more. I got to hear about the excitement of their adventures and tried
to give advice and encouragement to those having a hard time breaking
in to tech. Having shepherded so many people from neophytes to
professionals I&amp;#39;d like to think I could provide some guidance to some
of the people chatted with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know if there are any other conferences like Codeland but if
there aren&amp;#39;t there should be. It can be hard to break into tech and
Codeland created both a safe environment for tech newbies and also
provided really valuable content. I wasn&amp;#39;t familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codenewbie.org/&#34;&gt;CodeNewbie&lt;/a&gt;,
the organization behind Codeland before but now I&amp;#39;ll have to see if I
can have a sit down with them to talk shop and tech ed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A 10X Student Story</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ten-x-student-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 15:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ten-x-student-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There were a bunch of threads on the 10X Developer recently. You
know - that mythical beast that&amp;#39;s 10 times more productive than the
regular software engineer. I didn&amp;#39;t see any of the original threads
but I&amp;#39;m guessing they started with &amp;#34;your startup needs them&amp;#34; and then
moved to the &amp;#34;they can&amp;#39;t work with anyone&amp;#34; along with tons of fun
tongue and cheek 1X engineer tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It got me thinking about 10X students. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of what you think about 10X developers, 10X people do
exist - at least to the way I&amp;#39;m thinking about them. There are people
who in any given dimension are &amp;#34;better,&amp;#34; however you define that, than
other people. In our society, if they&amp;#39;re 10X in popular sports we
treat them like demi-gods and frequently when achievements are group
efforts, we, as a society designate one individual as the 10X star and
laud them rather than the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, there are 10X people. At Stuy, I&amp;#39;ve had a chance to work
with a number of them and I want to tell you a story about one and how
it affected the way I look at my students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s go back to the early to mid 1990s. I was teaching my first crop
of CS students. Many were math team aces. One in particular, Alex was
a superstar. Alex would end up representing the US in the
International Math Olympiad where he scored a perfect paper. He ended
up going right from Stuy to grad school even though his friends, the
math chair and I were trying to encourage him to start as an
undergrad. Why were we pushing Alex not to skip undergrad? Because
Alex was wired differently. While he was truly a genius with respect
to mathematics and he did pretty well in his other classes by turning
everything into a math problem he was not good with people. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
His friends spent years pulling him out of his shell and seemed to be
making progress but felt that if he ended up cloistered in grad school
all progress would be lost. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the end, he went to grad school but this story is about a
programming competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At some point, one of my students, Eliot, told me about the USACO and
that he and a few others wanted to participate. It would be one day at
Stuy - a Saturday I seem to recall. While Stuy was on the internet
back then, the competition wasn&amp;#39;t. We were working on IBM PS/2 machines
running DOS. The students would write the programs and run them, print
out their solutions and I would compare the solutions with the correct
answers. When all was said and done I either had to mail a disk with
the solutions or printouts, I forget which to Rob and Don in
Wisconsin. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the course of the day, participants would come up to me with
solutions and I&amp;#39;d check them off. At one point, Alex came up and said
he was done. I asked him to bring up his printout. I got a blank
stare. We went back and forth for a while with Alex seemingly being
recalcitrant about not bringing it up but he finally did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile, the other participants started to notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started to look over Alex&amp;#39;s code. Lots of variables. Typically named
X, XX, XXX, XXXX etc. Maybe there is something to the 10X dev not
being able to write code well with others :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I told Alex that I needed to see the printout with the input and
output. He looked at me quizzically. Again we had a few minutes of
back and forth and Alex went back to print out his results. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One again, the other students took note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, Alex gave me the printout with the results and I started
comparing the answers to the desired output - the answers were REALLLY
LONG integers so I had to check digit by digit. All the while Alex
looked at me as though I was nuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The competition concluded, we packed up and I took the stragglers out
for dinner at the local diner. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next week, some students apologized for Alex&amp;#39;s behavior. They
thought it was rude. Not as bad as what another math ace would do to a
teacher a couple of years later which caused that years math team to
go west side story on him and almost beat their teammate up for
disrespecting a teacher but still they thought Alex was out of line in
the way he treated me during the competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After thinking about Alex&amp;#39;s interactions with people, I had a
different take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My take was that Alex very much respected me. To him, at the start
when he said he was done, he felt that I was a smart guy so I saw how
trivial the problems would be for him to solve. He then understood
that rules said that he had to give me the printout of the programs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, to Alex, again, I was a smart guy so clearly I could instantly
see that his printouts were correct so why was I insisting on the
output? Finally when I had to compare the digits, Alex was very
confused. &amp;#34;Z&amp;#39;s a smart guy, surely he can instantly see that my
answers are correct&amp;#34; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alex wasn&amp;#39;t being disrespectful. He was showing me more respect than I
deserved. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My interactions with Alex through the rest of the year as well as
observing him with others confirmed this. This wasn&amp;#39;t a super smart
kid being a jerk and looking down on us mere mortals. Here was a kid
who saw the world differently and thought that the rest of us had his
gifts if not more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve had the opportunity to interact with a number of 10X
individuals. Some as students, some as peers and colleagues, and some
as friends. More often than not, in my experience,  they&amp;#39;re wonderful unassuming
people. They assume I bring as much if not more to the table than they
do and they value what I have to say. It&amp;#39;s my insecurity that makes me
uncomfortable if I don&amp;#39;t have my A game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sure, sometimes they&amp;#39;re jerks but most of the 10X people I&amp;#39;ve
encountered are anything but. The nice thing is that when I do meet a
10X who&amp;#39;s a jerk, I can remind myself that I know an 11X who isn&amp;#39;t so
I don&amp;#39;t have to waste my time on the 10X who is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ebooks, Nypl and Process Starvation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 12:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a big fan of E Ink e-readers. I had one a number of years ago. An &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mobiletechreview.com/gadgets/Astak-EZ-Reader.htm&#34;&gt;Aztak EZ
Reader&lt;/a&gt;. It was great. Small, cheap, and independent - that is, not
tied in to Amazon or Barnes and Nobles and I found myself doing a lot
more recreational reading with it. I still preferred paper for
technical books but for easy reading  there was nothing like having
tons of reading options always available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alas it sadly committed suicide by diving from my hand onto the hard
stone floor of the NY Post office as I waited on the passport line. I
tried other e-readers since then but found E ink so much easier on the
eyes. Not wanting to do my usual &amp;#34;schlepp all the books I might want
to read&amp;#34; on vacation a few years ago, I bit the bullet and bought a
kindle. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I originally had the EZ-Reader I loaded it with mostly public
domain books. With the Kindle, I have purchased a small number of
books from Amazon to go along with all sorts of goodies from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gutenberg.org/&#34;&gt;Project
Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt; but there&amp;#39;s also been one HUGE change in the landscape. The
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nypl.overdrive.com/&#34;&gt;New York Public Library&lt;/a&gt;.  Public libraries are some of our greatest
public goods and it&amp;#39;s unfortunate that they&amp;#39;re perpetually
underfunded. Where else can a kid or indeed anyone go on any given day
and spend time indoors with no expectation of spending money. What&amp;#39;s
more in addition to books and now movies and sometimes games they
provide all manner of community services and programs to and for the
public. In terms of e-books though, you can use the NYPL without
leaving the comfort of your home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
NYPL has a web site where you can search for and take out ebooks and
have them sent right to your kindle for 28 days at a time. If they
don&amp;#39;t have enough copies - something of a ludicrous point for a
digital resource, you can place it on hold. If it&amp;#39;s close to being
due, you can renew it unless someone else is on the queue at which
point the renewal request becomes a hold request. It&amp;#39;s all rather
seamless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My reading habits now regularly include taking out books from the
library and that&amp;#39;s led to an interesting resource issue - process
starvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In case there are any on CS people reading this, everything running on
your computer at any point in time is a process. Each process gets a
small slice of computer time and it appears that the computer is
running everything at once. Some processes have a higher priority and
can get a bigger slice of time. On older &amp;#34;batch processing&amp;#34; systems,
high priority processes or jobs would run before lower priority
ones. For example, in a university setting, jobs submitted by
professors would be run before jobs submitted by grad students before
those submitted by undergrads. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This of course could lead to some processes never getting run if
higher priority jobs keep getting submitted. There&amp;#39;s an apocryphal
story about a computer at MIT that had a job submitted in 1967 but
still hadn&amp;#39;t run in 1973.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So what&amp;#39;s happening to me? I have a number of free books just sitting
on my kindle as well as books that I&amp;#39;ve purchased. My friend Paul said
I had to read &amp;#34;Algorithms to Live By&amp;#34; so that&amp;#39;s thre. So is &amp;#34;Captains
Courageous&amp;#34; because I think I want to read it. There are also a bunch of
others. The trouble is, I keep seeing books that I want to read in the
library and I only have a 28 day window to read them, Most recently it
was &amp;#34;Sapiens&amp;#34; but before that it was &amp;#34;Turn Right at Machi Picchu&amp;#34; and
I read that right after &amp;#34;How Chance and Stupidity Have Changed
History,&amp;#34; &amp;#34;The Witch of Lime Street.&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;The Man with the Sawed-Off
Leg and Other Tales of a New York City Block.&amp;#34; As soon as, or before I
finish one, there&amp;#39;s a new one on hold and then on loan and the books I
own keep getting pushed back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Operating Systems usually implement process aging. If a job isn&amp;#39;t
handled fdor a long period of time its priority is increased. This
means that eventually it will be run. I guess I could do that and just
force myself to not read the next hot library book but I don&amp;#39;t kow if
I have that in me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busy Week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 07:32:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m glad it&amp;#39;s Saturday morning. It&amp;#39;s been a busy week. It looks like
there&amp;#39;s a couple more to plough through but hopefully then I can catch
my breath over spring break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why so busy? It&amp;#39;s the same old story - you&amp;#39;ve got all those projects
that you&amp;#39;re waiting on and everything comes in at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start off, it&amp;#39;s college decision season. The high school seniors
all know their options and are deciding where to go. While we&amp;#39;re still
considering some applications to my Daedalus honors CS program, most
of the offers have gone out or will go out within a couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started the week with an info session about the program. eBay was
nice enough to host. I&amp;#39;ve held this session there now for the past
three years. First time, I had about 20 attendees and am not sure if
it made a difference in any high school senior&amp;#39;s decision. Last year
we had about 40 in the room but this year we reached capacity
at 65. Each senior was allowed to brign a +1. Some didn&amp;#39;t, many
brought a parent but a few brought a friend. At the end of the
session, most of the friends sought me out and asked if it was too
late to apply. I told them where to fill everything out but
unfortunately I didn&amp;#39;t know if I would be allowed to consider them or
not. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also had about 10 of my current students at the event. This was the
first time I was able to have that many. First time, I only had a
handful in the program and last year we first had to reschedule due to
weather and most of my students had class on the rain date. Having a
bunch of current students there to mix and talk with the applicants
was proabably the most important part of the evening. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end, the high schoolers had left and the students and I were
BSing along with Paul, our host when Paul offered a tour and then went
into an impromptu tech talk with the kids. I really
wanted to get home to bed but the kids were loving it so I let it
ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all it was a great night for my current students and I&amp;#39;m hoping
also for the high schoolers but it was a draining way to start the
week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also had a big CUNY2X event last week on Thursday evening. Around
50 students interviewing with fifteen or so companies for summer
internships. We&amp;#39;ve had this event three semesters in a row now. It&amp;#39;s a
long evening but at the end of the day lots of students get both
interviewing experience as well as offers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Things also started to move this past week on our CS Education
programs but not in a good way. Rather than approving our programs
they came back with a bunch of questions. It&amp;#39;s rather frustrating
since we cover everything they want and then some but they don&amp;#39;t seem
to be seeing it. For example, we&amp;#39;ve got a big chunk of our topics
course where we&amp;#39;ll essentially cover full stack development light and
we cover way in excess of anything in NY&amp;#39;s forthcoming standards on
networks and systems not to mention things like cybersecurity,
accessibility, UX and more in that unit but the state said they don&amp;#39;t see
any evidence to that effect. So I had too start to take our syllabi and bloat
them with excruciating detail. Something I&amp;#39;ll be doing over the
weekend and into next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To add to the week I had to pack. I&amp;#39;ve been pushing for an office move
for about two years. When I came to Hunter they placed me physically
in the Ed school. It made sense - I&amp;#39;m officially appointed there but
I&amp;#39;ve done most of my work so far with CS. Even when my CSED programs
start, many of the students will be grad students or working teachers
so they won&amp;#39;t be on campus much except for when they teach. On the
other hand the CS undergrads are around all the time. Well, Monday I&amp;#39;m
moving to a new office right by the all the CS action. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also been a busy semester for my course planning. I&amp;#39;m teaching
data structures at Hunter for the first time. I&amp;#39;ve taught it many
times before but that was to a known audience with a different
toolset - Java instead of C++. To be honest, I&amp;#39;m not particularly
happy with how I&amp;#39;ve been doing. I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;ve been terrible but
I&amp;#39;ve left plenty of classes feeling I&amp;#39;ve missed my marks. I know
that it&amp;#39;s something I&amp;#39;ll have figured out and next time around I&amp;#39;ll be
back up to speed but it&amp;#39;s made planning and reflection more of a time
sink and it always bothers me when I don&amp;#39;t feel my students are
getting my best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, it&amp;#39;s been a busy week in a busy semester. For the most part, good
things happening but I&amp;#39;m really looking forward to spring break.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 17:38:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_right&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/monitors.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Got a new monitor today and wanted to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My old one was a 27&amp;#34; Hanns G. Actually, the old ones - my old set up
was 2 of them side by side. When I started at Hunter, I was given a
piddly small monitor so I tried to buy my own 27&amp;#34; Hanns G to bring in
but they were no longer available. The 27&amp;#34; jobs available then were
much more expensive so my work monitor situation has been sadly
lacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The 2 27&amp;#34; setup worked pretty well but then I read &lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/the-best-display-for-programming-8aad0be4227d&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post and did a
little research. It turns out that Costco has a great deal on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.costco.com/LG-43UD79-B-43%2522-Class-Ultra-HD-4K-IPS-Monitor.product.100378322.html&#34;&gt;LG
43&amp;#34; 4K&lt;/a&gt; monitor so I took the plunge. I also had to pick up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/EVGA-GeForce-Passive-Graphics-02G-P4-6332-KR/dp/B073VPKV26/ref=sr_1_3?keywords=gt+1030&amp;amp;qid=1552171987&amp;amp;s=gateway&amp;amp;sr=8-3&#34;&gt;cheap
video card&lt;/a&gt; to drive it since I was just using onboard video and my
setup is pretty old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s HUGE. I love it but am now working to figure out how best to set
things up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The added bonus is that I can now bring one or both of the 27&amp;#34;
monitors to work!!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re on the  market for a new monitor I have to say that I&amp;#39;m
really happy with the LG. Just wanted to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels in the Architecture - when they used to build schools like cathedrals.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 07:31:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the side benefits of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/&#34;&gt;visiting high schools&lt;/a&gt; is that I end up
going all over the city. This takes me to neighborhoods that I
normally wouldn&amp;#39;t have reason to visit. For a New York History wonk
that can be pretty cool even if you just limit yourself to looking at
the schools. A few of the schools I visited in the last couple of
weeks before the new year were self contained whole building schools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goddard High School&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FDR HS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Midwood HS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goddard was interesting because it was founded in 2008 and grew out of
the middle school in the same building. FDR was also interesting. It
was founded in 1965 which makes the building fairly young or at least
early middle aged for a New York City school building. When you
approach it, you see this small short modern looking one story structure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://proxy.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=http%3A%2F%2Fassets.nydailynews.com%2Fpolopoly_fs%2F1.1408243.1374717210!%2Fimg%2FhttpImage%2Fimage.jpg_gen%2Fderivatives%2Flandscape_635%2Fteacher25n-1-web.jpg&amp;amp;f=1&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hidden from view is the big rectangular tower that the entrance
connects to via a tunnel. I had an interesting conversation with the
school&amp;#39;s principal about how that came to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
James Madison and Midwood also have their own buildings and they are
both partially screened - that is, they have selective admissions for
at least a portion of their student population. FDR is particularly
interesting becuase it is frankly an &amp;#34;old school&amp;#34; neighborhood
school that survived the destructive years of Bloomberg/Klein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other schools I visited in that span were all housed in schools
that had been closed during the Bloomberg/Klein years and new small
schools created in their place. The original buildings were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas Jefferson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Franklin K Lane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christopher Columbus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Jackson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the coolest parts about visiting the older buildings is that
they were built in a different time. You have elaborate lobbies of
marble and polished granite. Beautiful murals and ornate
auditoriums. Unique architectural features like the ramps on the first
floor in Thomas Jefferson or the foyer in Brooklyn Tech (a school I
visited earlier in the year).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also have school history. In many of the buildings the walls are
still adorned with names of notable alumni.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Christopher Columbus boasts Sal Mineo,  (Anne Bancroft), and, well,
David Berkowitz. Andrew Jackson does pretty well for basketball with
Bob Cousy, Lly Daniels, Boo Harvey, and recent Knick Kyle
O&amp;#39;Quinn. Woody Allen and Mimi Sheraton among others went to
Midwood. James Madison has a political bent with Bernie Sander, Ruth
Bader Ginsburg, and Chuck Schumer. Finally, Thomas Jefferson was home
to Sylvia Fine, David Daniel Kaminsky (that&amp;#39;s Danny Kaye to you), Paul
Mazrusky, Al Lewis, and others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another tidbit I learned was about the history of Franklin K
Lane. Lane&amp;#39;s built in the Brooklyn Queens border. You can see the
hills of Forrest Park left from the last Ice Age rising up behind it
as you approach the building. Apparently there used to be a line of
paint denoting the border. Lane also saw a good deal of race related
turmoil throughout it&amp;#39;s history. I was talking to an alum during my
visit and he was telling me how that in his day, you either left the
building via the north entrance or the south one depending on your
crew and woe is he who got caught on the wrong side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, many of the older buildings were part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_Progress_Administration&#34;&gt;WPA&lt;/a&gt; from the New
Deal. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you do get a chance to go into an old school, take some time to
check out the architecture and the ghosts of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll leave you with a couple of pictures from Brooklyn Tech - mostly
because they were easy to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.khomarch.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/kevin-hom-architect-university-college-architect-brooklyn-tech-1.jpg&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/59aec48e9f7456bae98b8609/5ad7b923575d1f7d69412830/5ad7b93d88251b1250984d58/1524087471280/mural-image-bths-2.JPG&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bthsalumni.org/view.image?Id=812&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;#ZgotmplZ&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 09:55:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never been much of a New Years person. I get up really early and
so don&amp;#39;t usually stay up late and more to the point, as any teacher
knows, the year really goes from September through June with that
really long much needed  weekend that you regular folks call July and
August tacked on to separate years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This whole January first thing is really more  of a half time break or
perhaps an intermission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, I did start the calendar year productively - it was
warm enough for a run and on my way back got my first &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.citibikenyc.com/bikeangels/&#34;&gt;Bike Angel&lt;/a&gt; point
of the month and year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since I see January 1 as more of a mid year point than a start, I&amp;#39;m
not going to reflect back on what was or project what will be but I do
have a few projects that I want to make some headway on before classes
resum in a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost, I&amp;#39;m teaching Data Structures for the first time at
Hunter. Sure, I&amp;#39;ve taught it dozens of times but this will be
different. I haven&amp;#39;t done it in C++ since 2003 and teaching it in
college twice a week Mon/Thu for about 1:15 is not the same as high
school where we meet every day for 0:43. I&amp;#39;ve already been boning up
on my C++. Templates are much more of a pain than I remember them and
I still much prefer toString to operator overloading. I think once
I&amp;#39;ve written some more code and am back up to speed I&amp;#39;ll have a lot of
fun with the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other big project is that I want to make some progress on an
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/time-to-create-an-ethics-course/&#34;&gt;Ethics course&lt;/a&gt; that I want to have as part of my soon to be approved (I
hope) pre-service programs. I also want to make it available to
undergrads. I&amp;#39;ve been collecting thoughts and ideas for a couple of
months now and while I still believe that ethics is too important to
just be contained within a course - it must be woven through all our
courses, I do think I&amp;#39;ve got an overall plan that will result in a
very solid course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a couple of other projects I&amp;#39;m working on that I Can&amp;#39;t talk
about right now but I have no doubt I&amp;#39;ll be keeping myself busy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So to all the teachers out there, Happy Half Time and to everyone
else, Happy New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>