<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misc on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in misc on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 12:22:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting Our Students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/supporting-our-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 12:22:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/supporting-our-students/</guid>
      <description>Austin Cory Bart put together a great post about supporting Black students in CS1. Cory asked about this on the SIGCSE mailing list and in his post he both breaks things down and shares all the resources that he compiled from the ensuing discussion.  There&amp;#39;s a lot of good stuff both in the post and in the links but there&amp;#39;s a lot to get lost in. As teachers we can sometimes affect change at a department or school level but we can always make a difference in our classes and with our students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers and Police</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 10:56:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police/</guid>
      <description>Teachers and Police   It&amp;#39;s been an ugly few days but perhaps in some ways a hopeful few as people have been making their voices heard like never before in my lifetime. We&amp;#39;ve seen and endless stream of videos of peaceful protest and far too many instances of police officers overstepping their bounds. I keep hearing about violent protesters but those videos seem to be avoiding my feeds as are the videos of law enforcement going after the looters who are a separate group from the protestors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Before condemning try walking in their shoes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/privilege/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 19:20:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/privilege/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve got some CS Ed stuff I want to write but can&amp;#39;t bring myself to writing about it today. I rarely post outside of my wheelhouse - CS, Education and the intersection of the two.  I don&amp;#39;t really think I&amp;#39;m qualified to say much about the current crisis. The out of control police, racism, class warfare, a failed government not only at the federal level but also in New York city and state but maybe I can share something worthwhile from my narrow experiences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Covid-19 Journey (so far)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 07:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/covid/</guid>
      <description>I haven&amp;#39;t been posting much over the past couple of weeks and that&amp;#39;s partly because we&amp;#39;ve been under the weather.  Yep - Covid-19.  First things first - we&amp;#39;re all either recovered or well on the way.  I thought I&amp;#39;d write up our experience as it might be useful for others who are going through similar. This disease is weird and seems to affect people differently but three of us followed a similar path.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email or USPS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-or-usps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 14:00:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/email-or-usps/</guid>
      <description>USPS is in financial trouble. That&amp;#39;s been pretty well documented recently. Most reasonable people will recognize that the USPS is both an important service and while it receives no taxpayer support would be profitable were it not for the GOP imposing unfair and unrealistic pension funding requirements in 2006.  Although I&amp;#39;m an ardent supporter of the post office and feel that privatization of such an important intuition would be criminal today I want to talk about some small repercussions of so many things going to email rather than snail mail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passover 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/passover-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:59:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/passover-2020/</guid>
      <description> Yesterday was the start of Passover and like many others we weren&amp;#39;t able to physically gather with friends and family to celebrate. Since the Talmud, unlike the NYC Dept of Education, doesn&amp;#39;t seem to ban Zoom, like many others, we used Zoom to connect with family.  Tonight we&amp;#39;ll do it again.  In the meantime, I thought I&amp;#39;d share this small bit of research Natan did a couple of years ago on a traditional part of the seder: A Historically Informed Echad Mi Yodea  Enjoy </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest Post - Missing out on a great opportunity in education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 06:53:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</guid>
      <description>Preamble   I&amp;#39;ve never accepted a guest post before but when my friend and long time colleague JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver said he had something to say I was all for it.  JonAlf&amp;#39;s one of the best teachers I know - he started at Brandeis HS and has been at Stuy forever. Really sharp guy, great teacher, and really perceptive. When he has something to say it&amp;#39;s 100% worth listening to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brazilian Carrot Cake</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/carrot-cake/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 15:55:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/carrot-cake/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/carrot-cake.jpg&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;  Not my normal post but these are not normal times. Besides, this isn&amp;#39;t the first recipe I&amp;#39;ve posted.  I&amp;#39;m one of those that will, as long as supplies allow, bake and cook my way through our shelter in. Today I made Brazilian carrot cake. It&amp;#39;s not quite the same as an American carrot cake as you&amp;#39;ll see from the recipe below.  First, carrot cake rules:  Obviously since it contains carrot which is a vegetable, it&amp;#39;s healthy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Career Directions - how a sad day changed mine</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/career-directions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 14:39:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/career-directions/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend yesterday who had just started doing grad work in school leadership. It got me thinking about my original career plans and how you never know where you&amp;#39;re going to end up.  Well, not my original original career plans. When I started on Wall Street I had no idea what the future would bring. For all I knew, I could have been a career professional programmer or even gone over to the business side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;m looking forward to in 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/looking-forward-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 12:45:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/looking-forward-2020/</guid>
      <description>Happy new year to everyone.  I&amp;#39;ve been reading some prediction posts this morning on blogs and social media. Big national and world level stuff. I&amp;#39;ve never been much for predictions so I thought I&amp;#39;d share some more local and personal things I&amp;#39;m looking forward to in the coming year.  First a couple of big ones.  I&amp;#39;m just about to complete my fourth year at Hunter. Time really does fly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waterfalls - a trip report</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/waterfalls/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 19:18:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/waterfalls/</guid>
      <description>No, this post is not about the Waterfall development model. Devorah and I had a chance to take a little vacation up north.  First stop, Niagara Falls.      &amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;  We did the Canada side 9 years ago when we did our Erie Canal bike trip (you can read about that by checking out some of my early blog posts). This time, the American side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Codeland 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 19:46:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</guid>
      <description>I spent today at Codeland, a one day conference in NYC designed for developers in the early stages of their careers. Just as at CSTA, I was there with the GitHub contingent.  Codeland had talks and a keynote in a common auditorium, smaller breakout workshops and a couple of small vendor areas.  I spent most of the morning upstairs in the GitHub lounge so I onl caught part of one morning talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A 10X Student Story</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ten-x-student-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 15:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ten-x-student-story/</guid>
      <description>There were a bunch of threads on the 10X Developer recently. You know - that mythical beast that&amp;#39;s 10 times more productive than the regular software engineer. I didn&amp;#39;t see any of the original threads but I&amp;#39;m guessing they started with &amp;#34;your startup needs them&amp;#34; and then moved to the &amp;#34;they can&amp;#39;t work with anyone&amp;#34; along with tons of fun tongue and cheek 1X engineer tweets.  It got me thinking about 10X students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ebooks, Nypl and Process Starvation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 12:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ebooks-nypl-and-process-starvation/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m a big fan of E Ink e-readers. I had one a number of years ago. An Aztak EZ Reader. It was great. Small, cheap, and independent - that is, not tied in to Amazon or Barnes and Nobles and I found myself doing a lot more recreational reading with it. I still preferred paper for technical books but for easy reading there was nothing like having tons of reading options always available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busy Week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 07:32:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/busy-week/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m glad it&amp;#39;s Saturday morning. It&amp;#39;s been a busy week. It looks like there&amp;#39;s a couple more to plough through but hopefully then I can catch my breath over spring break.  Why so busy? It&amp;#39;s the same old story - you&amp;#39;ve got all those projects that you&amp;#39;re waiting on and everything comes in at the same time.  To start off, it&amp;#39;s college decision season. The high school seniors all know their options and are deciding where to go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 17:38:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_right&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/monitors.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;  Got a new monitor today and wanted to share.  My old one was a 27&amp;#34; Hanns G. Actually, the old ones - my old set up was 2 of them side by side. When I started at Hunter, I was given a piddly small monitor so I tried to buy my own 27&amp;#34; Hanns G to bring in but they were no longer available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels in the Architecture - when they used to build schools like cathedrals.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 07:31:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</guid>
      <description>One of the side benefits of visiting high schools is that I end up going all over the city. This takes me to neighborhoods that I normally wouldn&amp;#39;t have reason to visit. For a New York History wonk that can be pretty cool even if you just limit yourself to looking at the schools. A few of the schools I visited in the last couple of weeks before the new year were self contained whole building schools:    James Madison    Goddard High School    FDR HS    Midwood HS    Goddard was interesting because it was founded in 2008 and grew out of the middle school in the same building.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 09:55:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-year-2019/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve never been much of a New Years person. I get up really early and so don&amp;#39;t usually stay up late and more to the point, as any teacher knows, the year really goes from September through June with that really long much needed weekend that you regular folks call July and August tacked on to separate years.  This whole January first thing is really more of a half time break or perhaps an intermission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catskills Conf -  Knitting for Good 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 17:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/</guid>
      <description>Two weekends ago I took a group of my first year students up to Catskills Conf, an annual event that I describe as &amp;#34;light tech conference with a focus on diversity and inclusion meets summer camp.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ve written about the event before if anyone&amp;#39;s interested in more details. As in past years, Devorah ran her knitting for good project. In each of the first two years of the project, attendees of Catskills Conf learned how to know and collectively knit, crocheted and assembled a blanket for Project Linux which provides hand made blankets to children in crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2016</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/</guid>
      <description>Once again, it&amp;#39;s time for Advent of Code - a series of small programming problems released once a day.  I wrote a bit about it last year and you can still find last years problems here.  It&amp;#39;s only day three but so far, all of the problems look really nice for students in APCS-A or any similar intro course. I&amp;#39;m thinking of looking at a couple of the problems this week with my class at Hunter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College - Honors CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   It&#39;s been a while since my last post and a while since I started at Hunter.  Time to share a bit about what I&#39;ve been up to.  One of the better kept secrets in New York City is Hunter College&#39;s computer science program. It&#39;s been around for years and it&#39;s been that way for years. In fact, when I was looking to get my masters degree back in the mid nineties I carefully researched all of the area&#39;s MS in CS programs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving Stuyvesant</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Almost twenty six years. That&#39;s how long I&#39;ve been a NYC public school teacher. Most of that time at my alma mater, Stuyvesant.  A couple of years ago, the school paper wrote up an overview of my career. I re-posted it here. I&#39;m somtimes amazed at where we are now and how we got here.  Regulars here also know my frustrations. To Stuy, I&#39;m an interchangeable, generic math teacher and the DOE has shown no interested in supporting what we&#39;ve built.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    Has everyone seen Advent of Code?  It&#39;s a site with a series of programming problems that are being revealed one a day, a la an advent calendar. You can read more about it here.  I came to the party a little late so I&#39;m only up to day 6.  Each problem comes in two parts. The second is revealed after you complete the first.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Bell Tower</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-06-bell-tower/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-06-bell-tower/</guid>
      <description>No Edu-Rant today nor a clever lesson plan.  I just thought I&#39;d share an email exchange that cracked me up.  We&#39;re out in Ann Arbor visiting our son Natan who is in his first year at Michigan.  Devorah sent an email asking where we should meet.  It turns out that Natan&#39;s last class of the day is Music Composition.  Here&#39;s what followed:  Natan:    Composition is in the bell tower on Central.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coding schools - or why I chose NYCDA</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda/</guid>
      <description>Some of you might have noticed that a few months ago, I decided to affiliate myself with The New York Code and Design Academy or NYCDA. I took on the role of &#34;Academic Director, Youth Programs.&#34; It&#39;s a part time gig, at least for now and I&#39;m helping them develop their programs for middle and high school students.  Why did I choose them?  There are a number of coding schools with varying levels of hype around them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How it all began</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    This past week, Garth Flint wrote a couple of posts on how he got to be a CS teacher and on being a CS teacher. You can find them here: Part 1 Part 2   They&#39;re both well worth a read.  It got me thinking about how I got my start.  I never planned on being a teacher. I figured I&#39;d just work in tech.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I guess some people like the blues</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Funny story from yesterday.  Devorah, my better half, is an assistant principal at another high school. Yesterday evening, she was at work late for &#34;curriculum night.&#34; Parents came to the school after hours to hear a variety of presentations.  During her presentation, Devorah mentioned her name, that she had two former public school kids in college, and that&#39;s about it for the personal info.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suspension if disbelief and the Mikado</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   I was brought up on Gilberg and Sullvan. My father, who always wanted to be an opera singer sang with LOOM back in the day and there was always classical music playing. Either from the Hi Fi or my father singing.  Recently, there&#39;s been a kerfufle over what was to be NYGASP&#39;s production of Mikado.  My son, Natan wrote a terrific blog post on it and the suspension of belief in opera.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just another day at StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   .photo {width:60%;}   Last post was a little heavy so just a short fun one for today.  &#34;Just another day at StuyCS.&#34; That was the subject of the email Brian sent with the photo above. What&#39;s going on?  We&#39;re working on advanced JavaScript while also looking at Backbone.js.  Now, as sometimes happens, Batya, while in her CS class up at college, decided to open up a Google chat with me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A chocolate treasure in a city losing its soul</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-13-myzels/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-13-myzels/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}    I&#39;m a born and bred New Yorker and more and more I&#39;m lamenting what the city&#39;s becoming.  New York used to be a collection of neighborhoods. Yes, we were the city that never slept, but there were scores of mom and pop stores, sole proprieterships. You could become a &#34;regular.&#34; I&#39;m reminded of Tom Shachman&#39;s book Around the Block which looks at the businesses around a single NYC block, mostly all gone now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Ed Predictions 2015</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-04-predictions-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-04-predictions-2015/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   I just read Alfred Thompson&#39;s predictions for next year. I was going to leave a comment but since it would have gotten somewhat long winded, I thought I&#39;d comment in a post of my own.  If you haven&#39;t read Alfred&#39;s post yet, check it out: http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/01/computer-science-education-predictions.html On more states allowing CS to count for a graduation requirement:  Alfred&#39;s probably right but I&#39;m leery. Sure, it could end up terrific but I could see a number of ways this could play out badly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boys, Girls, Arts, Tech, and Vacation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-03-vacation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-03-vacation/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Spent most of vacation relaxing. Finished off the remaining college recs, tried to catch up on sleep, and worked on a few project.  We&#39;ve had an interesting December break dynamic in our household for the past few years. My son, Natan is very much into his music, both as a performer and a composer. A few years ago we discovered KlezKamp. It spoke to both Natan and Devorah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A birds eye view of my career</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-17-stuycs-spectator/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-17-stuycs-spectator/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   It&#39;s hard to believe that this is my 25th year teaching and that my first StuyCS class graduated in June 1995. It&#39;s really hard to believe that I&#39;m now looking at the end of a significant part of my life and career.  Over the summer, Mariya, Kachun, and Stella, all writers for Stuy&#39;s Spectator worte an article that chronicled StuyCS. It&#39;s a really nice piece.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dream It, Code It, Win It</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-01-dream-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-01-dream-it/</guid>
      <description>div.center {text-align:center;}   Last night, I attended the Dream It, Code It, Win It awards.  I&#39;d actually write up the event but Fred Wilson&#39;s already done a better job at that than I could: http://avc.com/2014/05/dream-it-and-code-it/  As Fred stated on his blog, it&#39;s a real shame that the high schooler&#39;s didn&#39;t get to show off their work but it was great to see that there were entries from a variety of schools including The Academy for Software Engineering and The Young Women&#39;s Leadership Academy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tapia 2014</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-09-tapia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-09-tapia/</guid>
      <description>Spent the past few days at the Tapia Conference in Seattle.
The Tapia conference is billed as a &amp;ldquo;Celebration of Diversity in Computing.&amp;rdquo; The bulk of the attendees seemed to be students. Undergrads and grads. The undergrads were mostly juniors and seniors, but a bunch of freshmen and sophomores were there as well. Of course there were faculty members to join them as well as people from industry.
What was I doing there?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from Pete Seeger</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-30-pete-seeger/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-30-pete-seeger/</guid>
      <description>This past Monday I, like may woke to hear about the passing of Pete Seeger. Ten days earlier we were up at Symphony Space for the &amp;ldquo;Woody&amp;rsquo;s Children&amp;rdquo; 45th Anniversary Concert. Pete was supposed to perform but was ill. At 94 years of age, I wondered if the end was near. I was at the concert with my family as well as with my buddy Ben. Fitting since Ben and I grew up on Pete&amp;rsquo;s music while many of our peers did not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plans for the New Year</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve never been one for New Year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions.
If I&amp;rsquo;m working on something specific, I might set a goal to finish it, but the idea of goals for a year never struck a chord with me.
It&amp;rsquo;s one of the things that I find absurd about the current teacher rating system - I have to decided on my three goals for the year. I always have one goal with respect to my profession - to be better at it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Year and a New look</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re practically at the close of 2013 and it&amp;rsquo;s high time I wished everyone wonderful things for the year to come.
It&amp;rsquo;s also time for a new look to this blog.
Why the rewrite? Partly because I was tired of the look, but mostly because, when I put it together, it was the first time I used that toolset and was just figuring things out.
I&amp;rsquo;m still no expert, but I thought it was time to clean things up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Project 1 - Citibike Data</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-14-summer_projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-14-summer_projects/</guid>
      <description>So, the Citibike program has been running for a bit. I like the idea, but I have some reservations &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s great for getting around in the zone - I&amp;rsquo;ve been using it for short shopping trips - run cross town to Fairway or take a quick trip from work to Porto Rico Importers or Rocco&amp;rsquo;s Pastries. On the other hand, the zone doesn&amp;rsquo;t get to the residential neighborhoods of upper Manhattan or the boroughs and the price per day is way too expensive for regular working class joes, particularly on top of a subway trip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graduation</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-02-graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-02-graduation/</guid>
      <description>One week ago today was Stuyvesant&#39;s graduation.  I usually know a number of seniors pretty well but, since I like to cycle through classes, every couple of years I have a group that I&#39;ve been with from 10th grade to 12th.  This was one of those years  It was extra special because it was also my daughter Batya&#39;s graduating class.  It&#39;s been an amazing gift to be able to work at her school for the past four years and she&#39;s been amazingly tolerant.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>