<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2016</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/advent-of-code-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/advent-of-code-2016/</guid>
      <description>Once again, it&#39;s time for Advent of Code - a series of small programming problems released once a day.
I wrote a bit about it last year and you can still find last years problems here.
It&#39;s only day three but so far, all of the problems look really nice for students in APCS-A or any similar intro course. I&#39;m thinking of looking at a couple of the problems this week with my class at Hunter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</guid>
      <description>Morgan Roderick pictures
https://www.flickr.com/photos/morganroderick/sets/72157660040372060/with/22362235148/
&amp;ndash;!&amp;gt;
   The Hudson Valley&#39;s a beautiful place, particularly during the Fall. We don&#39;t get up there as much as we should - usually just for apple picking and then for the New York Sheep and Wool Festival.  It&#39;s a region with great food, hiking, natural beauty, history and more.  So, what exactly is growing?  The Hudson Valley Tech community.  I first heard about what Hudson Valley was doing around Tech back at the August New York Tech Meetup.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tapia 2014</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-02-09-tapia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-02-09-tapia/</guid>
      <description>Spent the past few days at the Tapia Conference in Seattle.
The Tapia conference is billed as a &amp;ldquo;Celebration of Diversity in Computing.&amp;rdquo; The bulk of the attendees seemed to be students. Undergrads and grads. The undergrads were mostly juniors and seniors, but a bunch of freshmen and sophomores were there as well. Of course there were faculty members to join them as well as people from industry.
What was I doing there?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from Pete Seeger</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-01-30-pete-seeger/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-01-30-pete-seeger/</guid>
      <description>This past Monday I, like may woke to hear about the passing of Pete Seeger. Ten days earlier we were up at Symphony Space for the &amp;ldquo;Woody&amp;rsquo;s Children&amp;rdquo; 45th Anniversary Concert. Pete was supposed to perform but was ill. At 94 years of age, I wondered if the end was near. I was at the concert with my family as well as with my buddy Ben. Fitting since Ben and I grew up on Pete&amp;rsquo;s music while many of our peers did not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plans for the New Year</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-01-01-new-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2014-01-01-new-year/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve never been one for New Year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions.
If I&amp;rsquo;m working on something specific, I might set a goal to finish it, but the idea of goals for a year never struck a chord with me.
It&amp;rsquo;s one of the things that I find absurd about the current teacher rating system - I have to decided on my three goals for the year. I always have one goal with respect to my profession - to be better at it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Year and a New look</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re practically at the close of 2013 and it&amp;rsquo;s high time I wished everyone wonderful things for the year to come.
It&amp;rsquo;s also time for a new look to this blog.
Why the rewrite? Partly because I was tired of the look, but mostly because, when I put it together, it was the first time I used that toolset and was just figuring things out.
I&amp;rsquo;m still no expert, but I thought it was time to clean things up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Project 1 - Citibike Data</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-07-14-summer_projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-07-14-summer_projects/</guid>
      <description>So, the Citibike program has been running for a bit. I like the idea, but I have some reservations &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s great for getting around in the zone - I&amp;rsquo;ve been using it for short shopping trips - run cross town to Fairway or take a quick trip from work to Porto Rico Importers or Rocco&amp;rsquo;s Pastries. On the other hand, the zone doesn&amp;rsquo;t get to the residential neighborhoods of upper Manhattan or the boroughs and the price per day is way too expensive for regular working class joes, particularly on top of a subway trip.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>