<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pedagogy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pedagogy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pedagogy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 12:34:04 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pedagogy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching techniques - industry to classroom and classroom to industry</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/industry-techniques-in-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 12:34:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/industry-techniques-in-class/</guid>
      <description>There are things we do in school and there are things we do in industry and they&#39;re not always the same. In school we might use a learning language or an IDE which gives additional support and at times even take away language features while at work you might you might make heavy use of continuous integration tools.
On the other hand, sometimes we use the same things. Java is used in schools and in industry, StackOverflow consulted in both and many schools use professional IDEs like Eclipse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Is Good Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-is-good-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 17:13:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-is-good-teaching/</guid>
      <description>I had a conversation with my principal during my last year at Stuy. She said &#34;whenever the superintendent or high level education people come and ask to see our best teachers I can never bring them to Jim&#39;s class.&#34; Everyone knows that Jim is the best. I describe him as &#34;the teacher I aspire to be.&#34; What&#39;s the problem? The problem is that Jim didn&#39;t teach the way the powers that be wanted him to teach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequencing Topics</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sequencing-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 16:06:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sequencing-topics/</guid>
      <description>Monday&#39;s the start of the Spring semester. Other than the 8:00am start I&#39;m looking forward to it. My 8:00am class is the honors/lab component that goes with CS1. I taught it last semester and during each of the past two years at Hunter. My second class is the follow up - more OOP / C++, data structures and some algorithms.
The material is old hat. I&#39;ve taught it in Java more times than I can count and also in C++ albeit many years ago.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Teachers Teach</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/let-teachers-teach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 08:57:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/let-teachers-teach/</guid>
      <description>Mark Guzdial&#39;s post the other day about direct isntruction struck a chord with me. Right up front, Mark said:
  The research evidence is growing that students learn better through direct instruction rather than through a discovery-based method, where we expect students to figure things out for themselves.  Quite a surprise to the teachers who have been beaten over the head with &#34;everything must be discovery&#34; in recent years.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>